Lets say we have the relationship y is equal to cosine of five x minus three y
and what I want to find is the rate of which y is changing with respect to x
and we'll assume that y is a function of x
So lets do what weve always been doing
lets apply the derivative operator to both sides of this equation
On the left side of the equation, right here, we get dy/dx is equal to
Now here on the right hand side were going to apply the chain rule
The derivative of the cosine of something with respect to that something is going to be equal to negative sine of that something
so negative sine of five x minus three y
and then we have to multiply that by the derivative of that something with respect to x.
So whats the derivative of that something with respect to x?
Well the derivative of five x with respect to x is five
and the derivative of negative three y with respect to x is negative three times dy/dx
The negative three times the derivative of y with respect to x
and now we just need to solve for dy/dx
As you can see with some of these implicit differentiation problems, this is the hard part
Actually let me make that dy/dx the same color, so we can keep track of it easier
So this is going to be dy/dx and then I can close the parentheses
So how can we do it? Its just going to be a little bit of algebra to work through
Well we can distribute the sine of five x minus 3 y, so let me rewrite everything
You can distribute the sine of five x minus three y - you get, let me rewrite everything. You're going to get dy/dx. Your distribute the negative sine, youre going to have five x minus three y
all of this, so youre going to have negative five times the sine of five
x minus three y and then youre going have the negative times the negative
You end up with a positive and so youre going to end up with plus three
times the sine of five x minus three y
dy/dx
Now what we can do is subtract three sine of five x minus three y from both sides
So, this is essentially one dy/dx
So if we subtract this from both sides we are left with
So one the left side were going to have a one dy/dx
and were going to subtract from that three sine of five x minus three y dy/dx's
Youre going to have one minus three
Ill keep the color for three for fun
three sine of five x minus three y dy/dx's
on the left hand side
is going to be equal to
well we subtracted thsi from both sides, so on the right hand side this is going to go away
So were just going to be left with a negative five sine of five x minus three y
and were in the home stretch now! To solve for dy/dx
You just have to divide both sides of the equation by this and we are left with
dy/dx is equal to
this thing, negative five times the sine
of five x minus three y
all of that over one minus three sine
of five x minus three y and we are done