Let's talk about one of the most
important biological processes.
Frankly, if this process didn't occur, we probably
wouldn't have life on Earth,
and I wouldn't be making this video for you.
Because there'd be no place for me to actually get food.
And the process is called "photosynthesis."
And you're probably reasonably familiar with the idea.
The whole idea is plants --
and actually bacteria and algae and other things --
But we normally associate it with plants --
Let me make it in very simple terms.
So we normally associate it with plants.
And it's a process that plants use,
And we might have learned this when we were very young.
It's the process that plants use to take carbon dioxide,
plus some water, plus some sunlight,
and turn it into some sugars, or some, maybe, carbohydrates.
Carbohydrates or sugars, plus oxygen.
Obviously, this has two very profound pieces to it for us
as a living species.
One, we need carbohydrates or we need sugars in order to
fuel our bodies.
You saw that in the cellular respiration videos.
We generate all of our ATP by performing cellular
respiration on glucose, which is essentially a byproduct,
or a broken down carbohydrate.
It's the simplest one for us to process in cellular respiration.
And the second hugely important part
is getting the oxygen.
Once again, we need to breathe oxygen in order for us to
break down glucose, in order to respire, in order to
perform cellUar respiration.
So these two things are key for life,
especially for life [forms] that breathes oxygen.
So this process -- other than the fact that it's interesting,
that there are organisms around us --
mostly plants -- that are able to harness actual sunlight.
You have these fusion reactions in the sun
93 million miles away. And it's releasing these photons, and
some small subset of those photons reach
the surface of Earth.
They make their way through clouds and whatever else.
And then these plants and bacteria and algae are able to
harness that somehow and turn them into sugars that we can
then eat or maybe the cow eats them and we eat the cow if
we're not vegetarians, and we can then use that for energy.
Not that the cow is all carbohydrates, but this is
essentially what is used as the fuel or the energy for all
of the other important compounds that we eat.
This is where we get all of our fuel.
So this is fuel for animals.
Or if you eat a potato directly, you are
directly getting your carbohydrates.
But anyway, this is a very simple notion of photosynthesis.
But it's not incorrect.
I mean, if you had to know one thing about photosynthesis,
this would be it.
But let's delve a little bit deeper and try to get into the
guts of it and see if we can understand a little bit better
how this actually happens.
I find it amazing that somehow photons of sunlight are used
to create these sugar molecules or these carbohydrates.
So let's delve a little bit deeper.
So we can write the general equation for photosynthesis.
Well, I've almost written it here.
But I'll write it a little bit more scientifically specific.
You start off with some carbon dioxide.
You add to that some water, and you add to that-- instead
of sunlight, I'm going to say photons because these are what
really do excite the electrons in the chlorophyll that go
down, and you'll see this process probably in this
video, and we'll go in more detail in the next few videos.
But that excited electron goes to a high energy state, and as
it goes to a lower energy state, we're able to harness
that energy to produce ATPs, and you'll see NADPHs, and
those are used to produce carbohydrates.
But we'll see that in a little bit.
But the overview of photosynthesis, you start off
with these constituents. And then you end up with a
carbohydrate.
And a carbohydrate could be glucose,
(Doesn't have to be glucose.)
So the general way we can write a carbohydrates is CH2O.
And we'll put an n over here, that we could have n multiples
of these, and normally, n will be at least three.
In the case of glucose, n is 6.
You have 6 carbons, 12 hydrogens, and 6 oxygens.
So this is a general term for carbohydrates.
But you could have many multiples of that.
You could have these long-chained carbohydrates.
So, you end up with a carbohydrate and then you end
up with some oxygen.
So this right here isn't so different than what I wrote up
here in my first overview of how we always imagined
photosynthesis in our heads.
In order to make this equation balance-- let's see, I have n
carbons so I need n carbons there.
Let's see, I have two n hydrogens here.
Two hydrogens and I have n there, so I need two n
hydrogens here.
So I'll put an n out there.
And lets see how many oxygens.
I have two n oxygens, plus another n, so I
have three n oxygens.
So let's see, I have one n, and you put an n here, and
then I have two n, and I think this equation balances out.
So this is a 30,000-foot view of what's going on in
photosynthesis.
But when you dig a little deeper, you'll see that this
doesn't happen directly, that this happens through a bunch
of steps that eventually gets us to the carbohydrate.
So in general, we can break down photosynthesis.
I'll rewrite the word.
We can break down photosynthesis-- and we'll
delve deeper into future videos, but I want to get you
the overview first-- into two stages.
We can call one the light reactions.
Or sometimes they are called the light-dependent reactions,
and that actually would probably be a better
way to write it.
Let me write it like that.
Light dependent means that they need light to occur.
Light-dependent reactions.
And then you have something called the dark reactions, and
that's actually a bad name, because it also
occurs in the light.
Dark reactions, I wrote in a slightly darker color.
And the reason why I said it's a bad name is because it still
occurs in the light.
But the reason why they probably called it the dark
reaction is that you don't need light, or that part of
photosynthesis isn't dependent on photons to occur.
So a better term for it would have been
"light-independent reaction."
So just to be clear, the light reactions
actually need sunlight.
They actually need photons for them to proceed.
The dark reactions do not need photons for them to happen,
although they do occur when the sun is out.
They don't need those photons, but they need the byproducts
from the light reaction to occur, so that's why it's
called the light-independent reaction.
They occur while the sun is out, but they
don't need the sun.
This needs the sun, so let me make it very clear.
So this requires sunlight.
This requires photons.
And let me just make a very brief overview of this.
This'll maybe let us start building a scaffold from which
we can dig deeper.
So the light reactions need photons, and
then it needs water.
So water goes into the light reactions and out of the other
side of the light reactions.
We end up with some molecular oxygen.
So that's what happens in the light reactions, and I'm going
to go much deeper into what actually occurs.
And what the light the actions produce is ATP, which we know
is the cellular or the biological currency of energy.
It produces ATP and it produces NADPH.
Now, when we studied cellular respiration, we saw the
molecule NADH.
NADPH is very similar.
You just have this P there.
You just have this phosphate group there, but they really
perform similar mechanisms. That this agent right here,
this molecule right here, is able to give away-- now let's
think about what this means-- it's able to give away this
hydrogen and the electron associated with this hydrogen.
So if you give away an electron to someone else or
someone else gains an electron, that something else
is being reduced.
Let me write that down.
This is a good reminder.
OIL RIG.
Oxidation is losing an electron.
Reduction is gaining an electron.
Your charge is reduced when you gain an electron.
It has a negative charge.
So this is a reducing agent.
It gets oxidized by losing the hydrogen and the
electron with it.
I have a whole discussion on the biological versus
chemistry view of oxidation, but it's the same idea.
When I lose a hydrogen, I also lose the ability to hog that
hydrogen's electron.
So this right here, when it reacts with other things, it's
a reducing agent.
It gives away this hydrogen and the electron associated
with it, and so the other thing gets reduced.
So this thing is a reducing agent.
And what's useful about it is when this hydrogen, and
especially the electron associated with that hydrogen,
goes from the NADPH to, say, another molecule and goes to a
lower energy state, that energy can also be used in the
dark reactions.
And we saw in cellular respiration the very similar
molecule, NADH, that through
the Kreb Cycle, or actually
more importantly, that through the electron transport chain,
was able to help produce ATP as it gave away its electrons
and they went to lower energy states.
But I don't want to confuse you too much.
So the light reactions, you take in photons, you take in
water, it spits out oxygen, and it spits out ATP and NADPH
that can then be used in the dark reactions.
And the dark reactions, for most plants we talk about,
it's called the Calvin Cycle.
And I'll go into a lot more detail of what actually occurs
in the Calvin Cycle, but it
takes in the ATP, the NADPH,
and it produces-- it doesn't directly produce glucose.
It produces-- oh, you probably saw this.
You could call it PGAL.
You could call it G3P.
These all stand for-- let me write these down-- this is
phosphoglyceraldehyde.
My handwriting broke down.
Or you could call it glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate.
Same exact molecule.
You can almost imagine it as -- this is a very gross
oversimplification-- as three carbons with a phosphate group
attached to it.
But this can then be used to produce other carbohydrates,
including glucose.
If you have two of these, you can use those
two to produce glucose.
So let's just take a quick overview again because this is
super important.
I'm going to make videos on the light reactions and the
dark reactions.
Those will be the next two videos I make.
So photosynthesis, you start with photons.
All of these occur when the sun is out, but only the light
reactions actually need the photons.
The light reactions take photons-- we're going to go
into more detail about what actually occurs--
and it takes in water.
Oxygen gets spit out.
ATP and NADPH get spit out, which are then used by the
dark reaction, or the Calvin Cycle, or the
light-independent reaction, because these still
occur in the light.
They just don't need photons.
So they're the light-independent reaction.
And it uses that in conjunction-- and we'll talk
about other molecules that are used in conjunction.
Oh, and I forgot a very important constituent of the
dark reaction.
It needs carbon dioxide.
That's where you get your carbons to keep producing
these phosphoglyceraldehydes, or glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate.
So that's super important.
It takes in the carbon dioxide, the products from the
light reactions, and then uses that in the Calvin Cycle to
produce this very simple building block of other
carbohydrates.
And if you remember from glycolysis, you might remember
that this PGAL molecule, or this G3P-- same thing-- this
was actually the first product when we split glucose in two
when we performed the glycolysis.
So now we're going the other way.
We're building glucose so that we can split
it later for energy.
So this is an overview of photosynthesis, and in the
next couple of videos, I'm actually going to delve a
little bit deeper and tell you about the light reactions and
the dark reactions and how they actually occur.