Write 5.1/4 as an improper fraction
Let me remind you an improper fraction
is one where the numerator is gretaer than or equal
to denominator, absolute value of numerator
is greater than or equal to
absolute value of denominator
In this situation right here we have
a mixed number where 5 is the whole number
and 1/4 is a proper fraction as numerator
is less than denominator
So write as an improper fraction I will
show you the methodology
So 5.1/4, the methodology is simple
5 is the same thing as 20/4
So 20/4 + 1/4 = 21/4
Another way to think is 5 x 4 = 20 + 1 = 21
So its 21/4
You take the mixed number or you take the whole part
of the mixed number multiply it with
the denominator & add the numerator to it.
So let us see why it works.
lets us see what 5.1/4 is
We have 5 wholes, this is one whole
let me copy it five times
So that is 2, 3, 4 & that is 5
So we have 5 wholes and then we have 1/4
1/4th of a whole is like this
To write it as a improper fraction
Divide each of the wholes into 1/4ths
This is 4, 1/4ths, another 4,1/4ths another 4,1/4ths
this is another 4, 1/4ths. So how many
1/4ths we have it is 20 , 1/4ths in green
That is the same thing as 5
and then we can add to that 1/4ths.
Then we will get 21/4.
That is the conceptual way of how it works.
Multiply the whole number by the denominator
and add the numertaor to it
5.1/4 = 21/4
5.1/4 =( ( 5x4) + 1)/4