Simplify 3a times a to the fifth times a squared.
So the exponent property we can use here is
if we have the same base, in this case it's a,
if we have it raised to the x power and we're
multiplying it by a to the y power,
then this is just going to be equal to a to the x plus y power,
and we'll think about why that works in a second,
so let's just apply it here, and let's start with
the a to the fifth times a squared. So if
we just apply this property over here, this will result
in a to the five plus (2nd) power.
so that's what those guys reduce to or simplify to
and of course we still have, we still have the
3a out front.
Now, what I want to do to take a little bit to the side
and realize why this works.
Let's think about a to the fifth times a squared
means. A to the fifth literally means
a times a times a times a times a.
Now, a squared literally means a times a.
And we're multiplying the two times each other.
So we're multiplying these five a's times these two a's,
so what have we just done?
We're multiplying a by itself five times, then
another two times, so let me make it clear
this over here is a to the fifth, this over here
is a squared, when you multiply the two
you're multiplying a by itself seven times! Five plus two!
So this is a to the seventh power. (A to the five plus two power.)
So this simplifies to 3a times a to the seventh power.
Now, you might say, how do I apply the property
over here? What is the exponent on the a?
And remember, if I just have an a over here,
this is equivalent to a to the first power.
So I can rewrite 3a as three times a to the first power
And now maybe it makes it a little bit more clearer
a to the first power, and the association property
of multiplication-- I can do the multiplication of
the a's first before I worry about the 3's!
So I can multiply these two guys first.
So a to the first times a to the seventh,
I just have to add the exponents cause I have the same base and I'm taking the product,
that's going to be a to the eighth power,
and I still have this three out front.
So, 3a times a to the fifth times a squared simplifies to
3a to the eighth power.