Hey I'm Beth Harris, I'm Shana Lindsay
We're going to talk about this very odd
and disturbing photograph
This is a photograph by Diane Arbus
It say New York City photographer at dates 1962
and it's called Child with a toy grenade, New York City
It's incredibly disturbing
He's got a grenade in his hand
that's upsetting, It's look like there's
something wrong with him.
And selecting her photograph, she's always
brought something that seems and more handy
identify with and other hand seems
very awkward to you, it's very different
You may say disturbing
You don't find this disturbing? I do although
having children, and particulary boys,
sometimes they do make faces like this
You know just in their imagination, they play
They does, this is almost something like you
has to wonder something medically wrong with him
almost in this photograph, more than
he's just playing.
All right, he's neck is incredibly tense.
That's interesting is that she her training
as photograph she was an assistant with her husband
they had a homebased studio
where they which shoot fashion photos
so this type of you know
a straining little body is something that she
would never ever choose at her commercial work
It have everything to be very graceful, smooth
and say she wants us * this number
and so she asked this boy to pose?
She can cross him in the park and ask him to pose?
Yes, she was apparently just walking through the park
looking for something for shoot and she
find a boy and so * as you can see from this contact
sheet here, she's move him around to several different
locations and here he's standing next to
very-- He's rather ordinary in most others photographs--
right standing in some gallantly here
you know on a pass than she moves him to
this area where you see the tree in the background
which is ultimately that same, you know
area that final print was made from.
And I think she likes that (deepling) of the sunlight
You know, we can see light slightly coming from
behind, ultimately this is the shoot that
she choose as his, go back.
He's standing so there's continuation of the
tree, one tree with this suspender down the legs
This is slightly * access and there also
that parring of trees matches with parring of
two legs, you know-- one suspender falling down
and looping to the right just like this
little branch coming out of the top
of the other tree to the right
and * hands doing the same things
so there's all the symmetry and * symmetry
at that same time, there's pattern of course
in his shirt that in some way that flats
that light *
and he almost seems like all of these
he's * focal point of this *
seems to emerge from him
He's almost like halo of light or (dappling) around him
absolutely and since the light is coming
from slightly behind him It's almost like
light being projected toward us
*
like they checker floor of renaissance
right, did she take this to ordinary lens
She, yeah the type of camera she uses is
* flex and is has view finder
that's allow her to see the image
that is usally hanging around her waist, to the
camera so she looks down into the camera
and there's another one that
is actually use to shoot.