we are in the national gallery in washington,
looking at alovely set of madonna and child
from about 1404. i suppose the stress is so lovely to me
the beautiful soft curls of the headdress that
she is wearing, feigning her face, ther is a curve upwards
her face. madonna is often shown so beautiful
but the trouble here her sense of fear and sadness comes across
in suchan incredibly tender and in the way
her hand holds him back protectively,this is
that terrible quidid moment and looks out and us
its true and a sort of way of saying, we all know
what is going to happen. we all know what this means
but look at the price that i paid for this as amother
anything that i see with this is so obviously
the relevance of the lessons of the 15th century
mary becoming so human in the way she does
describe christ looking so much more like a baby
than he did. be it a hundred years earlier
the boy had chubby, not looking like a small man
but obviously we be comfortable with the notion
that here we have god in this divine figure in the
body of a child.that is looking down as would be his right
that suggests the visual placement of this painting
and instead of this fad called background that
we would have had a hundred years earlier
a babys cradle , a nithch for mary to occupy
so we are supposed to be very classical looking
and then that shadow that her body cast to the right
that we have a sense of real natural light coming from
the left casting a show, asense of her convincing
three dimensionality here. she is not a flat euphony
of figure anymore.that is brilliantand interestingly
she has that physicality that is expresed in
classical architecture but also you awe in the way
in which the shadow actually fathers the complex
contoversial arcchitecture. the lesson of mesachia
but on the other hand there is a kind of softnes and mracle
quality that isin;t in mesachia.so that this
beautiful curves around her face and down
you can see how it is but a likely feature
this lovely girl is showing. but slowly the girl is disappearing
and the halo is disappearing and it is just a recapcle in gold
like the gentle way in which he is held
and now that he is on the surround on the wedge
like a window there. sometimes as arefence
to that event she also monached from them
she pretexed in fonder. how to remember in
looking at the paintng in the museum that it has been
down earthed to some conservation efforts.
it seems about 600 years old and it could be so