In the last video, we talk about how seasons on Earth are not caused
by how close Earth is to the Sun, its orbit.
We also hint at the fact that it's actually bacause by tilt of the Earth.
And so, in this video, I wanna show you
how the tilt of the Earth causes the seasons to happen.
So let's draw...
I'll try to draw as many diagrams as possible here
because at least for my brain and they help me visualize what's actually going on.
So, we can imagine a top view first.
So, let's have a top view.
That is the Sun right over there.
And let me draw Earth's orbit.
So Earth's orbit maybe looks something like that.
Let me draw it almost - it is almost circular.
So I'll draw this something that's pretty close to a circle right over here.
Now,I gonna draw Earth at different points in its orbit
and I will try to depict the tilt of its rotational axis.
And obviously this is not drawn anywhere near close the scale.
Earth is much further away from the Sun
and much much smaller than the Sun as well.
So I'll draw the Earth at that point,
and at this point the Earth will be tilted away from the Sun.
So, Earth's tilt does not change if you think about the direction -
or this over the course of a year,
we're talking about relatively small periods of time -
it does not change relative to the direction that it's pointing at in the universe.
Let me .. I will talk about that in a second.
So, let's say right over here we are pointed away from the Sun,
so we're up and out of this page.
so I will put some perspective of an arrow.
Actually it would be more like up and out of this page,
so, that's the direction if you were to come straight out of the North Pole,
if you were to come straight out of the South Pole,
you would go below that circle right over there.
And if I wanna draw the same position but if we were looking sideways,
along the orbital plane, or the plane of Earth's orbit,
so for looking at from that direction,
so let me do it this way.
For looking at directly sideways,
this is the Sun right over here
and this is Earth at that position.
If I were to draw an arrow pointing sraight out of the North Pole,
it would look something like this.
So this arrow and this arrow, they are both popping straight out of the North Pole.
And so, when we talk about the tilt of the Earth,
we're talking about the tilt of its orbital axis,
kind of this pole that can go straight between the South Pole and the North Pole.
The angle between that and the pole that would actually be at a 90° angle
and perpendicular to the plane of its orbit,
compared to it if it was just sraight up and down
relativ to the plane of the orbit.
So, this right here is the angle of Earth's tilt.
Let me draw that a little bit bigger
just so it becomes a little bit clearer.
So, this is the plane of the orbit,
we're looking sideways along the plane of the orbit,
and this is Earth right over here.
My best attempt to draw a circle.
That is Earth.
Earth does not rotate, its axis of rotation is not perpendicular to the plane of the orbit.
So, this is how Earth would rotate if it was.
Earth's rotational axis is at an angle to that vertical
relative to the plane of its orbit, I guess you could say it.
It rotates at an angle like this.
So, this would be the North Pole,
that is the South Pole,
and so it rotates like this.
And that angle relativ to being vertical
with respect to the orbital plane,
this angle right here for Earth right now
is 24. ... is 20 ...
sorry, 23,4°.
23,4°
And for talking about relatively short periods of time,
like, you know, our life spans,
that is constant.
But it is actually changing over long periods of time.
That is changing between, and these are rough numbers,
is is changing between 22,1° and 24,5°, if my sources are correct,
but I guess they're rough estimate of what it's changing between.
But I wanna make it clear: this is not happening overnight.
The period that it takes to go from roughly a 22° angle to a 24,5° angle and back to the 22° angle
is 41,000 years.
And this long-term change in the tilt,
this might have played to some of the long-term climate change,
maybe it might have contributed on some level to some of the Ice Ages
that have formed over Earht's past,
but for the sake of thinking about our annual seasons,
you don't have to worry too much,
or you don't have to worry at all really about this variation.
You really just have to know that it is tilted,
and right now it is tilted in an angle of 23,4°.
Now, you might say: 'OK, I understand what the tilt is,
but how does that change the season,
the .. of the Northern or that Southern Hemisphere.
And to do that, I'm going to imagine the Earth
when the Northern Hemisphere is most tilted away from the Sun
and when it is most tilted towards the Sun.
So remember, this tilt, the direction this arrow poits into relative the rest of the universe,
if we assume that this tilt, that 23,4° it's not changing throughout the year,
but depending on where it is in the orbit
it's either going to be tilted away from the Sun,
as it is in this example right over here,
or it would be tilting towards the Sun.
I will do the "towards the Sun" in this magenta color.
Or it will be tilting towards the Sun.
So, six months later when the Earth is over here,
relative to the rest of the universe it will be tilted in that same direction,
up, out of this page and to the right.
So, out of this page and to the right again,
just like it was over here,
but now that it's on the other side of the Sun,
and that makes the tilt a little bit more towards the Sun.
If I were to draw it right over here,
it is now tilted towards the Sun.
And what I want to think about is
how much sunlight will different parts of the planet receive,
and I'll focus on the Northern Hemisphere,
but you can make a similiar argument for the Southern Hemisphere.
I wanna think about how much sunlight they receive
at when it's tilted away or tilted towards the Sun.
Let's think about those two situations.
So, first of all let's think about the situation here
where we're tilted away from the Sun.
So, let me zoom it a little bit.
This is the situation where we're tilted away from the Sun.
So, if this is the vertical ...
I could actually use this diagram, but let me make it.
So, we're tilted away from the Sun like this,
let me use a different color...
So, if we had an arrow coming straight out of the North Pole,
it would look like this.
If we have an arrow coming straight out of the North Pole
and we're rotating around like that.
Out of the page on the left-hand side
and into the page on the right-hand side.
And so we're rotating towards the east constantly.
So, this arrow is in the direction of the east.
So, when we're at this point in Earth's orbit,
and actually let me copy and paste this
and I'm going to use the same exact diagram for the different seasons.
So, let me copy and paste this exact same diagram,
I'll do it over here for two different points.
So, when we're here in Earth's orbit,
where is the sunlight coming from?
Well, it's going to be coming from the left,
at least the way I've drawn the diagram right over here.
So, the sunlight is coming from the left.
Sunlight is coming from the left in this sutation.
And so if you think about it,
what half of the Earth or what part of the Earth
is being lit by sunlight?
Or what part of the Earth is in daylight?
The way I have drawn it over here.
Well, the part that is facing the Sun!
So, all of this right over here is going to be in daylight.
As we rotate, whatever part of the surface of the Earth
enters into this yellow part right over here
will be in daylight.
But let's think about what's happening at different parts of the Earth.
Let me draw the equator
which separates our Northern and Southern hemispheres.
So, this is the equator.
And then let me go to the Northern Hemisphere.
And I wanna show you why when the North Pole is pointed away from the Sun,
why this is our winter.
So, when we're pointed away from the Sun...
or if we go to the Actic Circle.
So let me go right over here.
Let me go to some point in the Arctic Circle.
As it goes, as the Earth rotates every 24 hours,
this point on the globe will just rotate around just like that.
It will just keep rotating around just like that.
My question is: that point at the Arctic Circle that rotates,
will it ever see the sunlight?
Well, no, it will never see the sunlight.
Because the North Pole is tilted away from the Sun.
So, what I'm shading here in purple,
that part of the Earth that's completely tilted away
will never see sunlight.
Or at least it won't see sunlight while it'S tilted away,
why it's in this position in the orbit.
It never... I won't say never because once it becames summer,
they will be able to see the Sun,
so, no sunlight, no day I guess you could say.
No daylight.
If go to slightly more southern latitudes,
so let's say you go over here,
maybe that's the latitude of something like
New York, San Francisco or somenthing like that.
Let's think about what it would see as the Earth rotates every 24 hours.
So, this would be daylight,
then nighttime,
this is now going behind the globe,
nighttime, nighttime,
daylight, daylight.
So, if you just compare this,
let me do the daylight in orange,
daylight is in orange
and nighttime I'll do in this bluish-pruplish color.
So nighttime over here.
If you go to really northern latitudes like the Arctic Circle,
they don't get any daylight when we're tilted away from the Sun.
If we go to slightly still northern latitudes,
but not as northern as the Arctic Circle,
it does get daylight, but it gets a lot less daylight.
It spends a lot less in the daylight than in the nigttime.
So notice, if you say that this circumference represents the possition over 24 horus,
it spends much less time in the daylight
than it does in the nighttime.
So, because while the Northern Hermisphere is tilted away from the Sun,
the latitudes in the Northern Hemisphere are getting less daylight.
They're getting less daylight.
They're also getting less energy from the Sun,
and that's what leads to winter
or just being generally colder.