Let's say this past year I started a restaurant.
Now I wanna think about what type of profit I've been making
at that restaurant. We're gonna think about it in two different ways.
We're gonna think about it in terms of accounting profit
which is really the type of profit most of us associate with a business or a firm.
And we also think about it in terms of economic profit.
which we will see it a little bit different. And instead of telling us
whether a business is producing income, it tells
whether it makes sense to even run the business in the way
we are actually running it.
So first, let's focus on the traditional way of calculating profit.
Let's say my firm, my restaurant, my firm is a restaurant.
In year 1, it brings in a revenue 500 thousand dollars.
So revenue literally is the amount of money customers pay me,
the restaurant. They are paying for their dinner.
This is literally the money that is coming in door.
Sometimes, people call it Top Line because it is literally the top line of our income statement.
I just wrote it. It's the Top Line.
Now we have to think about our expenses. Expenses.
Now, when you are running a restaurant, one of the obvious expenses
is going to be the cost of food. So food,
So food, we're gonna say, cost us a 100 thousand dollars.
and you have the cost of labor.
I have wait stuff, I have the chief, busboy. All those peole