The owner of a restaurant wants to find out where his patrons are coming from
one day he decided to gather data about the distance in miles that people commuted to get to his restaurant
People reported the following distances traveled. So here are all the distances traveled.
He wants to create a graph that helps him understand the spread of distances
this is a key word, the spread of distances and the median distance, that people travel.
What kind of graph should he create?
So, the answer to what kind of graph he should create should be more straight forward
than the actual creation of the graph which we will also do
but he's trying to visualize the spread of information and at
the same time he wants the median, so what graph captures both of that information?
Well, a box and whisker plot! So let's try to draw a box and whisker plot!
To draw a box and whisker plot we need to come up with the median and we'll also see the median of the two
halves of the data as well, and whenever we try to take the median of something, it's
really helpful to order our data.
So let's attempt to order our data. So what is the
smallest number here? Let's see, there's one 2, so we mark it off. And then we have another 2
so we got all the 2's. And then we have this 3, then we have this 3. I think we got all the 3's
And then we have that 4, and then we have this 4
Do we have any 5's? No, do we have any 6's? Yup, we have that 6.
And that looks like the only 6. Any 7's? Yep, we have this 7 over here. And I just realized
I missed this 1 so I'm going to put it at the beginning of the set, actually I missed two 1's.
Both 1's are right at the beginning of the set.
So I have: 1's, 2's, 3's, 4's, no 5's this is one 6, one 7, one 8
Let's see, any 9's? No 9's. Any 10's? Yep, there's a 10.
Any 11's? Yes, we have an 11. Any 12's? Nope.
We have 14 and 15. We also have a 20 and 22.
So, we've ordered all our data is should be relatively straightforward to find the middle of our
data. The median. So how many data points we have?
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10
11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17
So the middle number is the number that has 8 numbers larger than it
and 8 numbers smaller than it. So let's think about it. One, two, three, four
five, six, seven, eight. So the number 6 here
is larger than eight of the values and if I did the calculations right
it should be smaller than eight of the values, one, two, three, four
five, six, seven, eight. So it is indeed
it is indeed the median. Now when we take
a box and whisker plot, the convention is we have our median and it is essentially dividing
our data into two sets, now let's take the median of each of
those sets, and the convetion is to take our median out and have the sets
that are left over. Some times people leave it in, but the standard convention
take this median out and look separately at this set and look separately at this set.
So if we look at this first, the bottom half of our numbers essentially
what's the median of these numbers?
Well, we have one, two, three, four, five, six, seven,
eight, data points. So we are actually gonna have two middle numbers.
So the two middle numbers are this 2 and this 3
three numbers less than these two and three numbers greater than them
and so when we are looking for a median, we have this two middle numbers and we are taking the mean
of these two numbers. So halfway between 2 and 3 is 2.5
2 plus 3 is 5. 5 divided by 2 is 2.5
So here we have the median of this bottom half of 2.5.
And then the middle of the top half, once again we have eight data points, so our
middle two numbers are gonna be this 11 and this 14
And so if we want to take the mean of these two numbers, 11 plus 14 is 25. Half of
25 is 12.5. 12.5 is exactly halfway in between 11 and 14.
And now we have all the information we need to actually
plot our box and whisker plot
So let me draw a number line, so my best
attempt at a number line. So that's my number line
And let's say this over here is 0.
I need to make sure I get up to 22 or beyond 22
This is 0, this is 5, this is 10
that could be 15, that could be 20
this could be 25, we can keep going
30, maybe 35. So the first
thing we might want to think about,there's several ways to draw it.
We wanna think about the box part of the box and whisker
Essentially represents the middle half of our data. So it's essentially
trying to represent this data, right over here
so the data between the two between the
medians of the two halves. So this is the part we would represent
with the box. So we would start right over here at this
lower at this 2.5, this is essentially seperating
the fist quartile from the second quartile, the first quarter of our numbers from the second quarter
of our numbers. So let's put it over here, this is 2.5
2.5 is halfway between 0 and 5 so that's
2.5 and then up here we have 12.5
and 12.5 is right over here
It's right over here, 12.5
This is halfway between, well halfway
between 10 and 15 is 12.5
12.5 right over here, 12.5
So that separates the third quartile from the fourth quartile
and then our boxes, everything in between, so this is gonna be the middle half
of our numbers, the middle half of our numbers, and we wanna
show where the actual median is so that's actaully one of things we want to think about
in our original.. When the owner of the restaurant
how far people are travelling from. So the median is 6
So we can plot it right over here
this is about 6, that's a pink color.
So this right over here, is 6. And then
the whiskers of the box and whisker plot, essentially show us the range
of our data, and so , let me do that.
I will do it in a new color, how about orange?
So essentially if we wanna see
look the numbers go all the way up to 22
this is 22 right over here, our numbers go all the way
up to 22. Our numbers go all the way up to 22.
And they go as low as 1
1 is right about here. They go as low
as 1...
So there you have it. We have our box and whisker plot. And you can see
if you have a plot like this, just visually you can immediatly see
what is the median? It is the middle of the box
it shows the middle half, or how far spread is, the meat of the spread
it shows beyond that, it shows the range, that goes way beyond
that it goes. Or how far the total spread of our data
is. So it gives us a pretty good sense of both the median and
the spread of our data