I think it's important [that] people look at art,
because we live in a visual world.
And understanding, and looking at,
and thinking about the way images communicate –
in all kinds of ways –
is important to being alive today.
If one has heightened visual acumen –
which you get from spending time looking at things –
whether it's looking at newspaper photos closely
or looking at works in a museum
or looking at your surroundings – or birds – more closely,
that sort of attention to an environment
makes you a better person.
You are existing in a more aware, alert, present space.
Sometimes people think that
the only way of looking at art is
going to museum constantly – at places like that.
But, maybe sometimes, art is everywhere –
in the street – if you look at architecture,
places, or everything.
So, you really don't need to go to a museum to see art.
It could be anywhere – in a park, or
looking at buildings, or going to the movies.
So I think that [art's] in everyday life.
It's all about noticing, for me.
It's all about trying to see beyond the first impression.
People look at art and they say,
"I like this. I don't like this." And they move on.
They have predetermined notions.
But if you can stop, and take a breath,
and look a little deeper at something,
you can really start to notice some kind of detail
that you might have not noticed before.
And I think that that skill applies
to so many things in life – aside from art.
About being able just to slow down
and be aware of where, actually – where you're standing –
and just even stop talking.
And just, maybe, open up your ears, for example.
There's so much detail around that you can absorb,
if you really just take a moment
and just let it come in – and listen.