Solve for z
5z + 7 is less than 27 OR negative 3z is less than or equal to 18.
So this is a compound inequality. We have two conditions here.
So z can satisfy this OR z can satisfy this over here.
So lets just solve each of these inequalities and just know that z can satisfy either of them.
So lets just look at this.
So if we look at just this one over here:
We have 5z + 7 is less than 27.
Let's isolate the z's on the left hand side,
so lets subtract 7 from both sides to get rid of this 7 on the left hand side.
And so our left hand side is just going to be 5z plus 7, minus 7, those cancel out
5z is less than 27 minus 20, sorry, 27 minus 7, which is 20
so we have 5z less than 20.
Now we can divide both sides of this inequality by 5
and we don't have to swap the inequality
because we're dividing by a positive number
and so we get z is less than 20 over 5.
Z is less than 4.
Now this is only one of the conditions.
Lets go to the other one over here:
We have negative 3z is less than or equal to 18.
Now to isolate the z we can just divide both sides
of this inequality by negative 3
but remember when you divide or multiply both sides
of an inequality by a negative number,
you have to swap the inequality.
So we can write negative 3z
We're going to divide by negative 3
and then you go 18 divide by negative 3
but we're going to swap the inequality!
So the left center equals greater than or equal to
and so these guys cancel out
negative 3 divided by negative 3 equals 1,
so we have z is greater than or equal to 18 over negative 3 is negative 6
and remember, it's this constraint OR this constraint
and this constraint right over here boils down to this
and this one boils down to this
so our solution set
z is less than 4 OR z is greater than or equal to negative -6.
So let me make this clear.
Let me rewrite it.
So z is less than 4 OR z is greater than or equal to negative 6.
It can satisfy either one of these.
This is kind of interesting here.
So, so let's plot these. Let's plot these.
So there's the number line.
Right over there.
Let's say 0 is over here
and we have 1, 2, 3, 4 is right over there
and negative 6, we have 1, 2 ,3, 4, 5, 6.
That's negative 6 over there.
Now let's think about z being less than 4
Z being less than 4,
we put a circle around 4,
since we're not including 4
and it'd be everything, everything less than 4. Everything less than 4.
Now lets think about z being greater than or equal to negative 6 would be
That means we can include negative 6
and it's everything... let's do this in a more different color...
It means you can include negative 6...
I'm going to do that....
Let me do that in a more different color...
I'm going to do it in orange...
so z is greater than equal to negative 6
and this means you include negative 6
and its everything greater than that
greater than that
including 4.
It's everything greater than that.
So we see we've essentially shaded in the
entire number line!
Every number will meet either one of these constraints
or both of them.
If we're over here, we're going to meet both of the constraints,
if we're one of these numbers, if we're a number out here, we're going
to meet this constraint
if we're a number down here,
we're going to meet this constraint.
You can just try it out with a bunch of numbers.
0 will work.
0 plus 7 is 7
which is less than 27.
And three times 0 is less than 18
so it meets both constraints.
If we put 4 here,
it should only meet one of the constraints.
Negative 3 times 4 is negative 12,
which is less than 18.
So it meets this constraint but won't meet this constraint.
Because you do 5 times 4
plus 7 is 27
which is not LESS than 27, it's equal to 27.
Remember this is an OR, so you just have to
meet one of the constraints.
So 4 meets this constraint
so even 4 works.
So it's really the entire the number line
will satisfy either one or both of these constraints.