So we're asked to solve for x and we have this equation with absolute values in it.
So it's 4|x+10|+4 = 6|x+10|+10.
And at first, this looks really daunting, but the key is to just solve for this absolute value expression and then go from there.
Let me rewrite it so the absolute value expression really jumps out. So this is 4|x+10|+4 = 6|x+10|+10.
So let's get all of the absolute values of x+10 on the left hand side. So I want to get rid of the 6|x+10| on the right.
Well, how would I do that? Well, I could subtract 6|x+10| from the right, but we already seen this multiple times,
if these two things are equal and I want to keep them equal if I subtract 6|x+10| from the right hand side, I'd have to subtract the same thing from the left hand side.
So we're going to have -6|x+10|, and likewise, I want to get this 4 out of this left hand side.
So let me subtract 4 from the left, and then I also have to do it on the right.
Otherwise, my equality wouldn't hold. And now let's see what we end up with.
So on the left hand side, the 4-4, that's 0. You have 4 of something minus 6 of something,
that means you're going to end up with -2 of that something. -2 of |x+10|.
Remember, this might seem a little confusing, but remember,
if we have 4 apples and you subtract 6 apples, you now have -2 apples. I guess you owe someone the apples.
Same way, you have 4 of this expression, you take away 6 of this expression, and you now have -2 of this expression.
Let me write it a little bit neater. So it's -2|x+10| is equal to --
well, the whole point of the 6|x+10| is to make those cancel out, and you have 10-4, which is equal to 6.
Now we want to solve for |x+10|. So let's get rid of this -2, and we can do that by dividing both sides by -2,
and you might realize, everything we've done so far is just treating this red expression --
it's almost just like a variable, and we're going to solve for that red expression and then take it from there.
So -2/-2 is 1, 6/-2 is -3. So we get |x+10| = -3. Now, this gets us to a very interesting situation. You might say,
"Hey, this could be the positive version or the negative version,"
but remember, absolute value is always non-negative.
When you take the absolute value of 0, you would get 0, but the absolute of anything else is going to be positive.
So this thing right over here is definitely going to be greater than or equal than 0.
Doesn't matter what x you put in there, when you take this absolute value, you're going to get a value that's greater than or equal to 0.
So there's no x that you can find that somehow -- you put it there, you add 10, you take the absolute value of it that you're going to get a negative value.
So this right over here has absolutely no solution. And I'll put some exclamation marks there for emphasis.