Solve for x plus 8 is less than or equal to 6 and graph the solution
So we have x plus 8 is less than or equal to 6
So let's solve this inequality for x, and the easiest way to isolate an x on, let's isolate on the left
hand side since it's already there is to just get rid of this 8,
and the best way to get rid of this positive 8 is to subtract 8 from both sides
So let's subtract 8 from both sides, that won't change the
direction of the inequality, so the left hand side
x plus 8 minus 8, you're just left with an x,
the right hand side 6 minus 8 is negative 2, and we still have the less than or equal
So we solve the inequality, we have x is less than or equal to
negative 2, so let's draw that on a number line.
So that's my number line, let's take 0 over here, maybe if
we go 1, then we can go negative 1, negative 2, negative 3
and we can keep going to the left, and we want
all the x's that are less than or equal to negative 2
since it can be equal to negative 2, we'll put a filled in
line right here at negative 2, and all of the values less than that
If it was just less than, if there wasn't the equal sign, we would have an open dot
but since this is less than OR equal to, we've closed this dot
Then we want all of the values below that
And you can just sample a few and verify for yourself that they work,
Based on this, negative 3 should work, and if you took
negative 3, negative 3 plus 8 is five, which is definitely
less than 6, so that works, and negative 1 shouldn't work,
it's not included in this set over here, so let's try that out.
Negative 1 plus 8 is 7, which is definitely not less than 6,
so just sampling some points, it seems like we've got the right solution.