Welcome to the presentation on the Level two exponents.
In Level two exponents,
the only thing we're going to add to the mix now
is the concept of a negative exponent.
So we learned already that 2 to the third power,
well, that just equals 2 x 2 x 2.
Hopefully, by now, that's second nature to you,
and that equals 8.
Now I'm going to teach you
what 2 to the negative third power is.
I know a lot of you are going to say, oh no, that's -8,
but whenever you see exponents,
you always have to remind yourself,
exponents are not multiplication.
I know there's that temptation to say,
well, 2 x -3 is -6,
so maybe 2 to the negative third power is -8,
but that's not the case.
And I'll explain in a future module
why we use this convention
but 2 to the negative 3rd power, it turns out,
is equivalent to 1/2 to the 3rd power.
So it turns out that the negative exponent,
what it does is it means to take the inverse of the base,
we'll call the number 2 as the base--
and take that to the positive version of the exponent.
And 1/2 to the third power?
Well, we already learned that's 1/2 x 1/2 x 1/2,
and that equals 1/8.
So we say 2 to the negative third power.
That didn't come out right.
2 to the negative third power is equal to 1/8.
Let's do another one.
Let's say 3 to the -2 power.
Once again, immediately when we see
that negative in the exponent, the easiest thing to do
is just immediately take the reciprocal of the base.
So we take 1/3.
And we raise that to the +2 power.
And that's easy now.
1/3 squared, well, that's equal to 1/9.
Let's do some more problems.
What if I had 2/3 to the negative third power?
Once again, just to make it simple, whenever I see
that negative in the exponent, I want to get rid of it.
So I immediately take the reciprocal of the base.
The reciprocal of 2/3 is 3/2 ,
and I raise that to the positive third power.
So what changed between the left and the right side?
The 2/3 I flipped,
and I turned the -3 into a +3.
And now this just becomes a Level one exponent.
This equals 3/2 x 3/2 x 3/2, and that equals 27/8.
So that's interesting.
2/3 to the -3 is equal to 27/8.
Let's do some more.
Let's do 4/7 to the -1.
Once again, we have a negative number in the exponent.
That's the same thing as taking the reciprocal of the base
and raising it to the positive exponent.
Well, 7/4 to the 1, any number to the first power
is just the same number.
It's equal to 7/4.
So when take it to the -1 power, all you're essentially doing
is getting the reciprocal of the number.
Let's do some more problems.
2 to the -5.
Once again, we take the reciprocal of 2,
and we say 1/2
and now that can be raised to the 5th power,
and that equals 1/2 x 1/2 x 1/2 x 1/2 x 1/2,
and that equals 1/32.
Another way we could have viewed 2 to the negative 5th
is that, 2 to the negative 5th,
we could have said that equals 1/2 to the 5th.
We know that 2 to the 5th is 32.
That would be the same thing.
Two ways to do it,
pretty much just changing the order of when you flip
versus when you actually calculate the exponent.
Let me do two or three more problems.
And after I write down each of these problems,
you might just want to pause it
and see if you can do the problem yourself,
and then compare your answer to mine.
So let's say I had -4 to the negative 3rd power.
Immediately, I like to get rid of the negative in the exponent,
and I know that that equals -1/4 to the 3rd power,
and that equals -1/4 x -1/4
x -1/4.
The negative times a negative is a positive,
but then we're multiplying that times another negative,
so we get a negative.
1 x 1 x 1 is 1.
4 x 4 is 16 x 4 is 64.
So it equals -1/64.
Let's do another problem.
Let me think of a good number.
8/9.
Let's make it negative.
-8/9 to the negative 2nd power.
Well, once again, that equals -9/8.
Notice, I immediately just took the reciprocal of the base
to the +2 power,
and now that equals -9/8 x -9/8.
A negative times a negative is a positive,
so we get 9 x 9 is 81/64.
I think you get the point now.
The only new thing we've learned, really, is that
when you have a negative exponent,
it's the same thing as taking the reciprocal of the base
and raising it to the positive exponent.
Hopefully, that last statement didn't confuse you more,
did more good than damage,
but I think you're ready to try some problems now.
Have fun.