so I want to talk to you a little bit about ,
and I have already cheated a little bit, and I started drawing,
I already make a slightly nice drawing, because I want to make sure that
the important thing is we can actually see them, and that is --it's pretty clear.
So, in the top left, I have a small vessel,
and it have the three layers, and in the middle is the lumen,
and on the outside is the --the outside.
So, this little white box I've drawn, I've tried to blow it up for you a little bit here,
so again, over on this side we have the lumen, just to orient you again,
and this is the outside of a blood vessel.
So, we know that a blood vessel have three layers and this particular blood vessel is--
actually, let me lable it, is a middle or large arteries.
so I'm specifically talking about  here.
And the reasons that this makes the differece, I'll point out specifically again,
but there're these green little coils I've drawn here, these little green squigglies,
and this is a little protein called the ,
and I specifically want to talk about these arteries, because
these large and middle arteries that have --in them, in the walls-- elastin,
are very very susceptible to atherosclerosis, this process.
And so, I've thought that it makes sense to point out just for you to know exactly
which vessels are being affected by this process.
So let's go through and --quckly refresh ourselves, and talk about three layers of the vessel,
we have the intima, the .
And I was writing 'T' for tunica.
And then --that's the innermost layer.
The middle layer right here, in red, is the ,
and remember that, because it's the middle layer, so media, middle.
And on the outside right here is the . Externa, kind of the external layer.
And sometimes you see that as , another word for it.
So these are the three layers, we know this.
And the way that atherosclerosis happens, now this is a process in --it's a,
it's a process that affects millions and millions of people.
The way this happens is that it usually affects these large vessels --large or middle arteries,
and actually these vessels just --to give you a little bit an orientation,
I'm talking about 1 mm size of vessels all the way about 25 mm in diameter.
So kind of a --kind of biggest vessels, that you could actually see with your naked eye,
this could be like the artery, that maybe-- maybe the aorta, the largest artery,
or could be an artery that goes up to my arm, the brachial artery.
So in here these large or middle size arteries fit in this category,
and they're affected by atherosclerosis.
So the first step in atherosclerosis, let's just jump and do it,
it's that you have an irritant, some irritant.
And that could be --I'm not talking about, maybe someone's annoying little brother or sister, annoying neighbour,
but some irritant like, let's say you have --here I'll draw in red-- a toxin from cigarrette smoke.
So let say you've got some toxin that's swimming through your blood vessels, and that could be an irritant.
Another irritant could be --so I'll put smoking up here for that--
another irritant could be, maybe having too much lipids, so maybe hyperlipidemia.
Hyperlipidemia.
And when I say lipid, I mean specifically fats and cholesterols.
So, you could have little droplets --it's showed a little yellow droplets, 'cuz I think yellow as fat,
of LDL, this is a protein. LDL stands for --actually I'll write that out--
Low Density --that's what the L dan D are--
Low Density Lipoprotein.
So this is basically something that carries fat and cholesterol around your blood.
So you could have too much of it. You could have too much LDL in your blood,
in the blood vessels, in the arteries.
And that could be an irritant.
Or it could be --maybe I'll use a dark-- maybe a white colour here,
maybe could be high blood pressure,
high blood pressure pushing out on these vessels, could be an irritant.
So any of these things could be an irritant, hyperlipidemia, smoking, or hypertension or high blood pressure.
Could be an irritant.
And what is being irritated?
What is the thing that is being irritated?
That's number two.
It's the layer of cells right here, these inner layer cells in the tunica intima.
and that layer itself we know as the endothelial layer.
So that's the layer that's being offended somehow, so it's being upset or angry.
It's getting upset at these irritants, so I'm going to show some unhappy faces here,
maybe some unhappy faces down here from the LDL,
maybe some unhappiness from that high blood pressure.
And right behind it, --just to orient you-- is the basement membrane,
but really again it's the endothelial cells that're being irritated.
Right, so that would be step two, is endothelial --actually leaving the same colour--
. This stop working the way they like to work,
in all, try to be a little bit more specific,
endothelial cells are basically a barrier, right?
they're creating a barrier between what is flowing through the blood and the wall itself,
right, they're the first thing that molecules and cells in the blood are gonna see.
And so, if you have endothelial disfunction, what you get is
that this barrier starts breaking down.
And so this barrier --let me erase some of this stuffs now, just to make some space,
we know that LDL is Low Density Lipoprotein, I'll erase that.
And I'll erase this white areas for the hypertension.
And I'll even erase that ciggarette smoke, the toxin.
and I'll leave the LDL for a second, you'll see why.
But please let me show you that these cells start getting unhappy,
and they start breaking down, and --I guess I'll erase a lot of it and I'll draw some of it back.
And what you get is something like this.
We've --We have, now, a breach. A breach.
So you have these cells here, but now they're letting stuff through.
And the stuff they get through, primarily --and this is of importance to us, is the LDL.
So even if something else was the irritant,
let's say cigarrete smoke was the major irritant here,
and you got endothelial disfunction from that,
the next step in atherosclerosis, step three, is LDL goes into --I'll just write--
into T. or tunica intima.
This is kind of the next major step, is that LDL decides that it wants to go inside,
it likes to be inside of this layer.
And so you got LDL hanging out over here --I'll just write LDL here, so you'll know what we're talking about.
So all this little molecule of LDL, which again, you bring with them a lot of fat and cholesterol,
and they're all now in this tunica intima layer.
So they're all within this tunica intima layer --let me try make that very clear,
all within this layer tunica intima.
So they're not usually there. And that's step three.
Now step four, really really interesting,
this is where things get really kind of wild,
is you have cells in your immune system that are right here, called
Macrophages.
and these macrophages, they have huge mouth,
and they're --actually macrophages really means 'big eater'.
So, macro-big, and 'phage' meaning to eat.
Macrophages actually swim through the blood, and they're patroling the blood,
almost like police officers,
and they sense that, "hey, something is not right with this wall, there's LDL in there"
and they go in pursuit --they go after that LDL.
And now they go into the wall.
So now you got LDL on the wall, you got macrophages on the wall,
and so I'm gonna draw these macrophages, it's not to scale, just again they're bigger than this.
But they're now in the wall, they're hanging out in this area, right.
And they start devouring, again they're big eaters.
So they start devouring, gobbling up all that fat.
So this is gonna get a little bit tricky, but let me try to sketch it out again up here for you.
These're gobbling up fat, and they get loaded with this little fat,
these little particles of LDL.
So this is now LDL that's inside of the macrophages, right?
and if you look through microscope, what this may look like?
is --you have to use your imaginaton here, but is seafoam.
So if you actually look --go out to the sea, you know, let's say you go to Mediteranean Sea.
And you look at seafoam, that's actually what it would look like, potentially.
That 's someone's thought anyway.
And so they called these cells, these macrophages that've gobbled up LDL,
and actually died, so these cells has now died.
I'll draw a little Xs, because it is so much have died.
These cells they called them .
Foam cells. I'll just write a little arrow here,
so you know which one I'm talking about. Foam cells.
So if you look in the tunica intima again, that's for all the action is, right?
this is --this is the important part here --I'll draw box around it.
That's kind of the central stage.
The LDL, the macrophages that chase down, now the dead foam cells,
are all sitting in here, in this lake of fat.
So now you got macrophages in step four --let me just make sure I catch up with our picture.
Macrophages and plus foam cells.
foam cells.
into tunica intima, right.
So now we're on the same page.
And this --this intima now, really, starts looking a lot like this.
Let me erase this, clean this up a little bit,
because it's getting quite a mess here, then you'd --you'd agree it needs a little cleaning up.
So let me erase all this stuff on the outside.
We know that LDL was in the blood, but it went into the intima, we know that.
So --so now you have, basically, this LDL, all of these molecules (...) is start merging,
into literally a lake. Think about it like a lake of fat.
and how disgusing about is that, right? Like a lake of lard, here, or fat, here.
It's your fat, or this person's fat.
And it's all, in this layer, called the tunica intima.
In fact, let me even draw another dead macrophage.
It's another foam cell, I'm making a foam cell out of this.
Looks like seafoam, maybe.
And so you have here a lake of LDL.
You have foam cells, and it's all sitting in the tunica intima.
And if you're actually to, let's say you're to fillet this cell open,
or this blood vessel open --let me to try to show what I mean.
If you're --let's say you have this blood vessel.
I'm drawing you very simply now, you know that that there're three layers,
it's not the one that I'm drawing there,
but let's imagine that you took a knife and you slice through it.
So now, you basically are looking at kind of just the inside of it.
Right, it's the inside of it.
What you would see is basically this giant streak of fat.
And this is kind of that lake, that I just showed you, right.
Now, looking at it lengthwise.
So this lake of fat is called the .
So if you open up a blood vessel, and look at it,
if this process has been going on, you might start seeing fatty streaks.
and so that's basically the first half of atherosclerosis.
So let's pick up there in the next video.
~o0o~