Let's review a little bit of all
we learned about titration
curves, and see if we can divine
any new information.
So let me draw a
couple of them.
I'll just do very simple
quick and dirty ones.
And these of course, the x-axis
is the amount of strong
acid you're adding.
In this case, it's my favorite
strong acid.
It's sodium hydroxide.
You're increasing the amount of
sodium hydroxide solution
in either case.
That's the titrator or I think
the word is titrand.
Or it also could be considered
the reagent.
And this is, of course,
the scale is pH.
Over here.
We'll call this 7.
Down here, 0.
And that's 1.
So I have some mystery acid
here, and it looks
something like this.
That as I increase my base,
my pH increases.
And then at some point
over there.
And then it levels off.
My pH is really high.
And you look at that one.
And then let me see,
I have another one.
And it look something
like this.
At some point, bam, it
just goes like that.
And then it goes like that.
So my question is if you look at
least two, first of all, is
one of them a strong
acid or weak acid?
Or is it one or the other?
And if you look at this,
you say, OK.
Let's look at the equivalence
points.
And the equivalence points
are the steepest
points on these curves.
On this one, the equivalence
point is right about there.
And remember, equivalence point
is the point at which
your hydroxide from your strong
base has essentially
sopped up all of the acid
in your solution.
Right?
So this is your equivalence
point right here.
Now in this case, we stopped
up all of the acid in our
solution at this equivalence
point.
And our pH 7.
So we've completely turned
into a neutral solution.
Because we know that we were
dealing with a strong acid.
So this is a strong acid.
Let me do a different color.
We were titrating
a strong acid.
How do we know that?
because at the equivalence
point, our strong base has
completely neutralized it.
There's nothing that's
really of basic
nature that's left over.
You do have the conjugate base
of the strong acid left over,
but the conjugate base
of a strong acid
really isn't basic.
If I have HCl and it
disassociates into hydrogen
and chloride-- and obviously,
it only exists in
hydrogen and chloride.
This form doesn't exist.
This isn't an equilibrium
reaction.
This is how it looks in
an aqueous solution.
You're like hey, I sopped up all
of this stuff once I'm at
my equivalence point.
Don't I have all of
these chloride
conjugate bases there?
Won't that make my pH go up?
Be more basic?
And I say, no.
Because the conjugate base of a
strong acid is pretty much a
neutral molecule.
It has no real basic
properties.
If it had some basic properties,
this would turn
into an equivalence.
You would actually have some
movement the other way.
But you don't.
If you stick a bunch of chloride
anions in water, it's
not going to start
creating hydrogen
chloride out of the blue.
So this has no basic
properties.
So once you have sopped up
all of the hydrogen,
your pH is at 7.
So if you look at the
equivalence point, pH at 7,
you have a strong acid.
Now in this situation, our
equivalence point--
we're at a higher pH.
I don't know.
Maybe that's a pH of 9.
So we sopped up all of the
acid, but we still have a
basic solution.
Or, just at that moment, we
still have a basic solution
before we continue to add even
more OH to the solution.
So what must have
been happening?
Well, this must be a weak acid,
because a weak acid, the
reaction looks like this.
HA and it's in equilibrium with
its conjugate base plus
some hydrogen ions.
As you continue to sop up this
and this, the concentration of
this base increases, right?
Your hydroxide from
your strong base
sops this stuff up.
The equilibrium goes more and
more to the right by Le
Chatelier's Principle
to make up for this
loss of hydrogen ions.
But the whole time that
equilibrium goes to the right,
and we're pulling these hydrogen
ions away, we're
increasing our concentration
of its conjugate base.
And the conjugate base for a
weak acid is a weak base.
But it has basic properties.
This is neutral.
It has no effect on pH.
This is a weak base.
It does affect on pH.
So at the equivalence point,
you've sopped up all of this,
and most of this.
And I mean, for all purposes,
all of it.
But you're still left
with a ton of this.
Essentially all of this, as many
moles of this have been
converted into this.
So at this point, let's say when
you started off, you had
A moles of this and B moles--
these were kind of the
original equilibrium
concentrations of this.
When you're done at the
equivalence point, you have
none of this, and then you
have B plus A of this.
Every mole of this has been
converted into at least 1 mole
of this, plus whatever you
had to begin with.
And because of that, you have
a basic equivalence point.
Your pH will be slightly
above 7.
Let's see if there's anything
else we can divine from--
especially this one here.
Let me write it down.
This is a weak acid.
Let me erase some of this.
It's getting messy.
Actually, I'll erase
all of this.
You know that we're titrating
with NaOH.
The hydroxide concentration is
going higher and higher.
But we know, for example,
that at this point--
let me write it right.
So OH minus is going up.
You can just view it-- sodium
hydroxide's what we're adding,
but sodium is really just what's
kind of carrying the
hydroxide before we put it into
the aqueous solution.
Once you go in there, the
sodium's kind of useless.
Similarly, if the conjugate--
well, I don't want to go into
that too much.
So we're adding hydroxide.
We get to any equivalence
point.
This is the point where
we have used up
all of our weak acids.
So let me write some
concentrations here.
Let's say at this point on the
left, right here, before I
started titrating anything,
my concentration of my
acid-- it was A.
And let's say my concentration
of my conjugate base--
Remember, this was in
equilibrium, so it's at B.
Now, at this point, remember.
I kept sopping up the hydrogen--
actually, I
shouldn't have erased that.
I shouldn't have erased
the actual reaction.
It's all in an aqueous
solution.
Equilibrium with H plus plus A
minus on an aqueous solution.
Now at this point, this is
some initial equilibrium.
We keep taking this up.
The reaction goes
to the right.
We keep producing more
of the A minus.
Essentially, by the time
we are here, our acid
concentration, let me
do that and green.
Our acid concentration
is essentially 0.
It might be some super small
negative number, but let's
just say for the sake of
simplicity, it's at 0 or very
close to 0.
What's our conjugate base
concentration going to be?
Let me do that in magenta.
Our conjugate base
concentration, and I know I'm
getting messy because I'm
overwriting this.
Well, every mole of this that
was moving forward in the
reaction turned into 1 mole of
this and 1 mole of that.
This stuff kept getting sopped
up by our titrator, our
reagent, but we ended up
with 1 mole of this so.
So we went from A moles
to 0 of our acid.
We went from B moles of our
conjugate base to B plus A
moles of our conjugate acid.
Interesting.
Now.
What can we do with this?
Well, if we can somehow figure
out the point along this curve
where we had an equal amount
of our acid and conjugate
base, there might be something
interesting
that we could do it.
And actually, I'll tell you
what's the interesting thing.
Let me write that the
Henderson-Hasselbalch equation.
I always have trouble
pronouncing the second L in
Hasselbalch, but I'm
doing my best.
But the Henderson-Hasselbalch
Equation tells us-- let me do
it down here.
Actually, I'm running
out of space.
I'll do it here.
The pH of-- and remember, this
is only true of a weak acid or
a weak base.
There is no equilibrium constant
for a strong acid or
strong base.
So you can only use
Henderson-Hasselbalch and what
I'm about to do now-- I'm going
to call it the half
equivalence point, and
I'm going to talk
about that a second.
You can only do this with a weak
acid or a weak base when
that's what you're actually
titrating.
Of course you're always
titrating with a strong acid
or strong base, but the solution
that you're trying to
figure out has to
be a weak one.
So that tells us that the pH
is equal to the pKa, or the
negative log of the acid
equilibrium constant, plus the
log of your conjugate base
concentration divided by your
conjugate acid concentration.
And we proved this a couple
of videos ago.
You essentially just take the
log on both sides of the
equilibrium equation
and you do a little
algebra and you get this.
Nothing fancy.
But what's interesting when
these two things are equal to
each other.
When the concentration of your
conjugate base is equivalent
to the concentration
of your weak acid.
Well then this whole thing
is going to be 1.
Right?
And what's the log of 1?
Well, 10 to the 0 power is 1.
So log base 10 of 1 is 0.
So this whole thing will be 0.
So that's interesting.
When you have your concentration
of conjugate
base is equal to your
concentration of your weak
acid, this whole term
turns into 0.
And then your pH is
equal to your pKa.
So if we can figure out the
point on this graph where our
concentration of our acid and
our conjugate base are equal,
and we figure out the pH of that
point, that point will
also tell us the pKa.
So if we don't know what acid
we're dealing with, all of a
sudden we'll be able to
figure out it's pKa.
And we'll know something
about that acid.
If we had a pKa table, hey, this
is ammonium, or whatever
we're dealing with.
So how can we figure out the
point at which these two
concentrations are equivalent?
What you do is you
just say, OK.
This is the equivalent point.
This is the point at
which we've run
out of our weak acid.
You go halfway to there.
This is called a half
equivalence point.
I'll write that down.
And you say, at this point,
they're roughly
equal to each other.
And the reason why say roughly
is because you say OK, at this
point, my concentration of
my acid is A over 2.
And my concentration of my
base, at this point-- I
started with B and A over 2 gets
more converted into my
conjugate base, so I have
B plus A over 2.
So you may say, hey, wait, I
still have a little bit more
of the base here.
Because I started with
some of the base.
And the reason why you can take
this as a point in which
they're equal is because this
term right here is very, very,
very small for the great
majority of acids.
And actually, when you're doing
an experiment like this,
it doesn't take long to just
go right past that point.
This is almost like your
experimental error.
It doesn't show up.
And if you don't believe me--
actually, let me just do a
little side there to make
you believe that.
So we know an equilibrium
constant is equal to your
concentration of hydrogen times
a concentration of your
conjugate base over
your concentration
of your weak acid.
Let's just do this
for ammonium.
The pKa for ammonium is 9.25.
That means that the Ka
for ammonium is 10
to the minus 9.25.
Right?
You could just take the reverse
log of both sides.
But what number is that?
10 to the minus 9.25.
is equal to 5.6 times 10
to the negative 10.
So that is equal to, roughly,
10 to the negative 10.
So if you just put some of this
into some concentration,
or you put some or your weak
acid into a solution and you
let it get to equilibrium--
If I just do a little algebra.
Your weak acid times your
equilibrium constant is equal
to your concentration of
your hydrogen times
your conjugate base.
Now, if they didn't have any
hydrogen or conjugate base to
begin with, every mole of this
disassociates into 1 mole of
that and 1 mole of this.
So these two things are going
to be equal, right?
So you could even say, it's
the same thing as the
concentration of your
weak base squared.
If you say, hey, this is the
same thing as A minus, they're
going to be equal.
So if you say that that is equal
to your concentration of
your acid times your equilibrium
constant, then you
say your conjugate base
concentration that
you start off with.
And this is all approximatating.
I'm just trying to show
you that your initial
concentration of your conjugate
base is much lower
than your initial concentration
of your
conjugate acid.
So it equals the square root of
your concentration of your
conjugate acid times the
square root of Ka.
In the case of ammonium, the
square root of this is what?
It's going to be like 2 point
something something times 10
to the minus 5 power.
So whatever your concentration
of your weak acid is, let's
say it's ammonium in this case,
you take the square root
of that and then you multiply
times something with a
negative 5 power to get the
concentration of your
conjugate base.
So this is much lower
than that.
These two numbers are much lower
than that number for
most weak acids.
So because of that, you can
ignore the amount of conjugate
base you started off with.
And so this point right here,
your half equivalence point,
you can pretty much assume that
your concentrations of
conjugate base and weak acids
are equivalent at that point.
And then by the
Henderson-Hasselbalch
Equation, this term right
here is going to be 1.
The log of 1 is 0.
And the pKa will be
equal to the pH.
So you measure the pH here and
say oh, that's the negative
log of my equilibrium
constant.
That will be my pKa.
And until you found out
something else that's
interesting about
your molecule.