in the last video we proved that
the sum of all of the positive integers, up to and including n
can be expressed as n(n+1)/2
and we proved that by induction
what I want to do in this video is show you that there is actually a simpler proof of that
but it's not by induction
so it wouldn't be included in that video, but I'll show you that it exists.
just so that you know that induction isn't the only way to prove it
so we defined that fuction s(n)
as the sum of all of the positive integers up to n including n
so this is equal to by definition
1+ 2+ 3 all the way to + (n-1) + n
so it's all the integers up to and including n
this is how we're defining it
well we can re-write it again
we can say that the sum S(n); we can write the same thing
but we can write it differently order
we can say that this is the same thing as n +( n -1 )+( n - 2 )
plus all the way down to + 2 + 1
well what does this do for us
we can actually add these two rows
if we add S(n) + S(n) we're going to get 2 times the sum
so we're just adding on the left
and then we can add on the right
so we're really just doing this sum twice
and what's interesting is how we're going to add it
we're going to add this term to this term; this term to this term
we're just trying to add these two things
we can pick any way we want to add them
(1 + n) is going to be( n + 1)
and then we're going to add 2 +( n - 1)
so what's that?
Let me write that over here
2 +( n - 1)
is the same things as 2 + n - 1,
which is the same thing as n + 1
so this is also going to be n+1
and this term over here, 3 + n - 2
or n - 2 +3
that again is going to be n +1
and you're going to do that for every term until you get over here
n -1 +2; that's also going to be n+1
and then finally you have n+1 right over here
so what's this whole sum going to be
well how many of these n + 1's do we have?
well we have n of them
for every term in each of these sums
So there's 1, 2,3 count all of the way to n
So you have n of these n+1's
so if you add something to its self n times
So you really have, this is exactly equivalent to
n times (n+1)
so two times the sum of all of the positive integers
up to an including in is going to be equal to n(n+1)
so if you divide both sides by 2 we get an expression for the sum
so the sum of the integers is going to be equal to
n(n+1) over 2
so here's a proof where we didn't have to use induction
it's really a pure algebraic proof