Let's define some sets.
Let's say the set A is composed of
the numbers 1, 3, 5, 7 and 18
Let's say the set B is composed of 1, 7, and 18
and let's say that the set C is composed of 18, 7, 1, and 19.
What I want to start thinking about in this
video is the notion of a subset.
The first question is: Is B a subset of A?
What does a subset mean?
It's a subset if every member of the set
is also a member of the other set.
We can write that B is a subset of A, this is the notation.
B is a subset of A.
B is a subset, let me write that down.
B is subset of A.
Every element of B is a member of A.
We can go even further and say B is a "strict" subset of A
because B is a subset of A, but it does not equal A
which means that there are things in A that are not in B.
So we could go even further and say that B is a strict, or sometimes a "proper" subset of A.
You can almost imagine that this is a less than or equal sign, and then you cross out the equal part of the sign.
So this means a strict subset
which means that everything that is in B is a member of A, but everything that is in A is not a member of B.
B is a strict subset or proper subset.
For example, we can write that A is a subset of A.
In fact, every set is a subset of itself because everyone of its members is a member of A.
We cannot write that A is a strict subset of A.
This right over here is false.
Let's give ourselves a little bit more practice.
Can we write that B is a subset of C?
Let's see. C contains 1, 7, 18, so every member of B is indeed a member of C
so this right here is true.
Can we write that C is a subset of A?
Every element of C needs to be in A.
A has 18, 7, 1, but it does not have 19,
so once again, this is false.
We could write that B is a subset of C, or we
could even write that B is a strict subset of C.
We can also reverse the way we write this, and then we're really just talking about supersets.
We could reverse this notation and
say that A is a superset of B.
This is just another way of saying that B is a subset of A.
The way you can think about this is
A contains every element that is in B.
It might contain more or it might contain every element.
You can view this as the equal symbol
if this was greater or equal to (≥)
they're not quite exactly the same thing
but we know already that we can also
write that A is a strict superset of B
which means that A everything that B has, and then some.
A is not equivalent to B.
So hopefully this familiarizes you with the notions of
subsets and supersets and strict subsets.