I have triangle ABC here
And in the last that we did started to explore
some of the properties of points that are on angle bisectors
And now why I wanna do this with you
is just to see what happens
when we apply some of those ideas
to triangles or the angles in triangles
So let's bisect this angle right over here, angle B, A, C
and let me draw an angle bisector
So the angle bisector might look something
And I wanna make sure I get that angle right into pretty close
So that looks pretty close
So that's the angle bisector
Let me call this point right over here
I don't know
I could call this I could call this point D
And then let me draw another angle bisector,
the one that bisects angle ABC
So let me just draw this one
It looks it might look something like that right over there
And I can maybe call this point E
So AD bisects angle BAC
and BE bisects angle ABC
So the fact that this green line AD
bisects this angle right over here
That tells us that this angle must be equal
To that angle right over there
They must have the same measures
And the fact that this bisects this angle, angle ABC,
tells us that the measure of this angle, angle ABE,
must be equal to the measure of angle EBC
EBC
Now we see clearly that they have intersected
at a point inside of the triangle right over there
So let's call that point
Let me call that I just for fun
I'm skipping a few letters,
but it will be it's a useful letter that based on
what we are going to call this in very short order
There's some interesting things we know about I
I sits on both of these angle bisectors
and we saw in the previous video that
any point that sits on an angle bisector
is equidistant from the 2 sides of that angle
So for example, I sits on AD so it's going to be equidistant
from the 2 sides of angle BAC
So this is one side right over here
This is one side right over there
And then this is the other side right over there
So because I sits on AD,
we know that these 2 distances are going to be the same
assuming this is the shortest distance between I and the sides
And we've also shown in the previous video that
when we talk about the distance between a point and a line,
we're talking about the shortest distance
which is the distance you get if you draw a perpendicular
So that's why I drew the perpendiculars right over there
And we could even let's label this some
This is could be point F
This could be point G right over here
So because I sits on AD, sits on this angle bisector,
we know that IF, we know that IF is going to be equal to,
is going to be equal to IG
Fair enough
Now I also sits on this angle bisector
It also sits on BE which says that
it must be equidistant from A
the distance to AB must be the same as I is distanced to BC
I's distance to AB,
we already just said is this right over here, it's IG
But we also know that that distance
must be the same as the distance between I and BC
So if I draw, if I draw another perpendicular right over here,
and let's say I call this point
Let's see I haven't used H right over here
This distance must be the same as this distance
because I sits on this bisector
So IG must be equal to IH
IG must be equal to IH
But IF is also equal to IG, so we can also say that IF,
I mean if IF is equal to IG is equal to IH,
we also know that IF, IF is equal to IH
Pretty much common sense!
If this is equal to that, that is equal to that,
then these 2 have to be equal to each other
But if I is equidistant from 2 sides of an angle,
this is the 2nd part of what we proved in the previous video
If you have a point that is equidistant from 2 sides of an angle,
then that point must sit on the angle bisector for that angle
So with this right here tells us,
tells us that I must be on angle bisector
I is on angle bisector, angle bisector sector of angle ACB
'cause it's equidistant to these 2 sides of angle ACB
And what we have just shown is,
is that there's a unique point inside the triangle
that sits on all 3 angle bisectors
It's not always obvious that if you took 3 lines,
in fact normally, if you took 3 lines
are not going to intersect in one point
2 lines is very reasonable thing to do,
but 3 lines not always gonna intersects in one point,
but once again, let me saw with the circumcenter
where we took the perpendicular bisectors of the side
That was pretty neat that they intersected in one point
Now it's also cool that we're showing that
the angle bisectors all intersect in one unique point
I is on the angle bisector of ACB,
so the angle the bisector of ACB will look something like this
Will look something like this
And this angle right over here is
going to be congruent to this angle right over there
So we have just shown that if you draw
If you take the 3 angle bisectors of a triangle,
it will intersect in a unique point right over there
that sits on all 3 of them so would
It seems worthwhile that we should call this something special
And we do!
And it's why I called it I
We call I the incenter, the incenter
The incenter of triangle ABC, ABC
And you're gonna see the 2nd why it's called the incenter
When we talk about the circumcenter,
that was the center of a circle that was
that could be circumscribed about the triangle
I, we'll see in about 5 seconds,
is the center of a circle that could be
that is circums that is
that can be put inside the triangle
that's tangent to the 3 sides
And how do we construct that?
Well, we have just established that
I is equidistant to each of the sides,
that this length is equal to that length is equal to that length
So what happens if you set up a circle with I as the center
that has a radius equal to the distance
between I and anyone of the sides which is equal,
that has a radius, that has a radius equal to IF, IG or IH?
Well then you're going to have a circle
that looks something like
You're going to have a circle that looks something like this
You're going
Let me draw it a little bit better than that
I don't have
Rarely, you can imagine
This is my best attempt to draw a circle
This circle right here that has the radius
equal to the distance between I and any of the sides,
which we've already established as being equal,
we see they're sitting inside of the circle
So why don't we call this an incircle!
So circle I
Remember you label circles usually with the point at the center
Circle I is the incircle, incircle of triangle ABC
And of course, the radius of circle I so we could call,
we could call this length R
Let's say R is equal to IF which is equal to IH
which is equal to IG, is equal to IG
We can call that length the inradius
And it make sense because it's inside
When we had
When we were talking about the intersection of
the perpendicular bisectors, we had our circumcenter
because that was the center of a circle
that is circumscribed about the triangle
Now we're taking the intersection of the angle bisectors
and then, using that we're able to define a circle
that is kind of within the triangle,
and that whose sides are tangent to the circle
And since it's inside it, we call this incircle
We call the intersection of the angle bisectors the incenter
And we call this distance right over here the inradius