Identify 15 eights, or 15 over 8, as a proper or an improper fraction.
or an improper fraction.
So this is actually just a good review of proper and improper fractions.
And there's a pretty easy way to identify them.
You have a proper fraction if your numerator --
so this right here is your numerator -- the number on top.
if your numerator ...
Let me just label them
numerator and denominator ... de nom in a tor
You have a proper fraction if your numerator
if your numerator is less than your denominator
and if you don't have a proper fraction
you have an improper fraction.
Improper fraction is if your numerator is greater
than or equal to your denominator
And over here, actually, all the numbers are positive,
But if you had some negative numbers here, you would actually say
the absolute value of numerator is lesser than
the absolute value of the denominator, for a proper fraction
And the absolute value of numerator is greater than or equal
to the absolute value of the denominator for an improper fraction
So let me just write that down
just to be a little bit more particular here.
Because we could have negative numbers in either the numerator or the denominator.
Anyway, let's go back to this problem
15 is clearly greater than or equal to 8
So 15 is greater than or equal to 8,
so we are dealing with an improper fraction.