[MUSIC PLAYING]
What I want to do in this video
is talk a little bit
about traditional IRA's.
And IRA stands for Individual
Retirement Account.
And the focus in this video
is the traditional IRA.
You'll hear of other types of
IRA's, especially Roth IRA's
and SEP IRA's, but this is
only on traditional.
The gist of all of them is
really it's the governments
way of encouraging you to save
for your retirement.
But they all have slightly
different details, so I'm just
going to focus on the
traditional right now.
So let's say we are
in the year 0.
That's right now instead
of year 0, let
me write right now.
And you have two options, you
could take advantage of the
traditional IRA, so this
is the IRA scenario.
And this is the no
IRA scenario.
Now, an IRA allows you to put up
to a certain amount of your
income aside.
Now depending on your age and
what year it is, that amount
will change.
But in 2010 that number
is $5,000 if you're
under the age of 50.
And it's $6,000-- this is for
an individual, not for a
family-- and it's $6,000 if
you're over the age of 50.
I guess the rationale was
probably gee, if you're over
the age of 50, you better save
even more for your retirement,
which might only be 10
or 15 years away.
So they give a little bit more
leeway for over the age of 50.
So let's say we're under the
age of 50 and we take full
advantage of this IRA, so
we set aside $5,000.
Here we set aside nothing.
Now in the very short term,
the advantage is that this
$5,000 of our income
will not be taxed.
So let's say that I'm in
the 32% tax bracket.
Let me write that on the
side because it will
apply to both scenarios.
32% tax bracket today, because
I'm making some good money.
So if on the $5,000 only-- I'm
only talking about the taxes
on the $5,000, you're going to
have to pay taxes above and
beyond that on the rest of your
income-- but today, I'm
going to pay zero taxes
on that $5,000.
So zero taxes on the $5,000.
Now if I don't set aside that
$5,000 into an IRA, then I
will have to pay taxes
on that $5,000.
So I'm going to have to pay
$5,000 times 32%, which is
equal to what-- I'll just get
the calculator out-- so you
get $5,000 times 0.32 is equal
to $1,600 in taxes.
So I'm going to pay $1,600
in taxes today.
So in the year that I actually
made that $5,000.
Now I can't set aside $5,000
if I made less than $5,000.
It's always the lower of your
income or these IRA limits.
And, of course, you're going
to pay, even in this
situation, let's say you made
a $100,000, when you put the
$5,000 aside, you're still
going to have to
pay taxes on $95,000.
In this situation, where you
didn't put the $5,000 aside,
you're going to have to
pay taxes on $100,000.
So you're going to pay
taxes on the extra
$5,000, which is $1,600.
Now, let's say in either
situation with that $5,000 you
want to buy and sell some
securities or some
investments.
So let's say right after you put
it in the IRA account, so
now everything is sitting in
our IRA account, all of our
transactions are sitting in this
special IRA account right
here, where we can actually buy
and sell investments and
trade them, but we can't cash
them in and turn them into
cash and then spend
it on a new car or
something like that.
So and if we did do that before
the age of 59 and 1/2,
we'd have to pay a penalty.
So let me write that down.
You might immediately say hey,
gee, this is a good deal.
Why doesn't everyone
always do it?
Well the answer is, when I pull
it out before 59 and 1/2,
I pay a penalty.
Let me write this down, because
that's important to
keep in mind.
Pay penalty and taxes if
withdrawn before 59 and 1/2.
And once again, this is
the traditional IRA.
The Roth IRA, for example, is a
little bit more flexible on
the actual principal amount that
you put into the account.
But we're just dealing with the
traditional, so this is an
important thing to
keep in mind.
This is kind of the tradeoff
that you're giving.
So the government is saying,
hey, I'm getting you an
incentive to put this aside, and
I really want to make sure
that you leave this aside until
you are ready to retire.
So you don't get tempted when
you see a nice sports car to
cash in your IRA and use it,
because you're going to have
to pay a penalty.
But as long as you don't
actually withdraw it and turn
into cash, you can actually
buy and sell
securities within that IRA.
So let's say as soon as you
put that $5,000, you buy
$5,000 of stock A.
Here we don't have $5,000
anymore, we only have $3,400
of our original amount.
So we buy $3,400 of stock A.
And let's say, I don't know,
10 years in the future--
that's going to be in either
situation-- let's say that
stock A has doubled.
So in 10 years and you sell
it, you have $10,000 here.
You have $10,000
from sale of A.
It's doubled.
Here it's doubled, but you only
had $3,400 of stock A, so
now that $3,400 is
worth $6,800.
So you have $6,800
from sale of A.
And let's say you want to put
that into another stock.
So let's say you put that
all into stock B.
And I'm painting a very rosy
picture, you can't always
ensure that stocks
will double.
And then so you buy $10,000
in this situation.
$10,000 of B and well,
I'll hold off there.
So you buy $10,000 of B.
And here you might say oh, I'm
going to buy $6,800 of B, but
because you are not operating
within an IRA account, you're
going to have to pay taxes on
the capital gains from this
right here.
So capital gains are gains made
from capital investments.
In this case, the capital
investment is
investing in stocks.
And since you owned your stock
for more than one year, you at
least will only have to pay
long-term capital gains, which
tends to be lower than
short-term capital gains.
So in this situation, you
made $3,400 profit.
You're going to have to
pay 15% capital gains.
Times 15%.
Let's get the calculator
out again.
So $3,400 times 0.15.
It's $510, you're going
to have to pay $510.
So you take your $6,800,
pay $510 to the IRS.
You're going to be
left with $6,290.
Remember, the reason why you
have to pay taxes is this is
not operating inside
of an IRA.
Here you are operating inside
of an IRA, so you don't have
to pay taxes.
Now let's say you invest in
stock B and then over the next
10 years, stock B
also doubles.
So stock B is now worth $20,000
and you sell it
from sale of B.
And once again it's sitting
inside of your IRA, so you
don't have to pay any
capital gains on it.
Now, in this situation, you use
that $6,290 to also invest
in stock B and, after 10 years,
stock B doubles, so it
is now $12,580.
But once again, it's sitting
outside of your IRA, you have
to pay 15% capital gains.
You had a $6,290
gain times 15%.
Let's see what that is.
Let's get the calculator.
Where's my calculator?
There it is.
So you have $6,290 times
15% is equal to $943.
And let me take that from
my $12,580 minus 943.5.
So I have $11,636.
Let's say 20 years have passed,
we're now over the age
of 59 and 1/2, we can now
withdraw from our IRA.
Now, of course, this situation,
this is cash that
we have. We can do
anything with it.
Maybe we're now over 60 years
old, this could be used for
our retirement for our
everyday expenses.
Now this money that was sitting
in an IRA, now that
we're over the age of 60, or
over 59 and 1/2, if you want
to be particular.
Now that we're over 60 we can
withdraw the IRA without
paying any penalty, but we
will have to pay taxes.
So we're going to withdraw, no
penalties, but we will have to
pay taxes, but the huge
advantage here is once we're
over 60, we're probably earning
less money, so the
actual tax bracket
that we're in is
probably going to be lower.
So let's say we're in
a 25% tax bracket.
Remember, when we first made
that $5,000, we were in a 32%
tax bracket, because we were
this young gun at the peak of
his or her career making
a lot of money.
Now we're making less money,
we're starting to live off of
our savings.
So we have to pay 25%
income tax on it.
So if we pay 25% on $20,000--
Remember, now we're actually
withdrawing it.
We're actually putting it into
our checking account so we can
spend it for living
or whatever we
want to do with it.
So 25% of $20,000 is equal
to $5,000 in taxes.
So we will be left with $15,000
to do anything that we
want with it.
Now, compare this.
This is $15,000 versus
$11,636.
And everything we did was
completely identical, except
for over here we took
the $5,000 and
invested within an IRA.
Here, we took the $5,000, we
had to pay taxes on it.
Then we invested it in the exact
same way-- we actually
made very good stock
investments in both
situations-- and we ended
up with a significant
less amount of money.
I mean, this is a $15,000 verses
$11,000, that's almost
a-- what is that?-- a
30-something percent
difference in the total amount
of money we have.
And not only that, but this tax
we have to pay, this is
only a situation where you
have a 25% tax rate.
When you're retired, you might
even have a lower tax rate
than that, and it's deferred
a good bit.
But the real thing to think
about is just, 20 years in the
future, you're sitting on
$15,000, versus, if you didn't
participate in an IRA, you're
sitting on only
a little over $11,500.
And of course, the main tradeoff
here is that in the
IRA situation, you really
couldn't touch your money.
So if you had an emergency, and
you have to withdraw the
money, you would have had
to pay penalties on it.
[MUSIC PLAYING]