We define the equation of the plane containing the straight line that goes the equation, right over here
and this plane has to be perpendicular to the plane containing the straight lines x/3 = y/4 = z/2 and
also it has the line x/4 = y/2 = z/3.
Now just to visualize this properly, let me draw the planes. So the first plane in question that we
defined the equation of, let me draw it, let me draw it like this.
I am going to try and do this problem using vector notations
because it is easier in my mind to manipulate vectors in a way that you can find
perpendicular vectors and equations of planes...There's other ways that you can do this problem.
SO we define the equation of this plane right here.
Now we know this plane contains this line and this line, if we look over here, contains this point (0,0,0)
If x, y and z all equal to 0 then all sides of this equation are zero. So it contains
the point (0,0,0) or you can view it as if it contains the position vector (0,0,0)
and it also contains the point (2,3,4) because if x=2, y=3 and z=4
then all of these are going to be equal to 1.
So it also contains the point where the position vector, we can say, (2,3,4)
So if we wanted to draw this line, 2 points specify the line so this line would look
like that. But if wanted to look at a vector that this plane contains, it would be the vector
that goes from (0,0,0,) to (2,3,4) which really is the position vector (2,3,4)
and I am gonna write it in the (i,j,k) notation just to make it clear that this is a vector.
So this vector that lies in the plane in question is the vector 2i +3j + 4k, i just wrote it
in the unit vector notation and will call this the vector a. Vector a is equal to that
and I will write a over here. Now we need to figure out the equation of this line
and the best way to do it, is if I can find another vector in this plane
then I can find a normal vector in this plane and then using a normal vector
and some arbitrary other vector in this plane, I can then figure out the equation of this line
because the normal vector dotted that arbitrary other vector has to be equal to zero.
Now if none of that makes sense, maybe as we go through this problem, it will make more sense.
Now what I am gonna do is use these other vectors that are implicitly defined by these lines to
figure out another vector in this plane over here. So let me draw
what I am talking about. So let me draw this other plane and I will draw it in white. And this other
plane also contains (0,0,0). Actually both of these lines contain (0,0,0).
So let me draw it over here. I think what I just said, if I do step by step
it will make a lot more sense. So the other plane, that one comes vertically over this plane and it
goes vertically below as well. And we see here that the plane that contains these two lines
is perpendicular to this, they are perpendicular to each other. Now this blue line over here contains
the point (0,0,0) and the point (3,4,2), same logic that we took to get to this point over here.
If this is (3,4,2) they all equal 1, the equality holds.
So let me just draw some arbitrary place, so (3,4,2). Now let me be clear,
we havent even defined the coordinate axes, we do not really know what angle we are looking at it from,
this is only for visualization purposes. So this line right over here,
I can draw will look something like this. It would look something like that.
It sits on that white plane. Let me do the same thing for this magenta line.
The magenta line also contains the point (0,0,0) but it also contains the point (4,2,3)
SO let me just draw it over here.
SO, (4,2,3), so that's the magenta line.
You wouldn't even see it if this was transparent, it would just keep going down like that.
Now, I am gonna try to explain how I am gonna tackle this problem again.
I am going to use vectors to find, that are implicitly defined by this blue line and this magenta line.
I am gonna take a cross product of those two vectors to find a vector that is normal to this entire
white plane and that vector has to sit in this perpendicular plane, and then I can
use that vector and vector a to figure out a normal vector for this plane and then I will be able to
figure out the equation of this plane.
So let me just do it. So what's a vector?
What are the two vectors that sit in this white plane? Well the point (0,0,0)
the position vector (0,0,0) and the position vector (4,2,3) is in this plane
so the vector p = 4i + 2j + 3k is also in this white plane.
I am really just subtracting this position vector from that position vector to get this
position vector, which clearly sits in this plane.
This vector starts from origin, goes to (4,2,3), this plane contains the origin
is clearly sitting in this plane, and by that same logic, I can figure out a vector, actually the position
vector itself that sits on this plane. I will call that c= 3i + 4j +2k. The
fact that everything is at the origin kinda simplifies everything.
The position vectors themselves sit on the plane.
If this wasnt sitting on the origin, we wouldn't have been able to do that.
We would have had to subtract between these two vectors or between two other points
to actually get vectors on this plane. But with that out of the way, I could take the cross
product of b and c and that will give us some vector that is perpendicular to both b and c
which means it is perpendicular or it is normal to this entire white plane
which means it must sit in this yellow plane. So I am gonna find a normal vector in the yellow plane,
just like that.
Lets call that vector d. SO the cross product of b and c is just, this is how I remember it.
the determinant, you take i, j, k, it has been discussed in a lot more depth in linear algebra.
playlist. The determinant of that. The next row is the determinant of vector b so it 4, 2 and 3. And
then the next row is that of vector c, so it is 3,4 and 2
and so this is going to be equal to, let's think about that.
So for i, cross out that column and that row. SO its 2 times 2 minus 3 times 4
SO that's 4 minus 12. So its -8i minus, remember we have to swap signs, plus-minus-plus
when you are taking the determinant.
So you ignore the j, so its 4 times 2 = 8 minus 3 times 3 which is -1.
So this would be a -1 here but there is already a negative here so its a +1j.
And then finally the k, you cross out that column.
4 times 4 is 16. 16 -6 =10. So plus 10. Let me be sure I got that correct.
So the first one, I always have to make sure, so i I got yup, 4-12 = -8 and negative j ...
4 times 2 is 8 minus 9 = -1 but j has a negative so that's right.
And then k, 4 times 4 is 16. 16 -6 = 10. So that looks right. So plus...plus 10k.
So this vector right here is the vector d.
I just figured it out. Now if we take the cross product of d with vector a
the vector that was....you can kinda view it as lying along this line over here, then we will
get a vector that is normal to this plane.
We can call that vector n, for normal, that is normal to this yellow plane
that will actually sit on this white plane.
So lets figure it out, we will see in a few steps, probably in the next video why is that
actually useful. So lets take, lets find what is d cross a...
this is equal to our normal vector which is = same thing. i..j...k. We are gonna take d
which is -8, 1, 10 and take the cross of that and vector a which is 2,3,4.
and we will get, actually, I will continue this in the next video so that I do not make these videos
too long.