[piano music]
We're looking at the famous sculpture called
"The Dying Gaul" in the Capitoline Museum in Rome
and this is a copy of a sculpture that dates from
the third century B.C. - the original.
So this is a Roman copy of an ancient Greek original.
But a Greek sculpture that would have actually come originally from Pergamon,
on the coast of what is now Turkey.
Right, in one of the areas that was a Greek colony...
and it was to commemorate an important battle over a group
that the Greeks would have looked at as barbarians.
It's interesting because in earlier Greek history,
if this Gaul was to be represented as defeated,
he would have been represented as a barbarian,
as somebody who was inherently less than the Greeks,
and although I think that you can still make the argument that that's the case
if you look at his hair - it's roughly handled, his face - his brow
is large, his nose is not as idealized as
the Greeks might have represented themselves,
nevertheless we see his pain.
We do. In images of death from the Classical period,
in the archaic period,
we get sometimes that archaic smile,
or a sense of... I don't want to say peacefulness,
but a lack of expression... a kind of nobility...
something that transcendes that moment of death,
and something that is eternal
and represents perhaps the heroic.
So that's interesting, but that would be the Greeks
representing themselves, but here, because perhaps
we're seeing a kind of a lesser being, not a Greek,
somebody outside the Greek culture, there is a
willingness to represent in a sense that pain, that suffering,
and that weakness, but also there is a kind of nobility here.
That interesting emotion was very typical of the Hellenistic period.
So this is a late period.
...move away from that classical period of the fifth century, the 400s,
of that interesting and ideal figures,
figures that transcend the everyday, turn interest
in figures that are older, figures that display emotion,
figures that are fully human in a way.
Yeah, that's right. And this is an extraordinarily
human rendering of something
that is losing his power.
He's fallen, he's been wounded, you see the broken sword,
the wound in his rib cage... and the horns
that have been dropped, perhaps he was a herald as well,
or this a heralding.
He's falling, he's about to lose his strength.
We've got have a real certain moment of time here.
A kind of transitional moment...
We feel him falling to the ground.
But even as we feel that, we feel the
original power of that body,
the strength of those arms.
But that's failing.
And it is a really tragic moment.
It is. It's that beautiful athletic body that
is now defeated by imminent death.
That's what makes it so poignant.
There is this real empathy that exists there
and it really is characteristic of that late
Greek... that Hellenistic moment.
[piano music]