so lets define some variables here
so lets let a=abby's earnings and
lets let b=ben's earnings
than they tell us how these earnings relate they first
tell us that together they earned 50$ so that statement can be
converted mathamaticly into, well together that means
the sum of the 2 eannings so a+b needs to be equal to $50
abby's+ben's earnings equals $50
and then the tell us abby earned 10 dollars more than ben
so we can translate that into abby is equal to
or abby's earning is equal to ben's earnings plus 10
abby earned 10 dollars than ben
so we have a system of 2 equations
and accualy 2 unknowns and then they say
how much did each earn so to do that
and they want us to solve this graph
so there are multiple ways to do it but
we will do what they want us to do.
Let me draw some axis over here
and it'll be in the first quadrant
scince we are dealing with earnings.
niether of the earn earnings can be negative
and let me just define the vertical axis
as abby's axisor the abby's earnings axis.
and let me define the horizontal axis as Ben's axis or Ben's
earnings axis.And let me just graph each of these equations
and to do that i'm going to take this first equation
and im going to put it in the equivalent of