So this is an ancient ne...
and it tells of the God of the underworld, the god of the Death
who is taking Persefony into the Underworld to be his wife against her will
sometimes his is the rape of Persefony
the thing that gets me more than anything is the look on her face
kind of crazed, terror
you can just feel it, her mouth, her eyes, her brows pushing together
how hard she is pushing away
how desperate she feels to get away
I mean, it's a horrible moment. Man: It is.
Well look on his face, I'm reading as responding directly physicly to the pressure of her hand
but also as a kind of power of amusement
Woman: I see glee, almost, as a in a terrbile way that makes it so much more terrible
look what I got
She is also
she has no chance
look at the way that his hands press into her thigh
you feel his force
you can see the elascicity of her flesh
and you forget this is stone
You feel he's striding forward. You feel him pulling her towards him.