Around 600 BC lived Thales of Miletus,
widely regarded
as the first Greek philosopher,
as he was the first to give a purely natural
explanation of the phenomena he observed.
A key observation he made was
that certain stones –
such as amber – when rubbed against fur,
would exhibit a strange property.
The amber seemed to emit an invisible force
which would attract small fibers.
He assumed this rendered the amber magnetic,
another force he observed
when playing with lodestones,
which are naturally occurring magnets.
Many after him observed
that contact or friction
with fur seemed to create an imbalance.
Something was pulled from the fur
and transferred onto other objects.
Now, not only did this result in
a small attractive or repulsive force,
but also in the potential
for shocks to occur.
Once the discharge occurred,
the force disappeared.
So the shock was some form of discharge
which reversed the imbalance
created by the friction.
Throughout history, we were also
fascinated with lighting bolts –
nature's most passionate displays
of power and aggression.
Most cultures assumed this was a divine force,
outside the reach of human hands,
and was therefore reserved for the gods.
Up until the 17th century, our descriptions of it
varied from an invisible, intangible, imponderable agent –
or even threads of syrup
which elongate and contract.
And it was Benjamin Franklin who, in 1752,
set out to prove that there was a connection
between lightning and these
tiny shocks due to friction
In a famously dangerous experiment,
done alone with his son,
he led a kite into a thunderstorm.
And near the the bottom,
where the thread was wet,
he tied an iron key.
And after some time, he brought
his knuckle up to the key,
and experienced a series of small shocks --
identical to the ones created
by contact with fur.
This showed that, indeed, lightning was simply
the same thing as these household shocks,
but on a massive scale.
And at this time, people had begun
to divide materials into two categories.
One were objects which would allow
or accept discharge such as gold or copper
which we call 'electrical conductors.'
And interestingly, these materials are also
generally good at conducting heat.
Number 2 were objects which would
not allow this discharge –
such as rubber – or electrical 'insulators'.
These materials also seem to
insulate the transfer of heat.
And we also began trying to measure
this force that Thales had encountered.
One way to do this was to suspend
a piece of spongy plant,
called a pith ball, by a thread.
And when we rubbed an insulator against fur
and brought it near the pith ball,
it would pull on it,
causing a deflection.
If we added more objects,
we noticed this deflection increased
due to a greater pulling force.
We also noticed that the shape
of insulators made a difference.
Large, thin insulators seemed
to exhibit a much stronger force.
And amazingly, it was found that conductors
such as copper wire
would transmit this pulling
effect over a distance.
This was demonstrated
by running a long wire
between the pith ball
and the charged insulator.
When the object was brought near the wire,
it pulled through the wire
and deflected the pith ball instantly.
When we later touch the wire with our finger,
a discharge occurs and the pulling stops
and the ball is released.
Immediately, people began speculating
that this could be the future
of optical telegraphs.
And in 1774, French inventor
George-Louis Le Sage,
was one of the first on record
to actually set up this idea.
He sent messages through
an array of 26 wires –
each wire representing
a letter of the alphabet.
When a discharge occurred at one end,
the pith ball would move at the other.
The trouble with this telegraph
was that it only extended between
the 2 rooms of his house.
The power of the deflection was small
and difficult to work with.
Though at the time, people were investigating
techniques for generating larger charge differences,
in order to amplify the force involved.
One improvement, popularized
by Alessandro Volta 1 year later,
was an easy way of generating
discharges on demand.
It was based on the idea
that a charged insulator
could induce or transfer a charge
onto a nearby conducting plate.
One needed to merely bring
the metal plate close to the insulator
which would pull on the charge
distribution in the metal plate,
resulting in an imbalance,
or electrical 'tension', in the metal plate.
Then one could bring their finger
to the plate, and a discharge would occur.
Then the plate is pulled away,
using an insulating handle,
and an excess charge would remain
trapped in the plate.
The plate could then be discharged at will,
simply by touching it to a conductor such as a finger.
And amazingly, this process can be repeated many times
without recharging the insulating plate.
We could then generate
many small discharges at will.
And by now, Benjamin Franklin
was focused on finding out how to trap –
or store up these discharges.
At this time, he still assumed that electricity
was some sort of invisible fluid,
since he knew it could
travel through water.
So he assumed that water inside an insulator
could hold electricity.
What we now call the 'Leyden jar'
was a glass jar with water inside,
and a metal probe running out the top.
Franklin also wrapped the outside
in a conductive metal.
When he brought a charged conductor
towards the top probe,
a discharge would occur
and stay trapped in the jar.
More importantly, was that the jar
could be charged multiple times.
Each spark would amplify
the charge separation –
or electrical tension – inside the jar.
A good analogy is
to think of the jar as a balloon,
and each discharge as a short jolt of water.
And after hundreds of iterations,
the tension becomes massive.
And to release the charge, he simply touched
the outside conductor to the top probe.
A large discharge occurred.
Franklin improved the design over time,
eventually realizing that the charge
was not stored in the water – but the glass.
The water was merely a conductive path
from the probe to the jar.
Today, we would call
the Leyden jar a 'capacitor'
or 'charge-storing device.'
And when he chained many jars together,
he found he could increase the capacity even more
and release deadly bolts of electricity.
And over the years, people focused on
more effective ways of building up charge –
using friction machines –
which could then be stored in capacitors
and released as spectacular displays
of man-made lightning.
And over the next 50 years,
people tried to design systems
for sending sparks across greater distances,
using longer wires
and more powerful discharges.
However, sending electrostatic discharges
as a communication method
seemed clumsy, archaic, and was no improvement
over the existing optical telegraphs of the day.
They were widely ignored
by government and industry.
Though the tides were rising.
An electric revolution
was just around the corner.