What I want to discuss a little bit in this video
Is the idea of a random Variable
And random variables are first a little bit confusing
because we would want to think of them as traditional
variables that you are first exposed to in algebra class
and that's not quite what random variables are
Random variables are really ways to map outcomes of random processes to numbers
So if you have a random process, like you're flipping a coin
or you're rolling dice, or you're messuring the rain
than may fall tomorrow, so random process
you're really just mapping outcomes of that to numbers
you're quantifying the outcomes
so what's an example of a random variable
Well let's define one right over here
so I'm gonna define random variable capital X and they tend to be denoted by capital letters
so random variable capital X, I will define it as
is going to be equal to
1 if my fair coin rolls heads
and it's going to be equal to 0 if tails
I could have define this any way I wanted to
This is actually a fairly typical way of defining a random variable supposed to be a coin flip
but I could have define this is a 100 and I could have define this is 703
and this would still be a legitimate random variable
It might not be as pure way of thinking about it
as defining 1 is heads and 0 is tails, but that would have been a random variable
Notice we have taken this random process - flipping a coin
and we mapped the outcomes of that random process and we quatified them
1 if heads, 0 if tails
We can define another random variable
capital Y as equal to
let say, the sum of, roll, let say, seven dices
we talk about the sum of seven
let me write this, the sum of upward faces,
after rolling seven dices