Steven: We're at the Museum of Modern Art looking at a really famous collage.
It's Jean Arp's, sometimes known as "Hans" Arp, Untitled Object,
but it's always known as Collage with Squares Arranged According to the Laws of Chance.
And That's exactly what it is.
It's a gray piece of paper, construction paper,
It's got some cream colored and almost denim colored squares that have been ripped into these shapes.
And then scattered on to the surface.
Beth:What strikes me is right here we're at 1916-17.
Steven: Right in the middle of the World War.
Beth: right in the middle to the end of the first world war.
But what strikes me is how far we've come from the
Les Demoiselles d'Avignon which is 1907.
And really how radical
Dada was. Completely abstract work.
it's not arranged with any kind of artistic intention.
Steven: It really gives to play fast
and loose with the definition of what a work of art is.
Beth: Yes! Absolutely.
Steven: It sort of rips at the heart of what
our definition is historically
Beth: It's not self expression, it's not still.
It's not expression of the unconscience,
like Surrealism would claim later.
Steven: So it's actually, in some ways it's still challenging.
Beth: It is.
Steven: In that we look at paintings as a decision by the artist.
And here that's just been given up.
It is a kind of real anti-art.
Beth: It is anti art.
Steven: It is a real destruction
of the very foundation with which we understand
how to deal with art.
Beth: It is.
Steve: So how do we understand this in the
context of the war? You mentioned that this
was 1916, 1917, the war is raging,
it's unprecedented.
But this is being made in Zurich.
Arp was one of founders of the
Zurich DADA movement.
Switzerland is a neutral country.
And so I'm just wondering
where is the relationship between this kind
of aggression against the traditions
of art and the violence taking place
across Europe.
Beth: I think the answer that's usually given
to that is that a sort of emphasis on the rational
and human reason was part of the bourgeois culture
that had created the violence and irrationalness
of World War I.
But what strikes me is that the irrationality -
created according to the laws of chance.
And people are being called to the war
they're drafted, being sent to the front lines
They live, they die, they suffer.
You get legs and limbs amputated.
All basically on a roll of the dice.
Steven: Arp would have seen that.
The number of veterans who came
back who were deformed and exposed to gas, disfugured.
Beth: Post Traumatic Stress Disorder.
Steven: It was extraordinary,
and then those who came back unscathed.
Beth: What rules are there then in Life?
Where is the rationality for what happens to who?
What reasons?
Steven: It actually makes the absurdity of this object
somehow much more profound.
Beth: Yes.