We know that three points define a triangle.
So if I were to take three random points here
So let's call that point A, point B,
and then point C right over here.
If we say that these three points are the vertices of a triangle
they define a unique triangle
So this would be triangle ABC.
Now we've also learned in the last few videos
That triangle ABC has a unique circumcenter
and that is a point that is equidistant to these three vertices
it's equidistant to these three points
So the way we can find it is to draw
the perpendicular bisector of each of these sides
and where the three perpendicular bisectors intersect
and we've shown that they always intersect at a unique point
that is that circumcenter.
And I'll do that really quick over here.
So let's say that this is the perpendicular bisector of that side,
this is the perpendicular bisector of that side,
and this is the perpendicular bisector of that side
So these are all perpendicular
and they each bisect the side,
so B to this point is going to be equal to
this point to A.
A to this point is going to be equal to
that point to C.
C to this point is going to be equal to
that point to B.
And this point right over here,
we've already talked about that,
we'll call that point O
We call that the circumcenter.
O is the circumcenter.
This is all a little bit of review.
So if we have three points,
we have a unique triangle,
that triangle has a unique circumcenter
which is equidistant to the three points of the triangle.
I should say three vertices of the triangle.
and that distance between the three vertices,
Let me draw that in a different color.
So this distance, the length of OA,
The length of OC, and the length of OB,
So OA = OC = OB, which is the circumradius
And, we've learned when we first talked about circles,
if you give me a point, and if we find
the locus of all points that are equidistant from that point
then that is a circle.
And when I say locus, all I mean is the set of all points
If you give me any point right over here,
so that's an arbitrary point
and you also specify a radius,
and you say what is the set of all the points
on this two dimensional plane, that are equidistant
that are a radius away from the center
that uniquely defines a circle
That's how we define a circle.
And similarly, if you say,
look, if you start with a center at O
and you say all the points that are a circumradius
away from O, it will uniquely identify
a circle, and that circle will contain that points A, B, and C
because those are the circumradius away from O
so they are included in that set.
So the circle would look something like this
Trying my best to draw it
Now everything we've talked about now
like in the last few minutes,
is all review.
We know all of it, but I went over it
just to kind of reinstate a pretty interesting idea
that if you give me three points,
that defines a unique triangle,
and if you have a unique triangle,
and, let me make this clear,
this is three non-colinear points
So three points not on the same line
If you have three points that are not on the same line,
that defines a unique triangle.
For any unique triangle you have
a unique circumcenter,
and circumradius
And if you give me any point in space,
any unique point, and a radius
the set of all points that are exactly that radius away from it
that defines a unique circle.
So we went through all of this business
of talking about a unique triangle
with a unique circumcenter and
unique circumradius
to really just show you
that if you give me any three points
that eventually really just defines a unique circle
So just as you need three points to define a triangle,
you also need three points to define a circle
Two points won't do it
And one way to think about it is that
if you give me just two points,
there's an infinite number of triangles
that I can construct with those two points
because I can put the third point anywhere
I could construct this triangle
I could construct this triangle.
And all of these triangles are going to have
different circumcenters and different radiuses,
and so they are going to construct different circles
that circumscribe about those triangles
So for example, this would be one circle
that could circumscribe that triangle
You could have this circle right over here,
so you see clearly that two points are not enough
You need three points.
Three points lead to a triangle, which leads to a unique circle
So that by itself is kind of cool
Now another question is if I have a circle
And if it circumscribed about an arbitrary triangle
is the center of that circle necessarily the circumcenter?
So let's think about that a little bit
because there are some non-intuitive cases here.
So if I draw a circle right over here,
its center is right over there,
and if I draw an arbitrary triangle
where all of the vertices of that triangle are
on this circle,
is this center necessarily the circumcenter of that triangle?
So let me draw a crazy situation
Let me draw one where this thing
is clearly outside of the triangle.
So we could have one that looks like this
and clearly all three vertices sit on the circle.
So you might first say,
wait, there's no way this could be the circumcenter,
it's not even inside the triangle.
But remember, this point right here
is equidistant to every point on the circle.
I should say, every point on the circle is equidistant
from this point.
They're all a radius away.
And all three points of this triangle are on the circle
So they are all exactly a radius away from
this point right over here.
So this distance is going to be a radius,
this distance right over here is going to be a radius,
and this distance right over here is going to be a radius
Now, this point is clearly equidistant from
that point and that point.
We know that. It's exactly R away
from both of those vertices of the triangle
So if it's equidistant,
and we proved this in a previous video,
if it's equidistant from both of those points,
it must be on the perpendicular bisector of the segment
that joins those two points
So this must be on the perpendicular bisector.
So that's perpendicular, and it bisects
that segment right over there.
But we can make the same argument for
this segment right over here.
because this point is R from the center
We're going to call it point 0, I'm tired of just calling it "this point"
point O is equidistant from
Let me label these,
so let's call this A, B, C.
So we already said point O is equidistant from
C and B, so it must be on the
perpendicular bisector of BC,
and it's also equidistant from A and B
It's R away from both because
A and B both sit on the circle
they are both a radius away from the center
So it also must sit on the perpendicular
bisector of A and B.
Let me draw it a little bit neater.
So it must also be on this perpendicular bisector
And finally, it also is equidistant from A and C.
because those are both R away
they both sit on the circle
So it must be on the perpendicular bisector of AC as well
So AC is right over here.
And this is what the interesting thing is
We're seeing that the three perpendicular bisectors
of the three sides of this triangle
they do definitely intersect, but
they're intersecting at a point outside of that triangle
And that point is the center of this circle.
So once again, that last idea is
O is equidistant from A and C,
so it must sit on the perpendicular bisector of A and C
Which would look something like this
So once again, we see that three perpendicular bisectors
are intersecting at a unique point
and O really is the circumcenter
so, if you take any circle
and you put any triangle whose vertices
all sit on that circle,
the center of that circle is its circumcenter
So we just drew a situation where this is
a circumcenter that sits outside of the
triangle proper.
So point O is also going to be the
circumcenter of this triangle.
And point O is also going to be the circumcenter
of this triangle right over here.
It's going to sit on all three perpendicular bisectors
and we know that because it's equidistant from
all three points of any of these triangles
where the vertices sit on the circle itself.