What I want to do in this video is really make some clarification
that goes a litle bit more in detail about the different layers of the Earth.
So let me draw a cross-section of the Earth over here.
I won't be able to do it perfectly to the scale,
but I will try to do a little bit better job
and giving you a little bit of the sense of how thick these layers are.
So let's say that this is the crust appear
and I'm going to make the continental crust a little bit thicker,
so let's say that that is continental crust and this is continental crust.
And that in between, let me put some oceanic crust which is going to be thinner.
So this right here is ... actually let me do the oceanic crust in blue,
but this is not water, this is rock.
I will do that in purple, that is even better. I don't want it to be that thick.
So the oceanic crust is thinner than the continental crust
which I'm trying to depict right over here,
so this right over here is oceanic crust
and up here is continental crust.
And the thickness or how deep you can go and still be in crust, it depends on where you are,
or we know that near hot-spots the oceanic crust can actually thin out a good bit,
but roughly, when we talk abou the crust, we are talking about something that is
30-60 km deep.
So if you are on a continent, which I am assuming you are,
and you dig for 20 km, you will still be in the crust,
30 km - probably still in the crust.
If you dig for 70 km or 100 km, you will probably reach the mantle.
Remember, what we are describing here, we talk abou the crust, the mantle and the core,
we are talking abou the chemical make-up, let me make this clear, the chemical make-up.
The crust is fundametally different than the mantle
based on the molecules that it is made up of. Based on its composition.
So let's talk about the mantle now.
So the mantle layer is like this.
And once again, this is not the scale,
because the crust, we are talking about 30-60 km,
the mantle, we are talking about 2900 to 3000 km thick.
So this right here is the entire mantle.
And this is 2900 to 3000 km thick.
So this isn't even one thirtieth ot that.
So I would have to draw even narrower than the way I have drawn over here.
And the mantle itself can be subdivided into the upper mantle and the lower mantle.
So let me draw this division right over here.
The upper mantle - there is different ways to define the boundary.
But the upper mantle is roughly about 700 km down.
So these are huge distances. I mean this it going straight down.
So this is the upper mantle.
Let me write on the actual mantle here.
This is the upper mantle and this over here is the lower mantle.
And just to be clear on things:
So the crust is solid.
Now when you go into the upper mantle, the upper part of the upper mantle
we will talk abou that a little bit more, is cool enough to be solid.
So there is a solid portion of the upper mantle.
So all of this appear is solid because it's cool enough, it hasn't reached the melting point of those rocks.
And we have leart in previous videos that the combination of solid part of the upper mantle and the crust combined
the we call that the lithosphere.
And when we talk about the lithosphere we are now talking about the mechanical make-up.
We are now talking about what is solid and what is not solid.
So this is the lithosphere.
You go a little bit deeper, right below the lithosphere,
now the temperatures are high enough for ...
and I used the word 'liquid' but that is not exactly right.
You kind of think it is a kind of a deformable solid or plastic solid or magma.
And that is the asthenosphere. So this area right over here,
the liquid part; actually I shouldn't use the word 'liquid'.
It is kind of deformable. It deformes over long perionds of time.
But it is more fluid than what we normally associate with rock.
Magma would be a good way to think about it.
That is what we call the asthenosphere.
It is fluid. Just not as fluid as water, it is more viscous than something like water.
So this is the asthenosphere.
Now, the upper mantle is hard enough for the rock to melt and be fluid,
but the pressure is low enough for to still be able to kind of move past each.. to be somewhat fluid.
But once you get even deeper, into the lower mantle, you have higher pressure.
And so it's still fluid but it's less fluid, it's kind of thicker.
I guess it's the best way to think about it, the lower mantle. It's thicker.
So this whole area over here, you can kind of think of it's molten rock, it's fluid,
but the upper part of the molten rock is more fluid, able to move easier because there is less pressure
and the pressure is just from all of the rock that is above it,
remember, gravity is pulling down on everything.
Every molecule here wants to go down because of gravity.
So it is applying pressure donw, so the deeper you go, the more pressure you get.
Now, when we get even deeper than that, we get to the core,
and the core is divided between the outer core and the inner core.
So the outer core,
and then, of course, you have the inner core.
And just so we have a sense for distances,
the width or the thickness of the outer core is approximately 2300 km.
So these are huge distances when you think about thickness.
You can go donw another 2300 km and you are in the...
or once you go to the mantle, you can go 2300 km to the outer core,
and then you are in the inner core, and that essentially takes you the rest.
That is essentially the centre of the Earth. The inner core.
Maybe I should draw the boundaries a little bit more to scale.
It should actually look a little bit more ... like this,
because the outer core is thicker than the inner.
So the outer core is, as I said, let me rewrite it.
Outer core is on the order, it is about 2300 km thick.
And then you have the inner core.
I should do it in a hot colour.
So the inner core right over here, it just kind of takes us in the centre of the Earth,
and that is a little over 1000 km thick.
So this is the inner core.
The number I have is about 1200 km thick.
And the entire core, both the outer core and the inner core, is mainly nickel and iron.
When you think about when the Earth was forming,
what happened is when this whole Earth was super-hot, it was in a kind of a fluid state
the heavier elements were allowed to sink down when everything was fluid,
the things that were in between, the things that were lighter would go up,
and then the gases, thing that would naturally be in gaseous state,
would kind of bubble up through that fluid,
kind of the way actually carbon bubbles up in a soda,
they would eventually bubble up the fluid and would actually form the atmosphere.
So that is why when you look at the composition of the Earth,
you have the densiest, the heaviest elements in the centre
and then the lightest elements are forming the atmosphere.
The outer core and the inner core, they are made up fundamentally of nickel and iron.
And their make-up is actually very similar.
These divisions, chemically they have very similar composition.
What is different about them is at the outer core
you have temperatures high enough that nickel and iron can melt,
but the pressures are low enough that they can still be in a fluid state.
So this our liquid outer core.
And this has a pretty low viscosity, especially in relativ to the mantle,
so that is why people kind of consider this in a more traditionally liquid state.
But as you get deeper and deeper and deeper, the pressure becomes so huge as you get to the inner core,
remember all of the weight of all of the rock above you,
of these thousands of miles of rock above you, is all pushing down on the rock below it.
So the inner core even that the temperature is really really hot,
the pressure is so big that them molecules cannot flow past each other,
they cannot be liquid, they are kind of jam-packed.
So the inner core because of the high pressure, despite the high temperature, is solid.
So the difference here is actually a mechanical one - between the outer core and the inner core.
They are made up of the same things, roughly the same chemical make-up,
there is just lower pressure on the outside so you can actually be in a fluid state.
So hopefully that clarifies and gives you a little bit the depth on the make-up of the Earth.