world war one shaped our world and many
many many ways as far as the wasn't that
long ago was not even one hundred years
ago but it was really the end of the
more traditional empires is the end of
kingdoms
it really reshaped much of the globes
muster up much more round states defined
by nations rather than states defined by
monarchies are states defined by empires
it was also
the first war were technology wrote in
modern technology technology has always
been a played a major role in wars
affected
wars have been a catalyst for technology
often and what was the person that much
of what we can surbhi modern technology
british huge role
in uh... the actual carrying out of the
warrant a larger this is what made the
war so much bloodier and and one could
argue even more protracted
so here i have a bunch of pictures of
the various technologies used in world
war one here in this picture you have
you have a machine gun
you have a machine gun which allowances
allows you to kind of
indiscriminately mow down folks these
guys are looks like they might be in
some type of a trench and so you could
imagine that combination is viewed from
above so let's say that this is a trench
this is a trench a rotary year we're
looking for a bar so there's some people
sitting in the trench a couple of these
folks have machine guns the rest of the
guys just have
rifles over here
if you wanted a storm this trench you'd
be in a bad situation they got the
machine guns and she could just mow
people down
to just more people down they also
tended to use barb wire barb wire wasn't
invented in world rwanda's invented many
decades before the eighteen hundreds
but that would make it very hard for
someone to cross the spirit of they
would get stuck in it
and at which point these guys in the
trench could shoot 'em down and be very
hard to shoot the guys in the trench
so it also other than making it very
deadly and give all the advantages to
the the defense so anytime someone to
gain ground especially in one of france
where trench warfare was being used
is issues which usually finchley bloody
affair
the other
technology they became into mainstream
use in world war one was the use of gas
and in particular poison gas
poisons
poison gas
always and gas and as you see these
gentleman right over here they're
wearing gas masks
because they're afraid for their
opponent is going is poison gas and the
benefit of
of gas
in particular is
let's say you have an artillery shell
that you throw over a dozen hit anybody
but then it starts releasing it start
releasing a canister of a different kind
of and different
it start releasing a canister of gas of
the gas i've drawn
in this purplish color
until effect it doesn't have to be
directed at kansas linger there in in
fact that trench in effect everyone
there
gas warfare was actually the germans
were the first jesus just gas warfare
but they were the first two years
they really thought we would call poison
gas in particular nineteen fifteen
they use chlorine gas
same down chlorine
chlorine gas which immediately attacks
the respiratory system of the person who
hails at and a essentially choked to
death with and seconds or minutes
uh... they also used farce gene gas
because this actually did not in this
did not allow the very kind of did not
stimulate that choking the token reflex
in some ways it kind of infiltrate the
respiratory system even more have
delayed effect so did kind of linger
around and you have the use of mustard
gas mustard gas was very hard
to protect against
against it wouldn't kind of immediately
have you choke to death like chlorine
gas should be severe blistering this as
we take you take you out of the battle
is very hard to protect against and
would also linger around in the trash so
they can meet the trench a very kind of
like talks toxic environment to work in
cities are very very very ugly weapons i
mean it's
war itself is ugly weapons themselves
are ugly i mean the machine gun is not a
solid pleasant weapon at city can pick
and more people down um... but but even
folks who do something like a machine
gun is an acceptable thing
uh... tend to view these things is
particularly
particularly idly things lately things
to use
other weapons that show up in world war
one we talked about this and other
videos but the tank
started to become
a factor this right over here is an
american tank
obviously you know what these kind of
these these these trades a convicted
goin tough terrain
it's heavily heavily armored
uh... you could pick it kind of you know
when you talk about the stretch type of
thing well if you had a big hulking
beast maybe that could roll to the
barbed wire
and and and take some being in and maybe
eventually
so you could imagine a
a tank overhear that could eventually
action to take this time did not have
these kind of these big parts of the
mind of a something more like that
but this might be able to actually
be part of an offensive against attracts
like this
we talked excel extensively about
submarine warfare more won the germans
especially
used it as sensitive to get to have a
chance against the the dominant british
but they get saddam issue the dominant
british navy you understated u_-boat
warfare was one of the primary reasons
given by the americans as to why they
entered the war on the inside of on the
side of the untied
these are kind of world war one error
us summer recess to give an idea of
how they act it looked
and probably
that in some ways the the the best for
shattering of of
would play a major major major role in
world and future wars
it was the
was the bringing up heavier than
aircraft into the wars in particular
talking about airplanes so before this
you have stuff like balloons and
saplings
use for reconnaissance
used to see where we should aim the
artillery things like that
but now
you had the right blood brothers only
frankly several years before inventing
the you know the they've issued the
engine powered heavier than air craft at
first the airplane in the beginning
stages the war was use for khana since
but as the technology improved as the
engines improved
it started the used for for bombing
sardar to use for air-to-air combat
and all of the folks involved and
air-to-air combat
this gentlemen
this gentleman right over here is
probably the most famous although you
might not recognize his name is he's
been kind of character
turn into a bit of a caricature and and
and the modern world but this is manfred
von
rigth told him
and he was a a a pilot or the germans
and he's more famously known as
the red baron
the red baron is call the red baron
because he was actually a barren and is
the title of mobility in imperial
germany and he painted his plane reds is
a picture of his plane right over here
so
potocari analysis isn't quite ready
should as you probably try to get a more
reddish color so maybe this is more of a
red
so that the colors on c_ black-and-white
photograph of me if i colored and for
you
you'll get more of the feeling of what
his plane might have looked like
knows a try plane at these three wings
over here
over three let levels of ranks whatever
his plane was read that's what is called
the red baron
and he was famous for
being the most the most
lethal pilot
in all of the warranties were kids
eighty confirmed
kills who is able to down indiana mere
crapster eighty
eighty confirmed wins i guess you could
say when in in in in combat which is
more than any other folks
in toward war once a very very famous
pilot
he himself and we're talking about any
of the combatants in ward one did not
have a long life expectancy
uh... the pilots especially this was a
dangerous game
and heat and he also despite being the
top pile at the top east
in in and almost all the pilot in world
war one he also
ended up getting shot in the air
in nineteen in teen hillary got shot in
the long term hearty somehow managed to
land his plane
and when the people ran up to them
uh... the accounts it is famous last
words as he died ah... right when he ran
up to him
was kaput
uh... interesting
and on top of that he's now been
character into a bit of a caricature i
mean us in the west in the us we
recognize the red red baron red baron
pizza is named for the red baron for
manfred von
ripped open kind of a strange name i i
think for for pizza company and he's not
even italian
uh... but but that's kinda so we don't
form a dc this guy right over here
looks a lot more like tom sellick
uh... than he does
bent love look like the real manfred von
ripped open