Write the equation of a line that is parallel to the line 2x - 4y = 8 and goes through the point (3,0).
So because this line is parallel to this right over here.
it is parallel,
that just means that it has the exact same slope.
So we're essentially saying find the equation of a line that has the same slope as this line
and goes through this point.
So first, let's figure out what the slope of this line is
and the easiest way to do that is to put this in kind of slope, y intercept form.
So we have 2x - 4y = 8.
We want to solve for y.
We want this to be in the form y = mx + b.
So let's subtract 2x from both sides
so we can isolate the y's on the left.
So that cancels out and we have
-4y = -2x + 8
And I'm writing the -2x first just because that gets us closer to the mx + b form.
Now we can divide both sides of this equation by -4
so we can isolate the y.
So we divide everything by -4.
and the left-hand side, we just have a
y is equal to (a -2 divided by -4 is 1/2)
so y is equal to 1/2x (and then 8 divided by -4 is -2)
so we could write plus -2 or we could just write minus 2.
So we just rewrote this line over here
but because we wrote it in mx + b form we now know its slope.
The slope of this line is 1/2;
that right there is the slope.
so the equation of the line that we care about it is going to have the same slope.
It's going to have the form y is equal to 1/2x plus some y intercept.
It's not exactly this line,
b is going to be different than this -2 here,
but it's going to have the same slope.
They're going to intersect the y axis in a different place but theyr'e going to be parallel to each other.
So now we need to figure out how to figure out b.
And to do that we have this information right over here.
On this line, the one we care about, when x is 3, y is 0.
Or we could say that 0 = 1/2 * 3 + b.
We just have to find a b that sets up this equation
so that when x is equal to 3, y is equal to 0.
So we get 0 = 3/2 + b,
subtract 3/2 from both sides,
and we get -3/2 = b,
or b = -3/2
So we have the equation for our line that is now parallel to this equation
and goes through the point (3,0).
It is y is equal to (it has the same slope as this guy up here)
1/2x and now we know it's y intercept, -3/2,
and we are done.
And, actually, if you're interested you could graph these two and see that they're parallel.
So if you were to graph these,
I'll do a very rough graph very fast,
so this is my y axis,
this is my x axis.
This line up here, (I'll do it in blue),
which is the same thing as this line right over here,
I just algebraically manipulated it
has a y intercept at -2 and has a slope of 1/2
so that means that for every one it goes over, it only goes a half up
or for every 2 it goes over it only goes 1 up.
So it's going to look something like this
I'll try my best to draw it.
It's going to look something like that.
And so this line over here,
it's y intercept is at -3/2
and -3/2 is the same thing as -1 1/2,
so it's going to be right above it and it has the exact same slope, so it's going to be right above it and so it would look like that.
They're parallel but they're different lines because they have different y intercepts.