Find the area of a square with side (6x - 5y).
So, we draw our square, and all the sides are going to have the same length.
And they're telling us that the length for each of the sides, which is the same for all of them, is (6x - 5y).
So the height will be (6x - 5y), and so would the width.
And if we want to find the area of the square, we're just going to have to multiply the
width times the height.
So the area of this square is going to be the width, which is (6x - 5y)
times the height.
Times the height, which is also (6x - 5y).
So we just have to multiply these two binomials.
And to do this you could either do FOIL if you like memorizing things,
or you could just remember this is just applying the Distributive Property twice.
So what we could do is just distribute this entire magenta (6x - 5y)
times each of, distributing over each of these terms in the yellow (6x - 5y)
If we do that, we will get, this 6x.
This 6x, times this entire (6x - 5y).
So, (6x - 5y), and then we have
minus 5y.
Minus 5y, again, times the entire magenta (6x - 5y)