Simply 4a squared b and this whole quantity is being raised to the third power
Now here we'll just use the property if we have the product of things,
let's say I have a times b and I'm raising that to some power n
this is just going to be equal to a to the n times b to the n.
And to realize why that happens, let's just try it out with a simple example.
If I have a times b to the third power, what is that going to be equal to?
That is going to be equal to a times be (that's to the first power)
and then times a times b (and that's to the second power)
times a times b (that's to the third power).
We're literally taking this expression and multiplying it three times.
Now, we can just swap these around, because of the communicative
and associative properties of multiplication.
So if we just swap these around and change the order in which we're multiplying,
we can write this as a times a times a times b times b times b.
We have three a's here and three b's.
So this right here is going to be equal to a to the third,
and this right over here is going to be equal to be to the third.
So we have a to the third and b to the third, and so it worked.
Hopefully this gives you a sense of why this property holds.
Now let's apply it to the actual problem!
So we have 4 a squared b to the third power.
That means that each of the components in the product are going to b raised
to the third power so that means that we have 4 to the third power times
a squared to the third power times b to the third power
let me color code, this third power
here in mangenta, that's this third power over here
I'm just raising it, sort of taking the product first and then
raising that to the third power
I can take each of the terms in the product eah of the numbers
in the product and raised those to third power first
and then take the product. So that's what we are doing
Let's try to simplify this
What is four, what is four to the third power
Four to the first is four, four to the second is 16
and we want to multiply 16 times 4,
So 4 to the third power is just 4 times 4 times 4 is 64.
and then we have a squared and we are raising that
to the third power. We know from the product property of
the exponents that's going to be a to the 2 times 3 power
or a to the sixth power, so this is a to the sixth power
we got six from 2 times three and then finaly
we juste have b to the third power, let me do that in a different colour
we just have b to the third power and I'll juste write it over here
So we simplify this expression to 64 a to the sixth
b to the third power.