so let's say you go out to get your flu shot.
one of the first things you're gonna realize
is that there are two types of flu shot available.
so two types and i'm gonna go through them kind of one by one.
so the first one is called TIV
and TIV stands for trivailent, refers to the fact that of 3 strains
inactivated, inactivated means that the strains are all dead
influenza, because there are of course three strains of influenza
and V is simply vaccine
so this is what TIV stands for
and on the other side we have LAIV
LAIV, and this one stands for Live, live attenuated
so this one is a live virus, but it's weakened
attenuated refers to weakened, influenza vaccine
so just like the other one it has the same three strains, we don't put different strains in this one
And it's live and attenuated.
So let me actually just take a moment to step back and talk about this word attenuated
Specifically, you might also hear the word cold-adpated
And what they do is literally chemically change the virus around
they kind of modify it, so that it's still alive
technically it's still alive, but it can really now only cause problems in you nose
because that's the only cold area, right
So the word cold adapted kind of refers to the fact
that it's only going to be able to cause problems in your nose
and so if you actually go, if the virus goes deeper into your body where it's now warmer,
it would not have any effects.
so the virus can cause a runny nose, it might cause a little conjestion
and sometimes it does for people who get this vaccine
but it won't cause any problems in other places
so in your throat you'll be okay, and your lungs you'll be okay because it's weakened
so let's start back with TIV
this one is dead and it's injected
and in adults it's usually injected in the upper arm
so if you see a picture of people getting injections
you know, this is the one they're getting, right?
they're getting injected usually in their deltswood muscle
and in contrast, the LAIV we said was alive, but weak
and we also give this one in a different way
we actually squirt this one, comes in a liquid
and this one gets squirted in the nose
and that makes sense, because the virus naturally would go into the nose
and so this one we give that way as well.
so now let's think about groups that cannot get these vaccines
which groups would we say no to
and the only group really on this side would be
anyone that's less than six months
so if they're less than six months old, they should not get the TIV vaccine
I'm actually gonna just draw a dividing line between these two
And on the other side for the laiv, who would we say no to
this groups has a little bit larger
so here you would say no to anyone less than two years or
i'll put a big or here
or if they're over 49 years old
49 year old is okay, but let's say they're 50
and you would not give the laiv
that's kind of a cutoff, right?
also on this side are pregnant woman,
so pregnant woman should not be getting this vaccine
and people with cronic diseases
so let's say you have athsma or you have kidney disease
some sort of a cronic disease that you take medications for
you should not be getting the laiv if that's the case
now there's some others actually in this group as well
i'm not gonna go to all the people that you would not want to get LAIV
there are few other groups, but i wanted to point these four out
because these are probably among the most common
and an interesting thing about this is that
remember when we talk about high risk groups for influenza
we talked about some of these.
We talked about pregnancy as being a high risk group
people with cronic disease, no very young kids
and also the elderly, and of course elderly
would be a sub group of this over 49 group
so and these folks, let's remember these folks
are high risk of getting problems or complications from flu.
So they're the group that you really want to make sure you vaccinate
and as it turns out, all of them are probably
gonna need the TIV, the one over here vaccine
now let me make a little it more space
and lets talk about a few more groups or things to consider
let me just kind of leave this space here
now whenever i'm giving vaccines
i always want to kind of keep in mind
that there are few questions i should ask people
and if they answer these question in a certain way
i'm gonna hold off on giving the vaccine
so who would i want to hold off giving the vaccine to
well one group,and this might sound kind of obvious
but one group is someone that's had a bad reaction
let's say they've had a bad, a severe reaction in the past to the vaccine
they've had a severe reaction or allergic reaction
maybe to the vaccine or an allergy
and that's the person i may not want to give vaccine to again, right?
i just want to clarify what was the cause
or what happened exactly, but if it turns out
that they didn't respond well to it
either the vaccine itself or to eggs actually
because the vaccine is made using eggs
so either of these things if they have an allergic reaction
so if you're reaction to eggs or vaccine in the past
i'm gonna hold off on giving vaccine
what's another group you might want to
hold off giving vaccine to?
well, they're a syndrome out there, you may not
have heard of it, but i'm gonna write it out here,
and we're gonna just kind of briefly discuss it
called guillion barre, kind of a french pronunciation
and guillion barre syndrom is a problem of the nerves
so it's actually a nerve disease basically a disease
of the nerves that causes muscle weakness
that's how I usually kind of explain it to people
that want to know what is guillion barre
causes muscle weakness
and there's a relationship in the past between people
getting gullion barre and the vaccine
that's why we always want to ask people
if they have guillion barre, and if they do
i would hold off on giving the vaccine in most circumstances
now a third one, and this is probably
the most common issue that i've seen come up
is when people are moderately ill
so sometimes people come into the office
and say well, i'm here for the flu shot
and it turns out that they're having a lot of fevers and chills
and so if they're having any sort moderate illness
or if they're looking moderately ill then i would not give it
now i say moderately, and i'm trying to
write this on purpose, this way because if they have
let's say a mild illness, a very mild illness then it's okay.
so this is a kind of a judgement call, right?
so you have to actually, as a doctor and nurse giving the vaccine
really think about what is the illness and is it severe enough
to really want to make you hold off
so mild illness is okay, and that would be something like
maybe a runny nose or a diarrhea that's very mild
something that's not too bad.
so now you know the two vaccines you know who you don't give them to,
and you also know somethings that we always
kind of ask to make sure think about before we give the vaccine.
things to kind of hold off on
so let's actually go down and kind of test our knowledge
i actually kind of wrote out a simple example of flu clinic
so let's say there's a flu clinic going on and you're in charge
so let's take a look at what you might do
this person, this is you, right? this is you
and you're smiling because a lot of people showed up to your flu clinic
so you gotta go through and let's go one by one
and figure out who would get what
so the ages of the people are on top
and any kind of illness they have or any kind of
cronic condition they have is written on the bottom.
so let's get through all these folks, one by one
and figure out if they can get TIV or LAIV, right?
these are the two vaccines, right?
and I'll put a yellow check if it's okay
and i'll put a red x if it's not okay
so the 3 year old and the 1 year old is brought in by their 62 year old grandmother
and all three of them are okay with getting the tiv, right?
because they are all over 6 months
and they don't have any illness, they don't have guillion barre
and they have no evidence of allergies in the past
otherwise i would have written it
so that whole family is okay with tiv
what about the next couple?
i've got a man and a woman and the woman is pregnant
well, both the man and the woman are over 6 months, right?
and the woman is pregnant but that's not an issue with this vaccine
and the man has asthma which is cronic disease
but again, that's not a problem with the tiv vaccine
what about the last family?
the 46 year old woman and her 12 year old son
well, she has a flu, so she's moderately ill
i would not give her the tiv vaccine, i'll hold off
her son on the other hand has mild diarrhea
so this mild diarrhea he's still okay to get tiv
so that's basically what it would look like if i was only giving out tiv
but of course i'm giving out laiv as well, so some people might want that one
so let's go through again and now think about LAIV
well, for the live vaccine, you have to be over 2 years old
so the 3 year's okay, but his one year old sister is not okay
so she's too young to get this one
and you also have to be 49 years or younger
you can't be over 50, or 50 or older
so grandma, who brought them in is also not okay to get this vaccine
so in the first family, only the three year old can that vaccine
and in the second family, we've got a man and a woman
and the woman is pregnant, so we know that's gonna make her inelligeable for this vaccine
and the man has a chronic disease he's got asthma
so he also cannot get this vaccine
and the last family we have a woman who's 46 and her son
now the woman has flu, so just as before,
for the same reason because she's got an illness
i'm not gonna give this vaccine either
and her son has a mild diarrhea
and in this case, just as before,
he can get the tiv, he also can get the laiv
cause he's not chronically ill with anything, right?
now as a final point it's a really great idea that this boy is gonna get flu vaccine,
because he's around someone who has flu
so you want to kind of prevent him from getting sick as well
so he can't really avoid being around his mom
so it's a good idea for him to get vaccinated
the vaccine usually takes about two weeks full effect
so he has to wait 2 weeks before he gets full protection
but of course, along the way it's gonna slowly creep up