Let's say I go to a store and I have fifty dollars in my pocket.
fifty dollars in my wallet.
And at the store that day they say it is a twenty-five percent
off marked price sale.
So twenty-five percent off marked price means that if the marked price is
one hundred dollars the price I'm going to pay is going to be
twenty-five percent less than $one hundred.
So my question to you is if I have $fifty, what is the highest
marked price I can afford?
Because I need to know that before I go finding something
that I might like.
So let's do a little bit of algebra.
So let x be the highest marked price that I can afford.
So if the sale is twenty-five percent off of x, we could say that the new
price, the sale price will be x minus twenty-five percent of x is equal
to the sale price.
And I'm assuming that I'm in a state without sales tax.
Whatever the sale price is, is what I have to pay in cash.
So x minus twenty-five percent x is equal to the sale price.
The discount is going to be twenty-five percent of x.
But we know that this is the same thing as x minus 0.25x.
And we know that that's the same thing as-- well, because
we know this is onex, x is the same thing is onex.
1x minus 0.25x.
Well, that means that 0.75x is equal to the sale price, right?
All I did is I rewrote x minus 25% of x as 1x minus 0.25x.
And that's the same thing as 0.75x.
Because 1 minus 0.25 is 0.75.
So 0.75x is going to be the sale price.
Well, what's the sale price that I can afford?
Well, the sale price I can afford is $fifty.
So 0.75x is going to equal $50.
If x is any larger number than the number I'm solving for,
then the sale price is going to be more than $fifty and I
won't be able to afford it.
So that's how we set the-- the highest I can pay is $fifty
and that's the sale price.
So going back to how we did these problems before.
We just divide both sides by 0.75.
And we say that the highest marked price that I can afford
is $50 divided by 0.75.
And let's figure out what that is.
0.75 goes into 50-- let's add some 0's in the back.
If I take this decimal two to the right.
Take this decimal, move it two to the right, goes right there.
So 0.75 goes into 50 the same number of times
that seventy-five goes into five thousand.
So let's do this.
seventy-five goes into fifty zero times.
seventy-five goes into five hundred-- so let me think about that.
I think it goes into it six times.
Because seven times is going to be too much.
So it goes into it six times.
six times five is thirty.
six times seven is forty-two.
Plus three is forty-five.
So the remainder is fifty.
I see a pattern.
Bring down the zero.
Well, same thing again.
seventy-five goes into five hundred six times.
six times seventy-five is going to be four hundred and fifty again.
We're going to keep having that same pattern over
and over and over again.
It's actually 66.666-- I hope you don't think I'm an evil
person because of this number that happened to show up.
But anyway, so the highest sale price that I can afford or the
highest marked price I can afford is $sixty-six dollars.
And if I were to around up, and $0.67 if I were to
round to the nearest penny.
If I were to write this kind of as a repeating decimal, I could
write this as 66.66 repeating.
Or I also know that 0.6666 going on forever is
the same thing as two / three.
So it's sixty-six and two / three.
But since we're working with money and we're working with
dollars, we should just round to the nearest penny.
So the highest marked price that I can afford is $66.67.
So if I go and I see a nice pair of shoes for
$fifty-five, I can afford it.
If I see a nice tie for $seventy, I can't afford it with
the $fifty in my pocket.
So hopefully not only will this teach you a little bit of math,
but it'll help you do a little bit of shopping.
So let me ask you another problem, a very
interesting problem.
Let's say I start with an arbitrary-- let's put
a fixed number on it.
Let's say I start with $one hundred.
And after one year it grows by twenty-five percent.
And then the next year, let's call that year
two, it shrinks by twenty-five percent.
So this could have happened in the stock market.
The first year I have a good year, my portfolio
grows by twenty-five percent.
The second year I have a bad year and my portfolio
shrinks by twenty-five percent.
So my question is how much money do I have at the
end of the two years?
Well a lot of people might say, oh, this is easy, Sal.
If I grow by twenty-five percent and then I shrink by twenty-five percent I'll end up with
the same amount of money.
But I'll show you it's actually not that simple because the twenty-five percent
in either case or in both cases is actually a different
amount of money.
So let's figure this out.
If I start with $one hundred and I grow it by twenty-five percent-- twenty-five percent of $one hundred is $twenty-five.
So I grew it by $twenty-five.
So I go to $one hundred and twenty-five.
So after one year of growing by twenty-five percent I end up with $one hundred and twenty-five.
And now this $one hundred and twenty-five is going to shrink by twenty-five$.
So if something shrinks by twenty-five percent, that means it's just going to
be 0.75 or 75% of what it was before, right?
one minus twenty-five percent.
0.75 times $125.
So let's work that out here.
$125 times 0.75.
And just in case you're confused, I don't want to
repeat it too much, but if something shrinks by twenty-five percent it is
now seventy-five percent of its original value.
So if $125 shrinks by 25% it's now 75% of $125 or 0.75.
Let's do the math.
five times five is twenty-five.
two times five is ten plus two is twelve.
one times five-- seven.
seven times five is thirty-five.
seven times two is fourteen.
Plus three is seventeen.
Sorry.
seven times one is seven.
Plus one is eight.
So it's five, seven, and then this is seven actually.
fourteen.
nine.
94.75, right?
Two decimal points.
94.75.
So it's interesting.
If I start with $one hundred and it grows by twenty-five percent, and then it
shrinks by twenty-five percent I end up with less than I started with.
And I want you to think about why that happens.
Because twenty-five percent on $one hundred is the amount that I'm gaining.
That's a smaller number than the amount that I'm losing.
I'm losing twenty-five percent on $one hundred and twenty-five.
That's pretty interesting, don't you think?
That's actually very interesting when a lot of
people compare-- well, actually I won't go into stock
returns and things.
But I think that should be a pretty interesting thing.
You should try that out with other examples.
Another interesting thing is for any percentage gain, you
should think about how much you would have to lose-- what
percentage you would have to lose to end
up where you started.
That's another interesting project.
Maybe I'll do that in a future presentation.
Anyway, I think you're now ready to do some of those
percent madness problems.
Hope you have fun.
Bye.