So, say your vector field green bean cassarole is in the oven
and it's time to think about a nice crispy onion topping.
Normal people might use French's French fried onions in a can,
but super awesome people use
a real French person and real fresh onions to make their own fresh onion toroids.
And they fry three linked with the Borromean property
to get Borromean onion rings.
The Borromean rings show up in many forms.
They come flat and in 3D, round, rectangle-y, triangle-y
but the important thing is not the way the rings appear
but the way they are connected to each other.
The thing about the borromean rings is that
no two of the rings are actually linked together.
Ignore the pink and just look at the green and brown.
They're sitting on top of each other--not linked.
And if you just look at the green and pink, or pink and brown,
it's the same thing.
And yet, all three together are linked inseparably.
So to make your borromean rings out of onion rings
you will have to cut one of your rings
and then fasten it back with a toothpick or something
which can be removed after frying.
Or you can use the fourth dimension.
And luckily, I have a four dimensional guest to help me out.
If you're stuck in three dimensions
you can think of it like this--
Here I have an outside ring and an inside ring.
Now the third ring, which I have cut is going to go
outside of the outside ring, but inside of the inside ring.
Each ring is wholely out of and wholey inside of
the other two rings
so that no two are linked but all three are.
You can also think of laying two on each other flat,
one on top of the other and having the third
weave through them, so that it goes over
the one on top and under the one on bottom
The result can be made to be flatter or more spherical.
In some, you can see the relationship that Borromean rings
have with braids.
Sure the orange, yellow and red ribbons are all twisted together,
but no two strands are twisted together.
If I pull out the orange one,
the other two fall apart.
Some people in cultures and stuff think of this
togetherness property as a metaphor for unity.
So when you eat Borromean onion rings
you get to feel all deep and symbolic.
But don't forget to save enough to put on top
of your green bean matharole.
And there we go.
At this point, I've got a gelatinous cranberry cylinder,
bread spheres with butter prism,
mathed potatoes, a vector field green bean matharole,
with Borromean onion rings, apple pi and pumpkin tau.
All I need is a double helix cut ham.
And of course the crowning glory of the feast,
which I will tell you about next time.