We're in the Museum du Louvre
looking at one of the great Jacques David paintings The Oath of the Horatii
probably his most important painting
Well just an incredibly important painting even at its time
not just looking back historically, it's from 1784
but it had enormous meaning to the French Revolutionaries
It did, a couple of years later, a few years later right
When the war and revolution would break out.
But had an enormously powerful impact even when it was first shown
at the salon in 1785. It was painted, not in Paris where we're seeing it
and where it was exhibited, but actually here in the Louvre
but was painted in Rome. David had won that important prize
for a young painter, the Prix de Rome.
But he had gone to Rome and ended up studying
not this great Baroque canvases that were expected to be looked at
but to go back further to the Ancient Roman
and even to the Greek tradition, and we can see that here
very much so, these figures look like Ancient Greek sculptures.
The notion of the Greek tradition and of the early Republican
Roman tradition was really one about rationalism and truth and those were...
and a kind of true nobility of character and heroism, verasity, and virtue
yeah, yes, truth.
And this was in and of itself a very radical set of political ideas in 1785.
And in complete opposition to the sort of percieved lifestyle
of the French nobility. Um, that's right, of the nobility of the king
which was all seen as excess and was seen as destroying the state.
Yes, and if you look at this painting, it looks so, I mean it must have
even looked in 1785 when it was exhibited, So paired down
so stark, so simplified, rationalized, yeah, think about the brush
work, the looseness, think about brush work,and looseness and openess
the poetic qualities of the Rococa, that this was direct in opposition to.