Welcome to the presentation on adding and subtracting fractions.
Let's get started.
Let's start with what I hope shouldn't confuse you too much.
This should hopefully be a relatively easy question.
If I were to ask you what one fourth plus one fourth is.
Let's think about what that means.
Let's say we had a pie and it was divided into four pieces.
So this is like saying this first one fourth right here,
let me do it in a different color.
This one fourth right here,
let's say it's this one fourth of the pie, right?
And we're going to add it to another one fourth of the pie.
Let's make it this one-- let me change the color-- pink.
This one fourth, this pink one fourth is this one fourth of the pie.
So if I were to eat both one fourths,
or one fourth and then I eat another one fourth,
how much have I eaten?
Well, you could look from just the picture,
I have now eaten two out of the four pieces of the pie.
So if I eat one fourth of a piece of pie or one fourth of a pie,
and then I eat another one fourth of a pie,
I will have eaten two fourths of the pie.
And we know from the equivalent fractions module
that this is the same thing as that I've eaten one half of the pie,
which makes sense.
If I eat two out of four pieces of a pie, then I've eaten one half of it.
And if we look at it mathematically, what happened here?
Well the denominators or the bottom numbers,
the bottom numbers in the fraction stayed the same.
Because that's just the total number of pieces that I have in this example.
Well, I added the numerators, which makes sense.
I had one out of the four pieces of pie, then I ate another one out of the four pieces of pie,
so I ate two out of the four pieces of pie, which is one half.
Let me do a couple more examples.
What is two fifths plus one fifth?
Well we do the same thing here.
We first check to make sure the denominators are the same.
We'll learn in a second what we do when the denominators are different.
If the denominators are the same, the denominator of the answer will be the same.
And we just add the numerators.
two fifths plus one fifth is just two plus one over five, which is equal to three over five.
And it works the same way with subtraction.
If I had three over seven minus two over seven, that just equals one over seven.
I just subtracted the three, I subtracted the two from the three to get one
and I kept the denominator the same.
Which makes sense.
If I have three out of the seven pieces of a pie,
and I were to give away two out of the seven pieces of a pie,
I'd be left with one of the seven pieces of a pie.
So now let's tackle-- I think it should be pretty straightforward
when we have the same denominator.
Remember, the denominator is just the bottom number in a fraction.
Numerator is the top number.
What happens when we have different denominators?
Well, hopefully it won't be too difficult.
Let's say I have one fourth plus one half.
Let's go back to that original pie example.
Let me draw that pie.
So this first one fourth right here, let's just color it in,
that's this one fourth of the pie.
And now I'm going to eat another one half of the pie.
So I'm going to eat one half of the pie.
So this one half.
I'll eat this whole one half of the pie.
So what does that equal?
Well, there's a couple of ways we could think about it.
First we could just re-write one half.
one half of the pie, that's actually the same thing as two fourths, right?
There's one fourth here and then another one fourth here.
So one half is the same thing as two over four,
and we know that from the equivalent fractions module.
So we know that one fourth plus one half,
this is the same thing as saying one fourth plus two fourths, right?
And all I did here is I changed the one half to a two fourths,
by essentially multiplying the numerator and the denominator of this fraction by two.
And you can do that to any fraction.
As long as you multiply the numerator and the denominator by the same number,
you can multiply by anything.
That makes sense because one half times one is equal to one half.
You know that.
Well another way of writing one is one half times two over two.
two over two is the same thing as one, and that equals two over four.
The reason why I picked two is because I wanted to get the same denominator here.
I hope I'm not completely confusing you.
Well, let's just finish up this problem.
So we have one fourth plus two fourths,
so we know that we just add the numerators, three,
and the denominators are the same, three fourths.
And if we look at the picture, true enough,
we have eaten three fourths of this pie.
Let's do another one.
Let's do one half plus one third.
Well once again, we want to get both denominators to be the same,
but you can't just multiply one of them to get --
there's nothing I can multiply three by to get two,
or there's no, at least, integer I can multiply three by to get two.
And there's nothing I can multiply two by to get three.
So I have to multiply both of them so they equal each other.
It turns out that what we want for,
what we'll call the common denominator,
it turns out to be the least common multiple of two and three.
Well what's the least common multiple of two and three?
Well that's the smallest number that's a multiple of both two and three.
Well the smallest number that's a multiple of both two and three is six.
So let's convert both of these fractions to something over six.
So one half is equal to what over six.
You should know this from the equivalent fractions module.
Well if I eat one half of a pizza with six pieces, I would have eaten three pieces, right?
That make sense.
One is one half of two, three is one half of six.
Similarly, if I eat one third of a pizza with six pieces,
it's the same thing as two over six.
So one half plus one third is the same thing as three over six plus two over six.
Notice I didn't do anything crazy.
All I did is I re-write both of these fractions with different denominators.
I essentially changed the number of pieces in the pie,
if that helps at all.
Now that we're at this point then the problem becomes very easy.
We just add the numerators, three plus two is five,
and we keep the denominators the same.
Three over six plus two over six equals five over six.
And subtraction is the same thing.
One half minus one third, well that's the same thing as three over six minus two over six.
Well that equals one over six.
Let's do a bunch more problems and hopefully you'll start to get it.
And always remember you can re-watch the presentation,
or you can pause it and try to do the problems yourself,
because I think sometimes I talk fast.
Let me throw you a curve ball.
What's one tenth minus one?
Well, one doesn't even look like a fraction.
But you can write it as a fraction.
Well that's the same thing as one tenth minus--
how could we write one so it has the denominator of ten?
Right.
It's the same thing as ten over ten, right?
ten over ten is one.
So one tenth minus ten over ten is the same thing as one minus ten--
remember, we only subtract the numerators,
and we keep the denominator ten, and that equals negative nine over ten.
one tenth minus one is equal to negative nine over ten.
Let's do another one. Let's do one more.
I think that's all I have time for.
Let's do minus one ninth minus one over four.
Well the least common multiple of nine and four is thirty-six.
So that's equal to thirty-six.
So what's negative one ninth where we change the denominator from nine to thirty-six?
Well, we multiply nine times four to get thirty-six.
We have to multiply the numerator times four as well.
So we have negative one, so it becomes negative four.
Then minus one over thirty-six.
Well to go from four to thirty-six, we have to multiply this fraction by nine,
or we have to multiply the denominator by nine,
so you also have to multiply the numerator by nine.
One times nine is nine.
So this equals minus four minus nine over thirty-six,
which equals minus thirteen over thirty-six.
I think that's all I have time for right now.
And I'll probably add a couple more modules.
But I think that right now that you might be ready to do the adding and subtracting module.
Have fun.