The purpose of this video is to just begin
to appreciate how vast and enourmous the universe is;
and frankly, our brains really can't grasp it
but we'll see in this video is that we can't even grasp things
that are super-small compared to the size of the universe
and we actually don't even know what the entire size
of the universe is.
But with that said,
let's actually just try to appreciate how small we are.
So this is me right over here.
I am 5' 9", depending on whether I'm wearing shoes.
(maybe five foot ten with shoes)
But for the sake of this video let's just roughly approximate
around six feet or around roughly,
I'm not going to go into the details
of the math, around 2 meters. Now If I were to lie down
ten times in a row, you've get about the length of a
18 wheeler, it's about 60 feet long. So this is
times ten. Now if you were to put an 18 wheeler;
kind of if you were to
make it tall as opposed to long, somehow to stand it up
and you were to do that 10 times in a row, you'll get to the height of
roughly a 60 story skyscrapper. So once again,
if you took me and you piled me up a hundred times,
you'll get about a 60 story skyscrapper. Now if you took that skyscrapper
and if you were to lie it down
ten times in a row, you'd get something of the length
of the Golden Gate bridge
Once again I'm not giving you the exact numbers. It is not always going to be exactly 10
But we are now getting to about something that is a little on the order of a mile long
The Golden Gate bridge is actually longer than a mile, but if you go
within the twin span, it is roughly about a mile. Actually it is a little longer than that. But that gives you a sense of a mile.
Now if you multiply that by 10, you get to the size of a large city.
And this right here is a satellite photograph of San Francisco. This is the actual Golden Gate bridge here.
And when I copy and pasted this picture I try to make it roughly 10 miles by 10 miles, so you appreciate the scale.
What is interesting here... and this picture is interesting because this is the first time we can kind of relate to cities when you look at the city of this scale starting to get larger
than what we're used to processing on a daily basis. This is a bridge. We've been on a bridge. We know what a bridge looks like. We know that a bridge is huge, but it doesn't feel like something that we can comprehend.