Let's say that you've got a blood vessel
here, and it's a longish blood vessel
and we'll give it a resistance of eight, and it has three branches
say two big ones, and a tiny one in the middle
and this goes straight across, and this has a resistance
of ten, and these biggish ones, they
have resistance of say, half that, so they're about
five, and on this side, they all come together again
and enter a short vessel, this has a resistance of three
so my question to you is what is the total resistance of blood going in here
and out here? So, again, it's going to have to go through this eight bit, and then it has three choices here
here, here or here, but eventually they all come together again into that three bit, and then exit out the other side
So, what is the total resistance, so what is Rt resistance, that's the question, and
what I'm going to do is to divide this into two parts: part one
i'm going to figure out in part one, what the resistance is for this part, right in here
so I can do that using an equation I introduced in the last video, which was you can basically take
Rt, which is the total resistance for that yellow box, equals one over, one over five plus one over ten plus one over five
and i can look at that and tell you that the common denominator is going to be ten
Right? For all three, and in the numerator, we got two, one and two.
So, putting it all together, I got one over..., what is that, five over ten.
And that equals, ten over five, which equals two
So that tells me that the resistance in this middle, yellow box is two
and that makes sense with our rule, because we said that when things are in parallel, the total resistance
is going to be less than any components, and in fact two is less than five, ten and five, right?
It's less than any of those numbers individually.
So, we've got now in part two, we have three things in series, right?
We basically have something like this, we have eight, and we have two, and we have three.
So, we've got basically three things in the series, and so we simply add those up
and i'm going to say Rt now equals eight plus two plus three
And so Rt equals thirteen, so if I wanted to know what is my total Rt, my total resistance
I would say it is thirteen, so that's the answer to this problem
And, what I wanted to get you thinking about is total resistance for the body, the human body
, which has obviously more than just a few vessels, unlike I have in this diagram here
LIterally, thousands and thousands of vessels