So we have the same setup here as we had in the previous problem
in problem number 42 where p is an odd prime number
and they say let T sub p be the following set of 2 by 2 matrices
where each of those matrices are of the form a is along the diagonals
and a b there and a c there and each of those numbers
are between 0 and p-1 inclusive. So they can be
1,2,3 all the way upto p-1
and then the number of A in the set such that
the trace of A is not divisible by p
but the determinate of A is divisible by p is
and they tell us the trace of a matrix is the sum of its diagonal entries.
Its actually the sum of its main diagonals. Its not going to be the that diagonal,
its only the sum of this. So if you sum this you are going to get the trace of the matrix. So lets use
this first piece of information. The trace of A is not divisible by p.
So the trace of A is going to be a+a
or 2a not divisible by p.
So let us think of a situation where 2a is divisible by p.
So 2a could be equal to 0, because 0 is a multiple of p.
In which case a would be equal to zero. So this is a possibility.
So if a is equal to 0 then 2a is divisible by p. So this tells us
one of the constraints from this sentence right here is that a cannot be equal to 0
because if a is 0 then the trace is divisible by p. So a cannot be equal to 0.
So let's think about it. Can 2a become any other multiple of p?
Can 2a equal p? Well, if 2a equalled p then 2 and a would be factors of p
and then p would not be prime. So we can cross that out.
Then 2a cannot be equal to 2p, that would make a equal p which is impossible because a can only be p-1
So thats not possible. You can keep going to higher and higher multiples of p. Not possible.
Because a is going to be smaller than p. So the only constraint that we get from this first sentence that the trace of a
is not divisible by p tells us that a does not equal 0. So now look at the second constraint.
The determinant of a is divisible by p. So the determinant of a is equal to a times a
equals a squared minus b times c or c times b. So this is going to be divisible by p.
This is going to be equal to some integer times p. Now one thing, just looking at this there is no obvious
simplification here. But one thing I am starting to appreciate not having taken the IIT Joint Entrance Exam in high school
not growing up in India is that when they have multiple choices, sometimes it might be faster
to do just the brute force method. Now when I say brute force method not just proving mathematically
which one of these expressions are true. But lets just try a simple p and then lets find the members of the set that
would satisfy for that p and then see which of these expressions equal that p
To simplify this, lets just say p is equal to 3 and i pick p is equal to 3
because that is the smallest odd prime number. So it is the smallest number that satisfies this constraint up here.
So lets say p is equal to 3. If p is equal to 3 our possibilities for a are that a can't be equal to 0
We know that already. So a could be equal to 1 or a could be equal to 2. And if a is equal to 1
then the determinate of a is going to be equal to 1-bc.
which needs to be equal to some integer multiple of 3.
Because we said our p is equal to 3. This must be equal to 3k.
If a is equal to 2, then the determinate is going to be equal to 4.
Because its a squared, so its going to be 4-bc.
must be equal to some integer multiple of 3. So lets see how many combinations of
b and c we can find in each of these constraints.
So 1 minus bc. So 1 possibility is 1 minus bc is equal to 3 times 0. That is one possibility.
Maybe another possibilty is 1 minus bc is equal to 3.