You bought your house recently
for $200 thousand
and the way you were able to pay
$200 thousand
is you were able to put 25% down
so you made a fifty thousand dollar down payment
and the balance, the other 75%
you borrowed from the bank
so one hundred fifty thousand dollar loan
from the bank
and you pay it off with your monthly payments
that include paying down the loan and the interest
Now something happened in your life
maybe unfortunately you lost your job
or your spouse lost their job
or maybe you just overestimated your ability
to pay off your mortgage payments
and so you are having difficulty making them
and quite frankly you can't make the mortgage payments anymore
So in this situation you have a couple of options
One option is you can try to sell the house
So some type of a sale
or the other option is you could essentially
give the house back to the bank
and that we will call foreclosure
in another video we will go more in depth of
what happens in foreclosure
but the bank is going to get the property
try to auction it off, and they can't auction it off
and the bank will own the property
and then maybe they will try to sell it at a later date
And this is not a good option for you
this will kill your credit
which will make it very hard for you
to get a loan, any type of loan
but especially a mortgage loan
any time in the near future
really over the next several or many years
so you say, OK, I want to do the sale option
Now unfortunately for you the housing market has
deflated dramatically
And so when you talk to a realtor
The realtor figures out, well look
after all is said and done
you try to sell it for more than your loan amount
but you are not able to
you are getting really low offers
low offers are like $120 - $130 thousand
so when you really sit with a realtor
and you think about what the market
is willing to pay for your house
you realize that the most you're going to get
for your house after you pay the real estate commissions
and all of the other things that are involved
when you sell a house
you could get, maybe, $120 thousand
for the house
And let's say you still owe pretty close to
$150 thousand on the loan to the bank
your loan might have even been
an interest only loan
but even after a year or two
you're probably not going to pay down
the balance of your loan too much
it might be like $140 thousand, or $145 thousand
And you're only able to get $120 thousand for the house
So what do you do?
You don't want to get into a situation
where you sell the house for $120 thousand
you still owe $150 thousand on the loan
and so you're still going to have to pay
$30 thousand dollars for a house that you don't even
have anymore
so what do you do?
Well, one option
and this is not always going to be an option
is to go to your bank and say
can I do a short sale?
And a short sale is essentially
selling the house for less than you owe on the loan
selling for less than what you owe
and the bank doesn't have to
well one, the bank would have to agree to the short sale
because their loan is secured by this property that you're selling
and in most cases the reason why you would want to do the short sale
is that the bank may forgive the balance of the loan
so you try to convince bank to forgive the balance
So for example you could go to the bank
and say look I lost my job
we're having trouble paying for this house now
after paying real estate commissions and all the rest
I can only get $120 thousand for this house
I know that I owe you $150 thousand
Can you forgive the extra $30 thousand that I owe
and the bank might choose to do that
Now, even in this situation you have to be
very, very careful
and this has to be negotiated with the bank and all the rest
is because the bank could still report you
to credit agencies
report to credit agencies
Which is really not going to be a whole lot better
than getting a foreclosure
So in part of this negotiation process
The bank is under not obligation to either
forgive your loan and let you go forth with that short sale
and they're under no obligation not talk to credit agencies
But part of that negotiation you should try to convince them
Or you would ideally try to convince them not to report it to the credit agencies
The other issue with a short sale
and this is something few people think about
is when you have
lets say in this case $30 thousand forgiven
The IRS might consider that to be income
So you might have to pay income tax
on this right over here
And people always ask me
if someone forgives a loan, why is that considered income?
And the best way to think about it
is if the IRS did not consider that income
it would be a huge loophole in how someone could compensate someone
If I wanted to pay someone
I could give them...
So this is me
this is the person that I'm trying to pay
I could give them a loan
Let's say I could give them $100 thousand loan
and then I could forgive the loan
And so it would essentially be I gave them $100 thousand
maybe to do some work for me
it would be a transfer of money by giving a loan
and then keep forgiving over and over
it would be completely identical to giving someone
a gift, which is taxed, or giving someone some type of income
So a short sale, you're not always going to be able to do it
it this scenario
but if your house is selling less than the value of the loan
you might be able to negotiate with the bank
to allow you to sell the house for less than the value of the loan
The bank's other option is they're going to have to
go into some type of foreclosure proceeding and take ownership of the house
which is expensive for the bank as well
but they keys here are even if the bank is willing
to let you sell house for less than the loan amount
the owner really needs to make sure that the bank is willing
to forgive the balance and ideally not report to credit agencies