"Per cent" literally means per hundred".
That's where the word comes from.
"Cent" from cents or century or any of those words mean one hundred.
So someone tells you 7 per cent,
and I'm separating the words so it makes a little more sense.
He is always saying 7 per 100. This is the same thing as 7 per 100.
Which is the same thing as a fraction as 7 / 100.
With that out of the way let see if we can write.
If we can write 0.601 as a... as a percentage.
We essentially want to write it as something over 100.
So you could view it as
- I just rewrite this part right over here -
you could write it as 0.601 over 1. This is obviously the same quantity
You divide anything by 1 you should get that same anything.
I'm gonna multiply it by... multiply it by 100 over 100.
Obviously this won't change the value.
This is just 1 here.
But what this does it'll give us a fraction
on term with the denominator being a 100.
So the denominator if I multiply... if I multiply
these two characters right over here in the denominator,
The denominator of our product is going to be 100.
If I multiply 0.601 times 100 what am I going to get?
Well every time I'm multiplied by a multiple of 10
or every time I multiply by 10
I'm gonna shift the decimal over to the right ones.
So if I'm multiplied by 10 I get 6.01
and if I multiply by 10 again or I multiply by 100,
I'm going to get 60.1
So 0 point 6 0 1 times a hundred is 60.1
Let me rewrite that again.
If were to write... if I were to write,
0.601 and I wanna multiply it by 100.
Shift the decimal ones, I multiply by 10
if I multiply by 10 again,
or essentially multiply by 100,
I get 60.1
So this is times 10, this is times 10 again,
I was essentially multiplied by 100.
But now we have it in the form we like,
we have 60.1 over 100.
Or you can rewrite this,
this is the same this as 60.1 per 100... per 100,
which is the same thing as 60.1 per cent.
And that we obviously want to write then
60.1 percent as one word.
Or 60.1 and we just use the symbol,
60.1%, we are done.