Find the perimeter of the parallelogram. We have a parallelogram right over here, opposite sides are parallel.
That side is parallel to that side right over here. This side is parallel to that side right over here.
And also in a parallelogram, opposite sides have the same length.
Now, we have to worry about the perimeter here.
Which essentially just says that if we had a field the size and shape of this parallelogram, and we wanted to make a fence around the field that was the shape of this parallelogram,
how long would that fence have to be?
Obviously, it would be the sum of the lengths of the sides.
So, we wouldn't even have to worry about this thing over here, we can ignore it for the sake of this problem.
We don't care about the actual height, or this altitude right over here, we just care about the lengths of the sides.
So the perimeter of this parallelogram is going to be 12 inches, plus 8 inches, plus 12 inches, plus 8 inches.
12 + 8 is 20, 12 + 8 is 20, so this is all going to add up to 40 inches. And we're done.
I guess this is a very small field, this is only 8 inches. I guess it's a little plot of land,
a little parallelogram plot of land. Anyway, we're done.
Its perimeter is 40 inches.