Simplify 16x plus 14
minus the entire expressions 3x squared plus x - 9.
So when you subtract an entire expression,
this is the exact same thing as having
16x + 14 and then your adding the opposite of this whole thing.
Or you're adding negative 1 times
3x squared + x - 9.
Or another way to think about this is to
distribute this negative sign along all of those terms.
That's essentially what we're about to do here.
We're just adding the negative of this entire [expression].
We're adding the opposite of it.
So this first part, I'm not going to change it,
that's still just 16x + 14.
But now I'm going to distribute the negative sign here.
so -1 times 3x squared is -3x squared
-1 times (positive) x is -x
Minus positive 1x.
-1 times -9
remember, you have to consider this negative right over here, it is part of the term.
-1 times -9 is (pos.) 9
negative times a negative is a positive.
so then we have positive 9.
and now we just have to combine like terms.
so what's our highest degree term?
We'd like to write in that order.
We have only one x squared term.
(second degree term)
We only have one of those.
Okay, -3x squared.
And then, what do we have in terms of first degree terms?
It's just an x, x to the first power.
Well, we have a 16x,
and from that, we're going to subtract an x.
Subtract one x.
so 16x - 1x is 15x.
If you have 16 of something, and you subtract one of it, you're going to have 15 of that something.