What I want to explore in this video is given some length of string or line or some line segment right here B
can I set up an A, so that the ratio of A to B
is equal to the ratio of the sum of these two to the longer side
so its equal to ratio of A plus B to A
so I want to sit and think about this for a little bit
I wanna see is, can I construct some A that's on this ratio, this perfect ratio
I am somehow refering to here
so that the ratio of the longer side, to the shorter side
is equal to the ratio of the whole thing to the longer side
and lets just assume we can find a ratio like that
and we'll call it, we'll call it φ (Phi). We'll use the greek letter phi
for that ratio over there
so lets see what we can learn about this special ratio phi.
Well, phi is equal to A over B, which is equal to A plus B over A
we know that A plus B over A is the same thing as
A over A plus B over A
A over A is just one
and B over A is just the inverse this statement right over here
so B over A, this thing right over here is phi
so B over A is just going to be 1 over phi. This is going to be 1 over phi.
So this is interesting, we've now set up a number
which is, we're gonna call this special ratio
phi, is equal to 1 plus 1 over phi
well just that is kind of a neat statement over there
first of all is you subtract 1 from both sides of this
you get phi minus 1 is equal to its inverse
that seems to be a pretty neat property of any number
that if I just subtract 1 from it, I get its multiplicative inverse
And so that already that seems intriguing.
but then even this statement over here is kind of interesting
because you've redefined phi in terms of 1 plus 1 over phi
so we can acutally think of it this way
we could say, that phi is equal to 1 plus 1 over
phi, but instead of writing phi, we say wait
phi is just 1 plus 1 over, 1 plus 1 over
and instead of saying phi. that's just 1 plus 1 over
and I could just write phi again, or I could just keep on going
i could just keep on going like this forever
I could say that's 1 over, 1 plus 1 over
and just keep on going on and on and on forever.
and this is a recursive definition of a function
were a func..were a recursive definition of a variable
was defined in terms of itself
but even this seems like a pretty neat property
but we want to get a little bit further into
we actually want to figure out what phi is
what is the value of phi this weird number this weird ratio
that we are beginning to explore
so lets see if we can turn it into a quadratic equation that we can solve
using fairly traditional methods
and the easiet way to do that is to multiply both sides
of this equation by phi
and then you get phi squared
plus, or phi squared is equal to phi
phi plus 1
phi squared is equal to phi plus 1
and then, actually im going to take a little bit of a side here
because even this is interesting
because of then if we take the square rot of both sides
of this, you get, scroll down a bit, you get phi is equal to
the square root of, and ill just switch the order here
the square root of 1 plus, the square root of 1 plus
phi
so once again we can set up another recursive definition
phi is equal to the square root of 1 plus phi
and i could write phi there, but hey
phi is equal to the square root of
1 plus, is equal to the square root of 1 plus
and i could write phi there, but hey phi is just equal to
the square root of 1 plus
square root of 1 plus
and you could just keep on going on and on like this forever
so even this is neat
the same number that can be expressed this way
the same number were if i just subtract one from it
you get it's inverse
it can also be expressed in this kind of recursive square roots
underneath each other
so this is already seeming, starting to get very very intriguing
well lets get back to business
lets actually solve for this, this magic number
this magic, this magic ratio that we started thinking about
and, and really from a very simple idea
that the ratio of the longer side
to the shorther is equal to reatio of the sum of the two
to the longer side
so lets just solve this as a traditional quadratic
lets get everything on the left hand side
so we are going to subtract phi plus 1 from both sides
and we get phi squared
minus phi, minus 1
is equal to zero
and we can solve for a phi now using the quadratic formula
which we've proven in other videos
you can prove using completing the square
but the qaurdatic formula
you say negative B, negative B is the coefficient
on this term right here
so let me just write down
A is equal to 1
that's the coefficient on this term
B is equal to negative 1
c is equal to negative 1
that's the coefficient that's really the constant term right over there
so the solutions to this - phi
we are actually only gonna care about the positive solution
cause we're thinking about a positive
both of, if we go to our original problem here
we're assuming that these are both positive distances
so we care about the positve value over here
we get phi is equal to
I'll do it in orange
negative B, well negative negative 1 is 1
plus or minus the square root of
B squared, B squared is going to be 1
minus 4AC
A is 1, C is negative 1
so negative 4 times negative 1 is positive 4
so 1 plus 4 all of that over 2A
so A is 1, so all of that over 2
so phi is equal to 2, and once again we only care about
the positve solution here
this is going be the square root of 5
you've have 1 minus the square of 5
you're gonna get a negative in the numerator
so we only care about the positive solution
1 plus the square root of 5
over 2
so this seems like a pretty
pretty interesting, interesting number
lets actually take a calculator out
and see if we can get the first, the first few places
of this magic number phi
so let me get my calculator out
and lets just actually evaluate it
and you might recognize that square root of phi
is an irrational number
and so this actually, this whole thing is going to be an irrational number
but I'll prove that in another video
which means its never repeats,
it goes on and on and on forever
but lets actually evaluate it
so its 1 plus the square root of 5
1 plus the square root of 5
divided by 2
so it this
1,6180339
so let me put that aside, put that aside
and let me write it down
and this is where it starts to get really interesting
and mysterious
so this number right over here
is 1,618033988....
and it just keeps on going on and on and on
keeps on never terminating, never repeating
so that by itself, hey its this cool number
its this ratio that has all of this neat properties
which are pretty crazy
any way that you express it
but whats really neat is if we revisit this thing right over here
because what is 1 over phi going to be?
so, 1 over phi, 1 over phi. which we sometimes denote
with a capital phi (Φ)
we already know, 1 over phi
is just phi minus 1
so we actually, we can do this in our heads
one over this is just going to be
0,618033988
It don't know, there something wacky about that
that the inverse of the number is really just the decimals
left over after you get rid of the one
that by itself is kind of a crazy idea
but it gets even crazier!
because this number is showing up everywhere
and as you might imagine from the title of this video
this phi right over here
this is called the golden raito
this is the golden ratio
and it shows up everywhere
"Golden Ratio"
it shows up in art, it shows up in music
it shows up in nature
and just as to get an idea of were it shows up in nature
it shows up in very pure ideas
so if I were to just draw
if I were to draw a perfect star
if i were to draw a regular star like this
let me just draw it like this
draw it right over here
so this is just a regular star
all the lengths are equal
all the, let me draw it a little bit better than that
so if I just draw a star like this right over here
or sometimes this would be called a pentagram
some amazing things start to happen here
the ratio of this pink side to this blue length
right over here, thats the golden ratio
the ratio of this magenta to this pink, is the golden raito
as it should, by definition
now the ratio of this magenta to this orange
is also the golden raito
it just keeps on showing up in a ton of different ways
when you look at a pentagram like this
if you look at something like a pentagon
a regular pentagon
were all the angles are the same and all the sides are the same
if you take any of the diagonals
of a regular pentagon
so right over here, so if you take this diagonal right over here
the ratio of this green side to
and what I am talking about the diagonals
the ones that actaully aren't one of the edges
the ratio of any of the diagonals
to any of the sides, is once again
this golden ratio
so it keeps showing up, on and on and on
and we can do interesting things
with the golden ratio
let's say we had a rectangle
were the ratio of the width to the height is the golden ratio
so lets try that out
so lets say this is its height
this is it's width
and that the ratio
so lets call this A, lets call this B
and the ratio of A to B is equal to phi
it's that 1,61.. so on and so forth
and let me scroll down a little bit
so that is going to be equal to phi
so thats, you know maybe thats something
interesting to do, maybe thats a nice looking rectangle
of some sort
but let me put out a square here
so let me separate this into a B by B square
so this is a B by B square right over here
and then, actually let me do a little bit
let me draw it a little bit differently
this rectangle, it isn't exactly the way I would want to draw it
so the ratio might look a little bit like this
so the ratio of the width to the length
or the width to the height, is going to be the golden ratio
so A over B is going to be
that golden ratio
and let me separate out a little B by B square
over here
a little B by B square
this has width B as well
and so this distance right over here
is going to be A minus B
so now it is a B by A minus B square
so we have a...actually I should say
we have a B by B square
right over here
this is B by B
and then were left with a B by A minus B rectangle
now wouldnt it be cool if this is also
this was also the golden ratio?
and so lets try it out
lets find the ratio of B to A minus B
So the ratio of B to A minus B
well that is going to be equal to
1 over the ratio of A minus B to B
I just took the reciprocal of this right over here
and this is just going to be equal to
1 over A over B minus 1
right, I just rewrote this right there
and that is just going to be equal to 1 over
phi, the ratio of A to B we said by definition was phi
phi minus 1
but what is phi minus 1?
Well phi minus 1 is 1 over phi!
It's this cool number
So this is equal to 1 over
1 over 1 over phi
which is once again just equal to phi
So once again, the ratio of this smaller rectangle
of it's height to it's width
is once again, this golden raito
this number that keeps showing up
and then we can do the same thing again
we can separate this into an A minus B by A minus B square
Just like that
and then we'll have another "Golden Rectangle"
sometimes it's called, right over there
and then we can separate that in to
a square
and another golden rectangle
and we can separate that in to a square
and then another golden rectangle
actually, let me do it like this
it will be better
so let me separate, let me do the square up here
so this is an A minus B by A minus B square
and then we have another golden rectangle right over here
I could put a square right in there, we'll have another golden rectangle
that we can put in another square right over there
you have another golden rectangle...I think you see
were this is going
another square and another golden rectangle
Which by itself starts to create a cool design that we can keep
kind of circling in and in and in
and then if we actually draw an arc here
something kind of cool happens
if we have an arc that kinda traces these things out
We have something, a pattern that you might have seen
many times before
and that pattern does not look too different from
what you might see in something like
a nautilus shell
and it shows up all over the place in nature
and that makes sense
because just the way cells construct themselves
it kinda makes sense to be the same
at different scales, and the ratio from one scale
to the next is maybe the same as
kinda the constituent ratios
This right here, and it shows up all over art
a lot of Leonardo da Vinci's paintings
He never, well, not explicity stated it but there's a lot of
interesing ratios in them.
But Salvador Dali, this painting right here
"The sacrement of the last supper"
he explicity used the golden ratio
So the actual ratio of the width to the height
is the golden ratio
so this is a golden rectangle
And also there's all sort of ratios and I'll invite you
to explore it, the ratios of the different parts in the tables
to were it sits in the painting
is the golden ratio
it shows up a ton in this painting
and then he does have the pentagons over here
and we know that the ratio of the diagonal to the sides of the pentagon
are also the golden ratio
and so he just tought it was a really cool thing
and theres all sort of neat things
that if you find, you know where these two
guys are bowing down are
if you draw that line right over here
this is the golden ratio
the ratio of this length right over here
to that length over there, once again the golden ratio
It just keeps showing up in this painting
So it's a really really really cool thing
and I really encourage you to explore this further
cause it's kind of exciting