Imagine Alice traveled
back over 50,000 years
to find her distant ancestor, Bob.
Now, up until this time, human
culture was relatively unsophisticated –
utilizing the same primitive stone tools
which went unchanged for thousands of years.
But somewhere around 50,000 years ago,
something interesting happened.
And nobody knows, for sure, why.
There was a sudden explosion
of diverse cultural artifacts,
including instruments
for making music, new tools,
and other forms of creative expression.
Humans developed the ability
to externalize their inner thoughts.
They began to communicate using language.
So, Alice begins her search
by looking for water.
She knows that human
and animal populations
tend to migrate towards
and along rivers,
which are the life blood of ecosystems.
Eventually, she comes across
an interesting marking –
Bob's handprint.
This marking contains
very little information.
Simply that he was here
and could possibly return.
Alice knows Bob is equally intelligent.
He can communicate orally –
although his culture has not yet developed
the ability to read or write in its native language.
At the time, the universal
written language was art.
So she finds natural materials around her,
to paint him a picture, in case he returns.
She renders an animal she is tracking,
hoping this will offer a clue about
the direction she is traveling in the future.
Our ancestors used natural materials
to create pictorial representations
of their reality.
Here is an actual cave painting –
from around 30,000 years ago –
found preserved deep inside
Chauvet cave, in France.
Similar renderings are found
in the caves of Spain as well.
A common theme among
these ancient paintings
[is] animal forms,
as well as the human hand –
perhaps as a signature,
a story, or a ritual calling.
When Bob returns to the waterfall,
he finds her painting,
and proceeds towards the river,
where he thinks she might be.
When he arrives, he does not find her –
though he finds a sign
that she was here before.
He decides to paint her a picture
explaining where he is going next,
which is half-way up the river,
towards the setting sun.
He has little time to paint the picture,
as night is approaching.
Therefore, he needs a fast way
to visualise his message.
He thinks about it for a moment,
and realizes his message only contains
three distinct mental objects:
'middle' -- 'river' -- 'west'
So he decides to use simplified
pictures to represent them.
For 'river,' he draws a symbol
which resembles its natural form –
known as a 'pictogram' –
which is a drawing
that resembles the physical
object it represents.
Pictograms are an important step
in the evolution of writing.
Here is a ceremonial slate palette,
found in Egypt,
dated before 3,000 BC.
The surrounding scene shows
a struggle between civilized humans
and the wild and ferocious animals.
However, it's difficult to draw pictures
of abstract concepts – such as
'calm,' 'old,' 'dangerous' –
or, in Bob's case, 'middle.'
For this, he draws a line
with a box over the middle.
It represents 'half way.'
This is known as an 'ideogram' –
or a conceptual picture
of an abstract idea.
Here is an example of the same symbol
on an ancient Chinese bronze inscription.
For the idea of 'west,' he decides
on a picture of the setting sun.
Now he does something interesting.
He combines these individual symbols –
in terms of their meaning –
to create a message.
Meaning plus meaning
equals new meaning.
He leaves this in hope of Alice finding it.
Some of the earliest artifacts
of this symbolic merging
are found in ancient Mesopotamia,
now modern Iraq,
home of the Sumerians.
This is the birthplace
of many of the world's
earliest civilizations.
Here we find clay accounting tablets,
which are some of the oldest
written documents ever found –
some dating before 3,000 BC.
The rectangular tablets record
the payments in cattle,
shipments of cattle
to shepherds for fattening,
and gifts of cattle as an offering.
Notice that, instead of drawing
a picture of ten sheep,
they draw a symbol representing '10' –
using small notches –
and another symbol representing
'sheep' or 'donkey,'
meaning, simply, '10 sheep.'
We call this 'proto-writing.'
Finally, Alice returns to the base
of the river, and finds Bob's message.
She interprets the meaning correctly:
'half-way, west, down the river.'
So, she marches down river,
towards the setting sun,
and eventually they finally meet.
Over time, Bob learns
to speak Alice's language,
allowing them to use the same oral language
to communicate shared concepts and ideas.
This gives them an idea –
the root of a more
powerful written language.
It starts with something
very simple – writing her name.
She disassociates the sound
from the picture,
for her name, Alice.
(Alice ... Al – ice)
She combines the mathematical
symbol for 'all'
and the picture of 'ice.'
'All ice.'
'al-ice.'
Notice her name has nothing to do
with the individual symbols.
Sound plus sound equals new meaning.
This is known as the 'Rebus principle.'
A great example of this was found in Egypt,
along the Nile river.
Dated to aroung 3100 BC,
it contains some of the
earliest hieroglyphic
inscriptions ever found.
'The Narmer Pallette' depicts
the Egyptian pharaoh, 'Narmer'.
On the back, we see him to
the left of a kneeling prisoner,
who is about to be struck down by Narmer –
who we see standing tall,
wearing a crown.
What we are looking for
is on the other side.
Between the two bovine heads at the top,
we see an inscription of his name.
It's written as a fish and a chisel –
which translates to 'Nar Mer' –
'Narmer.'
Two sounds, separated from the pictures,
together, giving new meaning –
a key development
in the history of written language.
But before they could advance towards
what we know of as an 'alphabet',
something had to happen.
They needed to save time.