We are in the Orangerie in Paris and we are looking at one of Monet's Waterlily rooms.
It's in an oval shaped lid from above which gives it a really lovely soft light.
There is the sense that these are contemplative works
which ties them in an interesting way
as to kind of celendity? of the sort you would expect in a relgious context.
Oh no doubt.
This is painted late in Monet's life after
the death of his wife and
after the death of his son.
So I think there is a sense for him of his legacy.
and gave them to French State.
And the State in return decided to build this pavillion
I keep thinking about Monet's life
long desire to capture the beauty of the optical world
from when he was in Paris and then in Argenteuil
and thinking back to Boulevard des Capuccines
and the light pouring down the Boulevard
and Gare de Saint-Lazare
and the light filtered through the steam
of the trains
and then later in his life in his garden
with the waterlilies.
he was interested on not only
in capturing and understanding and rendering
those effects of light
and the momentary but actually in creating them
you know he devoted an enormous amount of his life
to actually planting his gardens and maintaining them.
And then translating them onto canvas and in a sense preserving that sense of the momentary.
The thing that I can think about when we look at these is intensity of the colour
and the beauty of the color harmonies in
the paintings is more beautiful than reality.
So let's think about the history of landscaping and these are unprecedented in that way.
First of all their shape.These very very long panels
without a horizon line.
We are looking across the water
so we see neither the ground that we stand on
nor the horizon on the foresight.
Traditional landscaping often provided
a path for ones eye to travel
through the landscape.
Here we really can't do that because we are confronted
with the surface of the water and
the surface of the paintings themselves.
But I do think that the Monet is borrowing actually from the classical tradition
If you look on both sides of these canvases
you see the dark shadows
of the weeping willows and those functions in a sense that
trees often framed .. landscapes.
So Monet has placed us in a very particular place.
Obviously we are on the shore in some way.
But we are looking across the water so we see neither the ground that we stand on
nor the horizon on the foresight.
Monet had just enlarged his ponds but even then they are quite small and
so he really unmounts us by not giving us a ground to stand on.
Bu he has given us a very particular angle which we are viewing the paths of the waterlilies themselves.
And that does place us in relationship to the surface of the water so we can actually locate ourselves
And they also allow us to hop skip and jump from path to path and move back into space.
And then there is this extraordinary volume of space below the pond and the incredible dome of space
where there is these towering clouds right above us.
So there is sense of the extent of the volume that's portrayed and yet done so.
on the two dimensional surface of a pond which is of course a reflection of the two dimensional surface of the canvas.
It is a beautiful summation of this notion that Monet has worked for towards for so long:
How does one capture both the extraction of modern art