PROBLEM: “The circle, x^2 + y^2 - 8x = 0,
and the hyperbola, (x^2/9) – (y^2/4) = 1,
intersect at the points a and b.”
In Problem 46, they tell us the equation –
or they want to find the equation of the circle
with ab as its diameter.
So, let’s think about –
Let's visualize the circle and the hyperbola.
The equation of the circle, x^2 + y^2 - 8x = 0 …
(Let me write it this way.)
This can be rewritten as x^2 - 8x + y^2 = 0.
You can add 16 to both sides.
And I’m doing that to complete the square for the x term.
So plus 16/
This over here becomes (x-4)^2 + y^2 = 16.
And so, the circle’s going to look something like this.
That's my x axis.
That's my y axis.
It's center is at 4, 0.
So 1, 2, 3, 4.
4, 0.
And It's radius is 4.
Its radius squared is 16.
So its radius is 4.
So let me go 1, 2, 3, 4.
1, 2, 3, 4.
Let me go up four:
So, all of these points –
that point, that point, that point, and that point –
are all going to be on the circle.
(Let me draw that a little bit neater.)
That point, that point, and that point
are all going to be on our circle.
So my circle’s going to look something like this.
It's not drawn as neatly as it could be,
but I think you get the general idea.
This is our circle.
Then they have a hyperbola,
x^2/9 – y^2/4 = 1
This hyperbola is going to open to the left and the right,
since our x term is positive.
It's going to look something like this.
You can actually figure out the assymptote.
Actually, let me just do that.
Let me solve for y.
So you get –
If you – you would get –
Let me write it this way.
-y^2/4 = -x^2/9 + 1.
I just subtracted x^2/9 from both sides.
And then we would get –
Let’s multiply both sides by negative 4.
You get y^2 = (4/9)x^2 - 4.
Or y is equal to …
And now this will just be the positive part over here.
But I’m doing that so that we can understand its asymptotes.
y is equal to the square root of (4/9)x^2 – 4.
So, as x gets larger, and larger, and larger,
this term right here is going to stop mattering so much.
So as x approaches infinity –
As x approaches infinity, this is going to approach
the square root of 4 over 9x^2.
This constant’s not going to matter much.
And so, it's going to approach –
This thing right over here is going to be (2/3)x.
So it's going to –
If you imagine a slope –
Let’s see.
2/3rds.
If you go –
If you run 3, you rise 2.
So it's going to –
The asymptote is going to look like that.
It’s going to approach that line over there.
And, it's going to be symmetric – so it's also going to approach –
So three and two.
So it’s also going to approach that line over there.
And, if we want to see where it intersects the x-axis, you just set x –
– you just set y = 0.
You get x^2/9 = 1.
So x = +/- 3.
So the positive intersection is going to be over there.
So our hyperbola on the right side’s going to look something like –
something like that.
It's also going to show up on the left side.
But that's less interesting,
because it’s not doing anything with the circle.
Now, they told us that the hyperbola and the circle
intersect at the points a and b.
So this, right here, is the point a.
This, right here, is the point b.
In this question, we want the equation of the circle with
ab as its diameter.
So ab – with ab – with ab as the diameter.
(I could have drawn that a little bit straighter.)
So the equation of that circle right over there.
So essentially, we just need to figure out,
“Where does this hyperbola intersect this circle?”
Now, if we can –
The easiest way to do this is to –
Well, we have two constraints here.
Let's solve for y^2 for the circle,
and then we can substitute that in for y^2, right here,
and see what x values they intersect at.
And then we want the x value out here.
So, something that looks like this value
is the one we want to use.
Then we can figure out the y value.
The y value is going to be the radius of our circle.
The x value comma 0 will be the center.
And then we'll have our equation.
So let's do that.
So this up here, we have –
(Let me do it in yellow.)
So if we subtract x^2 and -8x from both sides,
the equation of the circle can be rewritten as y^2 is equal to –
I’m going to add 8x to both sides.
So it’s 8x …
and then subtract negative x^2 from –
or subtract export from both sides et
8x - x^2.
I really just moved that and that
over to the right hand side of the equation.
Now I can take this and substitute for y^2
in the equation of the hyperbola.
So the hyperbola’s is equation is x^2/9 - y^2/4 = 1.
But instead of writing a y^2 over there,
we know that it has to satisfy this equation, as well.
So for y^2, I’m going to put in 8x - x^2.
And let's see if we can solve –
Let's see if we can't solve this right here.
This is just a straight up quadratic equation,
although it might not look like it just yet.
Let’s simplify this.
So this tells us that x^2/9 – 8x/4 –
So -2x …
… plus x^2/ 4 … plus x^2/4.
(I just distributed, essentially,
the -1/4th over both of these terms.)
… is equal to 1.
And let's see, we can multiply the whole thing times 36,
to get rid of these fractions, because that’s 4 ª 9.
So 36 º 9 = 4.
So this is 4x^2-36 ª 2 (is 72).
72x …
… plus 36/4 is 9 …
… plus nine 9x^2 = 36
These two terms right here, we can add them.
We get 13x^2 -72x.
And then we could subtract 36 from both sides
So [continuing] -36 = 0.
So now we just have a straight-up quadratic equation.
We just have to find the x's – find the roots.
So let’s use the quadratic formula here.
So x is going to be equal to negative b.
So that's negative negative 72.
So that’s 72 ... plus or minus the square root of 72^2.
(I’ll just write that.)
72 ª 72 – 4 ª a ª c.
c is -36.
So that negative, you could just put it out here,
and you just put the 36 out back.
And then all of that – all of that over 2 ª a.
And then all of that –
All of that over all of that that over 26.
So the hard part is really to simplify this.
But it looks like we have some interesting stuff going on.
So let me rewrite this part over here.
So 72 –
Let me write it over here.
72 ª 72 is the same thing as –
This is the same thing as (2 ª 36)(2 ª 36), right?
Each of those are 72.
That’s the same thing as 72 ª 72.
And then, we’re adding to that 4 ª 36 ª 13.
4 ª 36 ª 13.
And we're taking the square root of this whole thing.
I’m just doing the work out here, so we don't
waste this real estate over here.
Now. We can factor out a 4 ª36.
This is 4, and this is a 36.
So this is equal to –
I know it’s getting –
(Let me write it a little bit neater.)
This is equal to the square root of –
We can take 4 ª 36 …
And actually, a 4 ª 36 is one 144.
I’ll just right 4 ª 36 right here.
4 ª 36.
Now over here, we used both 2’s and a 36,
so we have a 36 left.
We used this 4 ª 36.
So we have +13.
So this becomes the square root of 4 times –
4 ª 36 = 144.
36 + 13 = 49.
So, we're lucky that it actually worked out
to two perfect squares.
So this is the square root of 144 times the square root of 49,
which is 12 ª 7.
Or, this is equal to 84.
So this over here – this business over here –
simplifies to 72 +/- 84.
This whole thing over here simplifies to 84.
All of that over 26.
Now if we subtract 84 …
if we were to subtract 84, we would get something over here
that doesn't make sense in this context.
We're looking for something –
a positive x value.
So let's only consider – let's only consider –
Let's only consider the +84, and see what we get.
So the first thing to do –
Actually, let me just divide the numerator
and the denominator by 2.
So, this is the same thing as (36 + 42)/13.
And this is the same thing as 78 º 13.
And it looks like 78 is divisible by 13.
78 º 13 = 6.
This is equal to 6.
So the x coordinate here is 6.
It's right there.
So it's 6.
We don't know what the y coordinate is, so let's do that.
It's pretty easy to solve.
We could substitute x = 6 into any of these equations.
This one is probably easier right over here.
So we get y^2 = 8 ª 6 ... is 48 …
minus 48 – 36, which is equal to 12.
And so y is equal to the square root of 12.
We could simplify that radical if we wanted.
But we know the point now.
It’s 6 comma the square root –
Sorry.
This point over here is 6, 0 – but the actual intersect –
The center is 6, 0.
But the actual intersection point is going to be 6 …
… is going to be 6 comma positive square root of 12
(And I should say this is a positive
or negative square root of 12.)
And this over here is going to be 6,
negative square root of 12.
This right here is 6, 0.
That's the center of our circle.
So what's the equation of this new circle going to be?
What's the equation of this new circle going to be?
Well, we know its center.
It’s center is at 6, 0.
Let me write it down here.
Its center is at 6, 0.
So, it's going to be (x-6)^2 + (y-0)^2 =
the radius squared (r^2).
Now what’s the radius?
The radius is this height right over here.
Or it's just equal to the y value at the intersection.
It’s the square root of 12.
Now this is going to be the radius squared
The square root of 12^2 = 12.
So the equation is going to be x - 6.
And let’s see what form they have right here.
So they actually multiple everything out.
So let’s just do that.
So this is going to be x^2 - 12x + 36 + y^2 = 12.
And then we could subtract 12 from both sides –
subtract 12 from both sides.
and we get x^2 - 12x + 24 + y^2 = 0.
And let’s see which of the choices –
Let’s see which of the choices match that.
Let me copy it.
And then let me paste it up here.
Let me paste it up here.
And it looks like we have an x^2, positive y^2,
-12x, and then a +24.
-12x, +24.
So it looks like our answer is A.
Did I do that right?
x^2 - 12x + 24 …
Yep.
Our answer is A.