(lively music)
Voiceover: We're in the Museum of Modern Art on the fourth floor,
and we're standing in front of a little case that encloses
Alberto Giacometti, the Swiss sculptor's, "City Square," from 1948.
Voiceover: Strikingly odd in its materials, which are bronze,
and sort of heroic in its association
of the very small, and meager, and sad-looking figures.
Voiceover: Right.
Downstairs, when you walk into the museum,
you're confronted with a grand figure of Balzac by Rodin ...
Voiceover: In bronze.
Voiceover: And it's this gigantic bronze that,
as it's set up on the Boulevard Raspail in Paris,
it's something that you look up at,
and it's heroic in the extreme.
Voiceover: Then, there's the whole tradition of equestrian sculptures.
Voiceover: But here, we have these tiny little figures.
Voiceover: They're very [unintelligible].
Voiceover: There's such a great story behind this,
because what's happening here is that Giacometti,
who had been one of these dissident surrealists
before the Second World War, had fled -
gone to visit his mother, supposedly, in Switzerland,
with some friends - when the Nazis were threatening,
and stayed there for the duration of the war.
When he was there, he worked on his sculptures.
At the end of the war, he brought them all back,
and he brought them back in tiny little matchboxes.
Tiny little matchboxes contained his entire output
for the period of the war, and these are figures
that are even smaller than the ones that are in front of us here.
They're these figures that are so minuscule, so tiny,
that they seem like we could never get close to them.
Voiceover: What's funny is that, although they are so small
and so devoid of information, really, about who they are
and what they are in terms of their bodies,
but I'm noticing that I can still see that there's a female figure ...
Voiceover: And she's distinct.
Voiceover: And four male figures, and she is distinct.
But, I think it's interesting he so reduced them,
but that gender distinction is still there.
Voiceover: He does it through the hips, and through the breasts ...
Voiceover: And the clothing.
Voiceover: And the hair, but also - and if you're familiar
with Giacometti's post-war work - you'll notice
that his male figures are often walking.
Voiceover: And the female figure is standing still.
I noticed that, too.
Voiceover: And her legs - she's almost
like a [Kroisos} that is from an ancient Greek figure
where the legs are locked together,
and the arms are also sort of plastered ...
Voiceover: An archaic Greek sculpture.
Voiceover: That's right, plastered to the side,
whereas the men are mobile.
There this very serious distinction that he makes
in the representation of the genders.
Voiceover: It bothers me.
Voiceover: It bothers me, too.
Voiceover: It makes me wonder what it means ...
Voiceover: Well, she seems bound.
Voiceover: And I worry that he means something
that is not going to make me happy.
(laughs quietly)
Voiceover: No, I suspect that that's exactly right, in fact.
She seems bound.
Voiceover: Right, there's a sense of men's mobility in the city,
and her lack of mobility in the city.
It's hard to say that, because all of the figures are alienated.
Voiceover: They are.
Voiceover: And alone and isolated,
and she is, too, but she's moreso.
Voiceover: Well, think about his earlier
representations of women.
I'm thinking most famously, of course,
of "Woman with her Throat Cut,"
where we have this figure that seems
as if she had been raped and then murdered,
splayed, her limbs akimbo on the floor,
Even then, there's an even greater violence
because she's not only been attacked, clearly,
but she's also half insect,
more specifically, praying mantis-like.
Voiceover: Ah, someone who would kill her mate, right?
Voiceover: One of the ideas that was of particular interest to the surrealists.
Voiceover: Yeah, she looks like she's standing still
and sort of, therefore, a waiting victim, somehow,
to these men who walk by her, to men.
Voiceover: You wonder whether or not these figures
will come into contact with each other or,
if this was somehow animated,
if they would pass across each other's paths
so that they don't actually ever bump, but intersect only.
It's an interesting community of isolation, isn't it?
Voiceover: You know what it really reminds me of?
It really reminds me of Seurat.
Voiceover: Ah, I think that that's right.
Voiceover: Because the figures are reduced to their bare essentials,
and yet you can still tell some things about them,
and they're very isolated in their performance in the outside space.
Voiceover: The French philosopher Sartre wrote the introduction
to Giacometti's first major post-war exhibition.
One of the things that Sartre wrote about was the way
in which Giacometti's figures represented distance
and the reclaiming of the isolation of the figure
in the wake of the concentration camps,
in the wake of the camp that actually Sartre himself ,
apparently, was in briefly, where figures were constantly against each other,
and that all personal space or isolation was removed.
Voiceover: That's right, and the body became something that was - bodies were very [unintelligible],
[unintelligible] each other in a way.
Voiceover: That's right.
He said that for weeks on end, you always had
somebody's thigh or arm against you,
and that Giacometti's reclaiming that distance and,
therefore, the autonomy and possibility of action in the space.
But, of course, that has an especially potent meaning
if the female figure doesn't have that ability to act.
Voiceover: That reminded me of the description in Mautz,
of his father when he has to go
to the toilet in the middle of the night -
and I think he's in Dachau - and in order to go to the toilet,
he has to step over bodies.
Voiceover: Now, Sartre was not in a concentration camp in Germany,
but he was apparently in prison, briefly at least, for his ...
Voiceover: It's funny because this looks
like such a dystopic view of humanity,
but seen in that context, it's more Utopia.
Voiceover: I'm not sure that there's necessarily
that much positive light here, but I think
a sort of complexity of different kinds of negative.
Voiceover: Fair enough.
(lively music)