To get a better intuition for the price elasticity of demand
I thought I would take a look
at some of the more extreme cases,
and think about
what types of elasticities of demand we would see.
So this right over here is a vial of insulin.
Many diabetics (not all diabetics) need to take insulin daily.
They need to inject it in order to maintain their blood sugar level.
If they don't do it, bad things will happen to their bodies
and they might prematurely die.
if they don't take their insulin on time.
So let's think about what the elasticity of demand
might look like for something like insulin.
So in one column I'll put price
and in the other column I will put quantity.
So let's say that insulin right now is going for $5 a vial.
We have a group of diabetics who need insulin
and they're all going to buy the insulin they need
and let's say this group--
that turns out to be 100 vials per week.
(So this is in vials per week.)
Fair enough, that's exactly what they need to do
to maintain their insulin.
Now what happens if the price changes?
What happens if the price were to go down?
Let's say that the price were to go down to $1.
Well, what would the quantity be?
Well they're not going to buy any more insulin.
They're going to buy just what they need
in order to maintain their diabetes.
And remember, we're holding all else equal--
we're not assuming any change in expectations of price:
do they expect price to go up or down or anything like that.
So in this case, they'll still just buy 100 vials.
Now what happens if the price went up a ton?
What happens if the price went to $100 a vial?
Well, it would be hard for them,
but they need it to survive.
So it's going to squeeze out any other expenses
that they need to spend money on.
And so they still will buy 100 vials a week.
And so you could keep raising price within reason
and they would still buy the same quantity.
Obviously if you raise it to a billion dollars,
they would just not be able to afford it.
But within reason, they're going to buy 100 vials a week,
no matter what the price is.
So this is an example of "perfect inelasticity."
Another way...so if you think of the physical analogy
that we talked about with elasticity
it's like a brick.
It doesn't matter how much...within reason once again,
any amount of force pulling or pushing
that a human could put on a brick,
it's not going to deform the brick in any way.
And likewise, any change in price within reason
isn't going to change the demand in any way.
It's perfectly inelastic.
And if you want to do the computation,
you could figure out the demand elasticity.
But let's say when you are going from a price of $5 to $1.
So the price went down by 4
and the quantity changed by 0.
So your % change in quantity ...
delta % change in quantity is equal to zero,
and your % is going to be over your % change in price.
Your % change in price, if you use the averaging method,
it would be going down by 4 over an average of 250.
It'll be a fairly large number
but 0 over anything is still going to be 0.
So it doesn't matter what that thing is over here.
Your elasticity of demand in this situation is 0.
And if you want to see
what this demand curve would look like,
let's plot it.
So this right over here is my price axis
and that is my quantity axis.
and so, no matter what,
let's say this is a quantity of 100 vials per week.
That's true when the price is $5.
They're going to demand 100 vials per week.
That's true when the price is $1.
And that's true if the price is $20 or $100 or whatever--
they're going to demand 100 vials per week.
So a perfectly inelastic demand curve would look like this.
It is a vertical line.
It doesn't matter what price you pick--
the quantity demanded is always going
to be the exact same thing.
Now let's go to another extreme.
So this is perfectly inelastic,
you could imagine what is perfectly elastic?
Something that changes a lot
if you have a small % change in price.
And to think about that,
let's look at these two vending machines.
And we see that they both do sell cans of coke.
That's a can of coke there,
and that is a can of coke there.
Now let's say starting off, the can of coke,
let's say they cost $1 in each vending machine.
We're going to assume that this one,
remember all else equal,
so we're going to assume that
this vending machine right over here doesn't change.
So it's gonna be consistently charging $1 for a can of coke
and they're sitting next to each other and it looks like
they have a little coffee machine in between right over here.
So let's think about the demand curve for coca cola
in this vending machine right over here.
So let's think about the price and the quantity.
So let me do price column and quantity demanded.
So let's say if the price is a dollar
then, you know, just odds are,
it's going to get about half of the sales per week
and let's say that ends up being 100 cans per week.
Now what happens (let me put some decimals here)
So this is one dollar.
The price is $1 and it sells 100 cans per week.
We can probably ...
this one would also sell about 100 cans per week.
Now what happens
if we have a very very small change in price?
So if we go from a dollar
instead of a dollar we are at 99 cents.
What's going to happen?
So remember, this machine right over here is not changing.
We're talking about ... our demand curve is
for the quantity of cokes sold from this machine
and the price we're talking about is for this machine.
So if this machine is even a penny cheaper,
and assuming there aren't lines forming and things like that,
people are just always going to go to this machine.
If it's easy enough and there's no difference,
I will go to this machine.
So this machine will be able to sell all of the cokes.
So it's going to sell 200 cokes
Now what happens if,
instead of lowering the price by a penny,
you raise the price by a penny?
So instead of $1, you're at $1.01.
Well now everyone is going to go to the other vending machine.
They're going to say "oh, might as well walk to this one"
assuming everything else is equal.
So then they're going to sell zero
and so what would the demand curve look like here?
Well let's plot it out.
So this is the price,
this axis right over here is quantity,
and this is in cans per week
so this is zero, this is 100
and then this is 200
and then this is a price of $1, that's $1.
So at $1,
the quantity demanded is 100 cans, fair enough.
Now at 99 cents, the quantity demanded is 200 cans.
So at 99 cents the quantity demanded is 200.
So 99 cents is right below that--
it's 200 right over there,
just a little bit lower...
And at $1.01, a little bit over here,
the quantity demanded is 0.
So the demand curve here
is going to look something like that.
So it's going to be almost horizontal.
So it's going to be approaching perfect elasticity--
very small changes in price
end up with these huge changes in % quantity demanded
and I encourage you to work out the math you see here
that you will get a very large number for elasticity and
so something that is approaching perfect elasticity,
a truly perfect elasticity would be
something that is a horizontal line.
So in this case, our elasticity of demand,
and I'll talk about the absolute value of it, is zero.
And over here,
the absolute value of our elasticity of demand is infinity.
Because remember,
it's % change in quantity over % change in price.
When you go from one scenario to another over here,
your percent change in price is very small.
It's roughly about 1% in this scenario right over here.
You're changing the price up or down about 1%
but then you see your quantity is changing
depending on which one you're looking at,
your quantity is changing
on the order of 50 to 100% from that 1% change in price.
So you have a huge elasticity of demand here.
It would actually be a number, but as you can imagine
as it becomes more and more sensitive,
as quantity demanded becomes
more and more sensitive to % change in price,
this curve is going to flatten out completely
and you will have
an infinite absolute value of your elasticity of demand.