just a remarkable portrait itself lifelike
i love to have such a collar and the hat and the feather
and couldnt she pose the way and she peeks
out at something.its so animated and its so really
wonderful. for all of the odephus and all the complexities in the costume
not only very natural but she comes with full energy
and curiosity.you feel as if you'll get a sense of
fucials. oh completely. this is commisisioned by her
husband here.on the eve of french revolution
her name is madame perregaux and supported by
elizabeth vishale the bronx. just look at the way the
many is constructed. she has taken a very
simple composition. very traditional of a woman
and to have ones potrait, with the curtain on
one side and space on the other in a balcony. but
she has created first of all a sense of immanuation
by creaating something barn and also some humor.
absolutely. but hse is also forgoing considering that
lovely orcorn at the lower right that begins to
send off a couple of other arcs of her arms, of her collar
of her hat and then of her lovely red ribbon
the just trims her waist though. she has taken a formal element
of that broken curtain that we see behind
of figures and portraits that made it something
much more playful. yeh really engaging and its jus a piece of
example masterful to how a portrait can be brought to life