In the last video
we saw that if we had a market
with perfect competition
and if the current short-term equillibrium price
is above the price necessary
or is above the price at which
the firms would be generating economic profit
then more and more firms would start entering
because if the economic profit is positive
then that means it is a better place
to use your resources
than whatever your opportunity cost is
You're making profit
above and beyond your opportunity cost
so more and more enter it
so after a little bit
after one company enters it
or maybe the same firm
starts adding more seat-miles
or adding more planes
we have another short-term supply curve
that looks like that
and then a new equilibrium price
that's a little bit lower
and a new equilibrium quantity
that's a little bit higher
and that keeps happening
still your equilibrium price was higher
than your price necessary
for a normal profit
or a zero economic profit
and so more people enter still
and so we have another
short term supply curve
and we move further to
the bottom right of this demand curve
and then it keeps happening
until we have a supply curve
where the equilibrium price
where this new short term equilibrium price
is the same as the price
at which everyone is making a normal profit
or the price needed for zero economic profit.
at that point
people are neutral
whether they drop out
or enter into the market
and so the quantity remains stable
and so that's why
we view each of these curves over here
as our short run supply curves
but this line right over here
we do in yellow
this line over here
we've talked about this in previous videos
that's why this line over here
we call the long run supply curve
because depending on
whether the equilibrium price
is above or below this
at some point the supply
will enter or exit the system
so that we eventually get back
to some point
along this long run supply curve right over here
Now this was assuming perfect competition
many players
identical products
identical air travel
no barriers to entry
Let's think about what happens
if we have the exact opposite
of perfect competition
so we're gonna start at the same point
we're gonna start there
so we're gonna start
at the green supply curve
and we have this red demand
this orange demand curve
but let's say that instead of
having perfect competition
we live in a country where they say
and there are countries like this
where they say
there is only one air carrier
that can do business
it is the national air carrier
in our country
so instead of many players
we now have one player
and then obviously it's an identical product
well they only sell one product
one player
HUGE barriers to entry
no one else
you can also say infinite barriers to entry
no one else by law
is allowed to enter into this
I'm going into the extreme case
and obviously there is the ultimate advantage
for the existing player
they are the one that the government
the only one that the government
is allowing to participate
and price information
we dont really care about
there's only one price quote
coming from one player.
Now when we do that
when we talk about one player
as the only player in the market
we are not talking about
perfect competition
we are then talking about a monopoly
And it is the same word as
perhaps one of your favorite board games
and that comes from
the point of that board game
is to own all of the properties
of one of those colors
so at least in the framework of that board game
the Monopoly board game
you know the Parker Brothers board game
you have a monopoly on the blue
you know if you own park place and boardwalk
you have a monopoly
on that part of the market
so thats what you'll try to do.
when you have a monopoly
you can then charge higher prices
for when someone lands on your space
and something very similar
will happen here
now we only have one player
and lets say that right now
the equilibrium price
is higher than the price you need
to have zero economic profit
so we have one player
and that player is definitely
getting some seriou economic profit
well, they could just sit there
because no one else can enter
you're not gonna have this trend
where more and more supply
gets on the market
until you get to this
long run supply curve
in fact there will not be
this long run supply curve
the long run supply curve is
whatever frankly the monopolists decide
they want to do
if this is where
their profits are optimized
theyll do there
In fact they could even
go the other direction
even though they're already
making some economic profit
they might determine
"Hey we could make even more economic profit
if we lowered the quantity offered even more."
so they might even
take supply out of the market
and so they could have a new supply curve
that looks like this
we have a new equilibrium price
that is even higher
and is at a lower equilibrium quantity
they could even do more
they could raise price even more
and so you have a new equilibrium price
that is up here
and a lower equilibrium quantity
So clearly when you have a monopoly
something not so good is happening
for the consumer
they are able to raise price
it's actually not even efficient
because the optimal quantity
is not being produced
but I want to leave you there
and maybe leave you with
something to think about
I said that the monopolist now
because they dont have to worry about
other people entering in
to kind of lower the price
and get to this normal profit line
because they dont have to worry about that
they can set their quantity
to whatever they want
or I guess another way you could think about it
they could set their price to
whatever they want
and get the corresponding quantity
but the question is how do they set that
how do they determine
where along this curve
that they would like to
either set the price
or I guess you could say
set the quantity
by limiting production in some way