You could never have too much
practice dealing with the
normal distribution, because
it's really one of those super
important building blocks
for the rest of statistics.
And really, a lot of your life.
So what I've done here is I've
taken some sample problems--
this is from ck12.org's
open source flex book.
Their AP statistics flex book.
And I've taken the problems
from their normal
distribution chapter.
So you could go to their
site and actually look
up these same problems.
So this first problem: which of
the following data sets is most
likely to be normally
distributed?
For the other choices, explain
why you believe they would not
follow a normal distribution.
So let's see, choice a.
So this is a really--
this is, you know, my
beliefs come into play.
So this is unusual in
the math context.
It's more of a,
what do I think?
It's kind of an essay question.
So let's see what
they have here.
A, the hand span.
Measured from the tip of the
thumb to the tip of the
extended fifth finger.
So I think they're talking
about-- let me see if
I can draw a hand.
So that's the index finger, and
then you've got the middle
finger, and then you've got
your ring finger, and then
you've got your pinky.
And a hand will look
something like that.
I think they're talking
about this distance.
From the tip of the
thumb to the tip of the
extended fifth finger.
Which is a fancy way of
saying the pinky, I think.
They're talking about that
distance, right there.
They're saying, if I were to
measure it on a random sample
of high school seniors,
what would it look like?
Well, you know,
how far this is.
This is a combination
of genetics and
environmental factors.
Maybe how much milk you drank
or how much you hung from your
pinky from a bar when
you were growing up.
So I would think that it
is a sum of a huge number
of random processes.
So I would guess that it is
roughly normally distributed.
You know, if I look at my own
hand, and my hand I don't
think has grown much since I
was a high school senior.
It looks like roughly
9 inches, or so.
I play guitar.
Maybe that helped me
a stretch my hand.
But if that, you know, it's
really an essay question.
So I just have to
say what I feel.
So I would guess that the
distribution would look
something like this.
I don't know.
I've never done this.
But, you know, maybe it has a
mean of 8 inches or 9 inches,
and it's distributed
something like this.
Maybe it probably does look
like a normal distribution.
But it probably won't be a
perfect-- in fact, I can
guarantee it won't be a
perfect normal distribution.
Because one, no one can have
negative length of that span.
This distance can
never be negative.
So they're going to have a-- I
guess, you could have no hand.
So that would maybe
be counted as 0.
But the distribution wouldn't
go into the negative domain.
So it wouldn't be a perfect
normal distribution on
the left hand side.
It would really just
end here at 0.
And even on the right hand
side, there are some physically
impossible hand lengths.
No one can have a hand that's
larger than the height of
the earth's atmosphere.
Or, you know, an
astronomical unit.
You would start
touching the sun.
There is some point
which is physically
impossible to get to.
And you know, in a true normal
distribution, if I were to flip
a bunch of points, there's some
very, very small probability
that I could get 1,000,000
heads in the row, in a row.
It's almost 0, but there's
some probability.
But in the case of hand span,
there's no way-- out here-- you
know, the probability of a
human being who happens to be a
high school senior having a, I
don't know, 1 mile length
hand span, that's 0.
So it's not going to be a
perfect normal distribution of
the outliers, or as we get
further and further
away from the mean.
But I think it'll be a pretty
good-- in our everyday world,
as good as we're going
to get-- approximation.
The normal distribution's
going to be a pretty good
approximation for the
distribution that we see.
I guess one thing that,
you know-- it's funny.
This is high school seniors.
When I did this, it was kind of
from my point of view, a guy.
And I would argue that, you
know, high school senior guys
probably have larger hands than
women, so that it's possible
that you actually have a
bimodal distribution.
So instead of having it like
this, it's possible that the
distribution looks like this.
That you have 1 peak for
guys, maybe at 8 inches.
And then maybe a slight--
another peak for women
that, you know, I don't
know, at 7 inches.
And then the distribution
falls off like that.
So it's also possible
it could be bimodal.
But in general, a normal
distribution is going to be
a pretty good approximation
for part a of this problem.
Let's see what part b-- what
they're asking us to describe.
The annual salaries of
all employees of a
large shipping company.
So if we're talking about
annual salaries, we have
minimum wage laws, whatnot.
So I would guess at any
corporation, if we're talking
about full-time workers at
least, there's going to be
some minimum salary
that people have.
So I would say-- and probably
a lot of people will have
that minimum salary.
Because it'll be probably the
most labor intensive jobs.
You probably have-- most people
are down there at the low
end of the pay scale.
And then you have your
different middle level
managers and whatnot.
And then you probably
have this big gap.
And then you probably have
your true executives.
Maybe your CEO or whatnot.
If this mean right here is
maybe $40,000 a year, and this
is probably $80,000, where some
of the mid-level managers lie.
But this out here, this'll
probably be-- you know,
actually if you were to draw it
real, the way I've scaled it
right now, this would be
$80,000, this would
be about $200,000.
Which is actually a
reasonable salary for a CEO.
But the reality is that this
actually might get pushed
way out from there.
It might look
something like that.
It might be way off the charts.
You know, let's say the CEO
made $5,000,000 in a year,
because he cashed in a bunch
of options or something.
So it could be way over here.
And maybe it's a CEO and a
couple of other people,
the CFO or the founders.
So my guess is it definitely
wouldn't be a normal
distribution.
And it definitely would have a
second-- it would be bimodal.
You would have another peak
over here for senior management
up at the-- unless we're--
well, they're not saying, you
know, if we're in maybe Europe,
this would probably be
closer to the left.
But it won't be a perfect
normal distribution, and you're
not going to have any values
below a certain threshold.
Below that kind of
minimum wage level.
So I would call this-- when you
have a tail that goes more to
the right than to the
left-- call this a right
skewed distribution.
Since it has 2 humps, right
here-- 1 there and 1 there-- we
could also say it's bimodal.
I mean, it depends on what
kind of company this is.
But that would be my guess
of a lot of large shipping
companies' salaries.
Let's look at choice c.
Or problem, part c.
The annual salaries of a
random sample of 50 CEOs
of major companies.
25 women and 25 men.
The fact that they wrote this
here, I think they maybe are
implying that maybe men and
women-- you know, the gender
gap has not been closed fully,
and there is some discrepancy.
So if it was just purely 50
CEOs of major companies, I
would say it's probably close
to a normal distribution.
It's probably something like--
well, you know, once again,
there's going to be some level
below which no CEO is
willing to work for.
Although I've heard of some
cases where they work for free,
but they're really getting
paid in other ways.
If you include all of those
things, there's probably some
base salary that all CEOs
make at least that much.
And then it goes up to
some value, you know, the
highest probability value.
And then it probably has a
long tail to the right.
And this is if there
were no gender gap.
So this would just be a purely
right skewed distribution,
where you have a long
tail to the right.
Now if you assume that there's
some gender gap, then you might
have 2 humps here, which would
be a bimodal distribution.
So if you assume there's some
gender gap-- this is part
c right here-- then maybe
there's 1 hump for women.
And if you assume that women
are less than men, then
another hump for men.
And there are 25 of each, so
there wouldn't be necessarily
more men than women.
And then it would skew all
the way off to the right.
And, in fact, I think there
would probably be a chance that
you have this other notion
here, where you have these
super CEOs, or mega CEOs, who
make millions, while most
probably just make, you know,
just-- I'll put it in quotation
marks-- a few hundred thousand
dollars, while there's a small
subset that are way off, many
standard deviations
to the right.
So it could even be a
trimodal distribution here.
So that's choice c.
And then, so far, choice a
looks like the best candidate
for pure-- or the closest to
being a normal distribution.
Let's see what choice d is.
The dates of 100 pennies
taken from a cash drawer
in a convenience store.
100 pennies.
So that's actually an
interesting experiment.
But I would guess, once again,
this is really a question where
I get to express my feelings
about these things.
You know, as long as your
answer is reasonable, I
would say that it is right.
Most pennies are newer
pennies, because they
go out of commission.
They get traded out.
They get worn out as they age.
They get lost.
Or, you know, they get pushed--
you know, pressed-- at the
little tourist place into
the little souvenir things.
I'm not even sure if that's
legal, if you can do
that to money legally.
So my guess is that if you were
to plot it, you would have
a ton of pennies that are
within the last few years.
So if we were-- so the dates of
100 pennies, not their age.
So the dates.
So if this is 2010, I would
guess that right now, you're
not going to find
any 2010 pennies.
But you're probably going to
find a ton of 2009 pennies.
And it probably just
goes down from there.
And, of course, you're not
going to find pennies that are
older than, say, the United
States, or before they even
started printing pennies.
So obviously this tail
isn't going to go to
the left forever.
But my guess is you're
going to have a left
skewed distribution.
Where you have the bulk of the
distribution on the right, but
the tail goes off to the left.
That's why it's called a
left skewed distribution.
Sometimes this is called a
negatively skewed distribution.
And similarly, this right
skewed distribution
is sometimes called
positively skewed.
And if you have only 1 hump--
you don't have a multimodal
distribution like this-- in a
left skewed distribution,
your mean is going to be to
the left of your median.
So in this case, maybe
your median might be
someplace over here.
But since you have this long
tail to the left, your mean
might be some place over here.
And likewise in this
distribution, your median--
your middle value-- might be
some place like this.
But because it's right skewed,
and for the most part only has
1 big hump-- this hump won't
change things too much, because
it's small-- your mean is going
to be to the right of it.
So that's another reason why
it's called a right skewed,
or positively skewed,
distribution.
So to answer the question,
these are my feelings
about all of them.
But I would say, you know, for
the other choices explain why
you believe they would not
follow-- or they said, which of
the following data sets is most
likely to be normally
distributed?
Well, I would say choice a.
But it's really, you know,
a matter of opinion, at
least in this question.