Problem number 15, and we have two triangles.
So let's see, we have one triangle here,
one triangle like this.
We have another triangle that looks fairly similar.
I don't know if they actually are similar.
I haven't read the problem yet.
At least in the drawing,
they've drawn them to look fairly similar.
Then they tell us that this is triangle ABC.
This is triangle DEF.
We know that this is 8.
This is 5. This is x degrees.
This is also x degrees. This is 5.
Then they tell us that this is y degrees,
and that this is y degrees.
Now let's read the problem.
If y is equal to 60 in triangle DEF above,
how much greater
is the perimeter of ABC than the perimeter of DEF?
So y is equal to 60, right?
So what is this angle up here?
Well if we know that these two are the base angles--
well actually, we know 60, 60.
So what's this top angle going to be?
Well this is an equilateral triangle, right?
This also has to be equal to 60.
My brain's malfunctioning.
So if all the angles are the same,
then all the sides are the same as well, right?
It's 5 and 5.
That's an equilateral triangle.
Then the perimeter is 5 plus 5 plus 5, is 15.
This problem, we don't know the x angles,
but we know that they're equal.
So if these two base angles are equal--
we know from geometry class that,of course--
the sides are also equal.
So if this side is 8,this side is also 8.
So the perimeter here is what?
8 plus 8 is 16 plus 5 is 21.
They want to know how much greater
is the perimeter of this triangle than this triangle?
So 21 minus 15 is 6. That is choice C.
Next problem. Right? Yeah, choice C.
Problem number 16,
if x and y are positive, consecutive, odd integers
where y is greater than x,
which of the following is equal to y squared minus x squared?
So x and y are positive,consecutive, odd integers,
and y is greater than x.
So that means that y is equal to x plus what?
It's equal to x plus 2.
If they were consecutive just integers,
then y would be equal to x plus 1.
It would be 1 more than x.
But since we know that they're both odd,
and y is the next larger odd number--
the difference between any two odd numbers is 2--
so y is going to be 2 more than x.
If x is 5, then y is 7.
Consecutive, odd integers,if x is 3, y is 5.
y is 2 more than x.
So we know y is equal to x plus 2.
So they want us to kind of rewrite this expression.
Well we know from algebra class
we can factor this as y plus x times y minus x, right?
And then what is y plus x?
Actually, we don't even have to do this.
We don't even have to factor it.
We know what y is equal to, right?
y is equal to x plus 2.
So that is equal to x plus 2 squared minus x squared.
This is equal to-- we just multiply it out--
x squared plus 4x plus 4.
That's this term. Now we minus x squared.
So this cancels out with this,and we're left with 4x plus 4,
which is choice E.
Whenever I see something like this,
my first temptation is to factor it out.
You could have done it,
and then you could have substituted it back in.
But you didn't even have to do that.
Image: clear image,invert colors.
It's actually 6:30 in the morning after Thanksgiving.
You've got to appreciate my discipline.
All right, problem number 17.
My wife's actually a medical resident
and she had to work 36 hours yesterday.
Then she came home, essentially passed out,
missed Thanksgiving, everything,
and then she just went to work again.
She has like a 12-hour shift, it's crazy.
She only has a year left and I look forward to that.
But there might be fewer math videos once
I have my wife back.
But anyway, back to Math.
Problem number 17, in the xy plane,
line l passes through the origin
and is perpendicular to the line.
So l is perpendicular to the line 4x plus y is equal to k,
and l passes through the origin,
through 0,0-- that's the origin-- where k is a constant.
If the two lines intersect at the point t, t plus 1,
what is the value of t?
So first of all,
we know this line is perpendicular to this line.
So what does perpendicular tell us?
Perpendicular says whatever the slope was of this line,
the slope of this line would be the negative inverse.
So let's figure out what the slope of this line is.
So we know that 4x plus y is equal to k.
So y is equal to minus 4x plus k.
Now this is kind of familiar,y equals mx plus b format.
So the slope of this line is minus 4.
The slope equals minus 4.
So what is the slope of l?
Well l is perpendicular to this line.
So we know that
l is going to have the negative inverse of this slope.
So the negative inverse of minus 4 is--
well it'll become positive, and you take the inverse.
The slope of l is 1/4.
We also know that l goes through the origin.
So its y-intercept is 0.
So we know the equation of l.
We know that the equation of l is y is equal to 1/4 x.
We know there's no plus b,because it goes through 0, 0.
If you didn't believe me, you can put 0, 0 in here
and then solve for b.
You'll get 0 equals 0 plus b.
So b is 0.
But anyway, so this is l.
We've solved for the equation for l.
Now they tell us that we intersect-- where was the problem?
I lost track of the page--
we intersect at the point t, t plus 1.
They want to figure out what t is.
So when x is t, y is t plus 1.
So let's see, so y is t plus 1,
so t plus 1 is equal to 1/4. Then, x is t.
I just substituted t and t plus 1 for x and y.
Now we just solve.
Let's see, if we subtract 1/4 t from both sides--
let me finish this problem up here--
we subtract 1/4 t from both sides.
We get 3/4 t plus 1 is equal to 0,right?
I just subtracted 1/4 t from this 1t. So you get 3/4 t.
Subtract 1 from both sides,
you get 3/4 t is equal to minus 1.
Then you just multiply both sides times the inverse, 4/3.
So t-- this cancels out,of course--
t is equal to minus 4/3.
And what is my choice there?
Oh, there I go. Choice number A. I got scared.
I looked at the wrong problem,I didn't see my choice.
I thought maybe I did it wrong.
Choice number A.
And I will do problem 18 in the next video.
I'll see you soon.