Ever since the franco-prusian
war in 1870 to 1871
the Germans recognized that they were
likely to face another war with france.
That was a war that allowed Germany
to unify the humiliated France,
they were able to capture some very
valuable territory from France,
in particular Alsace-Lorraine,
which is very mineral rich,
and so the Germans were plotting to
uh... what are we going to do if
we're going to get into
another war with them.
At the same time, once France
and Russia had this alliance,
Germany fully recognized that
if there is a war with France,
it's likely to not be just with France,
it's likely to be a two-front war
on the western front... they will
be in conflict with France,
and on the eastern front they will
be they'll be in conflict with Russia.
And so to deal with this eventuality,
this is all the scheming that
Germany did in the decades
going up to Wold War One.
They came up with the Schlieffen plan,
and I'm sure I'm mispronouncing it...
Schleiff.. Schliff...
..Schlieffen plan,
named for Alfred von Schlieffen,
he was chief of the German Empire's
general staff from 1891 to 1905.
And it was based on how do you
deal with the two-front war,
and the general ideas here
were that Russia...
Russia had a large and almost
inexhaustible army but because it was
so large it would take a long
time for to mobilize...
long time...
...to mobilize.
and the Germans were actually able to
approximate it correctly 'cause this is
how long it did take the Russians
to mobilize at the beginning
of the World War One,
they estimated that it would take
them about six weeks.
So the Schlieffen plan called for
enough german troops on the
eastern front initially
in order to keep the Russians at bay, but
then the main fighting force of the germans,
while the Russians are mobilizing,
is to go after France
and try to essentially
knock France out of commission
so that they're not facing a
two-front war anymore
and that have those troops go back
to fight against the Russians.
And the way that they wanted to do it
is by rolling through Belgium in a kind
of a wheel-like pattern like this,
and the reason why they want to do this
wheel-like pattern is that they correctly
predicted that the French were very eager
to get this territory right over here
and the French actually had a plan -
they called it "Plan 17" -
for going after Alsace-Lorraine,
it was an offensive plan
and the view is that the French
army is going in that direction,
if the german army rolls through Belgium
and is able to get them from the rear
they could put the french army
out of commission.
So in early august 1914, the
Germans was to declare war
on France and on Russia.
The germans tried to put
the Schlieffen plan into action
and they frankly almost succeeded.
So through april... sorry, through
august and early september
the Germans were able to,
essentially rolled through Belgium,
were able to roll through Belgium,
and keep the combined mainly
french forces but there is also
some assistance from
British, to keep them on their heels.
And this happened all the way
until early september
when they get near the Marne or a little
bit past the Marne river in France
and it was here that the...
the sixth french army
so, and when we talk about armies
we're talking about huge numbers
of troops, the...
the sixth french army had
over two hundred thousand troops
in it. When we're talking about
the battle of the Marne, which I'm about
to talk to, we're talking about a...
the first battle of the Marne,
we're talking about a battle
that involves two million troops,
so these are... these are battles
that are occurring on an epic
scale, just each of these armies,
this army or... this one right...,
or even the german armies,
we're talking about hundreds,
tens to hundreds of thousands
of troops, in general an army
characterize, you're talking
about over fifty thousand,
sixty thousand troops.
So what happens as you go to
early september, specially
september fifth 1914,
the sixth french army
recognize... recognizes a
mistake that the first
german army made. By
trying to roll around like this
they exposed their right
flank, so right over here
would be the right
flank of the german army.
And just as... most mammals...
our flanks are kind of our weak spot
that area between your ribs and your
hips, the same thing is true for armies.
The front of the army tends to be
where you have the strongest forces
and then you have your
supply routes going back,
so if you can outflank an army,
that's what a lot of military strategy
is designed around, you can
hit an army in it's weaker point.
so by september fifth, the first german
army recognizes, but it was too late,
by september sixth they were
at in battle they were uh...
they were essentially being
confronted by the sixth french army
and by essentially turning to meet
them, by turning to meet them,
they created an opening between
them and the second german army,
and that opening was able to... the
French and the British were able to
take advantage of that to essentially
put the Germans on their heels
after a month of advancing,
and so right over here you have
the various... you have the various
you have the various french armies
and they were assisted by the
british expeditionary..
the british expeditionary force.
and so from the battle of the Marne,
which was essentially most...
most historians would say between
september sixth or september fifth
september sixth and
september twelve
they were able to put the...
the Germans on the retreat,
the Germans retreated
pass the Aisne river,
and then once you get into november
and the end of year of 1914,
at essentially... the Germans essentially
entrenched themselves and
literally they were building
deep trenches in...
...in northern France, and a little
bit of western Belgium,
and what i have right over here
- let me see if I can draw -
what i have right over here
what the boundaries were
eventually happened after
the german suffered essentially
their first big defeat, they had
to ... they had to retreat,
and they had to literally retrench,
and this is what the borders
would then be like,
and they were and...
and these were literally
trenches getting dug here,
and these borders are... you know
this first stage of the war was
hugely dynamic, you had
armies moving fairly rapidly
over a period of weeks and months,
but then once the Germans retrenched,
you have a roughly this position being
static for the next three years
in the famous trench warfare of the western
front that you might have seen movies on.
And I want to emphasize this was a
big deal, the first battle of the Marne
sometimes is called the
"miracle of the Marne".
If that... if the Allies at the french,
with the british help,
were not able to push the Germans
back, they might have accomplished
the Schlieffen plan and actually
maybe they would have won WWI,
or at least been able to win the western
front fairly quickly and then been able
to deal with the Russians a little bit better.
But because of the "miracle at the Marne"
which was hugely bloody, were talking
about 500.000 casualties on both sides,
we're talking a hundred to two hundred
thousand dead on both sides,
but because of that, that was able to
hold off the Germans,
but it got the western front in this kind
of ugly three year long trench warfare.