Lets do another one of these dependent probability problems
You have 4 coins in a bag
3 of them are unfair in that they have a 45% chance of
coming up tails when flipped
the rest are fair
so for the rest of them they have a 50% chance of tails or 50% chance of coming heads
You randomly choose one coin from the bag and flip it 4 times
What is the percent probability of coming 4 heads
So lets think about it
when we put our hand in the bag and and we take one of the coins out
there is some probability that we get an unfair coin
and 3 of the 4 coins are unfair so there is a 3/4 probability that we get an unfair coin
and there is only one of the 4 coins which is fair so there is a 1/4 probability
that i get a fair coin
now, given that I have so unfair-- Lets remind ourselves
a unfair coin has a 45% chance of coming up tails so this means that I have a 45% chance
of tails which also means -- we have to be careful here
because they are asking us about heads
If I have a 45% chance of getting tails that means
I have a 55% chance of getting heads, right?
when I have a 100% chance of getting on of these 2
If its 45% for tails then 100 - 45 is 55 for heads
For the fair coin I have a 50% chance of tails and 50% for heads
fair enough
now I want to know in either of these senarios
what is the percent probability of getting 4 heads
so if given--I have got the unfair coin the probability of getting
4 heads is going to be 55% for each of those flips
so the probability of getting exactly 4 heads is going to be
0.55 times 0.55 times 0.55 times 0.55 and so the probability
of picking an unfair coin and getting 4 heads in a row
is going to be equal 3/4 times all of this business over here
so thats 3/4 times and this is 0.55 times itself times 4 times
so I could write it as 0.55 to the 4th power
And we will get the calculator out in a second
and actually calculate what this is
now lets do the same thing for the fair coin
If I did pick a fair coin
the probability of getting heads four times in a row
is going to be 0.5 times 0.5 times 0.5 times 0.5
or the probability of getting the fair coin which is 1/4 chance and getting 4 heads in the row is going to be
1/4 times all of this so its going to be 1/4 times -- this is just 0.5 times itself 4 times so that's
so thats 0.5 to the 4th power
so lets get the calculator out to caculate one of these
so we get 3 divided by 4 times -- and it knows when I do the multiplication
its not in the denominator here
so its 3/4 times -- and I will just do it in parentheces
not to do in parenthesies because it the order of operation
so .55 to the fourth power is equal to 0. -- let me write it down
take it off the screen so that I can write properly
actually let me do both of these calculations
so this probability is that one right over there
and then this one down here is 1 divided by 4 times .5 to the 4th power
so its equal to that right over there
and so lets be clear
the probability of picking the unfair coin and then getting 4 heads in a row
is this top number its like roughly 6.9% chance
that you get the unfair coin and then get 4 heads in a row
the probability that you get the fair coin and then get 4 heads in a row
is even lower -- its only a 1.6% chance
now the probability of getting 4 heads in a row either way is going to be
the sum of this and this or the sum of that and that
which is going to be --let me get my calculator out
so its going to be equal to I could just take the previous Ans
let me just e type it so that I don't confuse you
so .015625 + .0686296875 -- I am going to round it anyway
wont matter too much
so if I take the sum -- let me take this of screen so I can still see
and that let me write it
so what I got here this one is 0.068629 -- I willl round it 7
and this down here was 0.015625
and when you add these 2 up
because we just care about getting 4 heads either way
there is a probability of getting it this way, the unfair coin
this is the probability of getting it with the fair coin
we want it either way so lets add the 2 which we have already
done on our calculator so if you add that number to that number
you get 0.08425 -- its keeps going -- I am just going to round it
so this is equal to8.425% or 8.43% chance of getting 4 heads in a row
and once again that's a slightly
higher number than if all the coins were fair
because there's a 3/4 chance that I get a coin that has
a better than even chance of getting heads
so thats why this number is going to be a little bit higher than the
probability if I had a fair coin of just getting 4 heads in a row