Let's say we have triangle A, B, C, say it looks something like
I wanna think about the minimum amount of information
I wanna come up with a couple of postulates
that we can use to determine whether another triangle
is similar to triangle A-B-C
So we already know that if, if all three angle,
all three of the corresponding angles are congruent
to the corresponding angles on ABC, that we know
that we're dealing with congruent triangles
So, for example, if this is 30 degrees, this angle is 90 degrees
and this angle right over here is 60 degrees
And we have another triangle that looks like this,
that looks like this, it's clearly a smaller triangle,
but its corresponding angles, so this is 30 degrees,
this is 90 degrees and this is 60 degrees
We know that X-Y-Z in this case is going to be similar
to A-B-C
So we would know, we would know from
this because corresponding angles are congruent
We would know that triangle ABC is similar to triangle XYZ
And you gotta get the order right to make sure
that you have the right corresponding angles
Y corresponds to the 90 degree angle, X correspond
to the 30 degree angle, A correspond to the 30 degree angle
so A and X are the first two things
B and Y, which are the 90 degrees, second two
and then Z is the last one
So that's what we know already, if you have three angles
But do you need three angles?
If we only knew two end of the angles, would
that be enough?
Well, sure
Cause if you know two angles for a triangle, you know the third
So for example, if I have another triangle, if I have a triangle
that looks like this, I mean to look or draw it like this
And if I told you that only two of the corresponding angles
are congruent
So maybe, maybe this angle right here is congruent
to this angle and that angle right there is congruent to
that angle
Is that enough to say that these two triangles are similar?
Well, sure because in a triangle, if you know two of the angles
then you know what the last angle has to be
I you know that this is 30 and you know that is 90
then you know that this angle has to be 60 degrees
Whatever you, whatever these two angles are, subtract them
from 180 and that's going to be this angle
So in, in general, in order to show similarity, you don't have
to show three angles are, three corresponding angles
are congruent
You really just have to two, show two
So this it'll be our, the first of our similar, similarity postulates,
We call it Angle-Angle
If you can show two that corresponding angles are congruent
then we're dealing with similar triangles
So for example, just to put some numbers here, if you showed,
if this was 30 degrees and we know that on this triangle
this is 90 degrees right over here
We know that this triangle right over here is similar to
that one there
And you can really just go to the third angle pretty straight,
in a pretty straight forward way
You say this third angle is 60 degrees so all three angles
are the same
That's one of our constraints for similarity
Now other thing we, we know about similarity is
that the ratio between all of the sides are going to be the same
So for example, if we have another triangle right over here
Let me draw another triangle
I'll call this triangle, I'll call this triangle X, Y and Z
And let's say that we know that the ratio between A B
and X Y, we know that AB over XY,
so the ratio between this side and this side
Notice, we're not saying that they're congruent, we're just saying
that they're ratio, we're looking at the ratio now
We're saying that AB over XY, let's say that
that is equal to BC, BC over YZ
That is equal to BC over YZ and that is equal to AC,
that is equal to AC over XZ
So once again, this is one of, this is one the ways we say,
Hey! this means similarity
So if you have all three corresponding sides,
the ratio between all three corresponding sides are the same
then we know that we are dealing with similar triangles
So this is what we call Side-Side-Side Similarity
and you don't want to get this confused
with Side-Side-Side Congruent
So this are all of our similarity postulates
Similarity postulates or axioms
or things that we're gonna assume
and then we're gonna build off of them to solve problems
and prove other things
Side-Side-Side, when we're talking about congruence, means
that the corresponding sides are congruent
Side-Side-Side for similarity, we're saying
that the ratio between corresponding sides are going to be the same
So for example, if this right over here, if this right over here is,
let's say this right over her is 10 - let me, no, think
of a bigger number - let's say this is 60, this right over here is 30
and this right over here is 30 square roots of 3
And I just made those numbers right cause, you, you,
what we will soon learn what typical ratios are of
the sides of 30, 60, 90 triangles
And let's say, this one over here is 6, 3 and 3 square root of 3
Notice, AB over XY, AB over XY, 30 square root's of 3
over 3 square root's of 3 this will be 10, this will be 10
What is BC over XY?
30 divided by 3 is 10
And what is 60 divided by 6?
What, or, AC over XZ, AC over XZ,
Well that's going to be 10
So in general to go from the corresponding side here
to the corresponding side there, we always multiply
by 10 on every side
So, we're not saying that they're congruent or,
or we're not saying are the side
for this Side- Side-Side for similarity
We're saying that we're really just scaling them up by
the same amount
Or another way to think about it,
the ratio between corresponding sides are the same
Now what about, what about if we had,
if we had, let's start another triangle right over here
Let me draw it like this
I shall not leave this here so we can have our list
So let me draw another triangle ABC
Let's draw another triangle ABC, So this is A,B and C
And let's say that we know, let's say that we know
that this side to go, when we go to another triangle,
when we go to another triangle that,
we know that XY, that we know
that XY is AB multiplied by some constant
So, A, so I can write it over here, XY is equal
to some constant times AB
Actually let me make XY bigger so it actually, it doesn't have to be,
that constant can be less than 1, in which case
it would be a smaller value, but let me just do it that way
So let me just make XY look a little bit bigger
So let's say that this is X and that is Y
So let's say that we know, that XY, XY over AB, over AB is equal
to some constant
Or if you multiply both sides by AB,
you would get XY subscaled up version of AB
So, you know, maybe this is, maybe AB is 5, XY is 10
then our constant would be 2
We scaled it up by a factor of two
And let's say we also know, we also know
that angle ABC is congruent to XYZ
and I'll had another point over here
So let me draw another side, right over here, so this is Z
So let's say we also know that angle ABC is congruent to XYZ
Now let's say we know that the ratio
between BC and YZ is also this constant
The ratio between BC and YZ is also equal to the same constant
So an example where this is 5 and 10, maybe this is 3 and 6
The constant we're kind of doubling the length of the side
So is this triangle, is triangle XYZ going to be similar
Well if you think about it there's only one, if you say
that this is some multiple, if X, if XY is, is
the same multiple of AB as YZ is the multiple of BC
and this, the angle in between is congruent,
there's only one triangle we can set-up over here
We're, we're only constraint to one triangle right over here,
and that, and so we're completely constraining
the length of this side
And the length of this side is going to have to be
that same scale as that over there
And so we call that Side-Angle-Side Similarity, Side-Angle-Side
So, once again, we saw SSS and SAS in our congruent's postulates
but we're saying something different here
We're saying that in, in SAS,
if the ratio between one corresponding side and
the other corresponding, one corres
if the ratio between corresponding sides of
the two triangle are the same
So AB and XY of one corresponding side,
And then another corresponding side, so
that's that second side, so that's between BC and YZ
and the angle between them are congruent
then we're saying it's similar
For SAS, for congruency we said that the sides actually had
to be congruent
Here, we're saying that the ratio between
the corresponding sides just has to be the same
So for example, SAS just to apply it,
if I have, let me just draw, show some examples here
So let's say I have an exam a triangle here that is 3,2,4
And let's say we have another triangle here,
we have another triangle here that has length, that has length 9,6
We also know that the angle in between i are congruent
So that, that angle is equal to that angle
What SAS ins ins in the similarity world tells you is
that these triangles are definitely going to be similar triangles
That we're actually constraining because
there's actually only one triangle we can draw right over here
It's the triangle where all of the sides are going to have
to be scaled up by the same amount
So there's only one long side right here that we can actually draw
And that's going to have to be scaled up by three as well
There's only have,thi thi this is the only one possible triangle,
if you constrain this side, if you're saying look, this is 3 times
that side, this is 3 times that side and the angle between them
is congruent, there's only one triangle we can dra we can make
And we know there, there is a similar triangle
there where everything is scaled up by factor of 3
So that one triangle we can draw, has to be that one similar triangle
So this is what we're talking about, SAS
We're not saying that this side is congruent to that side or
that side is congruent to that side
We're saying that they're scaled up by the same factor
If we had another triangle, if we had another triangle
that looked like this, So maybe this is 9, this is 4
and the angle between them were congruent
You couldn't say that they're similar because this side is,
is scaled up by a factor of 3
This side is only scaled up by a factor of two
So this, when we write over there, you could not say
that it is neccess necessarily similar
And like wise, if you had a triangle that had length 9 here
and length 6 there but you did not know, you did not know
that these two angles are the same
Once again, you're not constraining this enough
and you would not know that those two triangles
are necessarily similar
Cause you don't know those, that middle angle is the same
Now you might be saying there's a few other postulates
that we had, we had, we had A AS when we dealt with congruency
but if you think about it,
we've already shown that two angles by themselves
are enough to show similarity
So why worry about an angle, angle and a side or
the ratio between the sides
Why even worry about that
And we also had Angle-Side-Angle in congruence
but once again, we already know that two angles are enough
so we don't need to throw in this extra side
So we don't even need this right over here
So these are going to be our similarity postulates
And I want to remind you, Side-Side-Side, this is different
than the Side-Side-Side for congruence
We're talking about the ratio between corresponding sides
We're not saying that they're actually congruent
And here, Side-Angle-Side, it's, it's different
than the Side-Angle-Side for congruence
It's kind of related but we're here, we're talking about
the ratio between the sides, not the actual measures