We are at the Musee d'Orsay and we are looking at a really early and important Henri Matisse.
This is Luxe, Calme et Volupte.
The title, and the subject, comes from a poem by Baudelaire,
and it's a really enigmatic painting and one that I think we should locate in its making.
It was made during a summer trip to a seaside,
with one of the great post-impressionist painters Signac who was a pointillist
And so you can clearly say the influence of that art and the art of Seurat and Signac here,
But this is not pointillism.
It does use these little brushstrokes which have pieces of independent color
but it's using it in a way that really, in a sense, doesn't understand or isn't interested in the optical effects that Signac was interested in.
They are much more intense colors. They are very vivid and saturated colors,
used very unnaturalistically -- not used in the way that Seurat was interested in.
In terms of increasing luminosity
Here the colors are almost an affront to the senses
There are reds and purples and oranges
Well that's perfect because the next year Matisse
With a number of other painters will become known as "Les fauves"
The wild beasts
That's right using color in such radical and aggresive ways
that they are accused of being madmen.
And you can definitely see that beginning to happen here.
But this is a painting that's meant to have a kind of classical aspect to it
It's not meant to be sort of aggresive in that sense. There is a real tension here
There is, between the notion of luxury, of calm, of this kind of ideal almost classicized past
and of course this wildly imaginative use of color.
But there is also a tension between the forms themselves which seem classical
and created in a way where line is primarily important.
These beautiful harmonious lines and the arrangement between the figures
That might remind us of the art of Puvis de Chavannes or in Cezanne's bathers
Structured relationship of forms and that in contrast with this wild color...
it's creating this tremendously activated surface where it seems like the paint is constantly shifting and in motion.
It seems so antithetical to the calm
To the very subject matter. It's an artist who is in total flux, who is looking for a pathway
Who's looking to understand what painting can now do.
What to do with this extraordinary freedom that is available to the artist at the beginning of the 20th century.
Exactly, I think that the artist at the end of the 19th century had bequethed to the artist of the early 20th century
this incredible freedom in terms of color, thinking about the painting as an independent unit and structure
That could have its own internal organizaiton.
A sense of subjectivity of the interiority of the artist as important
One feels that this is a moment of transition
and yet the painting itself is a tour de force, it's an incredibly beautiful thing to look at
Even with all of its internal contradictions