Let's do some example problems
using our newly acquired knowledge
of isosceles and equilateral triangles
So over here I have a kind of a triangle within a triangle
And we need to figure out this orange angle right over here,
and this blue angle right over here
And we know that side AB is equal to！
or segment AB is equal to segment BC, which is equal to segment CD,
or we could also call that DC
So first of all, we see that triangle！ triangle ABC is isosceles
And because it's isosceles,
the two base angles are going to be congruent
This is one leg, this is the other leg right over there
So the two base angles are going to be congruent
So we know that this angle right over here is also 31 degrees
Well, if we know 2 of the angles in a triangle,
we can always figure out the third angle
They have to add up to 180 degrees
So if we！ we could say 31 degrees + 31 degrees
+ the measure of angle ABC is equal to 180 degrees
You could subtract 62
This right here is 62 degrees
You subtract 62 from both sides,
You get the measure of angle ABC is equal to
Let's see
You subtract another 2, you get 118 degrees
So this angle right over here is 118 degrees
Let me just write it like this
This is 118 degrees
Well, this angle right over here,
this angle right over here is supplementary to that 118 degrees
So that angle + 118 is going to be equal to 180
We already know that that's 62 degrees!
62 + 118 is 180, so this right over here is 62 degrees
Now, this angle is one of the base angles for triangle BCD
I didn't draw it that way, but this side and this side are congruent
BC had the same length as CD
Those are the 2 legs of an isosceles triangle
You can kind of imagine it was turned upside down
This is the vertex
This is one base angle
This is the other base angle
Well, the base angles are going to be congruent
So this is going to be 62 degrees, as well
And then finally, if you wanna figure out this blue angle
The blue angle + these two 62 degree angles
are gonna have to add up to 180 degrees
So you get 62 + 62 + the blue angle,
which is the measure of angle BCD, measure of angle BCD,
is gonna have to be equal to 180 degrees
These 2 characters, let's see
62 + 62 is 124
You subtract 124 from both sides,
you get the measure of angle BCD, is equal to let's see
If you subtract 120 you get 60
and then you have to subtract another 4
So you get 56 degrees
So this is equal to 56 degrees
And we're done!
Now, let's！ we could do either of these
Let's do this one right over here
So what is the measure of angle ABE
So they haven't even drawn segment E here
So let me draw that for us
And so we have to figure out the measure of angle ABE
So we have a bunch of congruent segments here
And, in particular, we see that triangle ABD,
all of its sides are equal
So it's an equilateral triangle,
which means all of the angles are equal
And if all of the angles are equal in a triangle,
they all have to be 60 degrees
They all have to be 60 degrees
So, then, all of these characters are going to be 60 degrees
Well, that's part of angle ABE,
but we have to figure out this other part right over here
And to do that,
we can see that we're actually dealing with an isosceles triangle,
kind of, kind of tipped over to the left
This is the vertex angle
This is one base angle
This is the other base angle
And the vertex angle right here is 90 degrees
And once again, we know that it's isosceles because this side,
segment BD is equal to segment DE
And once again, these two angles + this angle right over here
is going to have to add up to 180 degrees
We call that an x, you call that an x
You get x + x + 90 is going to be 180 degrees
So, you get 2x +, let me just write it down
Don't wanna skip steps here
We have x + x + 90 is going to be equal to 180 degrees
x + x is the same thing as 2x, + 90 is equal to 180
And then we can subtract 90 from both sides
You get 2x is equal to 90, or divide both sides by 2,
you get x is equal to 45
X is equal to 45 degrees
And then we're done,
because angle ABE is going to be equal to
60 degrees + the 45 degrees
So it's going be this whole angle, which is what we care about
Angle ABE is going to 60 + 45 which is 105 degrees
And now we have this last problem over here
This one looks a little bit simpler
I have an isosceles triangle, this leg is equal to that leg
This is the vertex, and we have to figure out B
And the trick is that, wait,
how do I figure out one side of the triangle
if I only know one other side, or I need to know 2 other sides
And we'll do the exact same way we just did
to the 2nd part of that problem
If this is an isosceles triangle, which we know it is
Then this angle is going to be equal to that angle there
And so if we call this x, then this is x as well
We get x + x + 36 degrees is equal to 180
The two x's when you add them up, you get 2x and then
I'll just！ I won't skip steps here
2x + 36 is equal to 180
Subtract 36 from both sides
We get 2x！ that 2 looks a little bit funny
And then you wanna subtract another 6 from 150 gets us to 144
Did I do that right?
Divide both sides by 2, you get x is equal to 72 degrees
So this is equal to 72 degrees
And we are done