Well, here we are looking at Pontormos' 'Entombment,'
[or 'Deposition from the Cross' – ]
a typical Mannerist painting from about 1520.
And we want to use this as a starting-off point
to talk about what follows Mannerism.
Right, a kind of rejection of Mannerism is going to happen.
Absolutely, very rhetorically, a rejection of Mannerism
is going to come around, beginning in
the last quarter of the 16th century, and in the late 1570s,
especially 1580s and onwards.
And I can see why people would reject it.
I mean, it's incredibly complicated.
Exactly.
Its difficult to read.
Sure.
Its hard to tell whats going on.
There are a lot of reasons that this
doesn't sort of seem like the traditional definition of art –
especially when you think about the Renaissance
and its interest in naturalism.
All of the qualities, its difficulty in reading,
its enigmatic qualities  – the very stylized, elegant nature –
these were all things that made Mannerist art good,
in the Mannerist period.
But after over fifty years of Mannerism's dominance in Italy –
beginning in the 1520s, and reaching towards
the end of the century – a backlash does begin to build 
exactly towards the issues that you were talking about.
And there's a growing desire 
for many reasons – a few of which we will talk about –
for a return to the basic principles
of the High Renaissance –
which they look back upon – from 70 years later –
as a period when art was good –
for several different reasons.
Wow, and so one of the reasons that they are going to
reject Mannerism has to do with its legibility
at a time when the Church is being attacked,
and really needs art to communicate
in a very easy and direct way – (Right?)
– because of the Reformation.
Sure. The Protestant Reformation was criticizing art
coming out of the Catholic areas for being too distracting,
and for not communicating the story well.
And so, as we know, the Protestants tended to put
their emphasis on the written word in the Bible,
rather than on art, because they would point to
something like this and say,
"This is not a good religious teaching tool."
Right.
And the whole way the Church defended art
was by saying it was there to teach.
Right.
So then how could you point to this
and say that it is teaching anybody anything?
Exactly.
And so a new style –
as the Counter Reformation is building –
even beginning in the 1540s,
but especially towards the end of the century –
they feel that a new style is needed.
That makes sense.
Our story about this reaction actually starts in Bologna.
And it starts there for a couple of reasons.
One reason is that Cardinal Paleotti –
who was one of the leaders of the Counter Reformation –
was a bishop from Bologna.
And at the various meetings of the Council of Trent –
which was this religious convention to formulate
the Catholic response to the Protestant Reformation,
Cardinal Paleotti was in charge, essentially,
of figuring out what to do about art –
how to make good  – in quotes – 
art that would be immune
to the criticism of the Protestants.
Right.
And the Council of Trent also meets
in Bologna several times .
Oh, I didnt know that.
I thought they only met in Trent.
No. As frequently happened during this era –
sometimes when the plague
or other diseases would break out –
they would move the conference to other places.
And so, because you have this Bishop from Bologna,
and because, also, the Council is taking place –
sometimes in Bologna – it's almost first in Bologna 
that you see artists responding to this need
for an art that is basically more straightforward,
clear, legible – a good religious teaching tool –
Didactic.
Exactly.
And it gets rid of all of the ambiguities,
and the overwrought elegance
that they see being the problem, by now,
with some of the most characteristic works
of Mannerism that had come before.
Yeah and I noticed that here in this image of the crucifixion –
This is by --
This is by Annibale Carracci.
This is a crucifixion from pretty early in his career –
around the 1580s.
And this was made in Bologna.
In fact, you can see a little miniature Bologna
down at the bottom, as well as in the distance.
And here we see an artist, who, as a young man,
is trying to formulate a new style of painting,
in part – although not exclusively –
because of this new religious atmosphere
of the counter Reformation thats pushing artists
to make art that is legible, straightforward,
easy to understand, and properly communicates the stories
from the Bible or other religious texts.
What I notice most about it is this kind of
emotional quality to it, where the gestures are very –
It's very clear from everyone's gestures
and facial expressions what they're feeling.
Right.
The grasping of the chest, or the throwing out of the arms.
And the facial expressions.
A kind of overwrought acting going on.
Yes, that's definitely true.
And the style that Annibale Carracci
and his brother and cousin –
who are also artists working with him –
and others that soon will follow them,
this is going to give birth to the Baroque style.
And what you've just described are very much
characteristics of the Baroque style.
Bold gestures.
Bold facial expressions to make the meaning
in the narrative as clear as possible 
in absolute contrast to all of the ambiguities,
and the emotionless fanciful renderings
that we saw in these kind of scenes in Mannerism.
Right.
And also a kind of emotion to make things have
a kind of impact on the viewer too.
Which is something we didn't see so much
in the High Renaissance, when there was
a kind of distance in that ideal beauty.
Here, there's a kind of down to earth.
This is what the story is telling us.
This is how the figures are feeling.
Its definitely more dramatic and energized
than a High Renaissance composition might have been.
What I always say, is in some ways the Baroque style
is a return to the principles of a High Renaissance,
but with the volume turned way, way up.
Way up.
To 11. [LAUGHS]
Exactly.
Past 10.
Right. And so, the gestures and the facial expressions
are one way that this becomes very dramatic.
Baroque paintings like already we can see in this one,
tend to have dramatic lighting very frequently.
Right --
And then something else that also increases the intensity
and the legibility, and the clarity of the image
is that all the figures are quite large
and pressed right up against the front of the picture plane that
is very close to the viewer 
to really almost enter the viewer's space,
and really heighten that sense that you are there too 
you can experience this,
and this will heighten your religious devotion.
Also, typical of Baroque art and its rejection of Mannerism
is the intense or great simplification of the composition.
There are no complicated patterns.
There are no contorted positions.
Theres no enigmatic representation of space or foreshortening.
Everything is boiled down to its essentials.
There's nothing extraneous in these early Baroque paintings.
So its the narrative
Exactly
The narrative is the core.
There's nothing extra, there's nothing confusing.
The other thing also, that compared to Mannerist paintings
Carracci and their later Baroque followers
are very intent in creating very naturalistic images.
Gone is the very attenuated, elegance stylization of Mannerism
There's a return to basics also in the rendering
of the figure and its anatomical accuracy
and the representation of fabric, and depth,
and space and gravity, and three-dimensionality.
Everything that was illogical in a Mannerist work of art,
and praised for it at that time, now becomes
logical and clear and straightforward.
So theres kind of an implicit criticism.
Sure --
in Mannerism, a kind of saying, "Mannerism wasnt good art."
Well the 'Carracci' (followers) literally did say that.
They were not only artists, but they were art critics in a way.
And they were responding to the praise of Mannerism
from the earlier decades.
And saying, "No, this is not good art,
because it doesn't replicate nature,
because it's not based on study from life."
And so they go around looking at artists
who they thought of as good 
including the typical ones we think of
from the High Renaissance 
Like Raphael and Michelangelo and so on.
But also traveling to areas that didn't tend
to be emphasized in the literature as much 
traveling around their native region of Emilia.
But also looking at people like Titian and ?? in Venice.
And you can see all of these influences in their paintings.
And an early one like this,
where also in a later more mature work like this Lamentation 
which is around 1605.
Still, this is Annibale Carracci.
And we can see the basic hallmarks
of this new Baroque style that's emerged.
Intense, very dramatic rendering of the narrative.
But at the same time very simple, very straightforward.
There's no mistaking the emotions.
There's no mistaking the narrative in what's going on here.
Christ looks dead
but again also very strikingly naturalistic, very descriptive.
And you know, its so easy to read.
My eye goes first to this figure of Christ at the bottom 
whos been removed from the cross.
And then it goes up to Mary Magdalene 
whos got that kind of dramatic emotion,
you know, throwing her arms up, and kneeling,
and looking down at Him and then up to, I guess,
the other Mary 
The other Mary.
Reaching out to those arms that reach out
toward the third woman.
So then, our eye then moves across.
And then it moves down towards Christs mother.
And then back down towards Christ.
Theres a kind of way that the artist really is leading our eye
through the composition in a very sort of methodical way.
And also playing down the areas of the composition
that dont necessarily contribute to the narrative.
And so again, notice that the figures
are very close to the front of the picture plane,
and everything behind them is in dark  in shadow.
Theres no architecture, theres no 
Exactly.
Nothing to distract you.
Theres no elaborate landscape.
Right.
And also in terms of the composition,
we should say that here we can see
one of the most important features of all Baroque art,
in addition to the naturalism and the drama 
the very strong diagonal that cuts across the picture plane
also adding  I just notice that  two parallel diagonal lines 
also adding to the energized drama at the scene.