We're asked to graph the equation y=-2(x-2)^2 + 5.
So let me get my scratchpad out so we can think about this.
So it's y=-2(x-2)^2 + 5
So one thing when you see a quadratic, or a parabola, a graph expressed in this way,
a thing that might jump out at you
is that this term right over here
is always going to be positive cause it's some quantity squared
non-negative, it could be equal to zero, so it's always going to be
some quantity squared, and then we're multiplying it by a negative, so this whole quantity
this whole quantity right over here is going to be non-positive
it's always going to be less than or equal to zero
so this thing is always less than or equal to zero, the maximum
value that y will take on
is when this thing actually does equal zero. So the maximum value
for y is at 5, so y
the maximum value for y is 5, and when does that happen?
Well y hits 5 when this whole thing is 0, and when does this thing equal 0?
Well this whole thing equals 0 when x-2 = 0
and x-2 = 0 when x=2
so the point (2, 5) is the maximum point for this parabola and it is
actually going to be the vertex. So if we were to graph this,
so the point (2, 5)
so that's my y-axis, this is my x-axis
so this is 1, 2, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5
so this right over here is a point (2, 5).
This is a maximum point for this parabola, and
now I want to find two more points so that I can really determine the parabola. 3 points
determine, completely determine, a parabola. So that's one,
the vertex, that's interesting. Now what I like to do is just get two points that are
equidistant from the vertex, and the easiest way to do that is to
maybe just figure out what happens when x=1
and when x=3. So I can make a table here actually
to do that. So I care about x
being equal to 1, 2, and 3, and what the corresponding y is
We already know that when x=2, y=5.
(2, 5) is our vertex. When x=1,
1-2 is -1, squared is just 1
so this thing is going to be -2 + 5, so it's gonna be 3
and when x=3, this is 3-2, which is 1, squared is 1
times -2 is -2 + 5 is 3 as well
so we have 3 points. We have the point (1, 3),
the point (2, 5), and the point
(3, 3) for
this parabola. So let me go back to the exercise and I should
put those three points in. So we have the point
(1, 3), there's a point (2, 5)
and we have the point (3, 3)
and we have now fully determined our parabola.