Problem number six.
That's too skinny. I want to use this tool.
I had to restart my computer, so everything got reset.
If m and k are positive, it's fairly complicated.
And they that 10m squared k to the negative 1
is equal to 100m, what is m to the negative 1 in terms of k?
Let's see if we can simplify that thing I wrote at the top.
k to the negative one is equal to 100m.
Well let's divide both sides by 10, you get m squared.
k to the negative one--
that's the same thing as m squared over k-- is equal to,
and we divide the other side by ten, is equal to 10m.
Let's divide both sides by m, and they're positive,
so we can do that. So it's not 0.
So you get m over k is equal to 10,
because m squared divided by m is just 10.
m is equal to 10k.
But they don't want us to figure out what m is in terms of k
they want to know m to negative one.
Well m to the negative 1 is just 1 over m,
so if we just invert both sides of this,
we know that 1 over m is equal to 1 over 10k.
That's the same thing, of course, as m to the negative 1.
And 1 over 10k, that's choice D.
Problem number seven.
We are on problem number seven, that I will do in mauve.
Edna and Nancy leave the house for a common friend
at the same time, and walk for 4 hours.
4 hours is how far they walk.
Edna walks due east at the average rate
of 4 kilometers per hour.
Nancy walks due north at an average of 3 kilometers per hour
I'm doing this a little bit messy, but you get the point.
Nancy's going north, Edna's going east.
What is the straight-line distance
between them in kilometers at the end of 4 hours?
So this is Pythagorean theorem.
At the end of 4 hours, how far has Edna traveled east?
They're starting at the same point, oh I don't like that.
How far has Edna gone east?
Well, she's going to be going
4 kilometers per hour times 4 hours.
And that equals 16 kilometers.
That's how far Edna went east.
Now how far did Nancy go north?
Well she went at, oh my god I was using the line tool.
Undo.
So same thing, she went north at 3 kilometers
per hour times 4 hours.
So she traveled 12 kilometers.
This is a Pythagorean theorem problem.
After 4 hours, Nancy's there, Edna's there.
And you just need to figure out
the straight-line distance between them.
We just have to figure out this.
And actually, a trick to this,
let's say that we want to solve for x, you could say that
x squared is equal to 12 squared plus 16 squared.
And you could figure it out.
Or you can make the further realization that
this is essentially a 3, 4, 5 triangle.
You could say that this is 4 times 4, this is 3 times 4,
so this side is going to be 5 times 4.
If you remember your 3, 4, 5 triangle, Pythagorean theorem.
If you don't, just do this.
You get x squared is equal to 144 plus 256.
So x squared is equal to 400,
and then you get x is equal to 20.
So you could do it either way,
this would have been a little bit less math.
So x is equal to 20, so it is choice E.
East, the other one walks north.
This is choice E.
Problem number eight.
I'm using an old workbook that was used by my cousin
when she was in seventh grade.
She's now in tenth grade,
and she's marked up some of these problems.
So I have a little bit trouble reading.
And she was only in seventh grade,
but some of the problems are circled incorrect so that's
what's making me second guess myself every now and then.
But anyway, back to the problems.
She now doesn't get any problems incorrect,
back to the problem.
She's actually the reason why I started doing this,
because I worked with her, and she saw improvement.
And then I worked with her brother,and they saw improvement.
And then I said, well let me just make a bunch of videos,
so a bunch of people can see some improvement.
So let's see what they have drawn here
for problem number eight.
So let me draw the x-axis.
Let me draw the y-axis.
And then they drew a parabola.
The figure above shows the graph of a quadratic function
that has a minimum at point 1, 1.
At the point 1 comma 1, it has its minimum point.
Let me do that in a different color.
That's the minimum point there.
If f of b is equal to f of 3,
which of the following could be the value of b?
So on the graph they drew, if you go to 3.
1, 2, 3, and if you just follow up.
You go to 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, so you go up 5.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, there's a point here.
And at least this side of the parabola,
or the quadratic, goes something like this.
I'm trying to draw as carefully as possible.
And the other side is symmetric. It'll do the same thing.
And they say f of b is equal to f of 3.
So f of 3 is here, and if you want to get the exact number
it's f of 3 is equal to 5.
But that actually doesn't even matter.
Because this is 1, this is the point 1, 1.
This is the point, this is x is equal to 3.
And the big realization is, well this is a quadratic,
this is a parabola, this is it's minimum point.
So it's going to be symmetric around this point.
So if it reaches 5 here,
so it took 2 units to reach 5 going to the right,
going in the positive x direction.
So similarly, it's going to take 2 units to reach 1
going in the negative x direction.
So what's 2 units less than 1?
So 1, 2, you'd get to negative 1.
So at b could be equal to negative 1.
Actually b would be equal to negative 1.
So the correct answer is C.
The choice is b is equal to negative 1.
Let's see if I can squeeze in problem number nine.
Problem number nine.
A family of 5 is planning a 4-day camping trip.
So 5 people times 4 days.
Each person will need 1 bottle of water
for each day of the trip.
So times 1 bottle per day, per person.
If water is sold only in 3-bottle packages,
how many packages must the family buy for the trip?
Well how much water do they need?
There's 5 people, 4 days,
and they each need a bottle of water a day.
So they need 20 bottles.
And it only comes in packages of 3, or multiples of 3.
If they bought 6 packages it would be 18 bottles,
that's not enough.
So they have to get 7 packages.
7 packages times 3 is equal to 21 bottles,
so they have to buy 7 packages.
Not too bad. All right.
I'll do the next problem in the next video.
I'll see you soon.