Find the area and the perimeter of the polygon
so lets start with the area first
so the area of this polygon
and there's kind of two parts to this
first you have this part that's kind of rectangular
or it is rectangular
this part right over here
and that area is pretty straightforward
it's just going to be base times height
so the area's going to be 8 times 4
8 times 4 for the rectangular part
and then we have this triangular part up here
so we have this area up here
and for a triangle this area is base times height times 1/2
that actually makes a lot of sense
because you just multiply base times height
you would get this entire area
you get the area of the entire rectangle
and you see that the triangle is exactly half of it
if you took this part of the triangle
and you flip it over, you'd fill up that space
and you took this part of the triangle
so the triangle's area is half of
the triangle's base times the triangle's height
so plus 1/2 times the triangles base which is 8 inches
and the triangles height which is 4 inches.
so let us calculate it this gives us
it is not 4, triangles height is 3, so let us go back
and calculate it area = 32 + 1/2 * 8*3 = 32 + 12 = 44
area of the figure is 44
now let us do the perimeter.We need to figure out the
sum of the sides. If we need to put a fence
what is the length that we need to cover
so the perimeter = 8+4+5+5+4 =26 inches
Let me get the unit right, here we are multiplying
8 inches by 4 inches we get 32 square inches and
here we multiply 8 inches by 3 inches we get 24 square inches
divide by 2 we get 12 square inches.
area = 44 square inches, perimeter is 26 inches
area is two dimensional and perimeter is one dimensional