We are starting off with triangle ABC
When we see the triangle we know that length
of AB = AC. This is a triangle with 2 sides of equal length
We call this an isosceles triangle
This means two sides are equal to each other.
What i want to prove here is that these angles
the angles opposite to the sides that are equal
are the same. For side AC the opposite angle is angle ABC
and for side AB the opposite angle is angle ACB
I want to prove angle ABC = angle ACB
So we have a lot of information here
and the first step is to construct two triangles
to construct two triangles, set up another point D here.
Let us say D is the mid point of line BC
this means BD = DC.
Let me draw segment AD. Now we have constructed
two triangles, triangle ABD & triangle ADC
In these two triangles, AB = AC, BD = DC and they share
the side AD.We know that triangle ABD = traingle ACD
we know this because all sides of these triangles are equal
What is useful about this information is if the sides are equal
then their angles are equal.We have proved our result.
angle ABC = angle ACB
If we have an isosceles triangle with two sides equal
then their base angles or angle opposite to these sides
are equal.
Now can we make the other statement, if the
base angles are equal then the opposite sides are
of teh same length. Let us construct another triangle
this triangle is called ABC, and am going to start
with the idea that angle ABC = angle ACB
what we want to do is to prove
that sides AB = side AC
or length of AB = length of AC
We need to have two triangles to prove this.
Like we did earlier let us construct two triangles
This time instead of defining the other point as mid point
I am going to define D as the point that goes
straight down from A
This point intersects BC at a right angle
Then in the two triangles these angles will be 90 degrees
What is interesting about this is
i have constructed AD such that
AD is perpendicular to BC
So over here we an angle and side in common
We know these triangles are same by AAS method
that is Angle Angle Side ( AAS)
triangle ABD = triangle ACD
If we know two triangles are equal, then
every corresponding angle or side of the two triangles are same
So we know sides AB = AC
Now we have proved that if two angles are equal,
then their opposite sides are of same length
So side BD = side DC , side AB = side AC
So point D is not only the mid point ,
it is the place where AD bisects BC at 90 degrees
So we're starting off with the triangle ABC here.
And we see from the drawing that the length of AB is equal to the length BC.
Or line segment AB is congruent to line segment AC.
And since this is a triangle and two sides of this triangle are congruent
or they have the same length. We can say that this is an isosceles triangle.
Isosceles triangle a hard way for me to spell
And that just means that two of the sides are equal to each other.
So we're starting off with triangle ABC here
And we see from the drawing that the length of AB is equal to the length of AC