A: We are here at the Metropolitan Meseum of Art,
A: in New York, looking at a monumental sculpture of a Bodhisattva.
B: So, the Buddha's the main figure we often see, and there are many Buddha's in Chinese Buddhist art.
There is the historical Buddha, but lots of other figures.
And there are also Bodhisattva's, and that's what we're looking at, and one of the main ways you can distinguish
them is that the Bodhisatta's are often heavily adorned, like this figure is.
A Bodhisattva is an enlightened being that has chosen not to pursue Nirvana, but remain with ties to the earthly realm,
and secure enlightenment, or release of Samsara,
which is the cycle of rebirth for all sentient beings.
So, Bodhisattva's are seen as beings of compassion.
B: So, they've decided to forego Nirvana, and be here for us, for regular people. To help us achieve our own Nirvana.
A: And they're shown to have these worldly ties through their princely garb.
The iconography of a Buddha is shown in monk's garb, having relinquished all ties to the earth, all ties to material things.
So, you see the Buddha with the elongated earlobes and the jewels removed.
Here we see a Bodhisattva in princely robes, and heavily adorned with
valuable jewels, showing their connections still to the earth.
B: What's funny is that is the Bodhisattva of compassion, and yet I don't feel a lot of identification with it.
It's very frontal, it's very symmetrical, and severe, and kind of abstracted. And it feels very distant in that way.
A: There is a solemnness, a serenity, but there is also a haughtiness to the expression of this image.
B: Exactly, he must be about fifteen or twenty feet high, and I imagine it stood in the temple complex.
A: Yes; it's huge, and frontal, so perhaps it was the main image for worship in its location.
B: And often these kinds of figures would be shown as groups within a temple.
And this one was so large that it's likely that it is the main figure.
A: Often, Bodhisattva's are show flanking Buddha's, and they'll have the weight on one foot, turning toward
the Buddha that they're flanking. And this image is presented frontally, and often this Bodhisattva is
attributed to being Avalokitesvara -Guanyin- the Bodhisattva of compassion, the most popular
Bodhisattva for worship in China, under Mahayana-type of Buddhism.
B: One of the ways we would normally identify a Bodhisattva figure, since there are many Bodhisattva's, representing
different ideas, is by what they're holding, but unfortunately, this sculpture, being from the Sixth Century,
has suffered a lot of damage, and its hands are no longer with it, and so, we don't know what it held.
A: Right, we don't know what the attributes may have been, and Avalokitesvara -Guanyin- in China, often has the
Buddha, Amitabha, in the crown. And that's an attribute that distinguishes it, and makes it clear that the
iconography is Avalokitesvara, but here the Buddha is not there. It's more of a floral crown, so there is some
A: uncertainty over which Bodhisattva this actually is.
B: It's interesting how much we can tell about it, but how much of it is really in dispute by scholars.
And the styles of art that we see in Art History are so connected to the historical circumstances. Often politics, the government.
And we know that the period just before this was called the Northern Wei, which had a really different style.
A: Yes, what happens is in the Northern Wei, the styles that was predominant was weightless and very linear.
Important examples can be found in the cave temple of Yungang, where in Cave 6 you would see a Buddha,
or Bodhisattva image that shows no attention to the body form, but a lot attention to the fold and lines
of the drapery, and the shapes are weightless.
B: So that period known as the Northern Wei is about fifty years before this, and is a relatively stable time in parts of China -
A: Particularly in the North, absolutely.
B: - and then a period of political upheaval follows.
A: And the two strong dynasties that emerge in the North are the Northern Qi, in the East, and the Northern Chou,
in the West. And this is a very interesting Bodhisattva example, when you're thinking about that time period.
There are some characteristics that really indicate the Northern Qi, but others that indicate the Northern Chou.
And, granted, there's a lot of overlap in between the styles of Buddha's and Bodhisattva's that come out of the two
dynasties. One thing is this incredible opulence in terms of the drapery and the jewelry, details that are
often associated with the Northern Chou. The other aspect that is Northern Chou is the square shape to the face,
the block-like features. Both the Nothern Chou and the Northern Qi broke in from this Northern Wei aesthetic of
weightlessness, and show the Bodhisattva's and Buddha's with a lot of three-dimensional and geometric forms.
B: This figure is anything but weightless.
A: Absolutely. And you can see its monumental and columnar, but it has this weight and volume.
We are looking at it the way that it would've been viewed in the temple.
We would be looking up at it, which is why the head is so oversized.
B: So, the artist would've wanted to make sure that we could really see the head
A: Yes.
B: And from far below, one way to do that is to enlarge the head.
A: And looking at the facial features, in particular, there is a head at the Metropolitan Museum of Art that is from Xiangtangshan,
a Northern Qi site in China. And if you compare this head, you can see that this is much more block-like, but when you
look at the lips, and the eyes and the other aspects of the facial features, there is a similarity.
B: So, we're really talking about dynasties, different historical periods, and different regional styles emerging in different places.
And art historians really needing to study each of those places, and the art that emerges,
and then comparing and contrasting to locate a lot of these early figures.
Buddhism had only come to China had only come to China a few years earlier, from India.
And, in those few hundred years, the styles that developed from Buddhist art are really dependent on those different regions, and different dynasties.
And therefore, there's so much change going on.
A: And this is an interesting example of that because we see here this very abrupt break
with the weightless, linear aesthetic of the Northern Wei, to this much more volumetric,
massive forms that is associated with the Northern Qi and Northern Chou.
This source for this change is often identified as Gupta in India. Sensuous Gupta style.
B: It's really a puzzle (A: It is) in many ways. So many questions.
One thing we know for sure, because we can see the residue here, is that the sculpture was painted,
and probably painted many times to keep the color vibrant over the years.
A: What we're really looking at is probably remnants of Ming dynasty painting,
maybe Sixteen Century. But it would've been an originally painted as well.
B: So, its important to imagine in its original context, within a temple, sensuously painted
and in that kind of religious, spiritual context.
A: Yes, and a much darker environment as well, and surrounded by other sculptures and paintings.
Subtitles by DaLinMan