After the fall of the Soviet Union and even China's migration to a market-based economy - even though
they called themselves communists the economy is now essentially capitalist -
there's been a kind of general consensus around the world that capitalism is the way to go.
You know, just to put my bias... I am in that camp. I would consider myself a capitalist.
But what I wanna do in this video is do a little bit more of a nuanced discussion
of capitalism versus, say, socialism.
Because I feel like there has been especially here in the United States and in the West
there's sometimes a knee-jerk reaction against anything that even has a whiff of the government getting involved, or
even a whiff of socialism.
So I want to think more about what are we trying to achieve in the capitalist system,
and where we could fall into kind of the things we don't want to achieve
if some of the aspects of capitalism are allowed to go on without any type of controls or maybe some
type of regulation.
I don't wanna advocate anything, I just wanna give you maybe a framework for thinking about it.
So if you ask any capitalist including myself you say
what is good about capitalism?
I would say that it aligns everyone's incentives.
Good incentives.
If you work harder you can earn more, you can generate the capital for yourself.
You can use that improving standard of living.
You can reinvest that capital.
So it's a good incentive structure.
I am not saying that everyone is motivated purely by the desire to earn
I think, you know, there's plenty of people in the world who are motivated for the desire for social good, for elevating mankind
But the general sense is in a lot of parts is that those types of things are specific to certain domains, but
in other domains if someone's running a trucking company it's not clear that someone would run
a trucking company optimally just for the good for mankind
Maybe they would run some non-profit that way but a trucking company or a farm or something like that, who knows.
So in general you have a good incentive structure.
There is also this notion in a capitalist economy: that it's a meritocracy. It is meritocracy.
And I am gonna actually put a box around this
because a meritocracy in my mind is super-duper important
Almost everyone is a fan of a meritocracy
Even the communists were a fan of a meritocracy.
They would give exams to people and have the people who were successful have more authority within the communist regime.
So meritocracy is something that other, everyone lays claims to
And actually a lot of socialists or communists would claim that
extreme forms of capitalism when the wealth disparity becomes too extreme
where you have inherited wealth
actually goes against the idea of meritocracy
Let me put meritocracy here as well. We'll talk about that in a second.
And then the other idea is that you have innovation in capitalism
And these are all related ideas.
That if the incentives are good, if capital gets in the hands of people
who are most deserving of it, because they've somehow earned it
they somehow innovated
that it can also lead to innovation
because right people are handling the capital
Now if we go to the socialist's side of things
They'll say: well look, there's a social cohesiveness to this.
Let me write this down.
And I won't speak to... You know...
I don't claim what I'm going to do in these video is comprehensive of all of the pros and cons of either
I just wanna give a little bit nuance to the discussion.
So social cohesiveness
You won't have this situation where you have you know
a gazillionaire sitting behind the walled compound with armed guards and there are people right on the other side of that walled compound starving to death
and these people don't even necessarily view themselves as part of the same society, as part of you know
as somehow the responsibility to each other
And that is happening in some parts of the world.
where we have severe disparities of wealth.
Where the rich people don't even view themselves as the same species as the poor people.
Or even vice-versa
The other idea
and I'll put this thing in quotes, of "fairness"
I'll put it in quotes because one could say: well, it's fair
if you make more, if you work harder you should get more, you should innovate more, you should get more.
And this notion of fairness as well. But looking sometimes at wealth is so extreme, sometimes we have this notion of inherited wealth, generation after generation, old money
What's fair about that?
That people just rent people can extract the interest out of the wealth
and never have to work and other people have to work super hard and and really get nothing for it.
So you know, the notion of fairness I'll put over here as well.
Fairness... because there's arguments for either
And so like I said I am definitely biased to the capitalist side of things
I think there is an important... Two of these things that we have on the right hand side
But the reality - at least, you know, what we've seen in the economic experiments of the 20th century
is that even though communists and socialists might speak to these types of things
to large degree there is less social cohesivness; the senior communists in the Soviet Union would drive fancy cars
and they did have a very different lifestyle than the workers,
and they would hide that lifestyle, and then it would lead to a lot of hypocrisy
in general the extreme forms of socialism. Not clear that it was a meritocracy.
It might have been just the best people climbing up the party ladder that get to the top as opposed to the people
who would innovate actually, produce in a better way.
But with that's said I wanna give fair warning.
I want to give fair warning that capitslism, if it kind of goes unchequed in certain ways,
it can also lead to those same problems as socialism.
The main problems there when we think about good incentives.
I think the incentives, and once again, I'm giving my opinion here. The incentives work out well when you have a bunch of competitors
who can compete and innovate
And it makes complete sense. Let's say that this person comes up with an innovation
and because they have the innovation they are able to provide a better good that's cheaper to society
So they make more profit. It seems reasonable that that person should get more profit, more wealth and grow
And it could even be good for society because this person is an innovator.
Maybe there is an element of luck there,
but it seems like they are competent at managing these resouces so it's good for society to give them more resources to manage.
The problem where capitalism... the area where it becomes less clear that capitalism is unambiguously good
is the situation where this person becomes outright dominant.
So let's say that this person becomes so big that none of these other players can even compete with him.
So they all disappear; this person can just undercut everybody and all of the other players disappear.
This is a situation of a monopoly.
And the problem here - monopoly -
is that when this guy had competition he had every incentive to work harder,
had every incentive to innovate.
It was a meritocracy because the person who innovates well grows fastest
But once it gets to a monopoly stage and everyone else has died down,
this is the only player in the economy.
Then all of a sudden he has not incentive to innovate. This corporation or this person can just keep raising prizes,
there is no competition. There is no one who can say: hey I can make a better product, or I can sell it to you cheaper.
So it actualy goes against the ideas of innovation.
That's why it is really important, that's why it is the part of, especially in the United States , is part of the economic system
that you try to break up monopolies.
That you don't like monopolistic practices.
The other risk that you have when you start having a lot of wealth and a lot of influence of one entity or one person or one cooperation
And this sometimes can happen in a democratic and even in a non-democratic regime
Is that the control of resources aren't just control of those resources, aren't just control of land and buildings and railroads
They can also use it to influence government.
And in the United States this is kind of institutionlised in the form of lobbying.
And when you have access to resources and you can influence government in this way
you can get the government - so let's say this is the government over here -
You can get government to essentially do things for you,
so it works to you advantage, and maybe allowing you eventually to become a monopoly
So you can kind of view this as crony capitalism
where, you know, lobbying can be a form of legalised bribery.
And in that way you can kind of own the elected officials.
I'm not saying that this is happenning everywhere, but it could happen.
And in that situation you have the government acting at the behalf of these.
And once again it goes against the idea of a meritocracy.
Because when you have this cycle of developing, maybe this person right over here has the innovation
But this person does not have the influence with the government
and so this guy gets the government contract for the plane.
so this guy gets the tax benefits from the government
So he can be even more competitive. He can undercut this guy.
Even though this guy has the innovation.
The other element - and I could talk about this for hours,
and these are just things to think about - are the idea of inherited wealth
and I am not saying that inherited wealth is a bad thing
But there's this idea that let's say someone through their competence, maybe competence with a little bit a luck
is able to accrue a huge amount of wealth
and maybe they are not even a monopolist
but they are able to get a huge amount of wealth
but they were able to do it, that they were really good managers, they are this kind of this, you know, really smart dude.
He can really manage a lot of resouces well.
The question arises is what happens when this person passes away.
In the very purely capitalist situation you pass this on to your children.
And the issue here is, one, what did this person do to earn it
And also from a society's point of view, maybe this person here is a dummy
maybe, you know, maybe there is another kid over here
who was born exact the same time who is way, you know, way smarter, and who, you know...
But this kid is now in control of a hundred gazillion dollars. And he can completely mismanage
these resources so that they're completely wasted.
And so you have this idea of, over time, inherited wealth in a capitalist society,
Can go against the ideas of meritocracy.
It can go against the idea of good incentives.
Because if this guy inherits enough money, he has no incentive to work.
Why should he study hard and go and, you know, tackle math and all of that?
He inherits enough money. He gets millions of dollars just of the interest
Why should he educate himself? Ge go daddy's or granddad's money and so it also goes against the idea.
Why should he try to innovate, why should he do anything?
I'll just... he can just hire some of these people and, you know, give them a minimum salary or whatever it takes.
And so it kind of goes against these ideas of fairness and all of that.
And I'm not saying that I am against inheritance.
I'm just saying it's something we should think and there's probably some threshhold of inheritance
That starts to undermine some of these ideas of a meritocracy and good incentives and fairness and all of that.
That's why I think it's funny when people who call themselves old money
are kind of proud of it, that they view themselves somehow being part of a better caste
Because old money means that you did not earn the money youself,
that your granddad or your great granddad earned the money,
And you've just happened to be born in this family, and, you know,
are essentially just living of the interest.
And it's funny cause they talk about new money, new money like it's not just as good as old money
But at least the new money people - maybe it was through luck but maybe it was through competence or innovation
This is something that at least in mind I'd respect more.
For old money you've done nothing. I mean what's the difference between old money or
king or queen or aristocracy in Europe that kind of go against a lot of philosophical under fittings that the US is sort of based on
So I'll leave you there
I just wanted to add a little bit of nuance to the conversation
We'll say that I come to this conversation with a capitalist bias
But I'm hoping that this gives you just a little bit of more nuance
So instead of saying that capitalism is an unabmiguous good and socialism is an unambiguous bad
these are the things that we should try to promote and to do that we do have to do soem things
Like make sure that everyone is educated so that we can can a meritocracy
If everyone is educated then we have equal opportunity
and that does involve on some scale some type of re-distribution in the form of education
Maybe we do need some form or way for people to get health care
You don't want people dying in the streets
I'm not going to take a stance here but I just wanted to show that you can't just say that everything has to be purely capitalist
and you cannot have any notion of government intervention
You want the governement to invest in things like long term research where maybe you don't have an immidiate
profit motive but 15, 20, 100 years down in the future it might help a society to thrive
or something else. So I'll leave you there