Okay so this is our microcontroller board, and let me move the plug here
see if I can take some of these plugs out,
so the power comes into this board through these 2 plugs here
flows to this socket here and this socket here,
and there are a number of different components and chips on this
board, we're gonna talk about each of them, and sorta what they do
Now, in full disclousure, there's certain components I'm not 100% sure
what this chip does, but I think I know
so we'll go through that and make the best guess that we can.
So this I belive is an EE prom, which is an erasable
memory chip that's electrically erasable
programmable, memoroy chip that stores an
indefeninte index of commands for this board, even when the power's
shut off. So this chip right here, which is the central processing unit
chip and controlls all the functions of this board
as well as the functions of the entire unit, this chip
can go and pull indexed commands from this as
you know, it acts as it's memory
And this is the clock chip, so this one has a little
quartz crystal in it, and when quartz, quartz has a
an interesting property, when it is squeezed, it can emit a
small electrical signal, or when electricity is run to it
it expands slightly. and because of that its very consistent
in the way that it responds to electricity, and very consistent in
the way that it expands, and so because of that property
there able to run electricity to it, and get it to expand, and get a return volt
voltage and they can determine
this device can allow the chips to determine
very precise timing. it's the same type of timing that's inside
of a quartz wristwatch. but anyway
it allows this board to synchronize itself which is really
important when your reading a lot of data from a disk
and you have to make sure the 1s and 0s end up in the right place
and everything happens in synch, and thats very important there
as i said before this is the central processing chip that controlls the board
and the functions on the board. i believe this chip is the
video and audio processing chip
so once the data comes in, it's routed through the CPU to this and
processed and converted into a signal that your tv
and stereo will understand. i believe this chip is an aup amp
chip will op - basically stands for operational amp
lifier, and whill boost the signal coming out of this chip
and this signal may be very weak, and in order to travel down
the chords to go to your tv and stereo you need to boost the signal
increase the voltage and thats what this guy can do. this chip
right here is a motor controller. and so what it does is it controlls the direction
and speed of the motors, and it does this in a very precise way.
So it
works with the cpu to make sure the motors are moving in the right direction
and at the right speed