In this video i wanna expose you to a special class
of mirrors called "PRABOLIC MIRRORS" or " PARABOLIC
REFLECTORS"
We need a parabolic mirror and i'll draw cross-section of one
right here...
and if you are familiar with algebra they are essentially
the cross section ,the cross section is in the shape of a parabola !
So let me draw a parabolic mirror right here.
So this is the shape of a parabola
And what we need about a parabolic mirror and i'm not g
gonna go into the math right here
jus gonna give you the general idea
Let me just draw its principal axis, so this is kind of the line of
symmetry of the parabola
so this is its principal axis right over here and it divides it