Well, I had to stop that last presentation because
I ran out of time.
But now we can start up right where we left off.
So far, we had figured out the slope and it made sense to
us because we figured out the slope was minus four / three.
You could look at it two ways.
When the run is three, the rise is negative four.
So rise we went down by negative four, we ran three, and
you can keep doing that on the line and you'll keep
ending up on the line.
You could've also gone down eight and then moved over six.
Or you could move over six and go down eight.
If you went down eight you would've showed up here.
Then you would've come down back here.
Whatever the slope is, if you change the y by the rise, and
you change the run by the x, you should end up
on the line again.
I know I'm doing this over and over again, but I think
it'll slowly sink in.
But anyway, where we left off we were going to solve for b so
that we could figure out the final equation for this line.
Well, just like we did the last time, we just have to
substitute a y or an x that we know works for this line.
We know either of these coordinates will work,
and then we solve for b.
Let's try this first one: two comma negative three.
So y is negative three.
Don't get confused between x and y.
y is negative three equals minus four / three times x, which is two.
Plus b.
And then we get negative three equals negative eight / three plus b.
And then we get b is equal to-- well, three is equal to minus nine / three.
And then I'm just going to put this on the other side.
So that's plus eight / three.
So we get minus one / three is the y-intercept.
So the equation of this line is y is equal to minus four / three x and
then this y-intercept is minus one / three.
I know this is extremely messy, but the equation of this line
once again, is y equals minus four / three x minus one / three.
Now let's look at the graph and see if that makes sense.
Well, let's see.
The y-intercept is right here.
That's where you intersect the y-axis at the point.
And we would know exactly what that point is.
It's zero comma negative one / three.
That's the y-intercept, and it makes sense.
And even when you look at an equation it's pretty obvious
that this is going to be the y-intercept because when x
equals zero this term gets crossed out.
Because zero times negative four / three.
And then y would equal negative one / three.
Let's do one more just to bore you.
And because my wife is a resident and she works thirty
hours of time and I have nothing better to do.
All right.
Let me put that graph back there.
I joke, but you don't realize that it's true.
Let's put the graph back there and I'm going to do
another random points.
I'm going to go a little faster this time.
So let's say I had negative eight comma five and I had-- let me
think of a good one-- two comma-- I'm just going
to make up a number.
two comma, let's say zero.
That's interesting.
two comma zero.
So let's graph negative eight comma five.
one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight.
one, two, three, four, five.
Right there is minus eight comma five.
And then one, two, and then zero is right here.
So that's two comma zero.
And now let me draw the line.
Oh my God.
I thought I was using the line tool.
That's horrendous.
I wish there was an undo tool.
That was horrendous.
That was unacceptable.
That's a little bit better.
Just so you know that the line doesn't end there.
Lines go on forever and ever in the coordinate axis.
There you go.
OK.
So let's figure out the slope of this line.
Well, change in y over change in x.
I'm using the line tool again.
I'm a spaz today.
Let's take this as a starting point.
We'll get five minus zero.
y sub one minus y sub two.
Over x sub one-- minus eight minus two.
So it equals five over minus ten.
And that equals minus one / two.
So that means for every two we go over, we go down one.
Well, for every one we go down, we go over two,
which makes sense.
If we go down two, we'll go over four.
Because two / four is the same thing as one / two.
I hope that makes sense to you.
I know this is a downwards sloping line.
So that was fast.
So we know that the equation of the line so far is y is
equal to minus one / two x plus b.
Now we just solve for b.
Let's substitute some numbers in here.
Well, let's use this one.
This is interesting: two comma zero.
So y is zero.
Equals minus one / two times two plus b.
Well, zero is equal to and this is minus one plus b.
And we get b equals one.
This is a pretty easy problem.
So now we get y is equal to minus one / two x plus one.
OK, now let's see if this actually looks right
on our problem.
Well, this is telling us that the y-intercept
is at the point zero, one.
zero, one is right here.
And our algebra confirms our drawing.
This is the y-intercept and we see that the
slope is negative one / two.
It makes sense because it's a downward sloping line,
but it's not too steep.
For every one that we go down, we go over two.
So that's negative one / two.
Or you could say for every two we run, we rise negative one.
Either one, we end up on a line again.
So I hope that helps.
I think you are definitely ready to do a lot of these
slope problems that we have on the Khan Academy.
So I hope you have fun and if you any questions you can
attend one of the seminars.
Have fun.