I want to talk about direct and inverse variations
I´ll do direct variations on the left over here
And I´ll do inverse variations or two variables that vary inversly on the right hand side over here
So a very simple definition for two variables that vary directly
would be something like this
Y varies directly with X if y is equal to some constant with x
we could rewrite this in kind of english
y varies directly with x
if this constant seems strange to you
remember this could be literally any constant number
so let me give a bunch of examples that would also
or particular examples of y varies directly with x
you cold have Y is equal to X
because of the situation the constant is 1, we didn´t even write it
you could have write Y is equal to 1X, then K is 1
we could write Y is equal to 2X
we could write Y is equal to one half X
we could write Y is equal to negative 2X
we are still variating directly
we could write Y is equal to negative one half X
we could have Y is equal to π times X
we could have Y is equal to negative π times X
You get the point
Any constant times X, we are varying directly
And to understand this maybe a little bit more tanginbly
let´s think about what happens and let´s pick one of these scenarios
I´ll take a positive version and a negative version
just because it might not be completely intuitive
So let´s take the version of Y is equal to 2X
and let´s explore why we say they vary directly with each other
so let´s pick a couple of values for X
and see what the resulting Y value would have to be
so if X is equal to 1, then Y is two times 1, so it´s 2
if X is equal to 2, then Y is 2 times 2, which is going to be equal to 4
So when we doubled X, from 1 to 2, so we doubled X, the same thing happened to Y
We doubled Y, so that´s what it means when something varies directly
If we scale X up by a certain amount, we are going to scale up Y
by the same amount
If we scale down X by a certain amount, we would scale down Y by the same amount
And just to show you it works with all of these
let´s try the situation with Y is equal to negative 2X
I´ll do it in magenta
Y is equal to ..., I´ll do a new example, let´s try Y is equal to negative 3X
so once again, let me do my X and my Y
when X is equal to 1, Y is equal to negative 3 times 1, which is negative 3
when X is equal to 2, negative 3 times 2 is negative 6
so notice, we multiplied, so if we scaled, let me do that in the same green colour
if we scale up X by 2, it´s a different green colour but it serves the purpose
we are also scaling up Y by 2, to go from 1 to 2, we multiply by 2
to go from negative 3 to negative 6, you´re also multiplying by 2
so we grew by the same scaling factor, and if you want to get the other way
let´s say we try, X is 1/3, if X is 1/3 then Y is going to be negative 3 times 1/3, is negative 1
so to go from 1 to 1/3, we divide by 3
to go from negative 3 to negative 1, we also divide by 3
we also scale down by a factor of 3
so whatever direction you scale X in you are going to have the same scaling direction as Y
that´s what it means to vary directly
now it´s not laways so clear
sometimes it would be ofuscated
so you could write, so let´s take this example right over here
Y is equal to negative 3X, (I´m saving this real state for inverse variation in a second)
you could writethis or you could algebraically manipulate it
you could maybe divide both sides of this equation by X
and then you will get Y/X is equal to -3
or maybe you divide both sides by X
and then you divide both sides by Y
so from this you would get, so if you divide both sides by Y now
you could get 1/X is equal to negative 3 times 1/Y
these three statements, these three equations are all the same thing
so sometimes the direct variation isn´t quite in your face
but if you do this, what I did right here with any of these
you would get the exact same result
or you could jus try to manipulate it back, to this form over here
and there´s other ways we could do it
we could divide both sides of this equation by negative 3
and then you would get negative 1/3Y is equal to X
and this is kind of an interesting case here
because here this is X varies directly with Y
or we could say X is equal to some K times Y
and in general that´s true
if Y varies directly with X, though we can also say that X varies directly with Y
it´s not going to be the same constant, it´s going to be essentially the inverse of that constant
but they´re still directly varying
now with that said so about direct variation
let´s explore inverse variation
inverse variation the general form (if we use the same variables)
it always doesn´t have to be Y and X, it could be A and a B
it could be a M and an N
now to inverse varitaion, so if I did it with Ys and Xs
this would be Y is equal to some constant (K) times 1/X
so instead of being some constant times X, it´s some constant times 1/X
so let me show you a bunch of examples
it could be Y is equal to 1/X
it could be Y is equal to 2 times 1/X
which is clearly the same thing as 2/X
it could be Y is equal to 1/3 times 1/X
whis is the same thing as 1/3X
it could be Y is equal to -2/X
and let´s explore this, the inverse variation the same way we explain the direct variation
so let´s pick Y is equal to 2/X
and let me do that same table over here
if X is 1, then Y is 2
if X is 2 then 2 divided by 2 is 1
so if you multiply X by 2
you scale it up by a factor of 2, what happens to Y?
Y gets scaled down by a factor of 2
you divide it by 2 now
notice the difference?
here however we scale X, we sacled up Y by the same amount
now if we scale up X by a factor
when we have inverse variation, we are scaling down Y by the same
so that´s were the inverse is coming from
and we could go the other way
id we made X is equal to 1/2
so if we were to scale down X, we are going to see that this is going to scale up Y
´cause 2 divided by 1/2 is 4
so here we are scaling up Y
so they are going to do the opposite things
they vary inverse, and you could try it with the negative way of it as well
so here we are multiplying by 2
and once again it is not always neatly written for you like this
it could be rearranged in a bunch different ways
but it will still be inverse variation as long as they are algebraically equivalent
so you could multiply both side of this equation right here by X
and you would get XY is equal to 2, this is also inverse variation
you would get this exact same table over here
you could divide both sides of this equation by Y and you could X is equal to 2/Y
which is also the same thing as 2 times 1/Y
so notice Y varies inversely with X
and you could just manipulate this algebraically to show that X varies inversely with Y
so Y varies inversely with X
this is the same thing (as seen in this example) as saying that X varies inveresely with Y
and there is other things
we could take this and divide both sides by 2
and you would get Y/2 is equal to 1/X
there´s all sort of crazy things
so in general if you see an expression that relates two variables
and they say do they vary inversely or directly or maybe neither
you could either try to make a table like this
if you scale up X by certain amount and Y gets scaled up by the same amount
that is direct variation
if you scale up X, you may want to try it a couple of different times
and you scale down Y, do the opposite with Y, then it is probably inverse variation
a sure way to know what you´re dealing with
it´s to actually algebraically manipulate the equation so it gets back to either this form
that tells you it´s inverse variation
or this form, which will tell you that it is direct variation