- This is one that actually does speak to me
in a very powerful way
but when you look at something
like an American flag
I think I kinda get it,
I mean...
it's such a powerful icon or image
and it evokes so many things
and it's something that you see
so frequently, at least if you're an American
and if you're not American
it's something you still see relatively frequently
and probably does represent something to you
but then to have it imaged and reimaged
in this, I don't know... antiqued way
I can't fully articulated it,
I won't claim that it's somehow challenging
my philosophy in some profound way
but I kind of get it at a base level
what's trying to go on here
I think that's why this painting
has got some popular traction
it was on a cover of my history books
when I was in high school
there's shirts made with this image
and I'm not seeing the full "there"
when I'm describing that
there is even more to it
- I think you're absolutely right
I think Jones would be very happy
to hear what you've just said
I think he wanted this painting to function as something that did raise all kinds of meanings
in a person who walked up to it
in a sense what he's shown us
is not so much a flag
as a mirror, right?
because it's such a potent symbol
and we all walk up to it with
a lot of personal life experiences
and it can mean very different things
to many very different people
and in a sense he's given us a very neutral field
so let's look at it really closely
we're not looking at a printed American flag
we're not looking at a flag of cloth
and in fact some critics of the time asked:
"Is this a painting or is this a flag?"
in other words: is it a representation,
or is it an actual flag
of course something that is symbolic
like a flag can raise that kind of issue
which I think is one of the reasons
I think that Jones was interested in it
but let's just look at the surface for a moment
this is an object
that actually stands off the wall a few inches
it's canvas that's on top of plywood
so it's slightly shallow box-like form
then when you look at the surface
it's really heavily worked
it's not traditional oil paint
or even the more modern acrylic
this is something called encaustic
which is an ancient Egyptian painting technique
that Jones revived
other people has used it in history
but it's ancient and it's translucent and it's lumpy
but it also allows you to see through it
and when you look through this lumpy surface of wax
what you see are strips of newspapers
it's sort of torn up so you really can't read it,
it's not a continuous story
but it is clearly this pigment, this wax
on top of the debris of our political life
- Yeah, I think that's why,
maybe you guys are just doing good job training me
I mean, this one really speaks to me
because especially the texture
and the fact that it is not printed
it is... handmade and it has those layers to it
it's a very powerful idea
when you just have a printed flag
it simplifies what a country is
or what the ideas the country represents are
and its history
and when you look at this painting,
yes, it's an American flag
but you appreciate it...
there's context to America
there's a history, depth, texture to America
you look closer at America,
it's not this simple idea
there's many, many, many layers to it
and I think this does a really good job
this is why it's a painting a lot of people respond to
even the people that might be
traditionally sceptical to modern art
I think this really feels a lot of those things
when they see that
they feel a depth,
the connection to the nation of America
more than this very
red, white, and blue simple idea of it
- I think that's exactly right
I think that Jones has taken
this opportunity to reimagine them
what is conveyed,
art can still in a very fundamental way
represent really complex things
not necessarily through the careful
rendering or the careful representation
of objects on the table or human face
but through kind of symbolic language
actually reference and in some ways
depict a very complex American history
I think that's exactly right
- We talked about a lot of artists...
what's really of note...
although I think this is one of these pieces
that I don't need that much context to really appreciate it
but to go to the next level of context...
Was Jasper Jones really one of the first
to take really powerful images like an American flag
and kind of rerender them in this type of way?
- He was and in fact this is the art
that's being produced before pop-art exists
so this idea about of
turning his canvas and paintbrush
on a visual form that is itself fixed
is a fascinating idea
think about what's he's giving up
the things that we value in painting
traditionally have to do
with artist choice of colour, of composition
and those things are given here
those are already set,
he's not messing with that
and yet this is still not entirely a flag
so much a representation of a flag
and in that way he is walking
on his very narrow edge
- It's really strange to me
because we've talked about traditional art
if you go five or eight hundred years ago,
it was always representational
then the Renaissance and then the more modern art
is all about ideas and pushing our thinking
and this definitely falls into that latter category
it really does... maybe it's just me,
it emotes something in me
that is aesthetic,
that is as powerful as any of these
obviously, it's an American flag
and that by itself can create powerful emotions
but just the way it was rendered
also creates feelings and depth
that I haven't actually felt
from a lot of the modern pieces we've looked at
A conversation with Sai Khan and Steven Zucker discussing Jasper Johns, Flag, 1954-55