Ron and Hermione are practising lifting feathers into the air with magic.
Hermione can lift a feather 35 feet into the air which is 5 times as high Ron can lift a feather.
How high can Ron lift a feather with his magic?
So Hermione – this 35 feet is 5 times more than Ron.
So to figure out what Ron can do we just take what Hermione can do and divide by 5.
So what's 35 divided by 5?
Well, 5 times 7 is 35. So 35 divided by 5 is 7. So Ron can lift a feather 7 feet in the air.
So let's check our answer.
If you have trouble with this –
And we can also look at the hints for this.
So they show that Hermione can lift a feather 35 feet, which is 5 times higher than Ron.
So this could be the length of how high Ron can raise it.
And so, if you actually divide 35 into 5 equal sections –
So 5 × ?? is 35.
That's the same thing as saying 35 divided by 5 is ??.
And 35 divided by 5 is indeed 7.