say "Hey, this is going to be a 2".
But what we'll do in this video is to think
How to troubleshoot these problems systematically.
Because what we'll find is that as more and more complicated
are these equations, you will not be able to
simply think about them and do them in your head
So it is very important that you first understand how
manipulate these equations, but even more important is
understand what they really represent
This literally just says 7 times x equals fourteen
In algebra, do not write "times" ali
When you write two numbers side-by-side or a number close
a variable like this, that means you
are multiplying
It is just a shorthand, a notion of shorthand
And usually we do not use the multiplication sign because
He is confused, because x is the most common variable
used in algebra
And if I had to write 7 times x equals 14, if I write my
sign of "times" or my x so a bit strange, it may seem
as xx "or" times "times"
So usually when you're dealing with equations,
especially when one of the variables is an x, you
would not use the traditional sign of multiplication
You can use something like this--you can use the point to
represent the multiplication
Then you can have 7 times is equal to 14
But this is still a little unusual
If you have something multiplied by a variable
you just going to write 7 x
This literally means 7 times x
Now, to understand how you can manipulate this equation to
solve it, let's see a thing
Then 7 times x, what is this?
This is the same as--so I'll just rewrite this
equation, but I'll rewrite it in visual form
Soon, 7 times x
Soon this literally means x added yourself 7 times
This is the definition of multiplication
So that's literally x x x x more more more more x--let's see,
This is 5 x 's--more x more x
Soon this right there is literally 7 x's
This is 7 x, right there
Let me rewrite it
This right here is 7 x
Now, this equation tells us that equals 7 x 14
Then, just assuming this is equal to 14
Let me draw 14 objects here
So let me say I have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8,
9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14
So literally we're talking 7 x equals 14 things
These are equivalent statements
Now, the reason why I drew it that way is to
you really understand what we will do when we
We divide both sides by 7
So let me erase it right here
Then, the default step every time--I didn't want to do this,
Let me do this, let me draw this last circle
So in General, whenever you simplify an equation to a
– a coefficient is only one number by multiplying
the variable
So, some number by multiplying the variable or we can call
the coefficient times the variable is equal to
something
What you want to do is just divide both sides by 7
in this case, or divide both sides by the coefficient
So if you divide both sides by 7, what do you have?
7 times something divided by 7 is only
This original thing
7 's if void and 14 divided by 7 is 2
Then your solution is x equals 2
But just to make this very tangible in your head, what
is happening here is that when we divide both sides of the
the equation by 7, we literally we divide both sides by 7
This is an equation
If you are saying that this is equal to it
Anything I do on the left I will have to do on the right
If they started being equal, I can't just do an operation
on the one hand and in doing so continue being equal
They were the same thing
So if I split the left side by 7, so let me break it
in seven groups
Soon there are seven x's here, so that's one, two, three,
four, five, six, seven
So that's one, two, three, four, five, six, seven groups
Now, if I divide it into seven groups, I also want to
divide the right side into seven groups
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven
So, if this whole thing is equal to this whole thing, so each
one of these small pieces that break, these seven pieces,
shall be equivalent
So that piece, we can say, is equal to that piece
This piece is equal to this piece--they are
all pieces are equivalent
There are seven pieces here, seven pieces here
Soon, every x must be equal to two of these objects
Soon, we have x is equal to, in this case--in this case
We had the drawn objects where there are two
of them. x is equal to 2
Now, let's just use two other examples here only for
really get into your mind that we are dealing with an equation,
and any operation that you make on one side of the equation
You must be on the other side
So let me turn down a bit more
So let's say that I have, I say, I have 3 x equals 15
Now, once again, you may be able to do it in your head
You're saying this is saying 3 times some
number is equal to 15
You can use your multiplication table 3 and figure out
But if you just wanted to do this systematically, and that
It is good to understand systematically, you say OK, this
thing on the left is equal to this thing in the right
What should I do with this thing on the left
to have only one x there?
Well, to have only the x, I need to divide it by 3
and my motivation to do this and that ' 3 times
anything divided by 3, 3 's Cancel and I stay
with only the x
now, 3 x 15 was equal to
If I am splitting the left side by 3, for equality
be satisfied, I need to divide the right side by 3.
What this in '?
The left side, the left side only
an x, then we have just the x
and the right side, and ' 15 divided by 3?
This and ' 5.
Now you could have done this equacao slightly
different, even though they are equivalent
If you start with 3 x equals 15, then we can say that
instead of dividing by 3, I can just see me free to 3
I can stick with the left side only equal to x, if I multiply both sides by
the equacao by 1/3
then if I multiply that estimate the equacao on both sides by 1/3
This also works
you say, 1/3 of 3 and 1.
When we multiply this part, 1/3 times
3, this and ' x
1 x e ' equal to 15 times 1/3 and ' equal to 5
and a 1 time x and ' the same as x, and this is the same thing
where x is equal to 5
and these two forms are equivalent to solve this
If we divide both sides by 3, this and ' equivalent to
multiply both side of equacao by 1/3
Now let's do one more and I'll make it a little
more complicated
I'll modify the ftminword_len a little
Let's say I have more 4y 2y = 18
now, suddenly it's a little harder and
to make this twin
We are saying that something twice over 4 times that
thing and ' equal to 18
and ' harder to think that number is this
You can try
Let's say we have 1 is 2 times 4 times 1, 1 more
and it does not work
but let's consider systematically solve this
You can try to guess and you can reach
the answer, but how do we do it systematically?
Let's show
If two y's terms, what does that mean?
This means literally that I have two y's summed up with one another
IE and ' y y more
and so I'm adding 4 y's
that I am joining 4 y 's, who literally are four
y's added with one another
logo and ' y y y y more more more
and that has to be equal to 18
and that and ' equal to 18
now, how many y's I have on the left?
How many y's I have?
I have one, two, three, four, five, six y's
Thus we can simplify this as 6y and ' equal to 18
and if you think about it, this makes sense
so this here, the more 4 y and 2y ' 6y
then more 4y 2y and ' 6y, and this makes sense
If we have two more litters 4 stretchers, I'll
have 6 stretchers
If I have more y 2y's 4 ' s, I'll have 6 y's
and this is equal to 18
and now, we know how to do this
If I have 6 times something equal to 18, if we divide the two sides
the equacao by 6, do I solve the equacao
then divide the left by 6, and divide the
so I figur by law 6
and we then y equals 3
and you can try
This and ' and ' cool about a equacao
You can always check if you got the right answer
Let's see if this works
2 times 3 times 3 and 4 more ' to that?
2 times 3, this and ' equal to 6
and then 4 times 3 and ' equal to 12
6 more ' equal to 12 and 18
soon this works