We have three different addition problems right over here...
and what I want you to do (so you get the hang of things), is to pause the video and try them on your own.
But as you do them, I want you to really keep in mind and think about what the carrying actually means.
So I assume you've tried on your own,
Now I'll work through them with you.
So we have 9 plus 6. 9 ones plus 6 ones. Well 9 plus 6 is 15. Well, we can write the 5 in the ones place, and carry the one.
But what did we just do? W.hat does this "1" represent?
Well, we put it in the "tens" place... one 10 represents 10..
So all we've said is that 9 plus 6 is equal to 10 plus 5. Is equal to one 10 plus 5, which is equal to 15..
Now, in the "tens" place... we have 1 plus 0 plus 9... which is 10..
So we can write 0 and carry the 1..
1 plus 0 plus 9 is 10..
Now... what does that really mean?
Well... this is one 10 plus zero 10s plus nine 10s... which is ten 10s. Ten 10s is 100.
Or another way of thinking about 100, it's one hundred, and zero 10s, so that's all that carrying represents.
So now we have a 1, plus a 7, plus a 9. That is going to be 17.
Now, we have to remind ourselves: this is in the hundreds place. This is actually 1 hundred, plus 7 hundred, plus 9 hundred, or 17 hundred.
Or 1 thousand, 7 hundred. And of course we have this 5 here... and we are done.
Now let's try to tackle this one. Now the reason why I wrote it that way is to make sure that we remind ourselves to align the proper places under the appropriate places.
So this we rewrite as (let me use that same green color) 373 plus... we want to write the ones under the ones place, and the tens place under the tens place,
so that we're adding the appropriate values.
So 3 plus 8 is 11. The 1 in the ones place, and the 1 in the tens place. 10 plus 1 is 11.
1 plus 7 is 8. 8 plus 8 is 16. This is actually 16 tens. So let's write down the 16...
What is 16 tens? Well, that's 160! So then this 6 is the sixty, and then I have 100.
1 plus 3 is 4. But these are actually hundreds, so it's 4 hundreds.
So we get 461.
Now finally, 9 plus 3 is 12. 2 ones, and 1 ten. 12 is the same thing as 10 plus 2.
Now in the tens place... 1 plus 4 plus 9 is 14. So we write the 4, and carry the one.
But remind ourselves this is actually 10 plus 40 plus 90... which is 140. Which is the same thing as 40 plus 100.
And then 1 plus 1 plus 2 is 4. But this is the hundreds place. So this is actually 1 hundred, plus 1 hundred, plus 2 hundred... or 4 hundred.
And we're done.