Welcome to my presentation on return on capital
Let's say we had return on capital
Now I wanna do this presentation first because
I think this is going to give you the big picture on how you need to think about
what something is worth, whether you should invest your money into it,
and how you should weigh the different options you had in terms of where you want it to point
you want to put it in the bank, you want to put it in a house, do you want to pay off your credit cards, etc, etc
so let's just define "return on capital", and just so you know
I'm not neccessarily gonna be strict on the accounting conventions or the gap conventions
I'm gonna do it more hands-on, how a "Joe investor" should
think about their money. So, in this senario, I define "return on capital" as just
the cash you get per year divided
by the total cash you put in
and well, I don't wanna just say cash. There's other ways to measure return
but let's just keep it simple. let's just say cash
so let's think about how this works out. let's say I have an idea, I have a restaurant
and that restaurant will cost a million dollars
of investment
and let's say that per year, after paying all the expenses, after paying all the utilities
after paying all the employees, after repairing and maintenance, after paying taxes
this restaurant makes 100k per year.
In this situation, my return on
capital, the way I've defined it, is 100k divided by 1 million, or you could say 1000k,
equals 10%. Pretty straight forward. You might be saying
"Sal, this is silly, why are you wasting my time?" Well, maybe it is
but I think you'll find that this going to lay a foundation that will eventually blow your mind
so let's keep going.
Okay, so I said the restaurant
return on capital is equal to 10%. I could put
a million dollars and I'll get in 100k per year
now's that one project. and let's say I know for sure that I'm gonna,
and I'm not gonna factor in things like risk just yet
let's just say for sure i know that if i put my money here I'm gonna get 10% on my money
and let's say the other option with my money is
a beauty parlor
and let's say that also costs 1 million dollars
and this beauty parlor gets me 50k per year
I think it's very obvious which investment you'd rather invest in
because the return on capital on this beauty parlor is only 50k divided by a million
or 5%. So this is obvious. you'd rather do the restaurant than the beauty parlor
and in general you, after adjusting for risk, always wanna go
with the project with the higher return on capital
and later on there will be nuances in terms of when you get that return
maybe you'd like a slightly lower return if you get the money faster
or a slightly higher return if
you're taking on risk or to compensate for risk
So we know we want to do the restaurant but do we definitely want to do the restaurant?
I mean we'd rather do the restaurant than the beauty parlor
but my question to you is "Do we definitely want to do the restaurant?"
and this is where the return on capital becomes interesting
because what matters before we put the money into the restaurant is to think about
what the cost of the money is to us
and this is what I think will be a little bit of a new concept
so I'm gonna introduce you now to the notion of a "cost of capital"
so the restaurant costs a million dollars and it gets me
100k a year
thats a 10% return on capital.
let's say I have to borrow all the money and theres some bank that willing to give me
all the money for this restaurant and the interest rate on this loan
the interest rate is 15%
is it still a good idea for me to open up a restaurant?
Well, if I have a loan and I have to borrow the whole amount
So I have a loan of a million dollars to buy that same restaurant
and Im gonna be charged 15% in interest every year
and I'm not gonna take taxes and the fact that you can deduct taxes etc etc
into account just yet
Let's just assume that my total cost is 15% per year in interest
so I'm gonna have to spend 150k per year in interest
So my question is "Does it still make sense for me to open up this restaurant?"
every year im gonna be making 100k from the restaurant itself but im gonna be paying
150k a year in interest. you'll probably say "Sal, once again you've just restated the obvious
no you would not want to do this restaurant
because every year, 50k will be burning out of your pocket"
Now you might think that this is obvious but I'm gonna show you many examples
of where people are actively doing this
people who you would otherwise assume could do this math and it's especially happening in the housing market
but anyway in this situation you wouldn't want to invest it and a very simple way
of thinking about this is you only want to invest, you only want to do a project, if your return on capital
is greater than your cost of capital
this is the only time that you want to invest in a project
I just showed you something that we thought was obvious
but I'm gonna re-ask you a question
so we had the restaurant, we have the beauty parlor
they both cost a million dollars
the ROC of the restaurant is 10%
and the ROC of the beauty parlor is 5%
so right now, it looks like the restaurant is the better project
but then we said the cost of capital, the interest rate
which is how much does it cost us to get the million dollars
the interest rate is 15%
and we said that this is not a good investment
because our cost of capital is greater than the return on capital
but what if there was some kind of government program
and they just felt that
there werent enough beauty parlors in the country
and they want to give you a really cheap loan to buy a beauty parlor
and the government program said "We're gonna give you a low interest loan
of 2%". so my question to you is "NOW which project would you rather do?"
superficially, it looks like the restaurant is better. you get a 10% return as opposed to 5%
but the cost of capital, the interest rate you'd have to pay on a loan for the beauty parlor
suddenly looks a little bit better
in fact this is actually a good investment
because your cost of capital is less than your return on capital
and we could be do the math
every year the beauty parlor will generate
50k and you'll be paying 20k in interest
so you'll be netting 30k without having to put any money for yourself
you'll be borrowing all the money so clearly this is a good investment
so thats it now for the intro on return on capital and cost of capital
in my next presentations ill go a little bit more in detail
and do a few more nuanced examples