We're at the Museum of Modern Art, looking at a really wonderful painting.
This is by Henri Matisse, this is The Piano Lesson
and it dates to 1916.
It's a big, austere canvas.
It's probably one of Matisse's most Picasso-like canvases, sort of cubist in its severity and its use of line.
And some art historians have seen it as Matisse really trying to, in a sense, answer cubism.
It certainly doesn't have the sensuality of many Matisse paintings, what we usually think of when we think of Matisse.
As explicitly, you're absolutely right. None of the sensuous hips or...
There are little hints of it with the arabesques of the wrought iron, which is of course the balustrade,
but that's perfect because some art historians actually see the rendering of that balustrade actually as a kind of written expression of the music that's being produced by Pierre Matisse,
Matisse's son, who's at the piano.
And so Pierre Matisse is at the piano, this is 1916...
Pierre Matisse, by the way, grew up to be a really important gallery owner in New York, selling his father's work, among others.
And we have a sense of real balance in this painting
because, you had mentioned the lack of sensuality, but actually if you look in the lower left corner --
that female figure on the lower left --
It's not a real female figure, or I shouldn't say "real,"
No, a Matisse sculpture, it's a painting of a bronze sculpture by Matisse.
So there we have a nude and she is curvilinear and really sensuous, and really contrasted, almost as if they were boxers, from the figure in the upper right.
Yes, she looks very strict, and reminds me of the metronome that's directly under her,
and is kind of uprightness and strictness and a sense of discipline and order in that figure.
She does hover over Pierre Matisse's head in a kind of menacing way, doesn't she?
And she's painted, you're right, so rectilinear, she's clothed, so much in opposition to the sculpture on the other side.
And the metronome is in that other corner, you're absolutely right, and that kind of alternates between the two.
So, soome art historians have suggested that this is a painting that is really about this opposition between order and structure, and beauty.
Sensuality and discipline, I can see that.
Now what about his face, do you think? Why one eye? Why is his face so cubist?
I have no idea. But it actually seems to reflect the metronome, doesn't it?
It does, and somehow I think it speaks to me of removing this image from reality.
So this is Matisse really trying to impose some of the strict geometric formal aspects in the painting to the figure itself,
so that we're not seeing it as a literal rendering.
I think so. And that figure in the upper right, is that really a figure there?
No, because this is his house in Issy, that's a wall,
and in fact the woman that we're seeing in a sense playing the role of the piano teacher is actually a painting of a woman on a high stool.
It's also in the collection at the Museum of Modern Art.
So it's really not...it's an allegory. It sort of is what it seems, but it is not what it seems.
Well, Matisse is playing with levels of reality here, right? He often does that.
Pierre looks out at us as though he would like to somehow escape
into the pleasures of the female nude on the far left!
Maybe, or perhaps of the shaft of...the daylight outside.
You almost see the last rays of sunlight coming across the lawn in that wonderful triangle between the windows.
It's a pretty austere allegory about what it means to make art.
In some ways I look at Pierre and I see him as a sort of stand-in for Henri, for Matisse himself.
(music)