Evaluate 1x when x is equal to -1,0,and 1.
So let's do the scenario x is equal to 1.
So 1x becomes 1 times.. one-which is now negative 1
So it's one times negative one.
There a couple of ways to think about it.
One times anything is going to be that anything.
So one times negative one is going to be equal to negative one
Another way you could have thought about it is that
you could just look at the absolute value of each number
so you say one times one is one
they have different signs so it's going to be negative
which have gotten you the same answer either way
So now with the scenario that x is equal to 0
So one times x is going to be the same thing as one times 0
We subsitute the 0 for x.
So once again,one times anything is going to be that anything.
This is going to become 0
Another way to think about this is that
0 times anything is going to become 0.
So either one of the ways of thinking about it would have gotten you the same answer.
Actually we can even write 1*x =x
So really when you value these numbers in x
x is equal to -1,0 or1
It's going to equal that number
one times anything is going to be that anything right overthere.
To make it clear 0 times anything is 0 (0x=0)
Just for good measure we kind or already went through the answers.
But let's try x is equal to 1
So this will give us 1 times 1 which you probably learned a while ago.
1 times anything is going to become that number!
so it's equal to 1