So let's say we've got the curve r, defined-
So this is our curve r, it's x of t times i
plus y of t times j it's a curve in 2 dimensions
on the xy-plane, and let's graph it,
just to graph it in a kinda of generalized form.
So that's our y-axis, this is our x-axis, our curve
r might look something like this, it might look something-
Let me draw it a little more of a-
Maybe it looks something
like this maybe that's just part of it,
and as t increases we're going
in that direction right over there.
What I want to do in this video,
and this is really more vector algebra than vector calculus,
is think about, at any given point here,
whether we can figure out a normal
vector, and in particular, a unit normal vector.
Obviously we can figure out
normal vector, you can just divide it's magnitude and you will
get the unit normal vector.
So I want to figure out, at any given point, a vector
that's popping straight out in that direction, and has
a magnitude of 1.
So that would be our unit normal vector.
And to do that
first we will think about what a tangent vector
is and from a tangent vector
we can figure out the normal vector.
It really goes back
to what you might have done in Algebra 1 or
Algebra 2, if you have the slope of a line the
negative reciprocal of that slope is
going to be the slope of the perpendicular line.
We are going to see a very similar thing
when we do it right over here, with the vector-
with this vector algebra.
So the first think I want to think about
how do we construct a tangent line.
Well, you can imagine at some t-some t
this is what our position vector is going to look like
so call that r1-r1 right over there.