What I want to explore in this video is the different ways of measuring the amount of money we have in circulation.
So we're going to start things with our Central Bank (in the US, this would be the US Federal Reserve.)
And let's say that they print $4.
And we're going to focus just for visualisation purposes, on them doing it phyisically,
they could also do it electronically, but we're just going to focus on the physical.
And they way they get this into circulation is that they'll take these four dollars
and they'll go buy securities in the open market, normally very safe and very liquid securities
Liquid means it's very easy to buy and sell those securities in large quantities.
For example, government treasuries is a liquid security or a liquid asset,
Pez dispensers would not be a liquid asset --
If i bought a billion dollars worth of pez dispensers
it would be very hard for me to sell.. one, it would be very hard for me to buy a billion dollars worth
and it would probably be even harder for me to sell a billion dollars worth
in any short or medium time frame.
So the central bank goes out, and let's say they go and buy 1 liquid security for $4,
[so this is the security right over here]
and the person they bought the security from decides to deposit it in a bank.
They could either directly deposit it in a bank or they could use that money
that they got from selling their security to buy things
and they person they bought things from could deposit in a bank...
but one way or another we can imagine it all gets deposited in a bank.
[So this is our private bank, I'll call this private bank number number 1]
So now all of these dollars are transferred to PB#1, and they are no longer...
the Fed Reserve or the central bank (the general case) is no longer in posession of them.
They've been transferred right over here (to PB #1). [I'm going to cross these out so we can keep track of things.]
Now, when they deposit in PB#1, they say "well, I need 3 of these dollars on demand
and I want to write cheques against them."
So they put $3 in a chequeing account, so they can write cheques up to $3..
and so they can get a little bit more interest, and the banks will even
give a little bit more interest on a savings account cos they don't have to keep the reserves;
they put $1 into a savings account.
And they cannot write cheques against that savings account
Now, there are special circumstances, but for simplicity, let's just say that they cannot write cheques
there are some that have restricted cheque writing and things like that...
So the banks says "ok, this dollar, I dont have to have
any reserves against it, and I can loan out this dollar
and the person they lend it to, let's say they immediately go deposit it into another bank
so they immediately go and deposit this in private bank 2 (PB#2)
So it's no longer in PB#1 [Let me draw PB#2... PB#2 is right over here...]
And they deposit it into a savings account in PB#2
and let's say that out of all of these
the bank says "well this is a demand deposit, I have to keep some reserves
(this is a fractional reserve system)
but I can lend out -- in the US I can lend out up to 90% of this
and maybe this bank is a little bit more conservative, and they only lend out two-thirds of these,
so they lend out 2 out of these 3 dollars.
And lets say the person they lend out to also happens to deposit it in PB#2, just coincidentally.
so this $2 also ends up in PB#2, and so they are no longer in PB#1,
although this person (PB#1) can still write cheques up to $3.
And here in PB#2, let's say these are deposited in a chequeing account.
Now, PB#2 can do a couple of things:
In this chequeing account, it has to keep some reserves,
let's say its even more conservative, it only decides to lend out half of this
(even though it could lend out 90%)
and so it lends out one of these dollars
and the person they lend it to just takes that dollar and puts it in their wallet.
They can also lend out this entire savings, and let's just say
that person that they lend that $1 in savings to also puts it in their wallet.
Notice, the original $4 is still there..
Now, and just to be clear, this person (PB#1) right over here can write cheques up to $3,
and this person over here (PB#2) can write cheques up to $2 [Let me do this in the same chequeing colour]
Now, let's think about the different forms of money there are here.
We could think of money in a very, very narrow way, which is 'Just what did the central bank print?'
or create electronically (as electronic reserves of its member banks' account)
but for simplicity here, you could just think of the physical currency it printed - it's base money.
And so that is often referred to as Base Money
and in the US (and other countries), it's often the same thing as M0...
(there are slight differences from country to country)
and in this example, as soon as they printed and put it into circulation...
(that was $4) we had $4 of base money...
and that's obvious because as soon as they printed this and bought the security with it
and it was in circulation, that $4 could be used to buy things,
it could be used to facilitate transactions.
Now, that clearly isn't all of the stuff that can be used as money in this little universe we created..
You have the $4, but these people (PBs) can also write cheques over here...
so we can have a slightly boarder definition of money
and over here we will call it M1,
and here, there's a couple of ways you could think about it
you could think about it as all of the currenncy that's in people's pockets
plus all of the cheque-writing capabilities, so if you view it that way
it would be these $2 plus $5 of cheque-writing capabilities over here.
So you could have $2 of physical currency that's in people's wallets (not in bank reserves)
plus the $5 of cheque-wrinting capability, which would give you $7.
Another way you could view it, is M0 plus cheque-able deposits [I'll just write 'cheques' here]
but if you do that, you are now double counting
because some of the M0 is reserves in the cheque-able deposits!
Or I could just say that some of the cheque-able deposits is held as reserves for M0
so you would have to subtract out the bank reserves...
and so then you would get $4..
cos we don't want to double count these over here... you'd get M0 is $4...
[I'm gonna do that in white]
M0 is $4
The cheque-able deposits is $5..
[Let me do that in pink.]
Plus the $5
and then you would want to subtract out the reserves...
and the reserves here, there are $2 of the reserves... so minus $2
and you would get yourself back to the $7.
The whole point of this is so that you are not double-counting something.
You are not double-counting this right over here as part of cheque-able deposits and part of the M0,
you are not using this twice.
It is both base money and chequeable deposits so we don't want to count it twice.
The simplest way to think about this is: 'What can be used in this boarder definition to facilitate transactions?'
These $2 in people's pockets and this ability to write up to $5 of cheques.
[So that's this view over here]
and if we want to get even boarder than that, we can get to something called M2
And here we could say, what is immediately usable to facilitate transactions right now,
so that would be our $7 of M1, plus things that can be easiliy converted to M1.
For example, these savings account can be easily converted to chequeing accounts
it might only take a couple of days (there might be resrictions) but it can be converted
and when it get converted, it will change the bank's reserve requirements a little bit, but it will allow
.. if this person converts it.. they will have the ability to write more cheques
so M2 includes M1 plus things that are very easy to convert to M1,
so they will include savings accounts, money-market accounts (which I won't go into detail here,
but they are really kind of similar that you get slightly higher interest but there are restrictions
on your ability to access it, but it is not too hard to turn it into chequing accounts...)
and things like small dollar-value time-deposit accounts.
But for the sake of simplicity in this example, it would be the saving accounts...
so it will be our $7 of M1, plus the $2 of savings account over here.
So this is just to give you a picture:
when someone talks about the money supply, you really have to say, 'what are you talking about?'
The most typical one is that you are talking about M1,
because this is the stuff that is directly usable to facilitate transactions.
Things like the ability to write a cheque or dollar bills in someone's wallet.
But they might be talking about base money...
(M0, narrow money are all ways of referring to the same thing especially in the Unites Sates)
or they might be referring to something even boarder
and there are boarder definitions even than M2, although M3, they've stopped reporting about it
but M3 would have things that are a little bit further from being true money,
from being a chequing account, but they are already fairly liquid
so they will include other types of assets,
but the Fed has already stopped reporting this in the recent past,
so these are the ones that are typically referred to.