I'm stending here in the galleries, the Japanese gallerise at the Portland Art Museum
and we are looking at a recent aquisition
it is a ewer, which is a particular kind of pitcher
that comes to us from late XVI century Japan
The first thing that comes to mind is its material, because when I first wallked up to this
I imagined, in some way, probably because of the sides, that it was metal
and when I came close to it I realized that it wasn't , it's wood. Is that right?
Yes, it's wood.
And what's interesting is that body, and we often talk about pots in this anthropomorphic way,
the body has a very slight, I mean it's almost a cylinder, but it tapers a little bit at the foot
so the body is sort of in the shape of a bucket
This isn't carved from a single block of wood
but it's rather a strip of wood that was steemed and wrapped
Then we see these things that, these ridges on it
Those are actually strips of bamboo
that are sort of like little reinforcing vergers
that help hold that steemed wood in that wrapped cylindrical shape
So it's really a process from struction that's made in a way that is not dissimulous to the way that we might treat metal
If you can think of a sheet of metal hammered and...
yes
...and then bent, that's like that
and what is so interesting, if we think
OK, what are the normal ways that you handle wood
well we think of carving wood...
yes, exactly
...that idea of making a vessel, by wrapping a slab of wood into a cylinder
and then putting a bottom on it
that is a technique, in which Japanese woodmakers excel.
There's a kind of delecacy and a kind of..
I think that I get the sense of the thinness of the wall,
that seems to me only possible in metal
and I think that's why I jump there
but I think it really speaks to the extraordinaries of the tradition out of which this is coming
and I see it as increadibly impressive
And can we talk a liitle bit about the way the wood is treated
and the color which I find beautiful
it's got this almost gorgeous, almost patina
Yes, it does have a patina
This ware is an example of Japanese lacquerware
so the wood turning, the wood bending, the wood shaping happens
and then it goes to a number of stages of being coated with lacquer
and lacquer is found really much of Southeast Asia and East Asia
but in Japan...
Japanese lacquer was so treasured by the Europeans when trade began
that analogous to the way we use the word "china" to associate ceramics with China,
Eouopeans used to call works that were lacquered "Japanned"...
Oh, is that right?
... It was so associated with Japan
And lacquer is the sap of a Lac tree
It's a naturally occurring sap, so think of maple syrup,
and think of it as something that, you know, trees oose out in a particular season of the year
you have to go and tap it
and it's thik and viscous like maple syrup
Interestingly it's also toxic...
Oh really?
... it has the same chemicals in it that poison ivy does
Woo
So lacquer workers have to spend a lifetime building a resistence to this
So you have this lacquer and then you can..
ther's a sort of traditional colors to dye it
and in Japan those two traditional colors were black