PROBLEM: "In the following graph,
is y a function of x?"
So, in order for y to be a function of x,
for any x that you input into the function –
any x for which the function is defined –
So let's say we have y is equal to f(x), [y=f(x)]
So we have our little function machine.
it should spit out exactly one value of y.
If it spits out multiple values of y,
we don't know what f(x) is going to be equal to.
It could be equal to any of those
possible values for y.
So, let's see if, for this graph, whether, for a given x,
it spits out exactly one y.
Well, the function seems to be only defined –
so the domain of this function is x is equal to -2.
That's the only place
where we have a definition for it.
– and if we try to input -2 into this little black box,
what do we get?
Do we get exactly one thing?
No. If we put a -2 in here, we could get anything.
The point -2, 9 is on this relation.
-2, 8 is on this relation.
-2, 7
-2, 7.5
-2, 3.14159
They're all on these.
So, if you put a negative 2 into this relation,
you actually get –
essentially, you actually get an infinite set of values.
It could be 9. It could be 3.14.
It could be 8. It could be -8.
You get an infinite number of results.
So, since it does not map
to exactly one output of this function,
in the following graph, y is not a function of x.