in the last video where we launched something at an angle, we figured out the horizontal and vertical
components of that launch velocity and we used the vertical components to find out how long that thing
is in the air, and we used that time to figure out how far it traveled given a constant horizontal velocity
What I want to do in this video is redo apart of that problem, to figure out how long that object stays
in the air, and I'm going to do it in a slightly more complected way from what I did in the last video
But it is kind of a more powerful way, and we will see that it is more powerful in future videos
So in last videos to figure out how long something was in the air, we said look,
We are starting and stopping at the same elevation, what ever our vertical velocity is here upwards
we are going to have the same magnitude of velocity, but it is going to be downwards
we used that insight to figure out the change in velocity and we used that change in velocity,
and the constant acceleration due to the force of gravity on an object in free fall,
to figure out the time in the air, and it was pretty simple mathematically.
And what we are going to do now is derive a formula, that is useful in Physics, but i always like to
derive it from scratch, and that's what I'm going to derive over here, and you have seen me
derive this formula before. But just to start off we need to remind our self's of that the vertical velocity
that we calculated in our last video, was 5 m/s and given that vertical velocity lets figure out how
long that thing stays in the air.
So our vertical velocity, our velocity in the y direction, is 5m/s and also as a reminder
our convection when we are dealing with conventions in 1 dimension, and this is in one direction now
since we know it is in the y direction, is positive is up and negative is down when we are dealing with
the vertical direction
when we are dealing the the horizontal direction positive means to the right, negative means to the
left, so just to make sure we have those conventions down
So how can we figure out how ling this thing stays in the air, so we can remind our self's that the displacement
and every thing we are talking about now, this will apply in any one dimension,
The displacement is equal the the average velocity
times our change in time
and what our average velocity? It is, if we assume constant acceleration,
it is our final velocity plus our initial velocity- actually let me write it this way, it will make it a little bit cleaner-
it is our initial velocity plus our final velocity divided by two
so literary the arithmetic mean of our initial and final velocity
and we are going to times that by change in time
Now what is our final velocity going to be, our final velocity is the same thing as
your initial velocity, plus your acceleration times how much time has passed by
this right here is your final velocity, so lets substitute that back into this right over here
and what do we get, we get our initial velocity- so our average velocity is now our initial velocity
plus our final velocity- the final velocity is this over here-so it's our initial velocity plus the acceleration
times the amount of time that passes by all of that divided by 2, and all of this is multiplied by
the amount of time that passes by. Once again this is our total displacement. so this part right over
here, I'll do it in magenta, we have 2 Vi's, so that simplifies to 2 Vi's- 2 times our initial velocity's
and this expression over here, simplifies 2 times Vi divided by two, is our initial viscosity and then
we have- well I will just do it all here, then I will multiply it by time after that
plus the acceleration times amount of time that passes by, divided by two, and all of this is multiplied
by the amount of time that passes by. and this is our total displacement
and we are almost done- and if you have to take a physics exam under time presser it's not ridicules
to not have to re-derive it every time, but I want to emphasize, that you should realize that these formulas
come from almost just common basic since principles and you should be able to derive them.
but it is good to mesmerize them if you have a time presser exam
So now if we multiply this delta t, you get the total displacement is equal to your initial velocity
times your change in time plus, your acceleration over two- you have a delta t times a delta t
remember delta just means change in time, triangle just means change in time.
so change in time times change in time is change in time squared.
And this expression right here this is in some physics books, or in some classes
they will just give you this formula, but I wanted to show you that it is derived from very very simple
principles, from just displacement is average velocity times change in time, what is average velocity
what is final velocity, it is just initial velocity plus acceleration times time and you will get this
expression right over here. so I did this to figure out much time we are going to spend in the air, so
how do we do that for this particular problem
Well we know our initial velocity, that the launch vertical component, because be are just dealing with
the verticle component here, and we know our initial velocity, we know the acceleration due to gravity
and in this situation we want to figure out when the displacement is going to be
and this is going to be a little bit unintuitive, but hopefully it makes sense, when the displacement is
going to be 0
because there is going to be 2 times when the displacement is going to be 0.