Let's get started with some problems.
Let's see.
First problem: what is fifteen percent of forty?
The way I do percent problems is I just convert the
percentage to a decimal and then I multiply it times the
number that I'm trying to get the percentage of.
So 15% as a decimal is 0.15.
You learned that from the percent to decimal conversion
video, hopefully.
And we just multiply this times forty.
So let's say 40 times 0.15.
five times zero is zero.
five times four is twenty.
Put a zero there.
And then one times zero is zero.
one times four is four.
And you get six zero zero.
Then you count the decimal spots.
one, two.
No decimals up there, so you go one, two and you
put the decimal there.
So 15% of 40 is equal to 0.15 times 40, which equals 6.00.
Well, that's just the same thing as six.
Let's do another problem.
Hopefully, that didn't confuse you too much.
And I'm going to try to confuse you this time just
in case you weren't properly confused the last time.
What is 0.2% of-- let me think of a number-- of 7.
So a lot of people's inclinations would just
say, oh, 0.2%, that's the same thing as 0.2.
And if that was your inclination you would be wrong.
Because remember, this isn't 0.2.
This is 0.2%.
So there's two ways of thinking about this.
You could say that this is 0.2/100, which is, if you
multiply the numerator and denominator by ten, is the
same thing as two / one thousand.
Or you can just do the technique where you
move the decimal space over two to the left.
In which case, if you're starting with 0.2 and you
move the decimal space two to the left, you go bam.
Whoops!
Bam, bam.
That's where the decimal goes.
So it's 0.002.
This is key.
0.2% is the same thing as 0.002.
This can always trip you up and I've made this careless mistake
all the time, so don't feel bad if you ever do it.
But just always pay careful attention if you see a
decimal and a percentage at the same time.
So now that we've figured out how to write this percentage
as a decimal we just have to multiply it times the number
that we want to take the percentage of.
So we say 0.002 times 7.
Well, this is pretty straightforward.
seven times two is fourteen.
And how many total numbers do we have or how many total
digits do we have behind the decimal point?
Let's see.
It's one, two, three.
So we need one, two, three digits behind the decimal point.
So 0.2% of 7 is equal to 0.014.
And you're probably thinking, boy, that's a really,
really small number.
And it makes sense because 0.2%, if you want to
think about it, that's smaller than even one percent.
So that's even smaller than one / one hundred.
And actually, if you think about it, 0.2% is 1/500.
And if you do the math, one / five hundred of seven will turn
out to be this number.
And that's an important thing to do.
It's always good to do a reality check because when
you're doing these decimal and these percent problems, it's
very easy to kind of lose a factor of ten here or there.
Or gain a factor of ten.
So always do a reality check to see if your answer makes sense.
So now I'm going to confuse you even further.
What if I were to ask you four is twenty percent of what number?
So a lot of people's reflex might just be,
oh, let me take twenty percent.
It becomes 0.20.
And multiply it times four.
And in that case, again, you may be wrong.
Because think about it.
I'm not saying what is twenty percent of four?
I'm saying that twenty percent of some number is four.
So now we're going to be doing a little bit of algebra.
I bet you didn't expect that in the percent module.
So let x equal the number.
And this problem says that twenty percent of x is equal to four.
I think now it's in a form that you might recognize.
So how do we write twenty percent as a decimal?
Well, that's just 0.20 or 0.2.
And we just multiply it by x to get four.
So 20%, that's the same thing as 0.2.
It's the same thing as 0.20, but that last trailing
zero doesn't mean much.
0.2 times x is equal to 4.
And now we have a level one linear equation.
I bet you didn't expect to see that.
So what do we do?
Well there's two ways to view it.
You can just divide both sides of this equation
by the coefficient on x.
So if you divide 0.2 here and you divide by 0.2 here.
So you get x is equal to 4 divided by 0.2.
So let's figure out what 4 divided by 0.2 is.
I hope I have enough space.
0.2 goes into 4-- I'm going to put a decimal point here.
And the way we do these problems, we move the
decimal point here one over to the right.
So we just get a two and then we can move the decimal point
here one over to the right.
So this 0.2 goes into 4 the same number of times
that two goes into forty.
And this is easy.
two goes into forty how many times?
Well, two goes into four two times and then two goes
into zero, zero times.
You could've done that in your head.
two into forty is twenty times.
So 4 divided by 0.2 is 20.
So the answer is four is twenty percent of twenty.
And does that make sense?
Well, there's a couple of ways to think about it.
twenty percent is exactly one / five.
And four times five is twenty.
That makes sense.
If you're still not sure we can check the problem.
Let's take twenty percent of twenty.
So 20% of 20 is equal to 0.2 times 20.
And if you do the math that also will equal four.
So you made sure you got the right answer.
Let's do another one like that.
I'm picking numbers randomly.
Let's say three is nine percent of what?
Once again, let's let x equal the number that three is nine percent of.
You didn't have to write all that.
Well, in that case we know that 0.09x-- 0.09, that's the same
thing as nine percent of x-- is equal to three.
Or that x is equal to 3 divided by 0.09.
Well, if we do the decimal division, 0.09 goes into 3.
Let's put a decimal point here.
I don't know how many zero's I'm going to need.
So if I move this decimal over to the right twice, then I'll
move this decimal over to the right twice.
So 0.09 goes into 3 the same number of times
that nine goes into three hundred.
So nine goes into thirty three times.
three times nine is twenty-seven.
I think I see a pattern here already.
thirty, three, three times nine is twenty-seven.
You're going to keep getting thirty-three-- the three's are just
going to go on forever.
So it turns out that three is nine percent of-- you can either write it as
33.3 repeating or we all know that 0.3 forever is the
same thing as one / three.
So three is nine percent of thirty-three and one / three.
Either one of those would be an acceptable answer.
And a lot of times when you're doing percentages you're
actually just trying to get a ballpark.
The precision might not always be the most important thing,
but in this case we will be precise.
And obviously, on tests and things you need to
be precise as well.
Hopefully, I didn't go too fast and you have a good
sense of percentage.
The important thing for these type of problems is pay
attention to how the problem is written.
If it says find ten percent of one hundred.
That's easy.
You just convert ten percent to a decimal and multiply it by one hundred.
But if I were to ask you one hundred is ten percent of what?
You have to remember that that's a different problem.
In which case, one hundred is ten percent of-- and if you did the math,
it would be one thousand.
I think I spoke very quickly on this problem on this module, so
I hope you didn't get too confused.
But I will record more.