This is the Sant Ignatius Chapel, Ignatius of Loyola
and in his memory before he actually was proclaimed
as saint fully, the church was dedicated
and then when he was beatified and then canonised in 1622,
another entire church was built with his name Sant Ignazio,
which is nearby this chapel,
and celebrates his relationship to god.
It is explosion of light, precious material,
gold, lapis lazuli, silver, bronze and precious marbles.
And what we see is basically a painting enshrined in a great tabona.
A painting shows Sant Ignatius before God himself.
He is kneeling in his black habit before the figure of Christ
and he is holding a banner, bright red banner with the name of Jesus on it
as a representing or supplicating before God to be admitted to have.
And the most extraordinary thing about this
it is actually a theatrical mechanism.
In very recent years this has been restored
and it's functioning once again and generally speaking, at 5.30 p.m daily a painting
at combination of a fifteen to twenty minute sound and light show
lowers itself, the painting slides down gradually like a piece of theatrical
machinery into the ground, below the author
and reveals a full size but much larger than life size statue of Sant Ignatius.
He has not died and gone to heaven and above the whole figure cramps around by
angels as the image of Holy Trinity.
So this is Baroque scenery,
Baroque theatricality at its finest.
And at their call their machina back in those days as a machine.
The entire tabernacle is even on this deem day, is beautifully illuminated,
all of the incredible reflective qualities of the gold,
of the semi-precious stones, really reflecting light.
But if you look at the image itself it is so interesting, because below
the main scene you have the representation of the forming continents,
of the Africa of the new world.
The four corners of the world is like call of then
and then the Church of Sant Ignatius, church of few blocks from here,
we have a similar, the much larger painting on the ceiling in fresco
of that theme, of Ignatius' work, teaching and faith of the Jesuits
extending to the four parts of the now world.
The statue behind is not the original statue, part of it is,
but the great solid silver and gold parts were melted down,
when the Polian invaded in 1798
also to pay for the troops they also burnt a lot of the tapestries of the Vatican's
so they could get the precious gold and silver thread out.
This was the remain of the ninetinth century
and it still stands as a piece of absolutely wonderful
precious material.
I would add that between the gilded bronze shafts of those columns
are lots of pieces of lapis lazuli.
Lapis is ultramarine blue,
is one of the richest materials that we know,
still the most expensive colourig painting.
I clounge to use the last judgement ground up.
It comes from Afghanistan, but it is also highly expensive,
it's three times the price of gold,
three times the value of gold.
When the painting comes down and the sculpture is revealed
there is also musical accompaniment.
This is very central experience.