When most people buy a house
they need to borrow money for some part
of the purchase price of the house.
So let's say that we have a house right over here
and the purchase price is $200,000
And I want to buy this house
and I've saved up $40,000.
So this is my savings, and so I will use this as a downpayment
but I still need to borrow the rest of the money
in order to get to $200,000.
So I'm going to have to get the balance,
the $160,000 as a loan.
And the type of loan people get
or they usually get, is called a mortgage.
And a mortgage is really just a loan
where if you don't pay the loan off,
the person that you borrowed the money from
gets the house. So another way to think about it is
it's a loan that is secured by the house until you
pay off the loan. And when you pay off the loan,
it is your house to keep. But at any point,
if you don't pay it, the bank can come and take the house
and that is called a foreclosure.
Now what I want to focus on in this video
is the types of mortgage loans you will typically see,
and give you at least the beginning of an understanding
of how to understand what these different types of loans mean.
So all of these scenarios, let's just assume
that I'm in the market to borrow $160,000
for this house that I'm about to buy.
So if you look at any financial website, or any of the major
web portals, they'll give you quotes for mortgage rates
and you'll see something like this.
I made these numbers really simple, normally you'll have some decimals here
5.25%, 4.18%, I made these numbers a little bit simpler
just to make them simpler.
So, these are the typical types of mortgages you will see
but if you contact a mortgage broker, they'll
have many, many more types, more exotic types,
but these are the most common
this is what we will cover in this video,
and hopefully this will give you a sense of what the other types
of mortgages are like.
A 30-year fixed mortgage means that your
payment and your interest rate are fixed over 30 years,
and over the course of those 30 years,
you will pay off your loan.
So in this situation, so this is a 30... let me write it over here
So let's think about a 30 year fixed mortgage.
What will happen is you will have a fixed mortgage
payment every month. I'll draw a little bar graph
to show the size of your payment.
You'll see why I'm doing that in a second.
So let me just draw a little bit of a graph here.
So each of these blocks represent your
monthly payment for that month
and I'm just going to make up the number
let's say it's $2,000. I actually haven't
figured out the math of what is the exact payment
for a 30-year fixed with a 5% interest rate
for $160,000. But let's just say
for the sake of simplicity, let's say it's $2,000 a month.
So this height right over here
let me make it like this
So this is $2,000 a month.
$2,000. This is month one, then you will pay
$2,000 in month 2, and so on a so forth,
all the way... if you have 30 years times 12 months
you're gonna get all the way to month 360, and
that is going to be your last payment.
Month 360 is the last payment in the year 30,
and you would have paid off your loan.
The interesting thing here is, in the first month
since you have borrowed so much from the bank
you've borrowed $160,000. The interest that you have to pay on it
is going to be pretty large.
So most of the initial payments
are going to be interest.
So I'm going to the interest in this magenta color
That's not magenta... this is magenta.
In that first payment, it's going to be mostly interest.
And you're going to pay a little bit off of the actual loan,
so that right there is your principle payment.
So let's say after that first month, the principle part
of that $2,000 is (and I'm just making up numbers for the sake of simplicity),
Let's say that that is $200, and the interest portion
is $1,800. I'm not actually working it through
with the assumptions. You don't even have to assume
that's a $160,000 loan. But the general idea
here is that after this first month, you would have
paid $200 off of your loan. So if it was a $160,000 loan
after that first month, you don't owe $160,000 minus $2,000
because $1,800 of that was interest. You now owe
$160,000 minus $200, so you now owe
$159,800.
And so in the next period,
your interest is going to be just a little bit lower.
And your principle, since you're paying the same fixed payment
of $2,000 every month, is going to be a little bit higher.
Maybe it's going to be the next month something slightly higher
I don't know, something like $202, I don't know...
And you keep going like that
and the math works out, they you figure out the payment
so that by that last payment
you're paying very little interest,
and most of that last payment is principle.
it's actually being used for the loan.
And then after that last payment
the loan is paid off. And this will happen
over 30 years. This is a 30 year term.
A 15-year fixed is the same exact idea
except, instead of it taking 30 years to pay off the loan
you're going to do it over 15 years
so it instead of it being 360 months in the 30 year case
it is going to be 180 months
and because of that your payment for the same loan amount
is going to be higher every month
because you're paying it off quicker
you're paying it off in fewer months.
Instead of $2,000 per month, maybe it is something like
$2,800 a month for the 15 year case.
You're paying it off quicker.
The five one ARM case, you'll see there are many types of ARMs,
and I'm gonna explain to you in a second what an ARM is
but the five-one is the most typical
and I will explain that in a second.
ARM means Adjustable Rate Mortgage.
And as you see in these situations,
we have the word "fixed," and they're called fixed
because the interest rate was fixed.
Whatever your remaining loan balance was,
you paid the same fixed amount of interest for the next period
so for this 30 year fixed, we are being quoted
a 5% fixed rate over the next years (will not change),
for the 15 year, we're quoted a 4% fixed rate
for the ARM, the rate can change.
When someone tells you about a five-one ARM
They're actually talking about something called
a hybrid ARM, but the general idea behind an adjustable rate mortgage
is the amount of interest you pay on your remaining balance
will change according to some index.
The most typical types of adjustable rate mortgages
are things like this hybrid ARM.
This is a hybrid. And a hybrid, it's viewed as a mixture
of two things, or a combination of 2 things
and what a hybrid adjustable rate mortgage is
is it has a fixed rate for some period of time
in this case it's a fixed rate for 5 years.
and then the interest rate can change
once a year after that, or every 1 years after that
And that's what this right over here is telling you
So in the case of an adjustable rate mortgage,
your payment might look something like this
I'll just make up numbers for simplicity
just to give you a flavor of what it might look like.
So in the case of a five-one, your first five years
are fixed. So month 1 can look like that,
month 2 is going to look like that
you go all the way to month 60, which is the last month
of 5 years. So that's month 1, that's month 2, that is month 60
This is over the course of 5 years
And over the course of 5 years, the idea
is fairly similar. Some part of this is going to be
interest, and the remainder is going to actually be used
to pay down the loan. And each month you're going to
pay down a little bit more of the loan
and you're going to have to pay a little less in interest
because you have less remaining on your loan.
But by year 5, or month 60, you still haven't paid your loan off
So maybe the interest is right over here,
Maybe the interest is right over there
and actually it may be higher than that
I don't want to be too exact
and then this is what you're paying down from the loan
A hybrid adjustable rate mortgage, after that 5 year period
The bank can now change the interest rate
And the interest rate is going to be dependent
on some kind of underlying thing that every one is
paying attention to. And so if that underlying thing
increases in interest. So in this five-one ARM
it starts off at a 3% interest. If because of this thing
that we're paying attention to
and I'll talk more about that in a second
interest rates all of a sudden go up
and let's say they go up a lot
then all of a sudden your payment could increase.
Because the general idea behind a five-one ARM
is that you are still going to pay it off
in 30 years. So they typically, I should say,
have a 30 year term. So if you just stick with this loan
you never try to borrow other money to replace this loan
which is called a refinance
you stick with this loan, it will take you 30 years
to pay it off. But after the first 5 years
The amount of interest you pay might actually change
So your payment might actually change.
So if the interest rate goes up
All of a sudden, you might have to pay
a lot more interest
all of a sudden in month 61, or in year 6.
Let me do that part in that same blue color
And that for year 6, since this is a five-one ARM
They can't change the interest rate again until
year 7, so you'll pay this constant amount
until year 7. But then they will change the rate again.
And there usually are some caps on how much they can change the rate
each year or how much they can change the rate in total
but it is a little bit riskier
because you really don't know what your payment might be
in year 6 or 7, especially if interest rates go up a lot
Now you might be asking,
"What determines what that new interest rate is after the 5 years?"
And they usually pick some type of index
the most typical are treasury securities
so they'll look at the 10-year treasury interest rate
that essentially the government has to pay when it borrows money
and they'll usually take some premium over this
So if the 10-year treasuries are at 2%
The bank might put in your loan documents
that after the initial 5 year fixed period
you will pay 10-year treasury rate, plus 1%.
So you start off paying the 3%, that's fixed
even if the treasury does all sorts of crazy things
even if it goes up to 5%, you're just going to
keep paying the 3% for the first 5 years
but then in that 6th year
let's say that (let me just write it over here)
let's say that in year 6 the treasury security rate
now has bumped up to 4%
then by contract, by what's in your loan document
you're going to have to pay that, plus 1%
so now your mortgage is going to reset
to have a 5% rate, have a higher rate.
You might get lucky though
maybe the treasury rate goes down
maybe it goes to 1%, and then your mortgage rate would actually be 1% plus 1%
so it could actually go down to 2%
But the general idea is that that's a little riskier
because you really don't know how predictable that payment
is going to be.
And if you look at most times
if you look at quoted interest rates
you'll see that the 30-year fixed rate is higher
than the 15-year fixed rate, which is higher than
the adjustable rate. And that's because the bank,
there's a couple of different forms of risk
but the bank is taking the least amount of risk
on the adjustable rate mortgage
and taking the most amount of risk on the 30 year fixed.
And the biggest risk here, there's the risk that you don't pay it off
But that's why they like to see a downpayment
because they can get the house back and hopefully
the house doesn't devalue by more than the amount
of your down payment. But even more than that
there's an interest rate risk.
What happens if the bank lends you money
lends you a big chunk of money at 5%
and then interest rates go up to 6%, 7%
what if they go up to 10%? What if the banks borrowing costs,
the amount of money the bank has to pay people to borrow money,
goes up to 10%, then they will be taking a loss on your loan
They're fixing it for so long, that's why they want to
make up for some of that risk by charging you
higher risk.
A 15 year loan, a little bit less risk
so they'll have a little bit lower interest.
A five-one ARM, even lower risk
they're only fixed for 5 years
and then after that, this will float with the prevailing interest rate
on an annual basis.
So hopefully that give you a little bit of a primer
of mortgage interest rates
but I want to really make sure you don't view this video
as all you need to take out a loan.
It's super important to read the fine print and details
on what's happening with that loan,
especially if you're buying something more, if you're taking out a more exotic
like an adjustable rate mortgage
or an interest only loan, or an option ARM
or any o