We're on problem 129.
On a recent trip, Cindy drove her car 290 miles,
rounded to the nearest 10 miles,
and used 12 gallons of gasoline,
rounded to the nearest gallons.
The actual number of miles per gallon that
Cindy's car got on this trip must have been between?
So they want us to kind of say these are the rounded numbers,
now what were the actual numbers between,
and then from that what's the range of miles per gallon?
So if this is rounded to the nearest 10,
then her miles had to have been greater than or equal to 285,
because anything 285 or more would have been rounded to 290.
But then less than 295 because anything less than 295 would
be rounded down, but 295 itself would be rounded up to 300.
And her gallons had to have been greater than or equal to
11.5 gallons, by the same logic, and less than 12.5 gallons.
So what was the lowest possible miles per gallon?
So the lowest possible miles per gallon would have the
lowest miles and the highest gallons. You want to minimize
the numerator and maximize the denominator.
So lowest possible miles would be 285.
And the highest possible gallons,
at least it'll approach 12.5.
So 12.499999 is the possible number of gallons,
so it'll approach this.
But it can never be exactly 12.5 gallons,
so her miles per gallon are going to be greater than this.
It would've been greater than equal to this with like
12.499999, but since 12.5 can never get there, we're going
to be greater than this in terms of miles per gallon.
And then the highest possible miles per gallon is the
highest possible miles, which is 295.
But we're never going to be able to go twice quite there.
We're always going to be less than 295.
And then the lowest number of gallons-- going the highest
mileage with the lowest possible gallons,
you want to minimize the demonimator-- divided by 11.5.
Let's see if that is a choice.
I don't see that exactly, but choice D looks interesting
because choice D says-- so they say the actual number of
miles per gallon that Cindy's car got on this trip must have
been between.
Choice D looks close to what we have because we have this.
Choice D says between 284 divided by 12.5.
That's going to be even less than that,
because you have the 12.5 but the numerator's less.
So that's going to be even lower than the range that we have.
And then on choice D, 295 divided 11.4.
This number is larger than this number, because you have
the same numerator and you have a smaller denominator.
So you're dividing by a smaller number.
So this number's larger.
So if her miles per gallon is between these two numbers,
and these two numbers are between these two numbers,
then D is right.
Her miles per gallon need to be between 284 divided by 12.5
and 295 divided by 11.4. So it's choice D.
Problem 130.
Which of the following inequalities is an algebraic
expression for the shaded part of the number line above?
So this number line, let's try to draw it. That's the line.
And I'm not going to draw all of the dots on it,
but it essentially starts at positive 3 and it goes backwards
Let's switch colors.
It starts essentially from minus 5 to positive 3.
That's all of what this includes.
1, 0, and then minus 5.
So you could say that x is less than or equal to 3 because
it's filled in at 3, and greater than or equal to minus 5.
And that's not one of the choices.
They want it in terms of absolute value.
So how we can view this, this is a range around some number.
Whenever you're dealing without absolute value,
you're essentially saying the distance from some number.
So this is a range of minus 5 and 3.
This has a length of 8, so they're both 4 away from minus 1.
Think about it. You could go 4 backwards or 4 forwards.
So one way to think about it is the difference between x
and minus 1, and that might be a negative or positive
difference depending on whether we're positive or negative,
depending on whether we're above negative 1 or
below negative 1. But we just want the absolute difference.
We just want the distance away from negative 1.
And that's given by this,
the difference between any x and negative 1. And
we took the absolute value in case x is less than negative 1.
The distance is going to be less than or equal to 4,
because if we go above negative 1 we're at most at 3,
which is 4 more than negative 1.
If we go below negative 1, we're at minus 5 which is 4
less than negative 1. So it's less than or equal to 4.
if you simplify this, you get x plus 1,
the absolute value is less than or equal to 4.
And that is choice E. And this is a useful skill.
You have probably taken the SAT already, but in general,
a lot of standardized tests think of absolute value as a
distance in 1 dimension.So the distance along the number line
So they're saying all of these points,
they're within some range from 1 point.
And you can say if you take the midpoint of this,
you're at negative 1.
And every point here's within 4 of negative 1.
So the distance between every point on this line,
every x that satisfies this and negative 1,
the distance is less than or equal to 4.
Anyway, I kind of just did the problem twice for you.
Problem 131.
A factory has 500 workers, 15% of whom are women.
So 15% times 500 is equal to women.
If 50 additional workers are to be hired and all of the
present workers remain, how many of the additional workers
must be women in order to raise the percent of women
employees to 20%?
So how many women workers do we have right now?
5 times 15, we have 75 workers. 15 times 500.
We have 75 women right now.
If we wanted to find the proportion of women,
it's 75 over 500, which is once again 15. It's 15%.
We're going to add a total of 50 workers to this population.
And they want to know how many of the additional workers must
be women in order to raise the percent of women
population to 20%. So we're adding 50 total workers.
So how many of those have to be women in order for the new
proportion-- this is going to be the new number of women,
the number of women that are added to the 75 that were
already there-- divided by the 500 workers who were there,
plus the 50, some of whom might be women.
So this now has to equal 20%.
We get 75 plus w over 550 is equal to 0.2.
So we get 75 plus the number of women that need to be added
is equal to 0.2 times 550. We multiply both sides times 550.
That equals 110. And then subtract 75 from both sides.
Women has to be equal to 110 minus 75.
And that's equal to-- 25 plus 10-- that's equal to 35.
35 of the 50 employees have to be women.
And that's what they asked.
How many of the additional workers must be women?
So that's choice E.
Next question, 132.
At a small snack shop, the average arithmetic mean
revenue was $400 per day over a 10 day period.
So the average over 10 days was $400.
During this period, if the average daily revenue was $360
for the first 6 days-- so the average of 6 days was $360--
what was the average daily revenue for the last 4 days?
So we've done a lot of problems like this.
Hopefully this is a bit of second nature if you've
watched the solution to the other ones.
But what's the average of all of them?
It's the average of the first 6 days.
We can almost assume that the first 6 days had exactly $360
in revenue. So their average times 6.
So this would be the total revenue of the first 6 days
plus what's the total revenue of the next 4 days?
It's going to be the average of the next 4 days times 4.
That would be the total of those 4.
We're not saying that they all have to be exactly the average
but when you sum them all up they're equal to the
average times 4. Now if you divide all of those,
this is a total of the revenue all 10 days.
If you take that sum and divide it by 10,
you get the average for the 10 days.
And that is equal to $400. Let's simplify this a little bit.
Let's see what we could do.
So we get 360 times 6 plus the average for 4 days times 4 is
equal to 10 times 400, which is 4,000.
Before I get too involved in multiplication,
let's divide both sides of this equation by 4.
So 360 divided by 4, that's 90,
times 6 plus this divided by 4 plus A4 is equal to 1,000.
90 times 6 is 540 plus the average of the 4
days is equal to 1,000.
So the average of the 4 days is equal to 1,000 minus 540.
Which is what? That's $460 per day. And that's choice D.
And I'm out of time. See you in the next video.