So this is a picture of Dr. Korotkoff.
Dr. Korotkoff is a very famous Russian doctor who lived about a 100 years ago and something he came up with, something very clever, and that still affects all of us or most of us today.
So he lived in the early 1900s and around 1905, he started thinking.
He was thinking about blood vessels, and he was trying to figure "How to use the stethoscope to (let's just draw the skin here over the blood vessel)
How to use the stethoscope to listen and figure out the blood pressure?"
So he was thinking "How can I get about to do that?"
So, first thing he decided to do was inflate a cuff like a blood pressure cuff
and he would put a lot of pressure on the outside of the skin on that blood vessel,
so he thought, "well for example, let's do something like 200 mmHg
and for this example let's just assume that he is working with me,
let's assume that he is working with my blood vessel
and my blood pressure is about 115 systolic over 75 diastolic.
So, if you put 200 mm of pressure on the outside,
what's going to happen? The first thing is that that vessel is definitely not going to stay open, right?
It's going to collapse down, so it is going to do this.
As he gets all that pressure in the blood, it is going to turn right around
and say, "well we can't go through this way."
So, if he listens with his stethoscope here, if he is listening, he would really hear silence here,
he would hear a nothing at all, it would be very quiet.
So we put "silence"
because there is no blood flowing
at this point, because the vessel is collapsed.
Okay, so Dr. Korotkoff thought about this and said "okay well, what if I go ahead and
do something slightly different?" Let's open this up a little
bit, because what he is going to do next is instead of putting 200 mm of pressure
as he did the first time, he is going to put exactly 115,
exactly the systolic pressure