We've been talking a lot about elasticities of a demand,
so you were probably wondering,
can we think about elasticities of a supply?
And as you can imagine, the answer is:
of course we can!
And it's interesting to think about
how does the quantity the percent change in quantity supplied
relate to percent change in prices
So, for example, let's say we have
a lemonade stand of some sort.
So this is price on that axis
and that is quantity on that axis.
And let's say that our supply curve
looks something like that
Obviously, the higher the price,
the more quantity we are willing to supply.
And let's say at a price of $1,
the quantity supplied is going to be 10 gallons/week.
this is going to be 10 gallons/week.
So the quantity of supplies is going to be 10 gallons per week.
And let's say that if the price goes to $2,
the quantity supplied goes to 16 gallons per week.
So what is the elasticity of supply,
roughly, over this period right over here?
So the elasticity... elasticity of supply, and you can imagine
how we can calcalute this as % change in quantity supplied over our
% change in price, so what is our percent
change in price, well we went from $1 to $2, (so this part right over here) is going to be
we went up by $1,
so we went up by $1 per gallon,
so it's going up by $1,and we all use our starting point as base we can do in traditionally finding of percent change
because we have the same percent change , if we're going from 1 to 2, as from 2 to 1
so instead the conventionally we think about elasticity is to use the mid-point of these two, use the average of these two
so 1+2 is 3, 3/2 is 1,5. So it's 1 over $1.50. We can say, $1,50 is right in between these two things.
and 1 over $1,50 this is about 67 % roughly, so this is approximatelly 67%
change in price based on how we just calculate it, how we're using
the midpoint as our base, and that are % change
in quantity supplied, that's % change in quantity supplied, that's this, this right over here
we went from 10 to 16, so we have +6 over base of midpoint between 10 and 16, is 13. 10 + 16 is 26, divided by two
is 13. 6 over 13. Which is going to be something percent. We'll take calculator out, so
we have 6 divided by 13, get this 46 %. So this is, this right over here is 46%. So we have
when we had based on the way we have calculated, this 67%
increase in price we had 46% increase in quantity supplied.
So this is 46% increase in quantity supplied, it's all we can see about elasticity
of supply, it's goíng to be 46% over 67%, so it's going to be something less than 1.
We can get, so that's going to be that divided by 0,6666666... keeps going on forever, this is 0,69
So this is elasticity of supply 0,69, we've back see it approximatelly 0,69.
we've tell this, we get a smaller percent at least this price point right over here, we get a smaller percent change in quantity
supplied than our percent change in price. Let's think about like me did with let me talk about we do about elasticities of demand, let's think about different scenarios
So let's think about, let's think about a scenario that is inelastic.
That is maybe perfectly inealastic. So let's say that price,
price and quantity. So let's take me for an example - I make videos, I love making videos, this is what I want spend my days doing
and I don't care about how much they pay me, or how little you pay me, I guess prepair to be enough
that would maybe and I spent little bit more time making videos.
What else just as soon that I don't completely, I you know what you pay me a penny pro video or 0 pro video or do you pay me a $1000 pro video
I'm going to just make the same number videos every day. So this is the right over here videos, videos pro day on average and it's
and this is the price per video. And let's say no matter how much you pay - what do you pay me nothing or you pay me $1000.
I was going to produce on average, let's say 3 videos a day. So than you have this
right over here you have an perfectly inelastic
perfectly inelastic supply curve. Now you can have the other scenario, you can have the
when you are farmer, so let me do price and quantity. Now you can have the other scenario when you are farmer
and you can either do crop, aid cropy, maybe it's corn and wheat. And you can easily swap between the two
unless this is soon for simplicity cost you the exact the same to produce one or the other. So
in that situation so let's say that the price of wheat pearl, let's say we're using capable price units. So the price of wheat is for you know
adjusting 4 units in all of that, let's say is $10 I don't know for bushels or something like that. I like this simplyfy for the sink model right here but this
right over here we're thinking about corn. We're thinking about corn.
We're thinking about corn, and so if corn so let's say corn is right $10. We're bought it for right $10 I will produce, so them let me make this clear
So price of corn is $10 and the quantity of corn maybe I don't know produce, I produce 2000 bushels
I know these prices are away for what a real price for bushel of corn or wheat is the same thing
my quantity for wheat right here is 2000. Now
if the price of corn will go marginally up if the price of corn, so let me put this, so this is graph of corn. So this is $10
and this is 2000 bushels pro year of something, so let's say that we're right over there,
now if the price for corn goes marginally up, the price for corn goes up to even $10,5 per bushel
all cents awnished from wheat production to corn production, this is going to be zero and this is going to go to 4000
So then, whenever we go, just as 10, line, whenever we go all the way to 4000. And likewise if this price will go down
if this go down like 9,95, I will shift all my production to wheat and wouldn't produce any corn. And so there you see that we have the very
the main curve is getting very flat and you can see based on very very small percent changes in prices, I have very large percent changes in quantity supplied.
So this right over here is approaching, this is approaching, approaching perfect elasticity,
huge changes in quantity supplied elasticity for small percent changes in price
Now, the cool thing about elasticity of supply is actually much easier to make a curve that has unit elasticity or even
it's easy if you have unit elasticity, but if you have unit elasticity the easy as curve I can draw
for unit elasticity is going look like this, much this is curve for unit elasticity, it will be curve looks like that
and the reason why it works in this case is upwards sloping as price increases so as quantity
increase for the supply curve so that any point here the 2 are going to be proportional
So a given change in quantity and a given change in price they are going to represent the same percentages.
Because as price is increasing, what this is we have large price, or we have medium price, you have medium quantity
When you have a large price, you have large quantity.
So these steps are going to be the same percentage of I wonder you have small prices, you have small quantity.
It's much easier to construct a curve, a supply curve that has unit elasticity, than this is to construct a normal demand curve that has unit elasticity.