“We now know a little bit about inflation, deflation.
Now I want to introduce you to hyper, hyperinflation, and as the word implies, it’s inflation gone wild.
And the general idea how hyperinflation, or at least the cases that we’ve seen in modern times,
how they’ve happened, is you have some type of a government just going wild with the printing press, they’re just printing a ton of money.
So the general cycle is they print money. Let me draw it this way, so they print, they print like mad,
they print like mad usually, because they don’t have any other way of getting revenue,
they print like mad that leads to prices going up, prices going up,
and then because prices goes up, they have to print more in order to for them to
able to get the same goods and services or pay the government workers what they wanted to pay the government workers,
or pay the soldiers, what they wanted to pay the soldiers.
And on top of this, this is by self would probably drive the hyperinflation in and of itself.
But on the top of this, you can imagine, we’re used to thinking high inflation is five or ten percent,
but you can imagine what happens when inflation is five or ten per hour.
Because then, there’s no incentive to be actually holding currency.
Every second that you hold currency it becomes worth less and less and less.
And so what happens in the scenario like this is people want to hoard hard assets.
So if the price of bread is going up by the minute, or by the hour, or the price of shoes are going up by the minute or by the hour.
The increase in prices is going to make people hoard things, I spelled “hording” wrong, hoarding.
Hoarding goes through the roof, and you can imagine if hoarding goes through the roof,
if the shoe seller doesn't want to sell his shoes any more because –or he wants to hold them a little bit longer,
then the supply of shoes are gunna (going to) down, and the prices are gunna go up even higher,
so hoarding leads even to higher prices.
If when people go to the bread market and there's five loaves of bread,
they buy all of them and then the next person can't buy any,
because they know the price of bread is going through the roof.
It just keeps getting worse and worse and it's all started by the
government kind of just going nuts with the printing press.
The three most famous examples of this happening,
probably the most famous one is what happened in Weimar, Germany,
after World War I, they had huge reparations to pay,
that’s what the Weimar Government would have argued was their main cause.
But they just printed money like crazy.
Some people said that they were almost trying to destroy the economy
so that they wouldn't have to pay reparations for what they did in World War I.
But this just gives you a sense of how crazy it was, here’s the end of World War I,
and they just printed money like mad and the inflation, it was pretty –it was- this isn’t the rate of inflation,
this is how much was it relative to a gold mark, so this is one gold mark, over here.
So by, only after about two and a half years it was over ten fold.
And this is a logarithmic scale. Each slash-year, this a factor of ten.
So by the end of 1923, you’re looking at this is what: not one hundred thousand,
not or not a million, not a billion, this is a trillion.
It had gone up a trillion fold in the span of one, two, three, four, five, or was that six years.
The other famous examples of this is Zimbabwe, from 1980 until 2009,
once again printing money like mad, and there’s some of their productive capacity went away.
This right here is a one hundred trillion Zimbabwe dollar,
and this shows you the Zimbabwe dollar relative to the US dollar.
And once again this a logarithmic scale, this is ten to the 30th power.
And then the largest or the most extreme hyperinflation ever was Hungary after World War II,
and this right here is a ten million pin go note,
just to give you an idea of what people were carrying around their pockets.”