So we have this larger triangle here,
and inside of that we have these other triangles
And we're given this information right over here
that triangle BCD is congruent to triangle BCA,
which is congruent to triangle ECD
And given just this information, what I wanna do in this drawing,
I wanna figure out what every angle on this drawing is
What's the measure of every angle
So let's see what we can do here
So let's just start with the information
that they've actually given us
So we know, we know that triangle BCD is congruent
so BCD is congruent to, well we know it's congruent
all of these triangles are congruent to each other
So for example, BCD is congruent to ECD
And so their corresponding sides and corresponding
angles will also be congruent
So just looking at the word written,
B, vertex B corresponds,
in this triangle, in BCD ,
corresponds to vertex B in BCA, BCA
So this is the B vertex in BCA
which corresponds to the E vertex in ECD
So all everything that I've done magenta
all of these angles are congruent
And then we also know,
we also know that the C angle, so in BCA sorry, BCD
This angle, this angle right over here
is congruent to the C angle in BCA, BCA
The C angle is right over here,
or C is the vertex for that angle in BCA
And that is also the, the,
the C angle I guess you could call it, in ECD
But in ECD, we're talking about this angle right over here
So these three angles are going to be congruent
I think you could already guess a way
to come up with the values of those three angles
But let's just
let's keep looking at everything else that they're telling us
Finally, we have vertex D over here
So angle so, angle
so this is the last one in, where we lifted,
B so in triangle BCD, this angle,
this angle right over here corresponds to the A vertex angle in BCA
So BCA, that corresponds to this angle right over here
It's really the only one that we haven't labelled yet
And that corresponds to this angle, this vertex right over here
That angle right over there , and just to make it consistent,
this C should also be circled in yellow
And so we have all these congruencies
and now we can come up with some interesting things about them
First of all, here
Angle BCA, angle BCD, and angle DCE, they're all congruent
And when you add them up together, you get to 180 degrees
If you put them all adjacent, cause they all are right here,
they'd end up with a straight angle,
if you look at their outer sides
So you have if these are each x, you have
three of them added together have to be 180 degrees
which tells us that each of these have to be 60 degrees
That's the only way you have three of the same thing
adding up to 180 degrees
Fair enough
What else can we do?
Well, we have these two characters up here
They are both equal and they add up to 180 degrees,
they are supplementary
And the only way we can have two equal things that add up to 180
is that if they're both 90 degrees
So, these two characters are both 90 degrees,
or we could say this is a right angle, that's a right angle
And this is congruent to both of those, so that is also,
that is also 90 degrees
And then we're left with these magenta parts of the angle
And here we can just say,
well 90 + 60 + something is going to add up to 180
90 + 60 is 150,
so this has to be 30 degrees to add up to 180
If that's 30 degrees, then this is 30 degrees,
and then this thing right over here is 30 degrees
And then the last thing,
we've actually done what we said we would do
We've found out all of the angles
We can also think about these outer angles,
so this or not outer angles, or just combined angles
So angles, say AC, oh sorry angle ABE
So this whole angle we see is that whole angle is 60 degrees
This angle is 90 degrees
And this angle, here, is 30
So what's interesting is, these smaller triangles are all
they all have the exact same angles: 30, 60, 90,
and the exact same side lengths
We know that because they're congruent
But what's interesting is when you put them together this way,
they construct this larger triangle, triangle ABE,
that's clearly not congruent
It's a larger triangle that has different measures for its lengths,
but has the same angles: 30, 60, and then 90
So it's actually similar to all of the triangles that it's made up of