All right, this is a fun problem,
so it'll get a video on its own.
I started in the last video,
but I'm going to start over
just so we get it all in one take.
So they say, in the figure above,
arc SBT is 1/4 of a circle with center R and radius 6
And they actually tell-- they draw this distance,
which is the radius.
This distance is 6, right?
So this distance would also be 6, right?
If the length plus the width of rectangle ABCR is 8
so this is ABCR.
So the length plus the width is 8.
So let's call this L and this is W.
Actually, this should be-- well, it doesn't matter,
this should be height, but whatever.
We know that these two sides are equal to 8.
So we know that L plus W is equal to 8.
Fair enough.
Then the perimeter of the shaded region is--
that's this perimeter right here,
so there's a lot of pieces to it.
So let's start with
what I would call he low hanging fruit.
So the low hanging fruit, in my opinion,
is the length of this arc.
Arc SBT.
What's the length of that?
Well, it's going to be
1/4 the circumference of the entire circle, right?
Because this arc represents--
what we drew is 1/4 of the circle,
so this length is going to be 1/4 of the circumference
So the length of the circumference--
so the circumference of, let me see,
the circumference of the circle, is what?
It's 2 pi r.
r is 6, right?
So 2 pi times 6, is equal to 12 pi.
If the circumference of the circle is 12 pi,
then we could call the length of the arc, right--
let's call this LA--
the length of the arc is going to be what?
It's going to be 1/4 the circumference
of the whole circle.
1/4 times 12 pi is equal to 3 pi.
Good enough.
Now what else can we try to figure out?
Well, the second lowest hanging fruit is actually
the length of this line.
Which you're probably saying, well,
they give me no information, maybe
I have to use the Pythagorean theorem with W and L,
but it's really just a visual trick,
because I'll tell you that
you could actually just look at this graph
and figure out what the length from A to C is.
And I'll give you a hint.
What is the length from R to B?
What is that length?
Well isn't R to B a radius of the circle?
It's going from the center to the edge of circle,
so it's a radius.
So RB has length 6.
And RB is a diagonal of this rectangle just like AC is
so they're symmetric,
so this is also going to be equal to 6.
And you could look at it a bunch of different ways,
you could say that W squared plus L squared is
equal to this, AC squared.
Well, W squared, this is W as well, right,
you could also say that W squared plus L squared is
equal to this side squared.
So that's why they're equal to each other.
So we know length of AC is equal to 6, as well.
Right?
We figured out that.
So we have two pieces left.
We just have that piece, and that piece.
What's the length of this piece?
Well, this whole distance is 6.
We figured that out because that's a radius.
And this piece is L, right?
That's L.
So that piece is 6 minus L.
Similarly, what's this piece?
By the same logic, that's 6 minus W, right?
This is W, the whole thing is 6,
so this leftover is 6 minus W.
So if we want
the perimeter of this entire shaded region,
it's this perimeter of this brown arc, which is 3 pi.
So let me say, perimeter is equal to 3 pi.
Plus the length of AC, plus 6.
Plus this piece, plus 6 minus L.
Plus this piece, plus 6 minus W.
And let's simplify that a bit.
So let's see, that equals 3 pi,
and then we have three 6's,
so plus 18, minus L, minus W.
And this is the same thing
as 3 pi plus 18 minus L plus W.
Fascinating.
And really, I kind of just bumbled my way here.
You know the problem is solvable,
and that's better than most mathematicians have going for them,
and so you just kind of have to
bumble away with whatever information they give you.
The real trick here, I think,
is recognizing that AC is the same length as RB.
But once you get to this point,
you have to now employ the second trick.
You have to realize that minus L minus W,
well that looks a lot like this L plus W up here.
And this is really kind of
what separates the adults from the children, I guess.
So we know that L plus W is 8,
so just substitute here, 8.
So the perimeter is 3 pi, plus 18, minus 8.
That equals 3 pi plus 10, and that is choice B.
That was exciting.
I'll see you in the next section.