Let's say we've got the function f(x) is equal to e to the x,
just to get a sense of what that looks like
we do a rough drawing of f(x) is equal to e to the x.
It would look something like this. It would look something
like that. So that is e to the x, and what I want to do is approximate f(x) is equal to e to the x
using a taylor series approximation or taylor series expansion, and I want to do it
not around is equal to 0, I want to do it around x is equal to
3, just to pick another arbitrary value, so we're going to do it around x is
equal to 3, this is x is equal to 3, this right there, that is f of 3
, f of 3 is e to the third power. So this is e to the third power
over there. So when we take the taylor series expansion, if we have a
zero degree polynomial approximating it, the best we can do is have a constant
function going straight through e to the third. If we do a first order approximation
so we have a first degree term, then it will be the tangent line
. As we add more and more degrees to it, we should hopefully
be able to, kind of contour or converge with
the curve better and better and better. In the future we'll talk more about
how we can test for convergences, and how well are we converging, and all
that type of thing. But with that said, let's just apply the formula
, then hopefully we'll have the intuition for in the last video. So the
taylor series expansion for f(x) is equal to e to the x will be the
polynomial. So what is f of c. Well if x is equal to 3, we're saying
that c is 3 in this situation. So if c is 3, f of 3 is e to the third power
. So that is e to the third power plus, what's f prime of c? Well,
f prime of x is also going to be e to the x. You take the derivative of
e to the x to get e to the x. That's one of the supercool things
about e to the x. So thjis is also f prime of x, gfrankly this is also the sma e as
f, the nth derivative of x. You can just keep taking the derivative
of this and you'll get e to the x. So f prime of x is e to the x
, you evaluate that at 3, you get e to the third power again, times
x minus 3, c is 3, plus the second derivative of our function, we
it's still e to the x, evaluate that at 3, you get e to the third power
over 2 factorial times x minus 3 to the 2nd power, we can keep
going. The third derivative is still ex, evaluate that at 3, c is three in this
situation so you get e to the third power over 3 factorial times x minus
3 to the third power, and we can keep going with this, but I think you get
the general idea. But what's even more interestin than just kind of going through
the mechanics of finding the expansion is seeing how it
how as we add more and more terms it approximates e to the x
better and better and better, and our approximation gets further away from
x is equal to 3. A nd to to dthat I used wolfram alpha
available at wolframalpha.com/.And I think I tpyed in taylor series expansion
e to the x ad xis equals 3, and it knew what i wanted, and just gave
me all of this business right over here. And you can see that's its the exact same thing that we have
over here e to the third and e to third times times x-3 plus 1/2. They actually
expanded out the factorial, instead of 3 factorial they wrote 6 over here,
and they did a bunch of terms over here. But whats even more interesting is
that they actually graph each of these polynomials qwith more and more terms
So in orange we have e to the x, we have fi s equal to e to the x, and then they
#tell us, order and approximation shown wuth n dots, so the
order 1 approximation, so that should be the suituatioin where we have
a first degree polynomial, so literaally a first degree polynomial would be these
three temrs right over here. Cause this is a zeroth degree,, this is a first degree
we just hvae x to the first power involved her. That will be, if we just
qwere to plot this, if this was our polynomial that is plotted nwith
one dot, and that is this one right over here is one dot, and they plotted, they
plotted right over here and we can
can see that it's just a tangent line at , x is equal to 3, that
is x is equal to 3 right over there. So this is the tangent line. If
we add a term, now we're getting to a second degree polynomial
cause we're adding an x squared, and if you expand this out you'll
have a x squared term and you'll have another x term, but the degree
of the polynomial will now be a second degree. So let's look for 2 dots
So that's this one right over here. So let's see, 2 dots coming in
see you'll not notice one but two dots, so you have 2 dots and it comes in
and this is a parabola, this is a second degree polynomial, and then it
comes back like this. But notice, it does a better job, especially around x equals 3
of approximating e to the x. It stays with the curve a little bit longer
. You add another term, let me do this in another colour, a colour
that I have not used, you add another term. Now you hvae a third degree polynomial
. If you have all of these combined, if this is your polynomial, and you
were to graph that, and so let's look for the 3 dots right over here
. So 1, 2, 3, so it's this curve, third degree polynomial is this curve
right over here. And notice it starts contouring e to the x a little bit
sooner than the second degree version, and it stays with it a little bit
longer. It stays with it a little bit longer, and so you have it just
like that. You add another term to it, you add the fourth degree term
to it, so now we have all of this plus all of this. All this is
your polynomial now you have this cool curve right over here. Notice, if you add
a term, it's getting better and better at approximating e to the x
furht er and further away fromx is equal ro 3. And if you add anbother
term, you get this term, this one up here. But hopefully that
satisfies you that we are getting closer and closer the more terms
we add, so you can imagine it's a pretty darn good approximation