Now that we've done a series of videos on America's interventions during the Cold War
in Korea---Korea and Cuba and Vietnam, I thought it would be fun
to just think a little bit of the patterns here
and just as in all of these History videos
you have to take anything I say, or really
anything anyone says about History with a grain of salt
even when it comes to the facts
obviously the facts can only be written by the people
who survive, who knows what might have gone on
behind the scenes that never got documented by historians
so you have to take everything with a grain of salt. And even when
you know, in this video, I'll talk about maybe some patterns
some themes that I have seen
don't take that as just the truth
think about it for yourself. If it makes sense, it makes sense
and if doesn't, try to look into it more
and try to come up wth your own themes or your patterns or things that you can learn from
So the general pattern across all of these is that
before the US got involved and before a kind of a-- a Communist-leaning regime got involved
these were all in some ways subjugated populations.
In Korea, it was subjugated by the Japanese
It was the Japanese colony.
In Cuba, it was subjugated by the Batista government.
And this was a dictatorship, a corrupt dictatorship and it was
heavily influenced by the United States. You could almost view it
as United States influence--a United States colony. They had so much
influence with Batista.
And in the case of Vietnam, it was a
French colony. So you can imagine in all
of these situations, the existing rulers were not that popular.
People were looking for rulers who could
kind of liberate them from the messes they were inside of that.
On top of that, and this comes to the whole
discussion of Capitalism versus Communism
you can imagine that when you are colonized
or when you are in a corrupt regime, you do have people
accruing wealth. So there are people accruing wealth. Some
of whom who get it without
without being kind of that legitimate.
And so these circles are kind of the size of different people's wealth
So you can imagine, in Korea under Japanese rule, maybe there were a few people
who were successful by being legitimate entrepreneurs.
But there were probably a whole bunch of people
who were successful by just...kind of...sucking up to
the colonial powers. In the case of a corrupt regime,
doing things that were corrupt with the regime, using
the regime to get undue power in a certain market,
And it's always a combination.
In any of these countries, there were probably
some entrepreneurs and some other people and some others who got wealth
with good means and then some other people who, under these regimes
who got wealth under questionable means. Maybe because
they sucked up to the corrupt regime
or maybe they even did outright criminal activity
which was probably the case of the Batista regime
probably they did have people who were outright criminals
doing very well for themselves. Same thing in Vietnam,
maybe the Vietnamese, some of the Vietnamese, who really kind of
were aligned with the French probably got extra favors, so their wealth wasn't necessarily
due to innovation or competence.
But really just were they fitted into the political order.
Maybe some other people did have legitimate wealth
So you imagine when any of these types of
situations start to emerge, from subjugation
So, you start having independence movements
In all of these situations. You can imagine it's a very
popular notion to run on, and depending on how true it is
but its a very popular notion to run on, to tell people look
"You've seen all of these people who've gotten
questionable wealth and maybe some of these
people who got questionable wealth got it by
being aligned with our subjugators
By being, to some degree, traitors
to our people. And once again,
maybe not all of the people, but you can see how it's a popular line
for someone coming to power when you're
emerging from independent...or when you're
emerging into independence, to say, "Why don't we redistribute wealth?"
"Why don't we take the wealth from this person from right here who
got it in questionable means, and redistribute it, and
redistribute it to the rest of the society?
Why don't we take it from this person over here, and redistribute it to the rest of society?"
"Why don't we do that with this person here, and redistribute that wealth to the rest of society?"
And, if you're looking for a political ideology that seems to
fit with this idea of trying to correct things that
maybe looked wrong during the
colonial or subjugated rule, Communism
seems to fit that. It's kind of a
redistributing of wealth, or maybe the state
takes over all wealth. Or maybe something in between where it's Socialist
where the state is redistributing wealth fairly aggressively
but you still have kind of underpinings of Capitalism
And so you can imagine that Communism
especially to a population that---where you have many many many poor people
wealth concentrated in a few people, many of whom are
aligned with the older regimes, Communism at least seems
like a popular notion. And you have people
who ride this Nationalistic, Communistic feeling
and in the case of Cuba, you have people like
Fidel Castro, people like Fidel Castro.
In Vietnam, you have people like Ho Chi Minh
And then Korea's a little bit different because
you did have a Communist, Nationalist independence movement, but
Kim Il Sung wasn't necessarily the leader of that movement
the Soviets didn't actually want any of those people in charge
any of the kind of the Natonalist Communist the leaders of those
movement, they kind of marginalized them and installed Kim Il Sung
probably because he was more aligned with them, but he was Communist
Now the reality is, these guys
come in under these very egalitarian, you know, equality for all
let's get retribution for the wrongs that were done to us before
But probably all of them start to not just redistribute wealth from people who
might have gotten it in bad ways, but they're also
just redistributing wealth generally
Maybe because it's just a popular thing to do
Or maybe because these people didn't give them proper support
So they're getting retribution on their political enemies, and
as opposed to just kind of doing it for social good
So you know they might do it from people who have
legitimate wealth and so those people aren't
too happy about it. And
they ride kind of this Communistic, egalitarian movement
to install themselves and, instead of being a purely Marxist state
they kind of want to be more Marxist-Leninist
where you have this Communist party that has
this continuous revolution, which
is a justification for them to never hold real elections, and always stay in power
So, by no means is this kind of a rationale why these people
are legitimate. But what happened in every one of these cases
is that the United States was in the middle of the Cold War
They feared the spread of Communism.
Communism tended to correlate with non-free state.
It doesn't have to be that way. But every time Communism was implemented, it also
was these kind of authoritarian rule, no democracy. And you can also
imagine there were many capitalists in the United States who
for their own selfish reasons, were afraid of [Communism] spreading to the United States
because maybe their wealth would be redistributed.
But regardless of what the justification, whether it was a more noble
wanting people to have freedom of expression
freedom to hold property, or whether they were selfish
"Hey we don't want our own wealth to be somehow taken away."
Or it just might have been a balance of power between the US
and the Soviet Union, that every time a country fell to Communism
that somehow, the US was losing some power in the world.
Regardless of the US's rationale, they always say,
"OK, These guys are Communist, we're gonna take the other side of the equation
So the US ends up supporting
Sig Muh Ree in South Korea
whom we know was not the best character in the world.
They end up supporting Diem in South Vietnam
whom we also know was not the necessary the most savory person in the world.
In the case of Cuba, the US at least
they did support Batista while he was in power
but we saw in that video
Kennedy came on later saying, you know, Batista was pretty bad
dude, and it was probably a big mistake for the US to
support him. But the US goes on
the other side and they support the exiles against Fidel Castro
And here the Cuban exiles, they're not in the category of Sig Muh Ree or Diem
they probably favor democracy and overall
good people but what they probably
did feed Kennedy is a story that Fidel Castro
wasn't as popular as he actually was
And he probably was more popular
especially after the Revolution
because he had this egalitarian, people were getting over the Batistas
kind of anybody but Batista they would be happy about
Fidel Castro was this charismatic leader who kind of
working for the poor, at least it looked like he was working for the poor
So at least in the get-go
especially the Kennedy administration might have been fed
an overly optimistic view that kind of got them
involved in the Bay of Pigs invasion and all of that
But this is just the general pattern that happened every time
And every time, it ended up in either a US defeat
or a stalemate, and you know
Take whatever lessons there are from this
but it is kind of an interesting pattern that happened multiple times
pretty much every engagement that we had during the Cold War.