A digital signature is basically the mathematical mechanism
for essentially combining a public
sequence of numbers with a given digital message.
You can really, think of a digital signature in many ways, as the electronic
analog of a physical signature
So in physical signature, you typically affix let's say a sequence of characters, representing your name / identity
to a document.
And this process effectively binds your identity to that document
And more so, by formulating
the characters in your name, &amp; maybe some
particularly unique / peculiar way that's unique to you
the hope is that nobody will be able to forge your name on that document
Now, in a digital signature scheme, it turns out you can achieve these kinds of properties mathematically
Now, some of the more well known digital signature schemes include things like the
the RSA digital signature scheme which stands for "Rivest, Shamir, Adleman" scheme
there's also a scheme known as DSS which is the Digital Signature Standard, actually
and actually, if you were to use a scheme like
RSA / DSS, in my mind, it's actually a lot harder to forge
these digital signatures than it is to forge a hand-written signature
So in this particular video, I'll try to describe the overall
higher level mechanics, if you will, of a digital signature scheme
but I won't actually go into / describe the
the underlying mathematical details of let's say, a specific scheme like RSA / DSS
at least, not in this video
So the way a digital signature scheme works, let's say you have a user, &amp; we're gonna call her Alice
&amp; let's say Alice wants to
digitally sign a document
in the scheme, Alice is going to: first, generate
2 keys, and
these 2 keys are known as the
as the signing key
which is a private key. I'm gonna use red to denote it
we'll abbreviate the signing key as SK
and then, Alice is also going to generate a separate key, known as a "verification key"
now, the actual process of coming up with this signing key &amp; verification key can happen concurrently
Alice will generate these 2 keys at the same time, &amp; they're gonna have a mathematical relationship
But the interesting thing is that you want it to be the case that the
verification key is public &amp; the signing key will be private
but more so
in a digital signature scheme, it should be hard to come up with the verification key
or rather, it should be hard to come up with the signing key, rather
if you only see the verification key
Now, let's consider what a digital signature on a message will entail.
So basically, if you have a message and
let's call this message M
&amp; you wish to digitally sign that message
what you're gonna basically do is apply a
mathematical transformation. Alice is gonna apply a mathematical transformation
to the message M
and her signing key as K
And the result of that transformation
the output of that transformation will be a special
sequence of numbers that we call the signature
The signature on the message M
Now, the interesting here is that the signature basically is
one that is derived from a combination of
the message M together with the signing key,
the private signing key of Alice, and it's going to effectively
produce a short / relatively short sequence of numbers as an output
and
in particular, digital signature schemes should be / typically are designed so that
only the person who possesses
this signing key, that private signing key
is capable of generating
this type of output, this type of signature
SM on the message M
Now, the verification is kind of analogous to the signing process
but it involves the public verification key. So in the verification process,
you actually have 3 different inputs. So the first input will be the message that you want to
to verify the signature of
you also need an additional message, you need to get, as input, the
the signature on that message. What does the SM look like
and then finally,
the input, the final input to the
verification scheme will be the public key, the public verification key
that belongs to Alice
and these 3 inputs are put in, &amp; there's a mathematical transformation applied to these inputs
&amp; basically what that mathematical transformation is trying to
to ascertain / check
is that, the
the signature that you see corresponds with the message M
is one that would've been produced by Alice's private signing key
&amp; this private signing key, in turn, corresponds to Alice's public verification key
Now, what I think is really remarkable, is that
you can actually
carry out this process
with just the verification key. You don't actually need
the signing key to validate digital signature. You don't even
need it inadvertently / indirectly
You can do everything, you can verify everything with knowledge of only
the public verification. And the public verification procedure basically outputs kind of a
a yes or no. It tells should I
should I accept the signature or should I reject it?
It's a basic validation procedure
And so as you can see, the process of signing effectively will bind
this public verification key, it binds the public verification key
to Alice. Recall that Alice is the one who published
this verification key &amp; told the whole world: "Hey, this is my verification key &amp; the system
and only I will be able to sign messages that will be considered valid
with respect to that verification key"
And because the message is now being essentially bound to this public key,
and if you think of the public key as
an identifier of sorts, maybe an identifier for Alice
then you can think of digital signing
as a process that basically binds an identity
to an underlying message. And that really gives us
in the mathematical sense, it gives us the analog
of a traditional hand-written signature
Now, I wanna make 2 remarks, &amp; I think they're particularly relevant. First of all, you'll notice that the transformation that produces
the actual digital signature itself
this transformation right here that produces Sm
this transformation basically takes the message
it takes the message as one of its inputs
and what that means is that the
signature depends on the message. If you change the message, you'll get a different signature
Now, in this sense, a digital signature is actually different from a traditional hand-written signature
Your hand-written signature probably doesn't change, more or less
stays the same, regardless of what you're signing
But your digital signature is very sensitive to what you're signing. It will vary depending on what you're signing
If you sign a different message, you'll get a different signature as an output
The second remark I wanna make is that:
digital signatures are often associated with
cryptographic hash function. I told you in my video on cryptographic hash function and in fact,
I mentioned in that video and I'll reiterate here that the first
cryptographic hash functions were actually designed
specifically with digital signature in mind as their killer application, if you will
So in particular, what typically happens before you actually sign an arbitrary message, let's say you have a huge message
that you wanna sign. Before you sign this message,
you're going to basically apply
a cryptographich function to that message, and you're gonna get
an output from that function (the cryptographic hash function). You'll get a shorter output, the digest of that cryptographic hash function
and what you'll do in a signing algorithm, is that rather than signing the original message
you will first hash it &amp; then sign the
the hash of the message. You'll sign the resulting digest
instead of the original message
and this 2 step paradigm of
doing hashing &amp; then signing
?? simplifies the process of digital signing since you
effectively are no longer dealing with an arbitrary length input, but
instead you're working with a fixed length quantity
and this hash and then sign pardigm is actually safe
as long as it's hard to find
2 messages that map to the same output
under the application of the hash function. In other words, you can't come up with
with 2 messages that are different
but whose output, when the hash function is applied to them, are identical. In other words,
the hash function, as long as it is collision resistant,
will result in a secure signature scheme with the hash and then sign paradigm
Now, you can probably think about ???. But if you could find, lets say 2 input messages
that are distinct, but map to the same output
under an application of the hash function
that would in fact lead to some bizzare problems, because
a signature on the first message
would then be identical to the signature on the second message.
Since in both cases, you're not signing the actual message, you're signing the hash of the messages.
So the hashes are identical, you'll end up with an identical signature on 2 different messages
and that could create problems like: making it easy for maybe a particular message to be forged
under this digital signature approach. And that's obviously something that you don't want
You don't want someone to be able to come up with a signature on a different message
as opposed to maybe the one that you initially intended to sign
Now, it is possible
and I just gonna make this clear, it's possible to describe
digital signatures with a lot more mathematical formalism
but my hope with this video, really, was to give you
a flavor if you will, without drilling into all of the underlying nuances &amp; mathematics