Identify all sets of parallel and perpendicular lines in the image below.
So let's start with the parallel lines and, just as a reminder, two lines are parallel
if they're in the same plane, and all of these lines are clearly in the same plane.
They are in the plane of the screen your viewing right now.
But they are two lines that never intersect.
And one way to verify: because it sometimes looks like two lines will intersect,
but you can't just always assume just based on how it looks.
You really have to some information given to you in the diagram or the problem
that tells you that they are definitely parallel, that they're definitely never going to intersect.
And one of those pieces of information that they give right over here is that they show Line ST and Line
UV: they both intersect line CD at the exact same angle, at this angle right here.
And, in particular, it is at a right angle.
And if you have two lines that intersect a third line at the same angle, at the same angle.
so that these are actually corresponding angles. And they are the same.
If you have two of these corresponding angles and they are the same then these two lines are parallel.
So Line ST is parallel to Line UV, and you can write it like this:
So Line ST- you put the arrows on each end of that top bar to say that this a line and not just a line
segment. Line ST is parallel (two lines) to Line UV.
And I think that is the only set of parallel lines in this diagram. Yup.
Now let's think about perpendicular lines.
Perpendicular lines are lines that intersect at a 90 degree angle.
So for example Line ST is perpendicular to Line CD.
And we know that they intersect at a right angle or a 90 degree angle
because they gave us this little box here which literally means that the measure
of this angle is 90 degrees. By the exact same argument, Line UV
is perpendicular to CD.
UV (make sure I specify these as lines) is perpendicular to CD.
And so UV, ST they're perpendicular to CD. And then after that,
the only other information where they definitely tell us that two lines are intersecting at right angles
are Line AB and WX. So Line AB is definitely perpendicular to Line WX.
Line WX. And, I think we are done.
And one thing to think about AB and CD, well they don't even intersect,
so we can't make a comment about them being perpendicular, but they are definitely not parallel
You can even imagine that it looks like they are about to intersect.
And they give us no information that they intersect at the same lines, at the same angle.
So, if somehow they told us that this was a right angle, even though it doesn't look anything like a
right angle, then we would have to suspend our judgement based on how it actually looks
and say, huh I guess maybe those things are perpendicular.
And maybe these two things are parallel. They didn't actually tell us
that, and that would actually be bizarre because
these lines are so not parallel. And this would actually end up being parallel to other things if that
was done. But, it's a good thing that wasn't because that would look very strange.
Based on the information they gave us, these are the parallel and perpendicular lines.