we are asked 'what number set does the number 8 belong to?'
so this is actually a good review of the different
sets of numbers we often talk about
so the first set under consideration is
the natural numbers
natural numbers
and these are essencially the counting numbers
and you're not and not counting 0,
1, 2, 3, so on and so forth
so clearly 8 is a natural number,
you can count up to 8 here, you can count 8 objects
so 8 is a member of the natural numbers
so it is a natural number, we should say
the next one we should consider,
let's consider the whole numbers
whole numbers, right over here
and i should say natural numbers
so let's consider the whole numbers
the whole numbers are essencially the same thing as the
natural numbers, but we're now going to include the 0
so it's 0, 1, 2, 3, so on and so forth
so clearky 8 is one of these as well
you could eventually increment your way to 8 like here
just counting all of the whole numbers
another way to view this is the non-negative numbers
so 8 clearly belongs to this as well
so let's expand our set a little bit, let's think about integers
let's think about the set of integers
now these are all the numbers starting with
well, you could keep counting down, but all the way up to
-3, -2, -1, 0, 1, 2, 3 and you could just keep going there
now clearly 8 is one of these as well, you can just keep
counting to 8, in fact, you can
let me just put a check box there and
in general, you have the integers that contain
both the positive and the negative numbers
and the 0