Diya is looking to buy a plot of land to build her home on
She finally narrows her search to two plots that both have good locations.
The plot at 314159 Apple Lane has a width of 30 meters and a lenght of 40 meters.
The plot at 11235 Fibonacci Drive has a width of 50 meters and lenght of 20 meters.
They are each being sold for 36,000 dollars.
Which one is a better deal?
So they are the same price and they are in comparable neighbourhoods
So really the better deal is the one that actually gets me more area
So i encourage you to pause the video and think about
Which one of these am i getting more land for the same amount of money
Well to think about how much land im getting
im really thinking how much space is that plot taking up
or im really thinking up what is the area of each of these plots
And we have already figured out that you can calculate the area of a rectangle by multilplying its lenght times its width
So the area of Apple Lane is 40 meters times 30 meters which is equal to
40 times 3 is 120 .... 40 times 30 is 1200
and its meters times meters so you could view this as square meters
1200 square meters
Now lets think about what the area of the plotted Fibonacci drive is
So its lenght is 20, its width is 50
So here the area is 20 meters times 50 meters which is equal to
20 times 5 is 100... 20 times 50 is 1000 square meters
So its pretty clear when you calculate the area that Apple Lane
you are getting more square meters than you would get at Fibonacci Drive
And literary when we say 1200 square meters that means
if you would have put a 1 meter by 1 meter square here
so really small like that
that you could fit 1200 of these on this plot of land
while you could only fit a 1000 of them on this plot of land
these 1 meter by 1 meter squares
So we have a larger area, same neighbourhood or comparable neighbourhood for the same price
I would go with Apple Lane being the better deal