[Intro Music]
We're in the National Gallery of London, and we're looking at one of great Caravaggios.
This is the Supper at Emmaus. It dates to about 1605, and it's a large painting.
It is large.
And it's horizontal, and figures are actually life-size,
so that there's a real sense of art proximity are at presence at this table.
There's even a space for us.
And the story is that the Christ has been crucified,
and his disciples are walking along the road, a man joins them,
and when they all sit down for a dinner....
This third man breaks the bread, and at that moment is revealed to be the resurrected Christ
And we're seeing the reactions of those two disciples.
The moment when they recognize him. We have a split second in time, and this high drama.
The disciple on the left, in the tattered green shirt or jacket
looks into the table, sitted at the table as we are
so his reaction is our reaction as we look to Christ.
I love this gesture that he makes of this figure in the left corner
He's so taken back, he's frightened, he's moving his chair,
like "Holy Cow!" interested and frightened at the same time.
That's right drawn back and drawn in, simultaneously.
And in fact the entire painting draws forward and back, simultaneously.
Our eyes go into Christ, and in fact both of the Apostles frame our vision as we move towards that centre.
In other words, the whole painting is kind of a triangle of vision that moves into Christ's face.
At the same moment, all of the their hands, or I should say,
The left hand of the Apostle on the right, and Christ's right hand both move out towards us,
literally embracing us and inviting us visually into the image.
Well, I mean he couldn't be trying to do that more
It's not just in the hands, it's everywhere.
I mean, look at that basket of fruit in the front, that hangs off the table
Caravaggio was trying to make this painting burst into our space in every possible way he can
to make it immediate, and real, and emotional for us.
I want to join that table. And of course there's all of the complexity of the emotions of the figures,
which of course, is the majority of the painting and the painting's purpose.
But then there's a tremendous amount of attention that has been paid to the still life.
Look at the chicken, it looks good.
It does. The bread the fruit...
I would mind having the fruit, it's all beautiful.
It's that physicality that we expect of Caravaggio.
Well, look at, for instance, at the specificity of the joinery in the furniture.
If you look at the chair on the left, the very technique, its construction is revealed to us
everything in this painting is revealed and opened up to us.
And yet, the painting is also incredibly focused.
Where are we? We're in a kind of a shallow space. It's quite dark.
And he's really attending to our focus, making sure that our eyes go only where he wants it.
Well, he puts that light there. Sharp light, almost theatrical light on the left side of Christ's face.
And what I'm also struck by, is this thing we always see with Caravaggio, the ordinariness of the figures.
The Apostle on the right looks like he has a little bit of a cold.
His nose is a little red.
The Apostle on the left has a little tear on his clothing. They're poor.
That's what the Apostles were.
It's a rough and tumble world. And they're not in a church; they're in an inn.
So we have an inn keeper. And quite a plain furniture, quite a plain place setting.
This is not the pomp and ceremony that we might see Christ when he's represented in a church-like setting.
As is also so typical of Baroquen and so perfectly represented here,
that moment when the divine entres the everyday world.
making the miraculous, the spiritual, immediate in our modern world.
And so immidiately, physically, realistically in our space present.
That was such a goal of the counter reformation, of the moment in which this painting was made.
Confirming and reaffirming and strenghtening our faith.
[Outro Music]