we are asked to simplify nine p to the two thirds all of that over the square root of the four p cube
so lets just do this step by step the first thing we can do is well if its nine p of the two third thats
the same thing as nine to the two third times p to the two third that's what the stop part that we can
simplify too now the bottom part we can rewrite the bottom part right here the square root of four p
to the third this is the exact same thing as four p to the third to the one half part power this is the
exact same thing as four p to the third to the one half power this is the same thing square root of four
p to the third is same thing as four p to the third to the one half power so given that we can do the
same thing we did on the numerator we can say well this is the same thing as four to the one half
four to the the one half times p to the third to the one half power now lets see that we can simplify
this even more so this is going to be equal to lets do the denominator first here so whats four to the
one half power what's the principle rule of four well two squared is four so its two its positive root
is two and then p to the third and that to the one half that's the same thing p to the three times one
half or p to the three half p to the three over two nine to the two thirds so the cube root of nine is
anything easy well actually yo can think by this way yo could say its nine squared so we can do nine
to the two thirds le me do this this way this is the best to think about it this nine to the two thirds
one could write it some kind of making it unsimplifying it but it will help calculate it what it actually
means nine to the two third is the same thing as nine squared to the one third power right because two
times one third is two thirds and you have that off course times p to the two third and this is going
to be eqal to nine squared is eighty one so its eighty one to the one third power times p to the two
thirds now instead of writing this two and this p to the three half down here let me just write it as
negative exponents so you are going to just write it like this the two in the denominater is the same
thing as two to the negative one or one half so this right here somewhere in the numerator is the same
thing as one half that and that is the the same thing and p to the three half in the denominator is the
same thing as p as p to the negative p to the negative three half so this whole expressions so far simplified
to this right over here let me copy and past to the next line now so let me copy it and paste bring it
down right over there let's see if can simplify this even more so let's think about eighty one if we
can write it as well essentially we take something to the cube we take the cube root or something we
are taking some we are taking some thing one third power taking the cube root of it so we have to find
some numbers or may be we can factor it into things that do have cube root and other things they don't
so eighty one is divisible by three its three times twenty seven which is three times nine which is three
times three so eighty one is three to the fourth power or its three multiplied by itself three times
so we could rewrite this eighty one to the one third we could rewrite as three times three times three
to the well alright like this times three to the one third that's the same thing as eighty one and let's
think about this ps and i am doing more steps that if want to on piece of paper so i really want you
to understand kind of what's going on here so p to the two thirds times p to the negative three half
so that's going to be times p to the two thirds two thirds minus three half power so we did the ps then
we just had the times one half times one half now this right over here this is the same thing this is
the same thing as we could just use this as three times three times three so its the same thing as three
times three times three to the one third times three to the one third right we done this multiple time
times the two third minus three half so lets just work that out actually three half is the larger so
lets just say its negative of the three half minus two thirds which is equal to the negative if we use
six as a common denominator if we use six as a common denominator three half well six is the denominator
as nine six minus four over six that's what two third is equal to so nine minus four is five six let
me have this negative value so equals negative five six so times p to the negative five six power times
one half times that last one half here now three time three times three are twenty seven to the one third
the cube root of twenty seven is three so this right here simplifies to three and then three to the one
third that's cube root of three so we can say three and then this right here is the cube root of three
the cube root of three so we get three times the cube of three time p to the negative five six to some
time you wanna right p out here infront of the radical that's actually to be separate so iwill right
the p to the negative five six p to the negative five six
then i will right the radical so times the cube root of three and all that times one half so we can all
of that time one half or you can just divide it by two and we have simplified it about as far as you
can do as three half you can say three half is one point five p to the negative five six time the cube
root of three if you wanted to you can calculate it cube root of three multiply that times one half you