The following table contains the first five terms of the given pattern "A".
Generate pattern "B" according to this rule:
For every term of pattern "A"... so they give us the terms of pattern "A" here...
Multiply the term by 3, and add 1 to get the corresponding term of pattern "B".
Then Graph the pairs of corresponding terms.
So for every term in pattern "A", we want to multiply by 3 and add 1.
So if we multiply 0 by 3, we get 0, and you add 1, you get 1.
You multiply 1 by 3, you get 3... and you add 1, and you get 4.
2 times 3 is 6, plus 1 is 7.
3 times 3 is 9, plus 1 is 10.
Remember, we're just multiplying by 3 and adding 1.
4 times 3 is 12, plus 1 is 13.
So those are the corresponding terms for pattern "B".
Then they ask us to graph them... so let's try to graph these points.
So when Pattern "A" is 0, pattern "B" is 1.
So this is pattern "A" equaling 0... that's our horizontal axis: the value for pattern "A".
Pattern "B" is the value of our vertical axis. Pattern "B" is 1.
When pattern "A" is 1, pattern "B" is 4. So... (1, 4).
So when pattern "A" is 1, pattern "B" is 4. Pattern "B" is on the vertical axis.
When pattern "A" is 2, pattern "B" is 7. (2, 7).
When pattern "A" is 3, pattern "B" is 10. So: (3, 10).
So 3 in the horizontal direction, that's our Pattern "A" value, and our pattern "B" value is 10.
And then finally, when pattern "A" is 4, pattern "B" is 13.
Also let's look at these patterns. We see that pattern "A" is increasing by 1 each time.
While pattern "B" is increasing by... Well... pattern "A" starts at 0, and increases by 1.
While pattern "B" starts at 1, and increases by 3. Which makes complete sense.
It makes sense that it starts at 1... because all of these you multiply by 3 and add 1.
So you started with 1, and the fact that you're multiplying by 3... that's what's leading to the distance between these points being 3.
So let's check our answer and make sure we got this right... and we did.