PROBLEM: "Mitchell ran 8 miles today.
Sabrina ran 7 miles.
Which of the following statements is true?"
And I can choose more than one answer here.
So let's think about this.
The ratio of Mitchell's distance
to Sabrina's distance is 2:1 (SPOKEN AS "2 to 1.")
Well, that's not right – because the ratio is 8:7.
And 8:7 is not the same as 2:1.
(i.e., 8:7 cannot be reduced to 2:1).
"The ratio of Mitchell's distance
to Sabrina's distance is 16:14."
Well, that look's right.
If I double Mitchell's distance,
and double Sabrina's distance,
I would get [CALCULATING] 8 × 2 is 16 (for Mitchell),
and 7 × 2 is 14 (for Sabrina).
So that seems right.
"The ratio of Mitchell's distance
to Sabrina's distance is 7:8."
Well it looks like they've swapped it around.
The ratio of Mitchell's distance to Sabrina's is 8:7.
So that's not right.
The ratio of Mitchell's distance
to Sabrina's distance is 8:15.
Well, that's also not right. It's 8:7.
So I'll just go with that one right over there.
Let's do one more of these.
PROBLEM: "Jessica makes a cake using
4 cups of flour and 6 cups of milk."
Fair enough.
"Which of the following are correct statements?"
And I can pick more than one.
"The ratio of flour to milk is 2:3." Let's see.
So 4 cups of flour for every 6 cups of milk.
So that's 4:6.
If I were to divide both the numerator
and the denominator by 2,
that's the same thing as 2:3.
So, that's right.
The ratio of milk to flour is 8:6.
Is that right?
So, I have 6 cups of milk for every 4 cups of flour.
So, it's a ration of 6:4.
6:4 is not the same thing as 8:6.
So I will not choose that one right over there.
"The ratio of flour to milk is 10:15."
So, let's think.
We already know that the ratio of flour to milk is 2:3.
If we were to multiply 2 times 5, you'll get 10 –
and 3 times 5 you get 15. So this is right.
And then, "The ratio of flour to milk is 1:2."
Well, now that's not right.
2:3 is not the same thing as 1:2.
And I think we are done.