In this video we're gonna look an introduction to molecular orbital theory.
Now, MO theory involves some very complicated quantum math
and I'm going to completely ignore the math and we're just going to try to think about it
as simply as possible to see it in pictures.
So, when we did mechanisms,
we thought about electrons as being particles
but we can also think about them as being waves,
and we know that electrons are found in highest probability in what we call atomic orbitals.
When atoms combine to form molecules, those atomic orbitals actually recombine
to form what we call molecular orbitals. Combining atomic orbitals together is just like combining waves together, and
so we're going to start off with a very simple way of thinking about waves.
We could even think about waves like waves in the ocean.
So thinking of these horizontal lines as being the average level of my ocean
i can go ahead and draw a wave there.
And so i have part of the wave above the average level of the ocean
i'm going to call that a fase and i'm going to make that a red face like that
and then part of the wave is below the average level of the ocean
so i'm going to make that the blue fase.
So there's one wave. If i were to combine that wave
with another wave that looks exactly the same
so let's pretend that these two waves are identical
this part would be red, and this would be blue
if i were to combine these two waves there's a couple of ways to do it:
you can think of superimposing these two waves on top of each other
and one way to think about that would be to think about vectors
so if i thought about a vector in here, for the top wave,
-if you've taken a physics class you'll understand everything there is to know about vectors-
so here's one vector, and then this vector down here would be going in the same direction,
with the same length. If i were to superimpose these two waves on top of each other,
these two vectors would add to each other, so we would get another bigger wave here on the right.
So, these two vectors are going to add together like that.
The same thing happens with the fases in blue
This vector would be pointing down this time
this would also be pointing down, but if you add up these two waves together
if you superimpose them on top of each other
these two vectors would add like that, and
you would get an even bigger part over here like that.
So that would be the product of adding those two waves together
they add constructively
so over here these would be our two red fases added together
and this would be where our blue fases are added together.
So we get constructive overlaps.
I'll write that: "CONSTRUCTIVE OVERLAP".
And so, this is when we added our waves in fase, combined these two waves in fase
which means that their colours matched up
we combined the two red colours together, and we combined the two blue fases together
and that gave us constructive overlap.
Let's do another example of adding waves, another very simple one:
So we're going to start again with a wave that has parts above the average level of the ocean
and then this part is going to be below
This time, though, we're going to add something that is the opposite
So we're going to start below the average level and we'll finish above. Like that.
Let me go ahead and make this one blue now
and then this one red over here
and so we're going to add these two waves.
Once again, vectors help me think about it
and so if i think about this first wave
this vector would be going up
and for the second wave the vector would go in the opposite direction
So when i add these 2 vectors together
when i superimpose these 2 waves
the vectors would cancel each other
and you would get destructive overlap.
So you would get nothing over here on the right
this would be DESTRUCTIVE OVERLAP
those two vectors cancelled each other out
and the exact same thing happens when you try to combine this part of the wave
with this part of the wave, these 2 vectors would cancel each other out in space
we get destructive overlap
We tried to combine these two waves OUT OF FASE
meaning we tried to combine the red with the blue both times, and so
since we're combining out of fase, the vectors cancel and give us destructive overlap.
So, this is a very simple way of thinking about waves
the nice thing about it is that when we combine atomic orbitals
we can think about the same thing.
We can combine atomic orbitals either "in fase" or "out of fase".
Let's go ahead and do that. Let's combine some atomic orbitals and
we're going to do so for the simplest atom, which is hydrogen.
So, if i take hydrogen with its one valence electron
i know that this electron occupies an atomic orbital
that shapes like a sphere.
So if i were to draw that spherically-shaped atomic orbital
I know that hydrogen has a nucleus
and i know the most common isotope has only one proton in the nucleus (N.T.: all hydrogen isotopes have only one proton)
so that's going to represent the nucleus of hydrogen
and then the sphere around it is the atomic orbital of hydrogen, like that.
So i'm going to combine that H atom with another H atom, so once again
i'm going to think about a nucleus for the H atom
and then one valence electron occupies an s-orbital which is shaped like a sphere.
All right, let's go ahead and draw this again down here
so i'm going to have the nucleus, and i'm going to have the s-orbital
and the same thing over here, like that.
Now, when i combine my two atomic orbitals together,
i know that i can combine them "in fase" and "out of fase".
Let's put some colors on here.
If i'm going to combine the first two atomic orbitals in fase, i need to make them the same color
so i'm going to make these guys red
and then down here, i'm going to combine out of fase, so i'm going to use different colors
this is going to be red, and this is going to be blue. Like that.
Ok. So i know when i combine two waves in fase i got constructive overlap
and so when i combine my two atomic orbitals for hydrogen in fase
i'm going to have constructing overlap. So let's draw the molecular orbital that is produced.
Here's one nucleus, and here's another nucleus.
These two atomic orbitals are going to recombine, cease to exist,
they're going to produce a molecular orbital
an orbital associated with the entire hydrogen molecule
so here i have sketched in my molecular orbital on the right
These combined in fase, it was constructive overlap, and this is the molecular orbital that results.
The atomic orbitals have ceased to exist, they have produced a molecular orbital like that.
If i were to draw the dot structure of what's happened
you can think that these electrons have been shared to produce a covalent bond
between these two H atoms, like that.
And so, this is the molecular orbital that is produced as a result of constructive overlap
Again, the atomic atoms cease to exist to produce a molecular orbital.
And this is a bonding molecular orbital.
We know that because the electrons are shared between the two nucleae.
The delocalization, the sharing of these electrons, lowers the energy of the hydrogen molecule.
A bonding molecular orbital is lower in energy, it's constructively overlapped.
If you look down here, we try to combine our 2 atomic s-orbitals out of fase
when we try to do that, we get destructive overlap.
There is no sharing of electrons between our two nucleae
and so we produce what's called a nodal plane between the two nucleae.
There's no electron density between the two nucleae, so if i were to draw my molecular orbitals
like these, is what you see in most textbooks
so this is our red fase, and on the right is the blue fase.
So, when you try to combine atomic orbitals out of fase, you produce a molecular orbital
but there's no electron density between these two nucleae,
so really there's no bond,
and so we call this an anti-bonding molecular orbital.
So, destructive overlap means there's no electron density between the two nucleae
therefore, those two positive charges are exposed to each other
and we know like-charges repel, it's like trying to put two magnets together
on the same pole, they're going to repel
it would take a lot of energy to hold those positive charges together
so i like to think about the fact that an anti-bonding molecular orbital
is much higher in energy than a bonding molecular orbital.
[and repeats the same concept once again]
What we see here is: when you combine two atomic orbitals together
you produce one bonding molecular orbital and one anti-bonding molecular orbital
so, two atomic orbitals combine to form a total of two molecular orbitals.
The bonding molecular orbital is lower in energy.
The anti-bonding molecular orbital is higher in energy.
We could represent that on an energy diagram.
So, here's energy.
This energy level represents our atomic orbitals.
So there's one hydrogen atom with one electron
and there's another hydrogen atom with another electron
and when those two atomic orbitals combine they form two molecular orbitals
The one that's lower in energy, is our bonding molecular orbital.
And the one that's higher in energy, is our anti-bonding molecular orbital.
So when these two electrons from our atomic orbitals combine,
they're going to fill the bonding molecular orbital since is lower in energy
this is analogous to electron configurations,
electrons are going to fill the lowest energy orbital available
and [?] is going to pair up the spins.
So these two electrons in the hydrogen atom prefer to occupy the bonding molecular orbital
because it's lower in energy.
So, the anti-bonding molecular orbital does not have any electrons for this example
Of course, it is possible to give an electron in a bonding molecular orbital
enough energy where it could jump above to the anti-bonding molecular orbital
and that would break the bond between the two hydrogen atoms here.
So, hopefully, this video is a nice introduction to the concept of molecular orbital theory
we're going to use this concept a few more times to develop more complicated topics of organic chemistry.