Let's say that we have the indefinite integral,
and the function is 3x^2 plus 2x times e to the x^3 plus x^2 dx.
So how would we go about solving this? So first when you look at it,
it seems like a really complicated integral; we have this polynomial right over here
being multiplied by this exponential expression and over here, the exponent,
we essentially have another polynomial. It seems kind of crazy.
And the key intuition here, the key inside is that you might want to use a technique here called
u-substitution. And I'll tell you in a second how I would recognize that we have to use u-substitution,
and over time, you might even be able to do this type of thing in your head.
U-substitution is essentially unwinding the chain rule. In the chain rule --
I'll go in more depth in another video where I really talk about that intuition.
But the way I'd think about it is, well I have this crazy exponent right over here,
I have x^3 plus x^2. And this thing right over here happens to be the derivative of
x^3 plus x^2. The derivative of x^3 is 3x^2; derivative of x^2 is 2x,
which is a huge clue to me that I could use u-substitution.
So what I do here is, this thing where this little expression here where I also see its derivative
being multiplied, I can set that equal to u. So I can say, "u is equal to x^3 plus x^2."
Now what is going to be the derivative of u with respect to x?
du/dx (well, we've done this multiple times) is going to be 3x^2 plus 2x,
and now we can write this in differential form. And du/dx isn't really a fraction
of differential of u divided by differential of x, it really is a form of notation.
But it is often useful to kind of pretend it's a fraction.
And you could kind of view this, if you want to just get a du,
if you just want this in differential form over here, how much does u change for given change in x,
you can multiply both sides times dx. And so if we were to pretend it's a fraction,
and it will give you the correct differential form,
you're going to be left with du is equal to 3x^2 plus 2x dx.
Now why is this over here, why did I go through the trouble of doing that?
Well we see we have a 3x^2 plus 2x, and it's being multiplied by a dx right over here.
I could rewrite this original integral as the integral of -- let me do that in that color --
of 3x^2 plus 2x times dx times e -- let me do that in that other color --
times e to the x^3 plus x^2. Now, what's interesting about this,
well this stuff that I have in magenta here is exactly equal to du.
And then this stuff I have up here, x^3 plus x^2, that is what I said what u equaled to.
That is going to be equal to u. So I could rewrite my entire integral --
and now you might recognize why this might simplify things a good bit --
it's going to be equal to, and what I'm going to do is I'm going to change the order.
I'm going to put the du, this entire du, I'm going to stick it on the other side here
so it looks like more of the standard form that we're used to seeing in our indefinite integrals in,
so it's going to be, we're going to have our du times e to the u.
And so what would the anti-derivative of this be in terms of u?
Well, the derivative of e^u is e^u; the anti-derivative of e^u is e^u.
So it's going to be equal to e^u, now there's a possibility that there's some type of constant
factor here, so let me write that. So plus C. And now, to get it in terms of x,
we just have to un-substitute the u. We know what u is equal to.
So we could say that this is going to be equal to e -- instead of writing u,
we could say u is x^3 plus x^2. And then we have our plus C. And we are done!
We've found the anti-derivative. And I encourage you to take the derivative of this,
and I think you will find yourself using the chain rule and getting right back to what we had over here.