What I want to do in this video is cover something called the Triple Product Expansion
or Lagrange's Formula, sometimes.
And it's really just a simplification of the cross product of three vectors.
So if I take the cross product of A and then B cross C.
Now what we are going to do is express this,
we can express this really as sum and difference of dot products.
Well not just dot products but dot products scaling different vectors.
You're going to see what I mean.
But it simplifies this expression a bit because cross products are hard to take.
They are computationally intensive and, at least in my mind, they're confusing.
Now, this is not something you have to know if you are going to be dealing with vectors.
But it's useful to know.
My motivation for doing this video is I saw some problems for the Indian Institute of Technology Entrance Exam
that seems to expect that you know Lagrange's Formula or the Triple Product Expansion.
So let's see how we can simplify this.
So to do that, let's start taking the cross product -
the cross product of B and C.
And in all of these situations, I'm just going to assume that we have vector A.
I'm just going to call that A, the x component of vector A times unit vector i,
plus the y component of vector A times unit of vector j,
plus the z component of vector A times unit vector k.
I can do the same things for B and C.
So, if I say that B sub y, I'm talking about what's scaling the j component in the B vector.
So let's first take this cross product over here,
and as you've seen me take a cross products,
you know that I like to do these little determinants.
And what, let me just take it over here.
So, B cross C, B cross C, is going to be equal to the determinant,
and I put an i, j, k up here.
i j k
This is actually the definition of the cross product.
So no proof is necessary.
Let me show you why this is true.
This is just one way to remember the dot product.
If you remember to take the determinant of 3 by 3's.
And we'll put B's x term, B's y coefficient, and B's z component. [term, coefficient and component can be used interchangeably here]
And you'll do the same thing for the C's.
Cx, Cy, Cz.
And then this is going to be equal to -
So first you have its, the i component,
so it's going to be the i component times B, so you ignore this column and this row, so
By [times] Cz, By Cz
Minus Bz [times] Cy, minus so -
I'm just ignoring all of this, and I'm looking at this 2 by 2 over here.
minus Bz Cy, minus Bz Cy.
And then we want to subtract the j component.
Remember we alternate signs when we take our determinant.
Subtract that, and then we take that column and that row. So it's going to be [chuckle]
It's going to be Bx [times] Cz, Bx Cz
It's a little monotonous, but it'll have an intertesting result.
Bx Cz minus Bz [times] Cx, minus Bz, minus Bz Cx.
And then finally plus the k component.
k, we are going to have Bx times Cy, Bx Cy minus By Cx, minus By Cx.
So this is, this, we just did the dot product.
And now we want to take the - sorry we just did the cross product.
I don't want to get you confused. We just took the cross product of B and C.
And now we are going to take the cross product of that with A.
Or the cross product of A with this thing right over here.
So let's do that -
Instead of rewriting the vector, let me just set up another matrix here.
So let me write my i, j, k up here -
And then let me write a's components so we have -
A sub x, A sub y, A sub z
And then let's clean this up a little bit.
Let's ignore the, we're just looking at -
No I want to do that in black.
Let's do this in black so that we can kind of erase that.
This is a uh, this is a minus j times that, so what I'm going to do is
I'm going to get rid of the minus and the j
but I'm going to rewrite this with the signs swapped
So this is going to be -
This is going to be swap the signs
Bz Cx minus Bx, minus Bx Cz
So let me delete everything else.
So I just took the negative and I multiplied it by this.
I'm not making any careless mistakes here. So let me just, so I can make -
make the brush size a little bit bigger here so I can erase a little more efficiently
There you go. And then we also want to get rid of that right over here -
Let me get my brush back down to normal size. All right!
So now let's just take this cross product.
So once again, set it up as, set it up as a determinant.
And what I'm really going to focus on -
because it'll take the video, well it'll take me forever if I were to do, if I were to do the i, j and k components,
I'm just going to focus on i component, just on the x component of this cross product
and then we can see that we will get the same result for the j and k
and we can see what hopefully this simplifies down to.
So if we just focus on the i component here
This is going to be,
this is going to be i,
i times, and we just look at this 2 by 2 matrix right over here
We ignore i's column, i's row.
And we have
Ay times all of this.
So let me just multiply it out, so it's
Ay times Bx Cy minus, minus Ay times By, times By Cx, By Cx.
And then, we're going to want to subtract,
we're going to want to have minus Az times this.
So let's just do that.
So it's minus, or negative Az Bz Cx,
and then we have a negative Az times this, so it's
plus Az Bx Cz.
And now I'm going to do this -
This is a little bit of a trick for this proof right here.
Just so that we get the results that I want.
I'm just going to add and subtract the exact same thing.
I'm going to add an Ax Bx Cx
and then I'm going to subtract a Ax Bx Cx
So clearly I have not changed this expression,
I have just added and subtracted the same thing.
And let's see what we can simplify.
Remember, this is just the x component of our triple product,
just the x component.
But to do this, let me factor out -
I'm going to factor out a B sub x, so let me do this.
We get the B sub x
So if I were to factor it out
And I'm only going to look at,
I'm only going to factor it out of this term that has a B sub x
and I'm going to factor it out of this term
and then I'm going to factor it out of this term.
So if I take out the B sub x,
I'm going to have an Ay Cy,
actually let me write out a little bit differently.
Let me factor it, let me factor it out of this one first.
So that it's A, it's going to be an Ax Cx
A sub x, C sub x
So I used this one up.
And then I'm going to have a, I'll do this one now
plus, if I factor the B sub x out, I get A sub y, C sub y
I've used that one now, and now I have this one
I'm going to factor the B sub x out,
so I'm left with a plus A sub z, C sub z.
So that's all of those, so I've factored that out.
And now from these -
From these right over here, let me factor out a negative C sub x,
a negative C sub x.
And so if I do that, let me go to this term right over here
I'm going to have a Ax Bx
Cross that out
And then over here I'm going to have an Ay By
Remember I'm factoring out a negative C sub x
So I'm going to have a plus A sub y, B sub y
And then finally I'm going have a plus A sub z,
A sub z, B sub z
And what is this!
Well this right here in green,
this is the exact same thing as the dot product of A and C
This is the dot product of the vectors A and C
It's the dot product
of this vector and that vector.
So that's the
The dot product of A and C times the x component of B
times the x component, the x component of B
minus, I'll do this in the same
minus, once again this is the dot product of A and B now
minus A dot B, A dot B
times the x component of C
And we can't forget all of this was
multiplied by the unit vector i.
We're looking at the x component, or the i component
of that whole triple product.
So that's going to be all of this
it's all of this is being, is times the unit vector i.
Now, if we do this exact same thing
I'm not going to do it, because it's, it's computationally intensive
but I think it would, it won't be a huge leap of faith for you
This is for the x component
If I were to do the exact same thing for the y component, for the j component
so it'll be plus
If I do the same thing for the j component
We can really just pattern match.
We have, we have B sub x, C sub x
That's for the x component
And we'll have B sub y, and C sub y for the j component
And then this is not component specific
so it'll be A dot, A dot C over here,
and minus A dot B over here
You can verify any of these for yourself if you don't believe me.
But it's the exact same process we just did.
And then finally for the z component, or the k component
Let me put parentheses over here
Same idea!
B sub z, C sub z
And then you're going to have A dot B over there
and A dot C over here!
Now what is, what does this, what does this become?
How can simplify this?
Well this right over here -
we can expand this out.
We can factor out a A dot C from all of these terms over here.
Remember this is going to be multiplied times i.
Actually let me not skip too many steps.
because I really want you to believe what I'm doing.
So this, if we expand the i here.
Instead of rewriting it, let me just do it like this.
A little bit messier, but let me just, so I can write this i there and that i there.
I'm kind of just distributing that x,
that x unit vector, or i unit vector
and let me do the same thing for j
So I can put the j there and I can put the j right over there
And then I can do the same thing for the k.
Put the k there, and then put the k there.
And now what are these!
Well this part right over there
This part right over here is exactly the same thing as A dot C
A dot C times Bx,
B sub x times i, plus B sub y times j
plus B sub y times j
plus B sub z times k!
And then from that we are going to subtract all of this
A dot B, we are going to subtract A dot B
Times the exact same thing!
And you are going to notice this is the exact same thing as vector B!
That is vector B, and when you do it over here you are just going to get vector C
So I'll just write it over here.
You are just going to get vector C.
So just like that, we have,
we have a simplification for our triple product!
I know it took us a long time to get here, but this is a simplification!
It might not look like one,
but computationally it is! It's easier to do!
If I have, I'll try to color code it, if I have A cross
A cross B cross, let me do it all different colors, C
we just saw that this is going to be equivalent to
and one way to think about it is
You take the first vector times the dot product of the
The first vector in this second cross product
The one that we have the parentheses around, the one we have to do first
You take the first vector there, so vector B
and you multiply that times the dot product of the other two vectors
So A dot C, A dot C
and from that you subtract
You subtract the second vector [in the parentheses]
You subtract the second vector multiplied by the dot product of the other two vectors.
A dot B.
And we're done!
This is our triple product
This is our triple product expansion!
Now once again, this isn't
this isn't something that you really have to know
You could always obviously multiply
You could actually just do this, you know
you don't have to, you could do it by hand,
you don't have to know this.
But if you have really hairy vectors
or if this is from some kind of math competition
And sometimes it simplifies real fast when you reduce it to dot products
This is a useful thing to know.
The Lagrange's Formula, or the triple product expansion.