welcome to level one linear equations
let's start doing some problems
so let's say i had the equation 5 (that's a big fat 5).
5x equals 20
so at first this might look a little unfamiliar to you
but if I rephrase this, you'll realize this is pretty easy problem
all this is is, it's the same thing as saying this is 5 times questionmark
equals 20
and the reason why we notation a little bit
we write the 5 next to the x
because when you write a number right next to a variable you assume that you're multiplying them.
so this is saying 5 times x
so instead of a questionmark
we're writing an x
so five times x is equal to 20
now most of you can do that all in your head
you can say well what number times 5 is equal to 20?
well, it equals 4
but we can do it systematically just in case
that 5 is a more complicated number
so let me make my pen a little thinner. ok.
so rewriting it
if I had 5 x equals 20
we could do 2 things and they're essentially the same thing
we could say we just divide both sides of this equation by 5
in which case the left hand side those two fives will cancel out
we'll get x
and then the right hand side
20 divided by 5
is 4. And we've solved it.
Another way to do it and this is actually the exact same
way we are just phrasing it a little different
if you said 5 x
equals 20
instead of dividing by 5 we could multiply
by one fifth
and if you look at that you could realize that
multiplying by one fifth is the same thing
as dividing by five
if you know the difference between dividing and multiplying fractions.
and then that gets the same thing
one fifth times 5 is 1
so you're left with an x
equals 4
i tend to focus a little bit more on this
because when we start having fractions instead of a five
it's easier to just think about multiplying
by the reciprocle
actually let's do one of those right now
so let's say I had negative 3 over 4
times x
equals
10 over 13
now this is a harder problem
I can't do this one in my head
We're saying negative three fourths
times some number x
is equal to 10 over 13
if someone came to you on the street
and asked you that I think you'd be like me
you'd be pretty .. ah... stumped.
but let's work it out algebraically
well, we'll do the same thing
we multiply both sides by the coefficient
on x
So the coefficient, all that is
all that fancy word means
is the number that's being multiplied by x
so what's the coefficient, the reciprocal
of minus three fourths? well,
it's minus 4 over 3
times... and dot is another way to use times....
and you're probably wondering why in algebra
there are all these other conventions for doing times
as opposed to just a traditional multiplication sign
and the main reason I think it's just a regular multiplication sign just gets confused with the variable x so they thought
of either using a dot
if you're multiplying two constants
or just writing it next to a variable to imply you're multiplying a variable
so if we multiply the left hand side by negative four thirds
we also have to do the same thing
to the right hand side
minus four thirds
the left hand side the minus four thirds and three fourths,
they cancel out
you could work it out on your own to see that they do
they equal one so we're just left with x
x is equal to
10 times minus 4
is minus 40
13 times 3
well that's equal to 39
so you get x is equal to minus 40 over 39
and I like to leave my fractions improper cause it's easier to deal with them
but you could also... if you wanted to write that as a mixed number
minus 1 and one thirthyninth
i tend to keep it like this though
let's check to make sure that's right
the cool thing about algebra is you can always get your answer and put it back into the orgiginal equation
to make sure you're right
so the original equation was
minus three fourths times x
and here we'll substitute the x back into the equation
where we saw x we'll now put our answer
so it's minus 40 over 39
and our original equation said that that equals to 10 over 13
well. and once again when I just write the three fourths times right next to the parenthesis like that
that's another way of writing times
so
minus 3 times minus 40
is minus 100 ... actually we could do something a little simpler
this 4 becomes a 1 and this becomes a 10
and if you remember how when you're multiplying fractions you can simplify it like that
so it actually becomes plus 30 (because we have a minus times a minus is plus) and 3 times 10
over
the 4 is now a 1 so all is left is 39
and 30 over 39
if we divide the top and the bottom
by 3
we get 10 over 13
which is the same thing
which the equation said it would be
so we know that we got the right answer
let's do one more problem
minus 5 sixths
x
is equal to
7 eights
and if you wanna try this problem yourself
now is a good time to pause
And I'm gonna start doing the problem right now
So, same thing
What's the reciprocal of minus 5 sixths?
Well, it's minus 6 over 5
We multiply that
If we do it on the left hand side
we have to do it on the right hand side as well
minus 6 over 5
the left hand side the minus 6 over 5
and minus 5 sixths cancel out
we're just left with x
and the right hand side
we have
well we can divide both 6 and the 8 by 2
so that makes negative 3
and this becomes 4
7 times negative 3 is minus 21
over 20
and assuming I haven't made any careless mistakes
that should be right
actually let's just check that real fast
so minus 5 sixths
times minus 21 over 20
well
that equals
we could make this 5 a 1 and turn this into a 4
make this into a 2
make this into a 7
negative times negative is positive
so 7
2 times 4 is 8!
and that's what we said we would get
so we got it right
I think you're ready at this point
to try some level 1 equations
Have fun!