We here at the Khan Academy
are working on some type of a software project,
and we need to think about,
What's the optimal number of programmers we should hire?
And we think about how much productivity
we're getting per programmer when we are working on this software project
And so what I've done over here, this is a spreadsheet
So I'm not gonna be able to write
I'm only able to type
This is Microsoft Excel right over here
In this column I have the different numbers of programmers
And then let's say based on other studies
or industry studies or past experience
this tells us how many lines of programming code
we can get per month
And obviously lines of code isn't maybe the best way to measure things
because someone can write good lines
or bad lines of code
But let's just say this is one way of measuring
productivity for software engineers
So the first thing I wanna think about is
What are my fixed costs?
What am I going to spend
no matter how many software engineers I hire for this project
And for the sake of this video, my fixed costs will be
the office space, and the electricity
And let's assume I just have a
a huge, an office that can accommodate any number of the programmers
So that's a fixed cost, that's not going to change
Depending on the number of programmers that I have
And then the other fixed cost, let's just say I have a project manager for this project
That I'm going to pay her salary
to essentially help spec out what this software should actually do
So her salary, let's just say $10,000 a month
and then another $5,000 a month in office space for everybody
So it's gonna come out to $15,000 a month
And that's not gonna change regardless of however many programmers I have
So I'm gonna go in Excel
I'm gonna go to this little bottom right right over here
I'm gonna drag that down
And so it's gonna be fifteen thousand dollars in fixed costs
No matter how many programmers I end up hiring
Now the variable costs, let's assume
That the full, sometimes people
Let's just say that the full compensation for a programmer is $10,000 a month
So if you include the cost of their salary,
if you include the cost of their health insurance,
you include, you know, the extra goodies that they will eat from the company kitchen,
whatever it might be,
so it's going to be $10,000 a month
So my variable, my total variable costs
are going to be $10,000 times the number of programmers
So here I'm gonna write equals
and I'm gonna write, it's gonna be $10,000 per programmer
times, that little snowflake, I just pressed shift 8 to get that snowflake
times, and I can say times whatever is in that cell
so you see it's cell D7
Actually, let me scroll this over so you can actually see the cells
so actually cell D7, let me press enter
so that cell
is ten thousand dollars times D7
which is this one right over here
and I just selected that and I can press enter
and right now, that's nothing
Let me scroll over so you can see everything a little bit better
Scroll a little bit to the, there you go I'm having trouble
Ok, there you go
Now, what are going to be my total costs?
My total costs are my fixed costs plus my variable costs
So that's going to be equal to
And I'm just using my arrow keys right now
It's going to be equal to F7, that's cell F7
plus this one, plus my variable costs
My total costs are my fixed costs plus my variable costs
and so it's fifteen thousand dollars
And actually, I can make this true for every row over here
This is one of the really useful things about a spreadsheet
is, I define this cell as being $10,000 times whatever this cell is
right over here
So what I can just do is
I can just scroll, drag that all the way down
And for every one of these, it's going to take $10,000
times the cell that's essentially 3 to its left
This will be 10,000 times D8
This will be 10,000 times D9
or, then it will just look at that
So we can see right there, 10,000 times D9
You could click on there, you can actually see what the formula is
10,000 times D9
So by dragging that I was able to get the right formula all the way down
Now the total costs for every row here is going to be
2 to the left, plus 1 to the left
and so if I drag that down, it'll do that for every row over here
So now this is 25, is the 15 plus the 10
105 is the 15 plus 90,000
our total costs are fixed costs plus variable costs
Now let's think about the average fixed costs
and the average fixed costs, we're gonna think about it in fixed costs
per line of code produced
and over here line of code produced is 0, so we're gonna divide by 0 which is undefined
So we can leave that blank, but we can fill this one in
So our total fixed costs, this is going to be our total fixed costs
which is cell F8, I just use the arrow keys to select F8
divided by, our total lines of code per month
So divided by our total lines of code per month
and so, that gives me $3.75 in fixed costs per line of code
and then I can scroll, I can do the same thing that I've been doing before
I can drag this down
and then we see what the fixed cost is at any given point
if iItake the fixed cost $15,000 divided by the lines of code I get $1.38
and this actually makes sense because
the more programmers I add onto this project the more lines of code I get
I'm using the same fixed costs
I'm using the same project manager
I'm using the same office space
so the cost of that project manager and that office space
gets spread out amongst, or, along more and more code
So the cost, the fixed cost per line of code goes down
as we add more and more programmers
Now, what is the average variable cost?
So once again, the variable cost is going to be
whatever the variable cost is, per lines of code per month
So when we're talking about average, we're talking about the average cost per line of code
So this is, per line of code, per
let me write it over here
per line of code, and I'm gonna say, per month
Actually I wanted that to spread out more but the way I've set it up, I'll just scroll down
Woops! I'm even having issues here.
Alright, well! These are all per line, average lines of code per month
And so let's think about what happens with our variable costs
So I'm also gonna start here because I don't wanna divide by 0
So in this month, our total variable costs were $10,000
And our total lines of code are going to be $4,000
G8 divided by E8
So, average variable cost per line of code is $2.50
And then what happens, so let's do that for every row over here
So when we do it for every row, something interesting happens
Our average fixed cost went down
Because we're taking the saame cost and spreading it out among more code
But our average variable costs went up
As we added more programmers,
per line of code it actually cost us a little bit more
on average, per line of code
And that's actually if you look here,
as we add the incremental lines of code we get per programmer is actually going down
That first programmer by themselves, she can write 4,000 lines of code
But then, that second programmer is only, you're not getting to 8,000
You're getting to 3,000 and probably they have to co-ordinate with each other
They have to plan a little bit more
It's not all in one person's head
Then, when you add the third one
You're not even adding 3,000 lines of code, you're only adding 2,000 lines of code
And this is actually a real phenomenon, that actually happens in companies
The more people you add on to a project,
obviously maybe they can do more work,
there's going to be more co-ordination,
there's going to be more meetings, there's going to be more interruption
And so each person's individual productivity,
is going to go down
And this isn't to say that the third coder is somehow worse than the first coder
All of their, on average,
all of them are only going to produce 3,000 codes, 3,000 lines of code per month,
when maybe indivually they could have each produced 4,000 lines of code
but they have to spend some of their energies co-ordinating
And so that's why our average variable costs, per line of code is going up
As we add more and more people it's getting us incrementally,
it's getting more and more expensive on average,
to write that line of code
And as we look at average total cost, that's going to be,
once again, this is per line of code,
is gonna be our total cost H8, divided by the total lines of code per month
So, if we just hire one engineer,
we're going to have $6.25 spent per line of code
And that's because a lot is spent on,
and these are, this is actually just the sum of these two right here
And then, let me make that, set that formula for every row
And so, we see something interesting
When we start to hire a few engineers,
we are able to spread out our fixed costs,
even though our average variable costs per line of code are going up,
our fixed costs are going down
So, we're getting a little bit of a benefit for spreading our fixed cost per line of code
But then it starts to get expensive again,
because as we said,
the more people you have working on the project,
you're going to have to spend more time co-ordinating with each other,
and maybe even undoing each other's work,
or even redoing each other's work as opposed to just writing those actual software
And now let's think about the marginal cost
The marginal cost, the best way to think about it is,
what is the incremental cost of that next set of line of code?
So one way to think about it,
so this is going to be how much more you're spending,
divided by how much more code you're getting
So how much more, so for example, how much more,
And this is going to be once again per line of code
So once again, so we're getting,
we're spending, when we go from 0 programmers to 1 programmer,
we're going from $15,000 of total cost to $25,000 of total cost
So we're going from $15,000 to $25,000
that means we're increasing our expenditure by $25,000 minus $15,000
And so that's why I'm doing H8 minus H7
So that's how much more we're spending in expenditures,
and then how much more code are we getting?
Well, we're getting 4,000 minus 0 lines of code
And the reason why I'm doing the formula this way,
is so that when we drag it down on all the rows,
the formula will be right
So, because it is relatively taking the right cells into account
And the reason why I'm saying this it's average,
'cause this is saying,
What's the incremental cost for this first 4,000 lines of code?
And then we can go from there, maybe we can drag it down
And now this is the incremental cost of code,
for the next 3,000 lines of code
And once again, it got a little bit more expensive,
because, we're getting a little bit less efficient because we're adding more people
And there's something very interesting that happens here,
you might have noticed it in these numbers right here
We actually get a negative marginal cost,
this isn't meaning that when we add more lines of code
Somehow we're getting money,
it's actually saying that as we spend more money,
we're actually killing lines of code
Because at some point, if you have too many people on this one project team,
they actually start killing each other's productivity
And you can even see it right here in the numbers
When we had 7 people we were able to write 11,400 lines of code,
but then the 8th person, because of co-ordination,
it's not that this 8th person is incompetent,
it just, when you have 8 people in the team,
everyone's productivity goes down
So that you're only able to produce 11,200 lines of code
And that's why you have this negative marginal cost
Now when you get to 8 people, all of a sudden,
by spending more dollars, you're actually destroying some of what you're actually trying to produce
So what I wanted to do here is just to really get you behind numbers,
and really maybe give you a little sense of how you can actually do this with a spreadsheet,
and get you thinking a little bit about how a firm's cost structure might actually work