Art historians generally like to discuss things that
they do know, things that they've discovered,
things that they're sure of, but so often we don't
know much. And that's certainly the case with this
stunning portrait by Petrus Christus called only,
"Portrait of a Young Woman [Girl]"
So let's start with what we do know: we know that this
is a young woman, we know who the artist is, we
know that the artist is Flemish and the portrait was
made around 1470. We of course know it's
dimensions: it's quite small, and it's made out of oil
and it's on panel, and we know that it's exquisite.
And we also know that this portrait is somewhat
revolutionary. Petrus Christus was the first artist in
Flanders to place his subjects in an actual space,
and although there's not much, we do see a bit of
molding, a rear wall, and it does place her in space.
So, what do we want to know that we don't know
about her? I'm really hungry for information; I want
to know so much. I want to know who she is.
I want to know what she's thinking about.
I want to know where she's looking.
I want to know what, if anything, she's holding in her
hands. [laughs] I want to know who this portrait
was made for, who commissioned it, and what was
it's purpose. I want to know if this is the first time
she's ever worn this fabulous dress. I want to know
what that little loop is just over her forehead that
peeks out from under her hat. I want to know what
she dreams about at night. I want to know if she
has any ambitions. I want to know how old she is.
But you know what, even though we know so little
about this, I still love looking at it.