This right here is a picture of Fibonacci.
One of the most famous mathematicians of all time
And he was a mathematicians in medieval Italy
And he is most famous for the Fibonacci numbers
Fibonacci numbers
And he didn't discover them, they acturally discovered several centuries before mid India
But he popularized them, especially in the west
And Fibonacci numbers are super simple
The first two are defined as 0 and 1
And every number after that is the sum of the previous two
So what I'm constructing right here is really a Fibonacci sequence of numbers
So the next number in the sequence is gonna be 0 + 1, which is 1.
Then the next number after that is going to be 1 + 1, which is 2
And the next number after that, 1 + 2 is 3
2 + 3 is 5
3 + 5 is 8
5 + 8 is 13
8 + 13 is 21
13 + 21 is 34
And the Fibonacci numbers, you know especial once you start getting into number theory
Tons of fancinating things about them
Probably the coolest thing about them
is as you add more and more terms through the Fibonacci sequence
And you take the last two terms that you generated
You'll see there's no really last two terms you can keep going on forever
get arbitrarily large Fibonacci numbers
Say we take these last two terms over here
21, 34, we take the ratio of these two
21 over 34, this is going to be pretty close to the golden ratio
and I encourage you to look up the golden ratio on wikipedia and Internet
you will find all sorts of fascinating mystical things about the golden ratio
What's cool about the Fibonacci numbers or Fibonacci sequences
This gives you approximation of the golden ratio
We get a better even a better approximation if you add another terms for a sequence
So the next term over here 21 + 34 is 55
So the ratio of 34 than 55 is even closer
even closer to the golden ratio
So one way if you want to compute a really good approximation for the golden ratio
You can really just get super high Fibonacci numbers just adding the previous 2 terms to get the next one
and you will get a pretty good approximation we take ratio of the last two terms
Now that was the Fibonacci numbers are about
Now I wanna pose a challenge to you
I want you to write, since we already done some examples using factorials
I want you to write an implementation of a function that generate the nth term in the Fibonacci sequence
So the function will be like this, so this will be the Fibonacci sequence
So if I call your function (let me make it lower case)
Let me just give you some examples
If I take your function and I call fibonacci
you can really implement this in any language you want
or we've been dealing in python and like be simples to do it on python
If I call fibonacci of 1, what I want this to be is the 1st term
and just to make things clear, you should always clarify this especially in computer science
because that always clear what the 1st term is
and I'm going to make it clear right now
the 1st term is not gonna be this one over here
I wanna make this one over here, I'm gonna call this the zeroth term
That's the zeroth term and that is going to be the 1st term
This is going to be the 2nd term, 3rd term, 4th term so on and so forth
And so fibonacci of 1, the 1st term will be this right over here
It will, it should return one
Fibonacci of 0, so, should return 0
Fibonacci of 3 should return, 0, 1, 2, 3, it should return 2
Fibonacci...
Fibonacci of 5 should return, 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, it should actually return 5
What I want you to do is to write a function so we could put any argument over here
and return that term of the Fibonacci sequence