You sample 36 apples from
your farm's harvest of
over 200,000 apples.
The mean weight of the sample
is 112 grams with a 40 gram
sample standard deviation.
What is the probability that the
mean weight of all 200,000
apples is within 100
and 124 grams?
Let's think about what
they're asking.
So there's some distribution of
all of the weights of all
200,000 apples or there's
more than 200,000.
We don't even know how many
apples, just a huge number.
So there's some population
distribution of weights.
Maybe it looks something
like that.
It will have a mean weight.
It has a mean weight.
We don't know what that mean
weight is, and it also has a
population standard deviation.
So this might be one standard
deviation above the population
mean, that would be one standard
deviation below.
And we'll say this distance
right here is the population
standard deviation.
Both of these are parameters
that we do not know of the
entire population.
This is the population
distribution right over there.
Now, we know from our experience
with the last few
videos that you can repeatedly
take samples, or if you kind
of visualize, repeatingly take
samples of a certain size-- in
this video we're going to focus
on sample sizes of 36.
And you keep taking the means of
those sample size, and you
plot the frequency with which
you get those means, you would
eventually get something
called the sampling
distribution of the
sample mean.
Let me write this down.
The sampling distribution
of the sample mean.
So that might look something
like this.
I'll try to draw it a little
bit bigger since we're
probably going to use this
one a little bit more.
It is going to be pretty close
to a normal distribution.
It's going to have some mean,
and we specify that-- let me
draw it down here.
It has mean when we show that
this is the mean of the
sampling distribution.
And we know that the mean of
the sampling distribution,
that the means of all of your
means, or of the actual
distribution of means, is
actually going to be your
original population mean.
So this is going to be your
population mean over here.
And it also has some
standard deviation.
So maybe this is a standard
deviation above the mean, this
is a standard deviation below
the mean, right over there.
And we can specify that by the
standard deviation of the
sampling distribution
of the means.
And we know that this can
be a given, or I guess
approximated, because for fairly
large samples this
gives a pretty good indicator.
There's a couple of correction
factors if you
get to smaller samples.
But this is going to be our
population standard deviation
divided by the square root--
and we saw this in the last
two videos-- divided by the
square root of the number of
samples we have when we
calculate each of those means.
And we know in this example that
we are taking 36 samples.
So this is the square
root of 36.
This is a sampling distribution
of the sample
mean-- let me write it over
here-- 4n equals 36.
For each of our sample buckets
or baskets to have 36 items
and then we take their mean.
And then that is essentially
each of those means is a
sample from this distribution
right over here.
The means are the sample from
this-- the things that we're
using to calculate the samples
are samples, or the things
that were used to calculating
the means are
samples from that.
Hopefully that isn't
too confusing.
But this isn't the first
time we've seen it.
Anyway, this distribution's
standard deviation is going to
be the standard deviation of
this population standard
deviation divided by 6.
But we still don't know this.
We still don't know this
parameter up here.
Now with that said let's
refocus on what they're
actually asking us.
They want to know the
probability that the mean
weight of all 200,000 apples.
Well the mean weight of all
200,000 apples is that
parameter right over there.
And they want to know what is a
probably that it is between
100 and 124 grams. So they're
actually asking us if
something is between 100 and 124
grams it is within 12 of
our sample mean.
Right?
That's all they're saying.
What is a probability that this
thing is within 12 of our
sample mean?
Because if you're less than 12
or if you're 12 less you're
going to get to 100.
If you're 12 more you're
going to get to 124.
So what they're asking us is
what is the probability that
our population mean, this
parameter, this unknown
parameter, is within 12 of the
mean of our one sample.
Now if I told you that I'm
within 5 feet of you, then
that also means that you're
within 5 feet of me.
So this is the exact same thing
as the probability that
the sample mean is within
12 of the actual mean.
I really you to-- this
should make sense.
If I said what's the probability
that I'm either 5
behind you or 5 ahead of you,
that's the same thing as a
probability that you're either
5 behind me or 5 behind you.
This is asking what's the
probability that we're 12
apart, or what's the probability
that I am within
12 feet of you.
And this is the probability
that you're
within 12 feet of me.
They're asking the
exact same thing.
But when you phrase it this way
it might dawn on you that
you might be able to use the
sampling distribution of the
sampling mean.
There's some unknown mean here,
which is the same thing
as this value right here.
So this thing-- let me make it
very clear-- this is also the
same thing because this
value and this value
are the same thing.
This is exactly the same thing
as asking what is the
probability that our one sample
mean is within 12 of
the actual mean of the sampling
distribution.
So we're just saying what's the
probability that that one
sample mean we have is
within 12 of this
actual sampling mean.
At this point your brain should
be reading that gee, if
I could figure out how many
standard deviations that is,
how many standard deviations
away that is on this
distribution, I can then use a
Z-table to actually figure out
the probability.
And that's exactly what
we're going to do.
But there's one slight
complication here.
We don't know the actual
standard deviation of the
sampling distribution.
We just know that it's
this thing right over
here divided by 6.
But we don't know this thing.
So what we're going to
do is get our best
estimate of this thing.
So we need a good estimator
for the actual population
standard deviation.
What's our best estimate
of that?
What's going to be our sample
standard deviation?
We sampled 36 things,
and we had a sample
distribution of 40.
So we have a sample distribution
of-- let
me write this way.
This is going to be
approximately equal to our
sample distribution or sample
standard deviation, which we
got to be 40.
So we literally just took-- we
found the mean of our 36
apples, mean weight was 112
grams. Then we found the
square distance from each of the
apples' weights to this.
Took the average of those.
Well we didn't take the straight
up average, we
divided by n minus 1.
We learned all of this many,
many videos ago.
And then we took the square
root of that.
This gave us the sample standard
deviation, it is our
best estimator for this.
So if this is our best estimator
for that, our best
estimator for this thing right
here is going to be equal to
our sample standard deviation
divided by 6, which is equal
to 40 over 6, which is
equal to-- let's get
our calculator out.
So if we have 40 divided by
6, we have 6.6-- I'll
just write down 6.67.
So this thing right
here is 6.67.
So our best estimate of the
standard deviation of the
sample distribution of the
sample mean is 6.67.
So this distance right
here is 6.67.
So how many standard deviations
is 12 if you look
at this distribution
right over here?
Well we just divide
12 by 6.67.
So let me get the calculator
back up.
So if we have 12-- I'll just
divide it by that 6.--
actually this exact number--
12 divided by-- answer just
means the last answer we got--
that gives us 1.8 exactly.
The numbers just happened
to work out well.
So this is completely analogous
to saying what is
the probability that our one
sample mean is within 1.8
standard deviations.
Let me write it this way.
It was in 1.8 standard
deviations of the sample
mean-- within 1.8 of these--
of our actual mean of our
sampling distribution.
So we're literally
just asking that.
So if you look at this
distribution up here, within
1.8 standard deviations, this
is one standard deviation,
another 0.8 would maybe get
us right about there.
And we're within 1.8 above and
1.8 below, so this is 1.8
standard deviations above the
mean, this is 1.8 standard
deviations below the mean.
So we're just going to say
what's the probability when we
just took this one sample of 36
apples that we lie in this
space over here?
And to figure this out what I'm
going to do is I'm going
to use our Z-table to figure
out essentially
this space over here.
Just what's the probability
of being 12 above it.
And then we can just double it
because a normal distribution
is symmetric.
So let's go to our Z-table.
So what's the probability of
being between the mean and 1.8
standard deviations
above the mean?
So if you just go straight to
your Z-table, 1.80 is this
right over here.
Now you get this
0.9641 number.
But be very careful.
This 0.9641 number that gives
you-- so if I draw a normal
distribution-- let me draw a
better normal distribution.
If I draw a normal distribution
like that, and
this is our mean, this 0.9641
number tells us the
probability that we are less
than 1.8 standard deviations
above the mean.
So this is 1.8 standard
deviations up here, then this
is our mean right over here.
This is giving us this entire
area right over there.
So if I want just this area
right here, what I need to do
is from this value, from this
0.9641, I need to subtract
this, the probability that
you're essentially directly
less than the mean.
And that is this.
This is the probability that
you're less than the mean, or
you're less than the mean plus
0 standard deviations.
So this value right
here is 0.50.
This whole area that I
just showed you right
over there is 0.9641.
So this area right over here
is going to be 0.9641 minus
0.5, which is going to
be equal to 0.4641.
So this area right here, just
what's in the magenta.
Just between there and
there is 0.4641.
Let me make sure I
got that right.
0.4641.
And if I want this entire
area I just double it.
If I want to include this
as well, I just
have to double that.
So let me get my calculator
out, let me get the trusty
calculator.
So we're going to have 0.4641
times 2 is equal to 0.9282.
So this whole area right over
here is equal to 0.9282.
So we did something neat.
The probability that the--
remember that well, we're
answering right here.
The probably that our sample
mean just happens to be within
1.8 standard deviations--
remember, that was 1.8
standard deviations of the
sample means from the actual
mean is 0.9282, or there's
a 92.82% chance.
But that's also saying that
there's a 92.82% chance that
the actual mean is within 12 of
our measured sample mean.
And that is neat.
Because for the first time
ever-- we started with very
little information.
We just started with a little
sample over here.
And we were able to get as much
information about that
sample as possible.
But we can now say that there's
a 92.82% chance that
the actual mean is within 12
of the mean we measured.
That the actual mean is between
100 and 124, or that
we're 92.82% confident that
the actual mean is in the
range between 100 and
124 grams. I think
that's pretty neat.