According to Filipo Brunelleschi's biographer
he stood just inside the main doors of the Cathedral of Florence
when he conducted his first perspectival experiment
and that's where we are standing right now.
We're very close to it. Brunelleschi's experiment demonstrated that linear perspective could produce
an incredibly realistic illusion of three dimensional space on a two dimensional surface.
So this notion that we can actually develop a system that would be relatively easy to follow
but highly accurate that could translate the volumetric world that we move through,
through time, onto a frozen two-dimensional surface is really an extraordinary achievement.
There's some discussion amongst scholars
whether or not there was linear perspective in the ancient world
but if there was, it was lost.
Linear perspective was created at least for us in the modern world
by Brunelleschi in the 15th century, around 1420.
Right, and so some people say that Brunelleschi rediscovered linear perspective
in case the ancient Greeks an Romans had had it, before him.
Brunelleschi had gone to Rome, and had studied antiquity and some have hypothesised
that he developed the basis for linear perspective in an attempt to accurately portrait the buildings
that he was looking at, that he was sketching, that he was drawing.
It's certainly something that artists, begining really in the thirteen-hundreds,
were creating forms, they were creating human figures that were three-dimensional
by using modeling and making the figures poky and monumental.
Then you had the challenge of putting those figures within a believable space.
Giotto and Duccio had kind of approximated that space
and began to create a kind of earthly setting for their figures,
but had not achieved perfect illusion of space for their figures to inhabit.
As the culture becomes increangly analytical, mathematical it's a trade-based culture
this is a culture that is some ways may have demanded of its artist a kind of precision,
a kind of mathemetical accuracy in its representation.
And Brunalleschi delivers that.
So what does he do?
Brunelleschi creates a perpectively accurate image of the Baptistery and its surround.
Right. So Brunelleschi develops a system with just a few essential elements
and trough these elements is able to constract accurate scientific one-point perspective.
They include a vanishing point, which is at the viewer's horison line,
as well as a series of orthagonals or illusionisticly receding diagonals.
What Brunelleschi then does, is he paints or draws an image of the Baptistery with linear perspective
and puts a small hole in the center of it.
He takes that small drawing or painting, puts a handle on it,
and holds it in front of his face, but facig away from him.
He then takes a mirror, and holds it in back of that.
Now remember, that his painting has a small hole in it so he can see through it
straight to the vanishing point.
So he is holding a mirror, at arms length,
and the actual painting with the hole in it right in front of him for his eye to look through.
Right, so he can see the painting's reflection in the mirror and if he pulls the mirror away
he can see the actual Baptistery and he can bring the mirror back to see the painting,
move the mirror away to see the actual Baptistery
and see if in fact those lines are well coordinated and it was a very convincing experiment.
What Brunelleschi saw in the reflection of the painting
looked exactly like the reality that was in fron of him.
This would have the most profound effect on the history of western art
Virtually, every painting in the western tradition after the 15th century is responding to linear perspective,
either adopting it, or very consciously rejecting it for some reason.
And within a couple of decades after Brunelleschi's discovery,
Alberti, the brilliant architect and theoretician, writes the book called 'On Painting',
in which he codifies Brunalleschi's discovery and creates a manual for artists
of how to use linear perspective and how to make great paintings.