In the last video we began to explore the IS curve
which, as I think I mentioned, stands for investment savings
And we really analyzed it from the point of view of investment
we thought of it as real interest rates driving the level of investment
which drives the equilibrium level of real output
High real interest rates - low level of investment
low level of investment leads to low level of equilibrium output
So this scenario is closer to that right over there
If real interest rates are lower then that leads to higher levels of planned investment
which leads to a higher level of equilibrium output
so that right over there
What I want to do in this video
so that was more from the investment point of view
What I want to do in this video is explore the exact same relationship
the exact same curve, but think of it more from savings point of view
and in this situation we're going to have the exact same thing
but instead of viewing real interest rates as driving GDP
we're actually going to view GDP as driving real interest rates
So let me leave this up here
Let's just break down the expenditure model of GDP
So we know that aggregate income, or aggregate GDP, or aggregate output
however you want to think of it
Is equal to, and you can break it up into it's component expenditures
its equal to aggregate consumer spending, which is a function
of disposable income. Y - T is disposable income - aggregate income minus taxes
plus investment
plus government expenditures
and I could do net exports, but for simplicity for this discussion
we'll just assume we're in a closed economy
it makes conceptualizing saving and investment a little bit easier
Now, what I want to do is solve for investment
So if I solve for investment, I'm just going to subtract
this piece and this piece from this equation
and I get aggregate income minus total aggregate consumer spending
minus total government spending
is equal to, on the right hand side I'm just going to be left with investments right over here
and this thing right over here is interesting
because this is total income minus...
Let me make sure that we- I don't want to confuse you
because that looks like a lower case 'c'
and if we're talking about aggregate consumption, it's usually and upper case 'c'
So on the left hand side, we have total aggregate income minus consumer spending
minus government spending
so you could really view this as this right over here
really is aggregate savings
this over here really is savings
And as we see when one side of the economy, when people are saving that goes into banks
and it gets lent out, and then it gets reinvested
or you could save directly by reinvesting
And so what we have here, savings is equal to investment
and that's why it's called an IS curve
because when you look at the expenditure model, savings and investment are really the same thing
They could have- they are really just saying,
look, there's two ways to view this curve
it's investment driven, or it's savings driven
and when you think of it this way, you have slightly different view of this curve
because when you view it from a savings point of view,
you say "well what's going to happen if GDP goes up?"
"what happens if he have a high GDP over here?"
So if we have a high GDP-
or let's say in particular, if GDP goes up,
the consumer spending, which is a function of GDP, it will go up
but it won't go up as much
it's going to go up by this expression right here
times _ linear model, times the marginal propensity to consume
which is less than one, it's between 0 and 1
So this is going to go up less than that
and then we can- for the sake of this model we'll assume right now that happens without any changes in government expenditure
So this, if total aggregate income goes up, then savings are going to go up
if we assume government expenditure holds constant
so then we have savings goes up
and if savings goes up, that means we have more loanable funds
there is more money to lend
and if there's more money to lend, what's going to happen to interest rates?
Well, interest rates are just the price of borrowing money
the price of money
So if you have more of something, the price of that thing goes down
So if savings goes up, then real interest rates go down
So if you have a high GDP, you're going to end up with low interest rates
So, once again, looking at it from the point of view of GDP driving interest rates
we have high savings here, so we're going to have low interest rates
and you view it the other way around, if you have a lower income
this thing is going to also decrease
but it's not going to decrease as much as this did
because of the marginal propensity to consume is less than one
we saw that up here, we saw that all the way over here, right over there
and so, in aggregate, the savings are going to go down
once again, we hold government spending constant
So in this situation savings are going to go down
and if you have fewer loanable funds, there's less savings to lend out
Then, if you have less of a supply of something, what's going to happen to it's price?
The price is going to go up, the price of borrowing money is the interest rate
So in this situation, interest rates would go up
So that's going in this direction, right over here
if aggregate income goes down, loanable funds go down, interest rates are going to be higher
So, once again, same exact curve
IS curve, but there's two takeaways here
One is to realize why it's called IS - then investment and savings (when you view it from this point of view)
really are the same thing
One person's savings can be another person's investment
And when we viewed it from the investment point of view, we were viewing r as driving Y
now we're looking at it the other way around
Y is driving savings, which is driving r
but it gives us the exact same relationship for this model