We're asked, "What is the greatest common divisor of 20 and 40?"
Another way to say this is, "gcd(20, 40) = ?"
And "greatest common divisor" sounds like a very fancy term, but it's really just saying:
What is the largest number that is divisible into both 20 and 40?
Well, this seems like a pretty straightforward situation, because 20 is actually divisible into 40
Or another way to say it is that 40 can be divided by 20 without a remainder
So the largest number that is, I guess you could say, a factor of both 20 and 40 is actually 20
20 = 20 &times; 1, and 40 = 20 &times; 2
So in this situation, we don't even have to break out our paper, we can just write 20
Let's do a couple more of these
We're asked, "What is the greatest common divisor of 10 and 7?" Let's now break out our paper for this
So, our greatest common divisor of 10 and 7, so let me write that down, so we have 10
We want to think about, what is our GCD of 10 and 7
And there's two ways that you can approach this
One way, you can literally list all of the factors—not prime factors, just regular factors—of each of these numbers
And figure out which one is greater—or wait, what is the largest factor of both
So, for example, you could say, well, I got a 10
And 10 can be expressed as 1 &times; 10 or 2 &times; 5
1, 2, 5, and 10, these are all factors of 10. These are all, we could say, divisors of 10
And sometimes this is called "greatest common factor"
7, what are all of its factors? Well, 7's prime, it only has two factors: 1 and itself
So what is the greatest common factor? Well there's only one common factor here: 1
1 is the only common factor
So the greatest common factor of 10 and 7, or the greatest common divisor, is going to be equal to 1
So let's write that down: 1
Let's do one more
What is the greatest common divisor of 21 and 30? And that's just another way of saying that
So, 21 and 30 are the two numbers that we care about
So we wanna figure out the greatest common divisor, and I could have written "greatest common factor," of 21 and 30
Once again, there's two ways of doing this
There's the way I did the last time where I literally list all of the factors. Let me do that way really fast
If I say 21, what are all of the factors? Well, it's 1 and 21, and 3 and 7, and I think I've got all of them
And 30 can be written as 1 and 30, 2 and 15, and 3
Actually, I'm gonna run out of room, let me write it this way, so, get a little more space
1 and 30, 2 and 15, 3 and 10, and 5 and 6. So here are all of the factors of 30
And now, what are the common factors? Well, 1 is a common factor. 3 is also a common factor
But what is the greatest common factor, or the greatest common divisor? Well, it is going to be 3. So we can write 3 here
Now, I keep talking about another technique, let me show you the other technique, and that involves the prime factorization
If you say the prime factorization of 21, well, let's see, it's divisible by 3, it is 3 &times; 7
And the prime factorization of 30 is equal to, let's see, it's 3 &times; 10, and 10 is 2 &times; 5
So, what are the most factors that we could take from both 21 and 30 to make the largest possible numbers?
When you look at the prime factorization, the only thing that's common right over here is a 3
And so we would say that the greatest common factor, or the greatest common divisor, of 21 and 30 is 3
If you saw nothing in common right over here, then you would say the greatest common divisor is 1
Let me give you another interesting example, just so that we can get a sense of things
Let's say that these two numbers were not 21 and 30, but let's say we care about the greatest common divisor, not of 21, but let's say of 105 and 30
So if we did the prime factorization method, it might become a little clearer now
Actually figuring out, "Hey, what are all the factors of 105" might be a little bit of a pain
But if you do a prime factorization, you'd say, well, let's see, 105 is divisible by 5, definitely, so it's 5 &times; 21, and 21 is 3 &times; 7
So the prime factorization of 105 is equal to, if I write them in increasing order, 3 &times; 5 &times; 7
The prime factorization of 30, we already figured out, is equal to 2 &times; 3 &times; 5
So what's the most number of prime factors that they have in common?
Well, these two both have a 3 and they both have a 5
So the greatest common factor, or greatest common divisor, is going to be a product of these two
In this situation, the GCD of 105 and 30 is 3 &times; 5 = 15
So you can do it either way. You can just list out the traditional divisors or factors until you figure out which of those is common and is the greatest
Or you can break it down into its core constituencies, its prime factors, and then figure out what is the largest set of common prime factors
And the product of those is going to be your greatest common factor. It's the largest number that is divisible into both numbers