So this is the first of a series of videos
in which we show you how to build a ‘beetle bot’
without using any solder.
This is our Khan Academy ‘Spout’ beetle bot.
So it's got LED eyes,
and a bunch of different ways you can make it.
So the first thing we're going to do
is to organize all of our parts.
And we’re go through each of the different components.
In this kit, we've got
2 bottle caps,
2 sliding switches,
2 single-pole-double-throw lever switches –
We also have
2 1.5 volt motors,
4 large paper clips,
and 2 AA batteries.
You’ll need a AA battery holder, as well.
And some hot glue,
2 LEDs,
and 2 resistors.
You’ll want to make sure you pick
resistors that fit with those LEDs.
I believe those are under 60 ohm.
And then we have 5 multicolored wires.
Okay. So now we’re going to talk about
the tools that you need to make this project work.
You're going to need ...
a hot glue gun.
(And any standard one will do.)
And needle-nosed pliers to crimp the wires together.
And you’ll need something to strip the wires with.
You can either use a wire stripper
or scissors, if you like.
Alright. So let's get building.