In this video, we will cover the power rule,
which really simplifies our life,
when it comes to taking derivatives,
especially derivatives of polynomials.
You're probably already familiar
with the definition of derivatives.
The limit as delta x approaches 0,
f(x+delta x) - f(x),
all of that over delta x.
and it really just comes out of
trying to find the slope of a tangent line,
at a any given point.
What we're going to see with the
power rule is it simplifies our life.
We won't have to take these,
sometimes complicated, limits.
We're not going to prove it
in this video,
we'll hopefully get a
sense of how to use it,
and in future videos,
we'll get a sense of why it makes sense,
and even prove it.
So the power rule just tells us,
if I have some function,
f(x), equal to some power of x,
so, x^n, where n is not 0.
so n could be anything,
it could be positive and negative,
it does not have to be an integer.
The power rule tells us that
the derivative of this,
f'(x), is just equal to n,
so you're literally bringing this out front,
n * x, and then you just
decrement the power.
so f'(x) = n*x^(n-1).
So let's do a couple of examples,
just to make sure that makes sense.
So let's ask ourselves,
let's say f(x)=x^2.
Based on the power rule,
what is f'(x) going to be equal to?
Well, in this situation,
our n=2,
so we bring the 2 out front,
2*x^(2-1).
That will be 2*x^1,
which is just equal to 2x.
That was pretty straightforward.
Let's think about the situation
where g(x)=x^3.
What is g'(x) going to be,
in this scenario?
Well, n is 3, so we just
literally pattern match here,
you'll find this to be
shockingly straightforward,
so this is going to be
3*x^(3-1) = 3x^2.
And we're done!
In the next video, we will think about
whether this actually makes sense.
Let's do one more example,
just to show it doesn't have to
necessarily apply to only the positive integers.
We could have a scenario where
we could have h(x)=x^(-100).
The power rule tells us that
h'(x) would be equal to what?
Well n = -100, so it's
-100 x^(-100-1).
which is equal to -100x^(-101).
Let's do one more.
Let's say we had z(x)=x^2.571.
And we are concerned with
what is z'(x).
Once again, power rule simplifies our life,
so this is going to be
2.571 * x^(2.571 - 1),
so it's going to be equal to,
and make sure I'm not falling off
the bottom of the page,
2.571*x^1.571.
Hopefully you enjoyed that.
In the next video, we will
not only expose you to
more properties of the derivatives,
we'll get a sense for why
the power rule at least makes
intuitive sense,
and then also prove the power rule,
for few cases.