Just realized that I typed in the wrong
numbers at the end of the last video
when I was trying to put them in the calculator.
We were trying to determine
the coefficient of static friction –
and it's 50 Newtons divided by
49 square roots of 3 Newtons.
And in the last video, by accident, in the calculator,
instead of doing 49 square roots of 3,
I wrote 40 square roots of three.
So let's actually calculate it again.
50 divided by 49, times –
(Let me write it this way,
to make sure we get it)
– 49 times the square root of 3 –
gives us a coefficient of static friction of,
if we round it, 0.59.
So this is equal to 0.59.
And so, that's it!
I just forgot to –
I did the calculation wrong on
the calculator in the last video.