I want to make a quick clarification and then add more tools in our complex number tool kit.
In the first video I said that if I had a complex number z
and it's equal to a+bi
I used the word and I have to be careful about that word because you know, I use it
in kind of the every day sense but it also has a formal reality to it.
So clearly the real part of this, of this complex number is A.
Clearly, that IS the real part and clearly this complex number is made up of real number plus an imaginary number.
So I, just talking in everyday terms, I called this the imaginary part.
I called this imaginary number, this imaginary number, the imaginary part.
Just be carefull there. I did make it clear that if you were to see the function,