After going through many of these Indian Institute of Technology joint entrance exam problems, I realized that
there are a lot of problems where they really just expect you to know some things. So, that's what I am going to cover in this video.
One of those things that they just expect you to know. And what we're going to do is come up with a relationship
between a conic section in the particular hyperbola is what we will focus on and a tangent line. We've done this in
a previous problem, but that wasn't in the general case. So let's just say that we have a left-right
opening hyperobla so we are going to have the equation X squared over A squared minus Y squared over
V squared equals one. So if I were to draw that hyperbola, it' going to look something like this. That's
the x-axis. That's the y-axis and then it opens to the right. I can draw a better bottom half that opens to the right.
And it opens to the left. And in case you're curious, this point right here
if you said y is equal to zero, this point right here is (a,0), and this right here is (-a,0).
So what I wanna do is figure out a relationship about these a's and b's
and the equation of a tangent line.
So let's say I have a tangent line that looks something like this.