Lets say that I run some type of a pension fund and I have one billion dollars that I need to invest
some place. And I dig around little bit and there's this company A over here and it needs to borrow
a billion dollars and it's willing, it's willing to give 10% interest in exchange for borrowing that
billion dollars. So, if I give these characters over here - my billion dollars - if I lend it to
them; if I lend them the billion dollars on an annual basis they are going to give me 10% interest. There's
a problem here though. The rating agencies, the ones that in theory should be independent, they've only given
a company A a BB rating. This is a pension fund. I have to only invest in the safest of safest of
securities. I have to invest only in things that are AA. So, here I might enter a character like
AIG. And obviously, things have changed since their heyday. But, AIG based on at least Moody's perspective
has a AA rating. So, AIG could say, "Hey! look pension fund why don't you lend them the money and what we are going to do is
enter into a Credit Default Swap and what that essentially is - is a form of insurance. Of that 10% every year,
why don't you give us 1% of that?" And in financial lingo, that is sometimes, referred to as a 100 bases
points in exchange for that 100 bases points you can view this as an insurance premium. We are going
to insure that if for whatever reason company A defaults on that debt you can give us that debt security
and we will just give you back the billion dollars. Now, from the pension's point of view, this looks pretty
good. They are getting a net 9% of interest, 10% minus the 1% and they are essentially getting to lend to a BB company
but in effect like lending to a AA. Because as long as AIG is good for the money, the pension fund is going
to get their money back one way or the other. Now, where this gets a little bit shady is that AIG right
here didn't have to do anything. What's interesting about Credit Default Swaps sometimes referred
to as CDSes is that even though there are insurance for all purposes, they are not regulated like insurance. So, typically
an insurance company when they insure something will have to set aside some money in case that thing actually
happens and they have to work out the probabilities and all that. Now Credit Default Swaps were not
regulated in that way. So, AIG could do this without having to set aside any type of moeny. And, they
could do this over and over and over again kind of snowballing all of their potential liabilities.
So, you can imagine it's really good money while noone is defaulting but all of a sudden when people
start defaulting then all of a sudden AIG is gonna be in trouble and all of the people who thought they had in effect AA debt because AIG was insuring it might not