The measures of two angles of an isosceles triangle
are 3x+5 degrees, we'll say, and 3x+16 degrees.
Find all possible values of x.
So, let's think about this,
let's draw ourselves an isosceles triangle or two
So, that's an isosceles triangle.
Like that and like that.
And actually let me draw a couple of them.
It's because we wanna think about all of the different
possibilities here.
All of the different possibilities.
So, we know from, what we know about isosceles triangles
that base angles are gonna be congruent.
That angle is gonna be equal to be that angle,
that angle is gonna be equal to be that angle.
And so what could the 3x+5 degrees and the x+16,
what could they be measures of?
Well maybe this one right over here has a measure of 3x+5 degrees
and the vertex is the other one.
So, maybe this one up here is the x+16, x+16 degrees.
The other possibility, the other possibility
is that this is describing both base angles.
In which case they would be equal.
So, maybe this one is 3x+15
and maybe this one over here is x+16, x+16.
And that is, in the final possibility,
actually we haven't exhausted all of them:
Is that if we swapped these two, if this one is x+16
and that one is 3x+15.
Let me draw ourselves another triangle.
And obviously swapping these two aren't going to make a difference,
because they are equal to each other.
And then we can make that one equal to 3x+5,
but that one isn't gonna change anything either.
because they are equal to each other.
So, the last situation where this angle, now here is x+16
and this angle up here is 3x+5.
This is 3x+5.
So, let's just work through each of this.
So, in this situation, if this base angle is 3x+5,
so is this base angle.
Then we know all of three of these are gonna add up to 180 degrees.
So, we get 3x+5 plus 3x+5 plus x+16
is going to be equal to 180 degrees.
We have 3x, let's just add, you have 3x plus 3x
which gives you 6x plus another x gives you 7x.
And then you have 5 plus 5 which is 10 plus 16 is equal to 26.
Is equal to 26.
And that is gonna be equal to 180.
And then we have, let's see, 180 minus 26,
if we subtract 26 from both sides we get 180 minus 20
is 160 minus another 6 is 154.
154.
You have 7x is equal to 154
Let's see how many times this is, if we divide both sides by 7
7 will go to into 140 20x and get another 14.
So, it looks like 22 times so x is equal to 22, is that right?
20 times 7 is 140
140 plus 14 is 154.
So we have x is equal to 22 in this first 22 degrees,
in this first scenario.
Now let's think about this second scenario over here.
Now we have, now we have
these two characters are gonna be equal to each other.
Because they're both the x angles.
So, you have 3x+5 is equal to x+16.
You can subtract x from both sides.
So, this becomes 2x+5 is equal to 16.
We can subtract 5 from both sides and you get 2x is equal to 11.
And then you can divide both sides, you can divide both sides
by 2 and you get x is equal to 11, is equal to 11 halves.
So, that is our second scenario.
And now we do our third scenario right over here.
If this base angle is x+16 and then this base angle right over here
is gonna be also x+16, they're congruent.
Then we can do the first thing we did for the first scenario.
All of these angles are gonna have to add up to 180 degrees.
So, we have x+16 plus x+16 plus 3x+5
when you add them all up together you're gonna get 180 degrees.
Now let's add up all the x terms.
x plus x is 2x plus 3x is 5x.
So we get 5x.
5x.
Then you have 16 plus 16 is 32
32 plus 5 is 37.
Plus 37 is equal to 180 degrees.
Subtract 37 from both sides and we get 5x is equal to,
So it's not gonna divide nicely.
Divide both sides by 5 you get x is equal 143 over 5.
Which you can just leave as an improper fraction.
You can write it as a mix number
or however else you might write it.
And we are done!
These are the 3, these are the 3 possible values of x
given the information they gave us right up there.