Solve for y and check your solution
Twenty minus seven 'y' equals six 'y' minus six
So what I really want to do is just isolate all of the 'y's on one side of the equation then if there's some sort of coefficient in front of it, I can divide both sides by that coefficient,
and I can isolate the 'y' on either the left side or the right side of the equation.
Actually let me do it both ways.
So, first, let's... it looks like it'll be a little bit simpler if I isolate it on the right-hand side
and I'll show you that in a second.
So if I want to put all of the y's on the right
hand side, how can I get rid of all the 'y's on the left-hand side?
I have a minus seven 'y' or you can use the negative
seven 'y'.
I can add seven 'y' to both sides of this equation, so I'm just
adding seven 'y' to both sides.
Then the left hand side of the equation you have twenty minus seven 'y' plus seven y.
Those are going to cancel out you're going to be just left with twenty.
And on the right hand side of the equation
you have six 'y' plus seven 'y' which is thirteen y.
And then you have your minus six.
And I want only 'y's or multiples of 'y's on the right hand side of the equation
so I have to get rid of this minus six over here.
So let's add six to both sides of this equation.
Let's add six and then on the right hand
side, I have thirteen 'y' minus six, plus
six, that's just thirteen 'y'. Got rid of the minus.
Then I have twenty plus six, so that's twenty-six. So I get twenty-six is equal to thirteen 'y'.
I have isolated the 'y'
on the right hand side although it's to be multiplied by thirteen.
So if I just want a 'y'
on the right hand side, one 'y' on the right hand side.
I can divide both sides by thirteen.
Or the equivalent statement would be to multiply both sides by one over thirteen, same thing.
So let's divide both sides of this equation by thirteen.
On the right-hand side, thirteen times 'y' divided by thirteen, that's just going to be 'y'.
So this is just 'y'.
And then twenty-six divided by thirteen
that is two.
So our solution we got is 'y' is equal to two.
Now I'm going to take a step back, why did I say it was going to be a little easier to put the 'y'
on the right hand side of the equation.
That way I have a positive coefficient in terms of 'y'.
If I had subtracted six 'y'
from both sides, I would have got a negative thirteen on both sides, which would have been a legitimate t
thing to do
Let me just show you, what I'm talking about.
So I could have done the problem this way:
Twenty