I didn't even copy and paste all these.
But I can already see that these are positive y values.
So A was the answer.
I'm sorry, I ran out of space.
Anyway, I'll see you in the next video.
All of these y values, they're all negative.
You're staying in the third and fourth quadrant.
All right, next video.
Problem 5
Two airplanes left the same airport travelling in opposite
directions.
If one plane averages 400 miles/hour--so this is
the airport.
One plane goes in that direction at
400 miles per hour.
That's a mile not a meter.
And another plane averages 250 miles per hour.
And it's going in the other direction.
And I do this as vectors.
So the length of my arrow represents its
speed to some degree.
And the direction represents direction.
250 miles per hour in that direction, 400 miles per hour
in that direction.
In how many hours will the distance between the two
planes be 1625 miles?
So you just have to say, if you're sitting in this plane
right here, this plane to the left.
And you let's say you think you're stationary.
How fast is that plane going to be moving to the rightwards
direction, or I guess to the eastward direction?
Well from your point of view, it's going to be going in the
east direction at 650 miles per hour.
If you thought that you were stationary, it would just be
going away from you at 650 miles per hour.
Same thing, if you were sitting in this plane right
here, and you thought you were stationary- -and you are,
relative to yourself--you'd say, oh, why this guy is going
to the west t 650 miles per hour relative to me.
And we're starting at the same point.
So this just becomes a standard distance is equal to
rate times time problem.
So if we have to cover 1625 miles, because that's what
they want to know, when does that happen
At what point are the planes that far from each other
That is equal to their relative velocity, they're
separating from each other at 650 miles per hour.
And we want to know how long is that going to take?
So time is going to equal 1625 divided by 650.
Let's see if we can simplify that at all.
Well, we could divide the top and the bottom by 25.
If we divide the top one--let me just get my calculator.
So 1625 divided by 650 is equal to 2.5.
And we were doing everything in miles per hour.
So time is going to be equal to 2.5 hours.
The choice is A.
Problem 76.
I'll just copy and paste all these word problems. We'll
parse them together.
Problem 76 in green.
Lisa will make punch that is 25% fruit by adding pure fruit
juice to a two liter mixture that is 10% pure fruit juice.
How many liters of pure fruit juice does she need to add?
Pure fruit juice.
So let P equal liters of pure.
And that's what they want us to figure out.
So we have to figure out P.
All right.
And adding it to a two liter mixture, So so let's say M is
equal to the liters of the mixture.
That is 10% fruit juice.
So that is this right here, to a two liter mixture, that is
10% fruit juice.
We're calling that M.
That is the two liter mixture that is 10% fruit juice.
OK, how many liters of pure fruit juice
does she need to add?
OK, so let's think about it a little bit.
So, punch is going to be pure juice.
So let's think about how much pure juice is going to be in
the system.
The liters of pure juice she adds, plus the
liters of the mixture.
Well it's a two liter mixture that is 10% fruit juice.
So how much fruit juice is already there?
So it's 0.2 liters of fruit juice.
I should'nt even define M, we know that M is equal to 2.
So ignore that.
You can tell I'm doing these problems in real time.
I'm struggling with them as yoou would.
Anyway, so how much fruit juice is there going to be in
the mixture?
There's the amount of liters of the pure
fruit juice she adds.
This is a pure fruit juice, that's P.
And then you're going to have the two filters of the mixture.
that is 10% fruit juice.
So how much fruit juice is coming from that?
Well 10% of two liters is 0.2 liters already.
And then how many liters is there going
to be in the mixture?
In the combined, how many total liters are there?
Well, there's the liters of the pure fruit juice, plus the
two liters that we're adding to.
This is the amount of fruit juice.
This is a total amount of liquid.
And we got the 0.2 from 10% times 2.
And we said that this has to equal to 25%.
We want this to be 25% of this.
So this should be 0.25.
That was an inadvertent mark right down there.
So now we just solve for P.
The hard part is setting up the problem.
So let's multiply P plus 2 times both sides.
So you get P plus 0.2 is equal to 0.25 times this.
So 0.25P plus 0.25 times 2 is 0.5.
Fair enough.
Let's subtract 0.2 from both sides.
You get P is equal to 0.25P, 0.5 minus 0.2 is plus 0.3.
Let's subtract 0.25P from both sides.
1P minus 0.25P is 0.75P is equal to 0.3.
And let's see where this goes.
Did I do that right?
0.75P is equal to 0.3.
Right.
The decimals sometimes get confusing.
So let's multiply both side\s of this equation by 10.
You get 7.5P is equal to 0.3.
Sorry, is equal to 3, we multiplied by 10.
So you get P is equal to 3 over 7.5.
How many times does 7.5 go into 3?
So that's the same thing as how many times
does 75 go into 30.
Put a decimal sign.
Let's see, it goes into it I think four times.
It's 0.4.
So P is equal to 0.4 liters.
We have to add 0.4 liters of pure fruit juice to the two
liter mixture.
So you add 0.4 to the two liter mixture, so you end up
with 0.6 liters of pure fruit juice.
So the numerator becomes 0.6.
And the denominator becomes 2.4.
Which, sure enough, is 1/4 or 25%.
Fascinating problem.
Next question.
And these are good to learn.
A lot of times in math class people are like, what do I
need to learn this for?
But this type of algebra, you're going to
use it all the time.
Especially if you go into any type of science or
engineering.
Or, for that matter, investing or finance.
You're going to use these kind of, boy can I figure this out
or not type of equations all the time when you're mixing
things and figuring out margins and all the rest.
OK, let's see.
Which relation is a function?
So I have a little bit of a review of a function.
So a function is a relation that maps from
a domain to a range.
I want to say from A to B.
Or we could say from the domain to the range.
Where it takes one set of numbers, which you call the
domain, and we have another set of numbers.
And for every number here, there's exactly one
number in the range.
And that's the key.
From here to here, there's only one number.
Now two of these could meet the same number.
But you can't have one number here going to two separate
numbers there.
That's the key.
Here we have the same number.
You have a minus 2 here.
And you have a minus 2 here.
So that's like the same number.
Let's say this is a minus 2.
That minus 2 is going to a 6 and here it's
going to minus 2.
So you have the same number going to
two different numbers.
And you can't have that in a function.
For any given number in the domain, you definitely get
only one in the range.
So A is not the answer.
Let's see, does this have that same problem?
See every number is there exactly once.
You have one minus 2, one 0, one 1, one 2, so you're not
going to have that problem.
My suspicion is it's already B.
C has the same problem.
4 goes to a bunch of different nummbers.
4 goes to 0, 4 goes to 1, so it's not C.
And then this defines two values for 10.
So that doesn't work either.
So the answer is B.
Problem 78.
All right.
For which equation graphed below, are all
the y values negative?
So if all the y values are negative, we have to say
below the x-axis.
This is where all the y values are negative, right there.
So this one seems to work.
A seems to work.
Here, these aren't negative y values.
These are positive y values.
this is airport
one plane goes that direction
400 mile per hour
250 this is back , a kind of length our represents
It's be to some represents of the direction
250 m/h and 400 m/h
so you had to say if
you were sitting in this plane right here, and this planes were left
you don't know, you know, let's say you think you're stationary
how fast is that plane going to move to the right word direction, and I'm guessing
it's east, and east direction, or from your point you gonna
this gonna be going to the east direction at 650 m/h
right, if you taught, you were stationary. just be going to be away from
625 m/h
same thing, if you were sitting in this plane right here
and if you taught, you were stationary. you were relative to yourself, if you say, oh
this guys going to the west. and 650 m/h relative
to me starting at the same point. so it just becomes a standard distance
distance is equal to rate times time problem. so if you had a cover
1625 mile because ask, they wanna know, you know, when does
happen at what point other planes that far from each other
that is equal to, there're relative velocity
there're separating from each other. 650 miles per hour
we wanna know how long it's going to take
so time is going to equal 6
1625 divided by 650
so if you can simplify that it all
well, you can divid the
top and bottom by 25
right, divid top one of, let me just calicutrator
so 1625
divid by 25
is equal to 2.5
so time, if do everything miles per hour, time is going to be 2.5
hours, that choice A
problem 76, I just copy and paste
this word problem, person together, problem
76, in green
green, Lisa will male punch
so just let p
is equal to liters of
pure. that's why, that's why they want to just figure out
figure out p
alright, let's say that
2 liter mixture, so let's say m is equal to liter
of mixture
that's 10 percent
right, so that's this right here
2 liter mixture that is 10% fruit juice, what calling that
M
that's 2 liters mixture is 10% fruit juice
okay, how many liters of pure fruit juice dose she need to add
so let's think about little bit
the total amount of she just gonna
she going to add punch, so punch is going to be pure juice
she wants something like how much pure juice is going to be
in the system. there's pure juice
adds plus liters of mixture
2 liters mixture that is 10% of fruit juice. so how much fruit juice are already there. so it's 2 points
of liter juice
right, it's 2 liter mixture, oh you know actually in the fine
find them. m is equal to 2
so ignore that
you can done. you can just doing problem at the real time. I'm struggling with them as you well
anyway, how much fruit juice is it going to be in mixture?
there is amount of liters of the pure fruit juicy a
and then, pure fruit juice
that's p, and then you gonna have the 2 liters of mixture that is 10% of fruit juice. how much fruit
juice is coming from that?
well. 10%
of liters, o.2 litters already
then how many liters is there going to be in the mixture? combined
how many liter are there? there is pure fruit juice
plus 2 liters, we're adding to
this is amount of fruit juice. this is total amont of
liquid. right, we got 0.2 times from 10% times
we sad this has to be equal to 2
25 percent. we want this to be 25 percent of this. this should be 0
0.5. there was in bed mark
now on there, solve for repeat
hard part of setting up a problem. so let's say p multiply
p plus 2times both sides
so you gonna get p
plus 0.2 is equal to0.2 times this
0.25p plus
0.25 times 2 is point 5, fair enoigh
let's subtract 0.2 from both side,you get p is
equal to 0.25p 0.5 minus 0.2
plus 0.3
let's subtract 0.