So let's review the situation that has been emerging in Greece
and then dig a little bit deeper as to their options.
So as we saw in the last video, Greece was spending
a lot more then it was bringing in tax revenues.
So it was running these deficits, and year after year
these deficits were piling up and the national debt was increasing.
And to make matters worse, Greece actually tried to cover this up
for many years with some accounting shenanigans,
because there were some European Central Bank rules about how much debt you could take on.
So it was trying to not trigger those rules while still being able to
take on more debt, so that it could fund this spending.
But then, in the last few years it became clear,
the shenanigans were cleared up. And when they were cleared up;
one, it made people realize, wow, that was kinda shady what they did
and on top that, they had a much larger government public debt burden then people thought.
And the combination of the two, that the country was trying to not make its obligations
apparent and to be transparent to the market,
and on top of that, that this debt burden was so huge.
It made people wary of whether the country would actually be able
to fulfill its obligations. So trust,
investor trust, when I talk about investors, I'm taking about the people
who would invest in Greek bonds. So essentially, the lenders to Greece.
Their trust went down, and they expected higher interest.
Higher interest from the Greek Government, and that made things worse.
Now not only they had to keep spending on all their entitlements,
but now the cost of funding that existing debt that they already had
and the new debt that they had to do to keep spending at that rate,
the cost of that debt itself went up.
And that only kinda added fuel to this balloning debt problem.
Now in the last video, we explored a couple of options.
In particular, we said what about austerity?
What about the situation where you just really, mainly you could
try to increase your revenue or slah spending, but people really try to focus on the spending side.
What if really just slashed the spending,
in a very severe way? Realy jist cut straight to the bone.
Well, there's a couple of problems there.
One problem was that it is not popular at all
and then the bigger problem was that you are already in the recession,
and this could make the recession even more severe
...recession more severe...
Frankly, it was not popular, it is never popular
but as we move now, in 2012, is even less popular
because Greece has already gone through couple of rounds of this austerity,
This is not a new problem, they´ve been bailed out in small ways,
and I´ll talk more about what a bail out is,
as part of that package, people who were bailing them out
said, look if we´are going to give you something
if we are going to use some of our tax payers money to help you out,
you´ve got to cut your spending. But what is happening in every round of austerity so far,
is that it helps slow the economy even further.
The recession kept deepening and deepening and it kind of common sence that it would,
if government stops spending in a big way, it slows down already slow economy.
The other thing you might be saying is - why doesn't Greece just stop paying its debt?
Why doesn´t it just default on its debt?
So like, sorry investors that you have to take a loss here but we just not paying anymore.
Well, the problem is that it has a situation when spending more than it is bringing in
and its obligations are all in the euro.
It does not have its own currency. And so, if they would be on default on their debt,
obviously the people who lended them money would be very upset,
and there is not way they are going to lend more money to Greece.
And if they do not lend more euros to Greece,
Greece is not going to be able to continue spending euros the way it has.
it is promising all of their pensions, retirees, unemployment insurance,..
it is paying all these obligations in euros
and if they default, they are not going to be able borrow more euros to do those obligations
and once again, it will be kind of very fast and violent austerity
because there wouldn't be even the money to fund
and you would have this kind of drastic,..almost shut down of the government.
So, this right over here is not a good option.
Now, to start exploring the third option
and this is kind of the option it seems likely that Greece might have to going.
Let´s think about what Greece could have done
if it had monetary independence. If it had it´s own currency.
Just remember, this is completely hypothetical,
Greece did have its own currency, the drachma, before it joined the euro,
but let's think about what it could have done in this situation
if it actually did have its own currency.
It is not cut-and-dry here because Greece was
actualy able to historically borrowed at very cheap rates,
because it was part of this EuroZone. But let's just think about it
if it wasn't the situation, what it could of done if had its own central bank.
So this is some of our stats from our last video,
and if it has its own central bank, let me make this very clear,
this is all hypothetical, Greece does have no its own central bank right now,
for all of the Eurozone countries, the euro is printed by the European central bank,
it is not by anyone country. But - hypothetically, let's say
Greece does has its own central bank. So, Greek central bank...
that prints its own, let's call new drachma.
And so that Greek Central bank in this type of the situation
could just start printing drachma and essentially
use that drachma to buy government bonds
so essentially printing that money and buy government bonds
it is lending it to the government. It lends to the government
so that the government could spend on its entitlements, on all of its various obligations.
Now, that may seen very convinient, essentially one part of the government
or something associated with the government, prints money,
essentially lends it to the government, funds its obligations
but the immediate thing you may say is "well, hey..
..if you just print currency like this, willy-nilly,
won't this lead to an inflation?" And the simple answer is, it probably will.
But that actually might be the solution, if you are in conundrum like Greece is in.
First of all, inflation might not be so bad,
Right now the country is in a deep recession, so there
is all the extra capacity, you might even have a little bit
of price cushion. And just in general the inflation rates
aren't ultra dramatic, there are not super low but not
super high either, so there might be some.. you may not have to worry
about kind of hyper-inflationary situation, but on top of that
the government probably wants a respectable amount
of inflation, might not want 100% or 1000% of inflation
but it might like 10%, 20% or 30% yearly inflation.
And to think about that, think about the idea, in this hypothetical Greece,
all of its obligations wouldn't be in euro, its obligations
would be in drachma. And so, you can imagine a world,
let's think about hypothetical Greece and I'm going to use
hypothetical numbers, just to make things more simple
to understand or to do in our heads, let's take this hypothetical Greece,
but it could be Greece or any other country, and let's say it has a GDP ...
...GDP of 100, let's call it 100 of its currency, ...100 drachma is its GDP,
and let's say it has its entitlement obligations,..and this is all on the annual basis,..
...and let's say 10 billion of its currency, of its drachma. This is not the situation of Greece as
all its obligations are in euros but let's just think about the situation
and let's say that on top of that it has debt obligations, total debt, total value of debt
let's say that it was, ... I don't know,..there was another 150 billion of its currency.
Let's say you inflate over couple of years, so inflation occurs,
and let's say you have 100% of inflation over few years
but in real terms your GDP doesn't change, ....so in real terms
if you have 100% inflation but you producing the same amount,
the nominal value of your GDP will now be 200 billion.
It is the same amout of goods and services but everything now costs twice as much,
so you would value it to 200 billion. If you would have your
inflation adjusted, it would still be 100 billion. The good thing,
and it is very seldom that you use inflation to good context,
but it would be good for Greece in this situation, that these
entitlement obligations, they would still be 10 billion.
You still going to say " I'm gonna to still pay you 10 billion" even if that 10 billion
is goign to buy people half as much. That is much easy to do politically
than telling people over night that I'm going to reduce your pension by half. This is political suicide.
But to inflate away the obligations, nominally it looks like you paying the same thing
but just buying less, it is a little bit more viable to do.
And the same thing is to review debt obligations.
Your debt obligations won't adjust the inflation, and so you would still owe
150 billion but as the percentage of GDP you've halved how big the debt is,
you've halved how big the entitlement obligations are. So there is actually a viable solution
and in this hypothetical situation is probably the best solution
for government to essentially inflate away its obligations.
So, I'll leave you with that, something for you to think about and then we can think about
what could Greece actually do in this directions but more importantly
let's think about, and you can start to think why is the whole world so scared,
all of this is Greece, it is relatively small country, so why is whole Eurozone
so scared, why are people thinking about bailing out Greece
in some way to prevent all this craziness from happening
and what are the repercussion in the larger global market.
But I'll leave you there and leave you to think about all this stuff.