We're on problem 154
They ask us, is x negative?
So the question is x less than 0
Statement number 1 tells us-- let's see, they say x to the
third times 1 minus x squared is less than 0
Now let's simplify it
Let's see, x to the third minus x to the fifth is less than 0
We could add x to the fifth to both sides
x to the third is less than x to the fifth
Let's divide both sides by x squared
That won't change the inequality since x squared is
definitely going to be positive
Any integer squared, even if it's negative, is a positive
So you divide both sides by x squared
you get x is less than x to the third
Now let's see, does this answer that question?
Let's see what x's would satisfy this condition
So we can already say that x cannot be equal to 0, right?
Anything where this would have been an
inequality doesn't work
So x can't be equal 0, it can't be able to 1
because 1 is equal 1 to the third
and it can't be equal to negative 1
So we know that immediately
We know that for regular positive numbers
for numbers greater than 1
taking it to the third power is always
going to be greater than the number itself
If you took 2 to the third power, that's greater than 2
3 to the third power is greater than 3
1.5 to the third power is greater than 1.5
So we know that this statement right here implies
that x is greater than 1
Now let's see, is there a situation
where x can be negative?
Well, let's see
First off, x is between 0 and 1
1/2 is not less than 1/8
So it doesn't work between 0 and 1
But what if x were between negative 1 and 0?
Let's try an example
Negative 1/2 is less than negative 1/8
It's more negative
Negative 1/2 is less than negative 1/8, right?
You could try that with any fraction
Because when you take it to the third power
it becomes a smaller fraction
but it becomes a smaller negative fraction
So x will be less than it, because it's more negative
So this is true
If this is true, then x is either greater than 1
or it's between negative 1 and 0
Let's see, does it work if x is less than negative 1
Negative 2, is negative 2 less than negative 8?
Nope
Right
So these are the only ranges where it works
This statement implies this
But this still isn't enough information to tell us
whether x is less than 0
x could be greater than 1
which is definitely greater than 0, or x could be less than 0
So we don't know yet just from statement 1
Statement 2 tells us x squared minus 1 is less than 0
So add 1 to both sides
that tells us that x squared is less than 1
So when could something squared be less than 1?
Well, it's going to have to be between
negative 1 and 1, right?
It's essentially going to have be a positive
or a negative fraction less than 1
That's the only way that when you square it
you get a number less than 1
you're definitely going to get a number greater than 1
and it's going to be positive either way
If it's 1, it's going to be 1, and then 0 is in our range
So statement 2 tells us this
but it includes both positive and negative numbers
So it doesn't answer our question whether x is less than 0
But if we use both statements combined
what is the intersection?
What is the overlap of this and this?
Well, if x has to be between negative 1 and 1
and it has to be one of these
the only one that it overlaps with is this one
You cannot have x being greater
than 1 and x being in this range
You can have x being in this range and x being in this range
since this is a subset of this
So this is actually the more restrictive
And so since we go to that
that actually tells us that x has to be negative
So both statements combined are sufficient
to answer this question, but individually they're not
The last question, 155
Marsha's bucket can hold a maximum of
how many liters of water?
So we want to know the capacity of her bucket
Statement number 1 says
the bucket currently contains 9 liters of water
That's useless
We don't know how-- that could be the bucket
9 liters could be that
Or maybe 9 liters is the full capacity
That tells us nothing about what the capacity
of the bucket is
If I told you I had a bite of the sandwich
that tells you nothing as far as
how large of a sandwich I can eat
So statement 1 doesn't seem that useful
Statement 2, if 3 liters of water are added to the bucket
when it is 1/2 full of water
So 1/2 times the capacity, right?
When it's 1/2 full of water, you add 3 liters
So if 3 liters of water are added to the bucket
when it is 1/2 full of water
the amount of water in the bucket will increase by 1/3
To increase something by 1/3, that is like multiplying it
by 1 1/3 That's 1 1/3 times the capacity
That's what they're saying
The amount of water in the bucket will increase by 1
Sorry
You're going to have 1 1/3 times what you started off with
which was half your capacity
That make sense?
We say we're starting with 1/2 of our capacity
and we're adding 3 liters
They're saying that that will increase the amount
we have by 1 1/3
Let me write that
Let's say we start with x, and we're adding 3 liters
They're saying that will equal 1 1/3 or 4/3 times x, right?
This shows that x is increasing by 1/3
You could view this as 1 plus 1/3 times x
This is an increase of 1/3
They tell us that our starting point is 1/2 of capacity
So that's where I get the 1/2 c-- that's our starting point--
plus 3 is equal to 4/3 times the starting point
or where we're adding water to, 1/2 times c
We could easily solve for c here
So you get a 2, this cancels out
Then you get 1/2 c plus 3 is equal to 2/3 c
Let's see, we could subtract 1/2 c from both sides
and you get 3 is equal to 2/3 minus 1/2 c
Then you can just do that fraction
and you get c is equal to 3 over-- well, what is this?
1/2-- so if you do it over a 6, 4 minus 3, so this is 1/6
So this turns into 1/6
So c is equal to 18
Wait a minute
You didn't have to do all that
You should have just realized that as soon as you can write
this algebraic equation down
it's a linear equation with one unknown
and that one unknown is what we're trying to solve for
you have enough information to solve the problem
So statement 2, alone, is sufficient to solve this problem
We're all done with data sufficiency
See you all in the next section