What I want to do in this video
is think a little bit about
how the unemployment rate is actually computed
by the bureau of labor statistics.
So to figure that out, let's just start off
with the entire US population. So let me
draw a big circle here that represents the entire US population.
US population, and right now, if my numbers are correct
the latest numbers are 304,000,000 people.
Now, not all of those 304 million people are capable of working
including my 2 1/2 year old son, or my new born daughter,
so, you have to think, when you think of unemployment
you want to think about the percentage of these people that are actually old enough
to work, that actually can be employed theoretically.
So let's take a subset of that US population
and let's think about who's essentially an adult
who's working age?
So this subset right over here is 16 years
and older. So people who can legally work
and the numbers I have here, this is 100
sorry, this right here is 237,000,000 people
Now, we can't just say all of these people could possibly work
because a lot of them are in college
some of them are in high school, some of them might not have
the ability to work, some of them might be retired,
so what we want to do is take a subset of this
population that is essentially you could say,
part of the labor force, in that they are working
or they are actively looking for work.
Let me draw that right over here.
So this right over here is the labor force.
So these are not retirees, or people who are in college
those people would be sitting right over there
assuming they are 16 years or older.
The labor force, this is working and actively looking for work
and we'll think about what actively looking for work means
in a little bit more depth in a few minutes.
Actively looking for work.
And that number, if my numbers are correct,
is right around 154,000,000. Although the numbers
here are not so important, the more important thing
is the idea of how the unemployment rate itself is calculated.
And then so within the labor force, you have a subset
So this is working and actively looking for work.
So you have a subset of the labor force that is actively looking for work.
So they don't have a job, but they're actively looking.
So this right here is unemployed
and actively looking, this actively looking
is probably more important than you might realize at first.
And this number, let's just say for the sake of argument
this is sitting around 15,000,000 people.
So if you have a job, you're right over here,
if you don't have a job, but are actively looking
you're going to be right over here.
What we're going to see in a little bit is
if you have, if you don't have a job, but you are
not actively looking, you could be working
you would actually be sitting out here.
This is going to be interesting when we think of trends
and the unemployment rate, when it goes up or down.
But just to see how the unemployment is calculated
let's use, let's do it for this example.
So the unemployment rate
is literally just the number of unemployed,
over the entire labor force.
So in this situation, it would be
15,000,000, so that's just the number of unemployed
and actively looking, over the entire labor force
Over 154,000,000. So if we get my handy TI 85 out
that gives us in this example right over here
and unemployment rate of 15 divided by 154 million.
So it's about 9.7, if we write it as a decimal, it would be 0.097
if we write it as a percentage, this would be 9.7%
so this is approximately 9.7%.
Now I told you that the details are going to be important
And the reason why they are is interesting things happen
when people stop looking for work, or when they
start looking for work.
So I said "unemployed and actively looking"
puts you in this bucket over here.
If you're unemployed, if you don't have a job
and you're not actively looking
you're actually not in the labor force.
And so you might be saying, "Sal, what does it mean
to be actively looking for work?"
And this means that you've looked for a job
or you're actively searching in the past
We'll do this in a new color
in the past 4 weeks
And you might say "Sal, how do they know whether these 15 million people,
have actively searched for jobs in the past 4 weeks?"
And the answer is they do a survey.
They're not going to survey every human being in the labor force
or the US population, or all 15 million
that are unemployed, that would be logistically impossible
what they do is they do a survey
and right now they do about 60,000 every month
and they essentially ask them,
are you employed?
are you unemployed?
if you are unemployed, have you looked for a job
in the past 4 weeks?
If you have looked for a job in the past 4 weeks
as an unemployed person, you'd get thrown into this bucket
right here, you're actively looking, you're still part of the labor force
but if you've got so discouraged that you're no longer
looking for work, maybe you've given up
then you get thrown out of here, you get thrown
out of the labor force. And that is what most people
don't realize, when things get bad enough
and people get really discouraged,
you have people not going,
you have people actually exiting the entire labor force
and see how that affects the numbers
imagine a situation, so this is the unemployment rate
right now, there's 15,000,000 who are unemployed
and actively looking for work. Let's say that this
is just a horrible recession or depression
and 5,000,000 of these people get so
discouraged, they don't, in the last 4 weeks
they do not look for work anymore.
So they've maybe stopped altogether or they want to take a break
so what we're gonna do, is we're going to take
5,000,000 people out of this bucket over here,
so we're going to take 5,000,000 people and move them
out over here. Outside of the labor force.
If you did that what happens?
Well now, the number, the official unemployed number
is now going to be 10,000,000
and what's the labor force number?
Remember, they went completely out of this green circle over here
So they also left the labor force,
so the labor force number is now 149,000,000
So in this bad situation, where people have left the labor force
the unemployment rate would now be 10 million people
unemployed and actively looking for work
over a labor force of 149,000,000.
The labor force has shrunk because they're so discouraged
so what do we get there as our unemployment rate?
We have 10 divided by 149
it gives us 6.7%
So this is fascinating, if things get bad enough
and people actually exit the labor force
then the unemployment rate could actually go down
because the labor force is shrinking.
The other thing could also happen,
maybe things get really good and you have
10,000,000 people who are sitting out here
they're either marginally attached to workers,
which are people who are hoping to get a job,
but haven't looked for a job in the past 4 weeks
or they could be discouraged workers
who would mind working, but they've given up altogether looking
but you can imagine when the economy gets good
let's say we're starting from this baseline
here, the economy gets good, and all these people
who are unemployed, but not part of the labor force,
all of a sudden start looking for work.
So then they'd be part of the official unemployed
So 10,000,000 would grow to 20,000,000
So now this number is 20 million, and this green area
would go up by 10 million,
so now this would be 159 million,
so in this situation, the official unemployed would be
20 million, and the entire labor force would be
159 million, and now you get a situation
so you have 20 divided by 159 million,
which is 12.6%
Approximately 12.6%
So the whole point of this video,
I'm not saying that the unemployment rate is
the way it's calculated is wrong, or that it's
supposed to be misleading,
I just want to give you a little bit of nuance
that it doesn't always give the complete picture
in particular, that one number, just this
and there's other unemployment rates that give
a little bit more nuance here, but this one
headline unemployment rate that's typically given on the news
doesn't capture the whole story, in particular
it doesn't capture the people who might be exiting
the labor force when things are bad, so in that situation
the unemployment rate would probably be
understating how bad things are.
And it also doesn't capture the people who are entering the labor force
in that situation the unemployment rate
would probably make things look worse than they are
when things might actually be improving.