Welcome back. I think I was rushing that problem.
So let me just make it clear again,
just so you don't get confused,
because I was trying to get under that 10-minute limit.
But they want to know what the perimeter of this red is,
right?
That's kind of the outside of this thing that looks like
a flower or something.
And what I'm saying is that the perimeter of the red part
is equivalent to the sum of the perimeters of the rectangle
of the triangle,
sorry-- the sum of the perimeters of the triangles.
But if I were just to take the sum of the perimeters of the
triangle, I wouldn't just be getting the red part.
I'd also be getting in these parts, right?
Because those are parts of the perimeters of the triangles.
So if I want just the red part,I subtract out this,
what I just drew in blue,
and the blue is the perimeter of that inside square.
And the perimeter of that inside square is 9plus 9plus 9plus9
or 36.
So I just take the perimeter of all four triangles.
Each of them has a perimeter of 30, so together they have a
perimeter of 120, and then subtract out the perimeter of
the square inside, which has a perimeter of 36.
So 120 minus 36 is what? 84. Right, 84. That's choice D.
Next problem.
Let me remember that this is where I ended the last one.
OK, next problem. Problem number 13.
The graph of g of x is shown above.
OK, I'd better draw it because they want us to essentially
look at the graph and figure out a value.
Well, let's see, it starts at roughly-- so if I were to--
let's see, 2, 4, 6, 8. And we have 2, 4, 6, 8, 10.
I'll try my best to draw it like they have. So the line
starts roughly a little bit above 6, not even up to 7.
And then, where does it go? It goes to like 4.
Oh my God, I thought I was using the line tool.
It starts a little bit above 6, not even up to 7.
It looks like about at 1. It starts here,
then it goes to the point 4 comma 2, it looks like.
And then it goes from 4 comma 2 to 6 comma 3, roughly.
Or maybe even exactly. 6 comma 3.
And then it looks like it goes to 8 comma 8.
8 comma 8 is like there, roughly. That's about right.
And then it goes down to like-I don't know--almost 11 comma 2
It goes to someplace like that,
and they're saying this is the graph of g of x.
And they're saying, if g of 2 is equal to k,
which of the following could be the value of g of k?
g of k is what?So what could k equal?Let's figure out g of 2.
So when x is 2, bum, bum, bum,bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum.
what is y equal to?
Well, it looks pretty darn close to 5, if not exactly 5.
So k is equal to 5, right? g of 2 is equal to 5, right?
And they want to know what g of k is.
Well, we figured out that k is equal 5,
so now we want to know what g of 5 is. So we go to 5.
We go, bup, bup,bup, bup, bup. This is 5.
And then we go bup, bup, bup,bup, bup, bup, bup, bup, bup.
Looks pretty close to 3. g of 5
and actually the way they drew it,it doesn't look close to 3.
The way they drew it, if you look at where 5 is, it looks
actually less than 3. It looks like 2 and 1/2, actually,
the way they drew it. My drawing is a little off.
So if you look down, look at the x value.
When x is equal to 5, you go up to the graph, it looks like
the graph value there is right around 2 and 1/2.
So I should say this is 2 and 1/2.
And that is one of the choices, B. Next problem.
Problem 14.
If 0 is less than or equal to x,which is less than or equal
to 8, and negative 1 is less than equal to y, which is less
than or equal to 3, which of the following gives the set of
all possible values of x times y?
OK, so we really just want to figure out
how low can x times y be and how high can x times y be?
Well, what's the lowest possible value for x times y?
Well, if we make y negative, and we make x really big, or
as big as it can be, if x is 8 and y is negative 1,
then that is the lowest value for x times y I can think of.
So xy is going to be greater than or equal to negative 8
because when you take a negative number,
you want the other number to be
as big as possible so you get a large negative number.
And it's going to be less than or equal to
well, what's the largest number that I can think of?
Well, if I take 8 and I multiply it times the large
value of y and this is a positive value, then I get 24.
So xy is going to be greater than or equal to negative 8
and less than or equal to 24. And that is choice E.
And once again, how did I get negative 8?
This is probably the part that's not intuitive for you.
It's because-- I mean, your instinct might have said the
minimum x is 0, right?
So I'll take 0 times any of these, so this is going to be 0.
But, you can actually get a smaller value for xy by using
negative 1 and 8, so that's where we got the negative 8 from.
Next question. 15. Switch colors. 15. Let me draw that.
It looks like a line there, line there, line there,
then there's another line that goes like that.
And they write that this is n degrees right there.
In the figure above, what is this sum in terms of n of the
degree measures of the four angles marked with arrows?
Fascinating.
So they want to know that plus that plus that plus that.
Well, let's just do the angle game.
If this angle as n, well, then this angle is n, right?
Let me switch colors. What is this angle here?
Well, it's supplementary to n, so this is 180 minus n.
And so is this.This is also 180 minus n.
And so what are these? What's the sum of these two angles?
Let me call this a, b. What's the sum of a plus b?
Well, we know that a plus b plus this angle,
plus 180 minus n is equal to 180, right?
Because they're all in the same triangle.
So a plus b is equal to 180 minus 180 plus n.
I just took this and subtracted 180 and added n to both sides
This cancels out so you get a plus b is equal to n.
And similarly, if you had c,if this were c and d,
you could do the same thing.
c plus d plus this angle, 180 minus n is equal to 180
because they're all in the same triangle.
Subtract 180 from both sides and then add n to both sides.
You get c plus d is equal to n.
So if you want to know what a plus b plus c plus d is,
a plus b is n, c plus d is n,
so the whole thing is going to be n plus n or 2n.
And that is choice B.
Let's see if I have time to do problem 16,
considering I have a little under a minute left. Problem 16.
After the first term, each term in a sequence
actually, this is going to be-- I think this will take some
explanation, so I'll do 16 in a video by itself.
I'll see you in the next video.