So what do we have here
We have a triangle,
and we know that the length of AC is equal to the length of CB,
so this is an isosceles triangle we have
Two of its legs are equal to each other
And then they also tell us that this line up here,
let me put another label there
Let me put another label there just for fun
Let' call this！
listen, you can call this a ray cause it's starting at C
That line or ray CD is parallel to this segment AB over here
And that's interesting
Then they give us！ they give us these two angles right over here,
these adjacent angles, they give it to us in terms of x
And what I wanna do in this video is try to figure out what x is
And so given that they told us that this line
and this line are parallel,
you could！ we could turn this into a line CD,
so it's not just a ray anymore,
so it just keeps going on and on in both directions
The fact they'd given us a parallel line tells us
that maybe we can use a little！
we know about transversals and parallel lines
to figure out some of the angles here
And you might recognize,
you might recognize that this right over here, this line
Let me do that in a better color
You might recognize that line CB
is a transversal for those two parallel lines
Let me draw both of the parallel lines a little bit more,
so that you can recognize that as a transversal
And then a few things might jump out
You have this x+10 right over here,
and its corresponding angle is right down here
This would also be x +10
And if this is x + 10,
then you have a vertical angle right over here
that would also be x + 10
Or you could say that you have alternate interior angles
that would also be congruent
Either way, these base angles wanna be x+10
Well, it's an isosceles triangle
so you're 2 base angles are going to be congruent
So if this is x+10, then this is going to be x+10 as well
And now we have the 3 angles of a triangle expressed as
as functions of, expressed in terms of x
So when we take their sum,
then they'd be equal to 180 and then we can actually solve for x
We get 2x + x + 10 + x + 10 is going to be equal to 180 degrees
And then we can add up the x's,
so we have a 2x there, plus an x, plus another x
That gives us 4x 4 x's
And then we have a + 10 and another +10,
so that gives us a +20, is equal to 180
And we can subtract 20 from both sides of that
And we get 4x
4x is equal to 160
Divide both sides by four, and we get x is equal to 40
And we're done!
We figured out what x is
And we can actually figure out what these angles are
This is x+10, then you have 40 + 10
This right over here is going to be a 50 degree angle
This is 2x, so 2 * 40
This is an 80 degree angle
It doesn't look like it, the way I've drawn it
And that's why you should never take anything
you should never assume anything based on how a diagram is drawn
So this right over here is going to be an 80 degree angle
And then these 2 base angles right over here are also going to be
are also going to be 50 degrees
So you have 50 degrees, 50 degrees, and 80,
they add up to 180 degrees