What we have got over here is a triangle
where all 3 sides have the same length.
All 3 sides are congruent, a triangle like this,
we call as equilateral triangle
Now what i want to do is to prove that
if all 3 sides are the same then all
all 3 angles will measure the same
So let us think how we can do this.
First we know that AB = AC,
Let us pretend that we do not know that it is equal to BC
for an isosceles triangle, two sides have the same length
the base angles will be the same.
We know that angle ABC = angle ACB
because side AB= side AC
So if two sides are equal, base angles are equal
We can also view this triangle from the other way
maybe sides BC & side BA have the same length
that means angle CAB& angle ABC are the same
If the sides are AC & BC, then these will be base angles.
So let us review what we have said so far
Sides AB and AC are same so
angle ABC = angle ACB
and sides BA = BC so angle ABC = angle CBA
If angle ABC = angle ACB = angle CAB
then all the angles are congruent to each other
so equilateral triangle is one in which all 3 angles are
the same . All angles add up to 180
so if we call the angle as x, then x + x + x = 180
or 3x = 180, so x = 60 degrees.
In equilateral triangle are three angles are the same
and are equal to 60 degrees
Now let us think about it the other way round
I have a triangle where all teh angles are the same
Point X, Y ,Z of the triangle , what we showed in the last video
is if 2 bases angles are the same then the corresponding
sides are going to be the same
We know YX = YZ and we know that because the
base angles YXZ = YZX
now we also know that YZ = XZ
here the base angles are XYZ = YXZ
The base angles in the first case are
angles YXZ = angle YZX
in the second case the angle XYZ = angle YXZ
we said that all sides are equal to each other.
If we have a triangle with all 3 angles at 60 degrees
then all 3 sides will be the same