Solve for y.
We have three y plus seven is less than two y and
four y plus eight is greater than negative forty-eight.
So we have to find all the y's that meet both of these constraints
so let's just solve for y in each of the constraints and just remember that this "and" is here.
So we have three y plus seven is less than two y
so let's isolate the y's on the left-hand side
so let's get rid of this two y on the right-hand side
and we can do that by subtracting two y from both sides.
So we're going to subtract two y from both sides,
the left-hand sides we have three y minus two y,
which is just y, plus seven
is less than two y minus two y and there's nothing else there
that's just going to be zero.
And then we can get rid of this seven here
by subtracting seven from both sides
so let's subtract seven from both sides,
left-hand side, y plus seven minus seven, those cancel out, we just have a y
is less than zero minus seven, which is negative seven.
so that's one of the constraints. That's this constraint
right over here.
Now let's work on this constraint.
We have four y, plus eight is greater than negative forty-eight.
So let's get rid of the eight from the left-hand side
so we can subtract eight from both sides, subtract eight from both sides,
the left-hand side we're just left with a four y because
these guys cancel out.
Four y is greater than negative forty-eight minus eight
So we're going to go another eight negative,