What we have drawn over here is 5 different triangles
What I wanna do in this video is
figure out which of these triangles are congruent
to which other of these triangles
And to figure that out I'm just
over here, going to write our triangle congruency postulates
So we know that 2 triangles are congruent
if all of their sides are the same
So side, side, side
We also know they are congruent if we have a side
and then an angle between the sides,
and then another side that is congruent
So side-angle-side
If we reverse the angles and the sides,
we know that's also a congruence postulates
So if we have an angle and then another angle,
and then the side in between them is congruent,
then we also have 2 congruent triangles
And then finally, if we have an angle and then another angle,
and then a side, then that is also
Any of these imply congruencies
So let's see our congruent triangles
So let's see what we can figure out
right over here for these triangles
So right in this triangle ABC over here,
we're given this length 7, then 60 degrees, and then 40 degrees,
or another way, think about it
We're given an angle, an angle, and a side
40 degrees, and 60 degrees, then 7
And in order for something to be congruent here,
they would have to have an angle-angle side given
at least, unless we made
We have to figure it out some other way,
but I'm guessing for this problem
Though this already gave us the angles,
so do I have to have an angle and angle side
And it can't just be any angle angled side
It has to be 40, 60 and 7
And it has to be in the same order
It can't be 60 and then 40 and then 7
The if the 40 degrees side has
if one of its side has a length 7,
then that is not the same thing here
Here the 60 degrees side has length 7
So let's see if any of these other triangles
have this kind of 40, 60 degrees
and then the 7 right over here
So this has the 40 degrees and the 60 degrees
but the 7 is in between them
So this looks like it might be congruent to some other triangle
Maybe closer to something like angle-side-angle
'cause they have an angle-side-angle
So it wouldn't be that one
This one looks interesting
This is also angle side angle,
so maybe, these are congruent but we'll check back on that
We're still focused on this one right over here
And this one we have a 60 degrees, then a 40 degrees, and a 7
This is tempting
We have an angle, an angle and a side,
but the angles are in a different order
Here it's 40-60-7
Here it's 60-40-7
So that's an angle and angle and side,
but the side is not on the 40 degree on the 60 degree angle
It's on the 40 degree angle over here
So this doesn't look right either
Here we have 40 degrees, 60 degrees, and then 7
So this is looking pretty good
We have this side right over here
Is congruent to this side right over here
Then you have your,
you have your 60 degree angle right over here
60 degree angle over here
So it may not be obvious 'cause it's flipped
and they've they're drawn a little bit different
We should never assume that
just the drawing tells you what's going on
And then finally, you have your 40 degree angle here
which is your 40 degree angle here
So we can say we can write down that
And I'll do it
Let me think of a good place to do it
I'll write it right over here
We can write down that triangle ABC is congruent to triangle
And now we have to be very careful with how we name this
We have to make sure that we have the corresponding
the corresponding vertices mapped up together
So for example, we started this triangle at vertex A,
so point A right over here that's where we have the 60 degree angle
That's the vertex of the 60 degree angle
So the vertex of the 60 degree angle over here is point N
So I'm gonna go to N
And then we work from A to B
B was the side was the vertex that
we did not have any angle for
And we could figure it out
if these 2 guys add up to a hundred,
and this is going to be the A degree angle
So over here, the A degree angle is going to be M,
the one that we don't have any label for
It's kind of the other side
It's the thing that shares the 7, the 7 length side right over here
So then we wanna go to N then M,
and then finish up sorry
And M, and M, and then finish up the triangle
And oh!
And I wanna really stress this
That we have to make sure we get the order of this right,
'cause then we're kind of referring to
We're not showing the corresponding vertices in each triangle
Now we see vertex A or point A maps to point N
on this congruent triangle
Vertex B maps to point M
And so you can say,
"Look AB the length of AB is congruent to NM "
So it all matches up
And we can say that these 2 are
congruent by angle, angle side, by AAS
So we did this one is this one right over here is
congruent to this one right over there
And now let's look at these 2 characters
So here we have an angle, 40 degrees,
a side in between and then another angle
So it looks like ASA is going to be involved
We look at this one right over here
We have a 40 degrees, 40 degrees, 7 and then 60
And you might say,
"Wait, here the 40 degrees is on the bottom
and here it's on the top "
But remember, things can be congruent if you can flip them
If you can flip them, rotate them, shift them, whatever
So if you flip this guy over, you will get this one over here
And that would not have happened if
you had flipped this one to get this one over here
So you see these 2 by you have
Let me just make it clear
You have this 60 degree angle
Is congruent to this 60 degree angle
You have this side of length 7
Is congruent to this side of length 7
And then you have the 40 degree angle
Is congruent to this 40 degree angle
So once again, these 2 characters are congruent to each other
And we can write
I'll write it where I have to
I'll write it right over here
We can say triangle DEF, triangle DEF is congruent to triangle
And here we have to be careful again
D point D is the vertex for the 60 degrees side
So I'm gonna start it at H
which is the vertex of the 60 degrees side over here,
is congruent to triangle H
And then we went from D to E
E is the vertex on the 40 degrees side
Kind of the other vertex that shares
the 7 length segment right over here
So we wanna go from H to G
HGI
And we know that from angle-side-angle by,
by angle-side-angle
And so that gives us it
That character right over there is
congruent to this character right over here
And then finally we're left with this pool chap
And it looks like it is not congruent to any of them
It is tempting to try to match it up to this one,
especially 'cause the angles here are on the bottom,
and you have the 7 side over here
Angles here on the bottom and the 7 side over here,
but it doesn't match up
because the order of the angles aren't the same
You don't have the same corresponding angles
If you try to do this little exercise,
when you map everything to each other,
you wouldn't be able to do it right over here
And this over here, you know,
it might have been a trick question
or maybe if you did the math,
and this was like a 40 or a 60 degree angle,
maybe then maybe, you could have match this
to some of the other triangles
And maybe some of them to each other,
but this last angle and all of these cases,
40 plus 60 is a hundred
This is going to be an 80 degree angle right over there
They have to add up to an 180
This is an 80 degree angle
If this ended up by the math being a 40
or a 60 degree angle,
then it could have been a little bit more interesting
There might have been other congruent pairs
But this is an 80 degree angle in every case
The other angle is 80 degrees
So this is just alone, unfortunately for him
He is not able to find a congruent companion