Odie the octopus swam home.
He swam at a constant speed.
He plotted how far he'd gone
every 1/7th of a second.
(This is a little typo here, it should be
1/7th of a second on the graph below.)
Not all octopi can create graphs,
but Odie was no ordinary octopus.
And actually, octopi are some of the
smartest creatures on this planet.
What was Odie's speed after...
(after probably dolphins, and and great apes and probably most primates, and, but, but they're still fairly smart, smarter than most fish)
What was Odie's speed in meters per second?
Note we use m/s to show the units
of meters per second.
Meters per second.
Alright, so to figure out speed,
to figure out speed in meters per second,
we essentially need to divide distance in meters,
(distance in meters) divided by time in seconds
(time in seconds).
So let's see if we can pull that off.
So, the easiest thing - let's, let me find a point that I can clearly read how far Odie has traveled.
So it looks like this point right over here. It's clearly that the distance in meters is 4/7ths.
(Let me do that.) So the distance in meters is 4/7ths, so I'll do that in the numerator, the distance in meters -
Gee, I don't like that cont...well, let's just go with this color, even though the contrast with the white background is a little hard on the eye...
...and it took him, it took him 5/7ths of a second...5/7ths of a second to get there.
So 4/7ths meters...
...actually let me make sure I put the units here...
4/7ths meters in...in...5/7ths...
5/7ths seconds.
And so literally we just need to divide 4/7ths by 5/7ths and we're going to get it in meters per second.
So this is going to be the same thing as
4/7ths over 5/7ths
...over 5/7ths meters per second. Meters per second.
And 4/7ths divided by 5/7ths
is the same thing as 4/7ths times 7/5ths.
So let me write that down. So 4/7ths times 7/5ths.
Dividing by fractions is the same thing as
multiplying by it's reciprocal.
So times 7/5ths, and we get...
we get this, well this 7...
This 7 and this 7 cancel out and you get 4 over 5.
You could have also done that by multiplying the numerator and the denominator here by 7.
If you multiply by 7 and multiply by 7
you would get 4/5ths.
But either way, his speed in meters per second is 4/5ths meters per second.