Based on the last two videos we've been able to figure out what a marginal revenue curve looks like
for the monopolist here, for the monopolist in the orange market.This is what we got.
Right over here is a line with a slope twice as, twice as steep as the slope of the main curve.
and we'll see that's actually generalisable. There's an optional video that I'll do very shortly where I'll prove it with a little bit of calculus.
But it is very important to realise that this marginal revenue curve looks very different than the marginal revenue curve if we were dealing with perfect competition.
If we were dealing with perfect competition there would be some equilibrium price in the market and all the competitors would essentially just have to take that price.
So let's say that the equilibrium price was $3 per pound.THen our marginal revenue curve would look like this.
If we were not a monopolist. If we were a one of the many perfect competitiors. I guess you could view it that way.
Because we would have to just take that price. If we wanted to sell 1000 pounds, each of those, each of those pounds
we would get $3 per pound and then if we wanted to sell 1001 we will just get $3 per pound for the next one.
It doesn't change. We are just taking that price.
With the monopolist things do change because we are the only producer in the market.
The price at what which we can get changes depending on what we produce because we are the entire supplier for the market.
And we have this downward sloping marginal revenue curve.
Now with that all the way, let's think about what would be the optimal quantity for us to produce if we wanted to maximise profit.
And if we think in pure economic terms that's what firms try to do.
They try to,their exist to maximise profit and to do that we are going to think about.
Remember it is not to maximise revenue.To maximise revenue we would say oh they should just produce 3000 pounds.
But it is not about maximising revenue. It's about maximising profit we have to take the cost into consideration
and to do that we'll have to draw a marginal cost curve and so let's see i did the research so let's say the owners of this firm
And we have a marginal cost curve that looks something like this.
Let' say our marginal cost curve looks like this.
It is important to realise we are the market.We are the only producers here.
So this isn't just our marginal cost curve. This is the marginal cost curve for the market.
Or in another way to think about it. This is the supply curve for the market.
It tells you in any given price how much the market is going to supply.
You could view as the marginal cost or you could view it as a supply curve and we have talked about it before - you could view a supply curve as a marginal cost curve.
If you want the market to produce one extra pound what's the minimum price you would have to give and that is the marginal cost.
Now with this out of the way let's think about what you would produce.
Well you would definetly, you would definetly want to produce something, you definetly start to produce a few, a few pounds right over here
because the marginal revenue that you are getting is way above your marginal cost/
Each incremental pound you are producing right over here, you are getting much more revenue.
You are getting you know 5 or 6 dollars of revenue it's only costing you a little over a dollar.
SO you just think, ok i'm gonna keep producing, i'm gonna keep producing over here.
Your still, each incremental unit you are getting, you are getting more revenue than the cost of that incremental unit.
And then it keeps being true all the way until you get to, all the way until you get to 2000 pounds right over here.
at this point right over here you don't want to produce an incremental unit.