The speed of light is 3 times 10 to the power 8!! So as you can tell light is very fast.
3 times 10 to the power 8 metres per second.
If it takes 5 time 10 to the second power seconds for light to travel from the sun to the earth.
Lets just think about that a little bit.
So 5 times 10 to the second thats 500.
500 seconds. You have 60 seconds in a minute. So 8 minutes would be 480 seconds
So 500 seconds would be about 8 minutes 20 seconds
So it takes 8 minutes 20 seconds for light to travel from the sun to the earth
What is the distance in metres between
the sun and the earth. So they are giving us a rate, they are giving us a speed, they are giving us a
time and they want to find a distance. So this goes straight back to the standard
distance is equal to rate times time. So they give us the rate.
The rate is 3 times 10 to the 8 metres per second
So its 3 times 10 to the 8 m/s
That right there is the rate
They give us the time
The time is 5 times 10 to the second seconds.
So times 5 times 10 to the second seconds
Seconds use that with an s
So how many metres? What is the distance? What is the distance?
So we can just reassociate these or actually just move these around
from the commutative and dissociative properties of multiplication.
So this right here is the same thing.
And actually you can multiply the units its called dimensional analysis
And when you multiply the units you kind of treat them like
variables. You should get the right dimensions for distance
Lets just rearrange these numbers.
This is equal to 3 times 5