So let's think about how
we could find the slope of the tangent line
to this curve right over here, so what I've drawn in red-
at the point x=a. We've already seen this with the definition of the derivative.
We can try to find a general function that gives us the slope of the tangent line at any point
So let's see we have some arbitrary point - let's define some arbitrary point x right over here
then this would be the point (x,f(x)) and then we could take some x+h - so let's say that this right over here
is the point x+h, so this point
would be (x+h,f(x+h)), we can find the slope of
the secant line, that goes between these two points,
so that would be your change in your vertical,
which would be f(x+h), f of x plus h,
minus f(x), minus f(x), over the change in the horizontal,
which would be x+h minus x, minus x;
and these two x's cancel, so this would be the slope of this secant line,
and if we wanna find the slope of the tangent line at x - the slope of the tangent line at x-
we would just take the limit - the limit of this expression -
as h approaches 0, as h approaches 0, this point moves toward x, and that slope of the
secant line between these two is going to approximate the slope of the tangent at x
And so this right over here - this we would say is equal to f'(x) [f-prime of x]
This is still - this is a function of x! You give me an arbitrary x, where the derivative is defined,
I'm gonna plug it into this, whatever this ends up being, it might be some clean algebraic expression,
and then I'm gonna give you a number. So, for example, if you wanted to find
you, you could calculate this somehow or you could even leave it in this form, and then if you wanted f'(a)
[f-prime of a], you would just substitute a into your function definition,
and you would say, well that's going to be the limit as h approaches 0
of every place you see an x or every place you see an a. I'll stay in this colour for now...
Blank plus h minus, minus - minus f of blank, minus f of blank - all of that over
all of that over h. And I left those blank so I could write the a - I could write the a in red.
Notice every place where I had an x before, it's now an a.
So this is the derivative evaluated at a. So this is one way to find the slope of the tangent line when x=a.
Another way - this often viewed as the alternate form of the derivative - would be to do it directly.
So this is the point (a,f(a)), let's just take another arbitrary point [unintelligible] someplace -
so let's say this is the value x - this point right over here on the function would be (x,f(x)) -
So what's the slope of the secant line between these two points? It would be the change in the vertical,
which would be f(x) minus f(a) - minus f(a)- over a change in the horizontal.
Over x-a. So let me do that in a purple colour - over x minus a.
Now, how could we get a better approximation of the slope of the tangent line here?
Well, we could take the limit as x approaches a, as x gets closer and closer and closer to a,
the secant line slope is going to better and better and better approximate the slope of the tangent line.
This tangent line that I have in red here. So we would wanna take the limit
the limit - as, as x approaches a here. Either way, we're doing a very similar -
we're doing the exact same thing - we're finding the - we're taking the s- we're, we're having an expression
for the slope of a secant line, and then we're bringing those x values of those points closer and closer together,
closer and closer together, so the slopes of those secant lines better and better and better
approximate that slope of the tangent line.
And at the limit, it does become the slope of the tangent line, that is the derivative of - that is the definition of
so this is the cl- the more kind of standard definition of the derivative, if would give you your derivative as a function
of x, and then you can then input your x if you wan- your, your uh - the particular value of x, or you can
use the alternate form of the derivative - if you know that hey, look, I'm just looking to find the derivative exactly at a,
I don't need a general function of f, then you could do this. But they're doing the same thing.