So we have this rectangle right over here,
we call it, the length of AB is equal to 1
So that's labeled right over there, AB is equal to 1
And they tell us that BE and BD trisect angle ABC
So BE and BD trisect angle ABC
So trisect means dividing it into 3 equal angles
So that means that this angel, is equal to this angle,
is equal to that angle
What they want us to figure out is,
what is the perimeter of triangle BED, triangle BED
So it's kinda this middle triangle and the rectangle right over here
So at first it seems like a pretty hard problem,
because you're like, what is the width of this rectangle
how can I start on this, they've given only one side here
They've actually given us a lot of information,
given that we do know that this is a rectangle
We have four sides and then we have four angles,
the sides are all parallel to each other
and the angels are all 90 degrees,
which is more than enough information
to know that this is definitely a rectangle
And so one thing we do know that,
the opposite sides of a rectangle are the same length
This side is 1, then this side over there is 1
The other thing we know is that this angle is trisected
Now we know what the measure of this angle is
It was a right angle, it was a 90 degrees angle
So this divide into 3 equal parts,
that tells us that this angle is 30 degrees
this angle right over is 30 degrees
and this angle right over here is 30 degrees
And now we see we're dealing with a couple of 30, 60, 90 triangles
So this is other side over here needs to be 60 degrees
So that side right over there needs to be 60 degrees
This triangle over here, you have 30, you have 90,
so this was one have to be 60 degrees, you have to add up to 180
30, 60, 90 triangle
30, 60, 90 triangle,
and you can also figure out the measure of this triangle
although its not gonna be a right triangle
But knowing what we know about 30, 60, 90 triangles,
if we just have one side of them
we can actually figure out the other sides
So for example, here, we have the shortest side,
we have the side opposite of 30 degree side,
now whatever, if the 30 degree side is 1
then the 60 degree side is gonna be squared 3 times that
So this length right over here is gonna be squared to 3
And that's pretty useful because now we've figured out
the length of the entire base of this rectangle right over there
Now we just used our knowledge of 30, 60, 90 triangles
if you see, if that was a little bit mysterious,
how I come up with that
I encourage you to watch that video
We know that 30, 60, 90 triangles,
there side are in the range of 1 to the square root of 3 to 2
So this is 1 this is a 30 degree side
this is gonna be square root of 3 times that
and the hypotenuse right over here is going to be 2 times that
So this length over here is going to be 2 times,
the side right over here, so 2 times 1 is just 2
So that's pretty interesting, let's see if we can do something
similar with this side right over here
Here the 1 is not the side opposite of the 30 degree side
Here the 1 is the side opposite of the 60 degree side
This is the 1 opposite the 60 degree side
So once again, if we multiply this side by square root of 3,
we should get this side right over here
This is the 60, remember this 1, so right over here, this 1,
this is the 60 degree side,
so this has to be 1 over square root of 3 of this side
Let me write this down 1 over the square root of 3
And the whole reason, why I was able to get this is well
whatever this side is I multiply it by the square root of 3
I should get this side right over here,
I should get the 60 degree side, the beside the 60 degree angle
or if I take the 60 degree side if I divide it by the square root of 3
I should get the shortest side, the 30 degree side
I start with the 60 degree side, divided by square root of 3,
I get that right over there
And then the hypotenuse is always gonna be twice
the length of the side opposite the 30 degree angle
So this is a side opposite the 30 degree angle,
the hypotenuse is always twice that
It is gonna be 2 over the square root of 3
So we're doing pretty good,
we have to figure out the perimeter of this inner triangle
right over here
We already figured out one length is 2,
we figure out another length is 2 over square roots of 3
And then, all we have to really figure out is what ED is
And we can do that it's because AD
is gonna be the same thing as BC
We know that this entire length,
we're dealing with a rectangle is the square root of 3
This entire length, the entire length of the square root of 3
if this part, this AE is 1 over square root of 3,
then this length right over here, ED is gonna be square root of 3
minus 1 over the square root of 3
That length minus that length over there
And now to find the perimeter is pretty straight forward,
we just have to add these things up and simplify it
So it's gonna be two, so let me write this perimeter
of triangle BED is equal to, this is sort of, perimeter
I just didn't feel writing the whole word,
is equal to two over the square root of 3
plus square root of 3 minus 1 over the square root of 3,
minus 1 over the square root of 3 plus 2
And now this just boils down to simplifying radicals
you can take a calculator out
and get some type of decimal approximation for it
Let's see, we have two square root of 3 minus one square root of 3,
that'll leave us with one, one over the square root of 3
2 square of 1/3, I should say, 2 over square root of 3
minus 1 over square root of 3, 1 over square root of 3,
and then we have plus the square root of 3 plus 2
Now let's see I can rationalize this
if I multiply the numerator
and the denominator by the square root of 3
This would get me the square root of 3
over 3 plus the square root of 3
which is, I can rewrite that as, plus 3 square root of 3 over 3
Right I just multiplied this 3 over 3
Plus 2 and so this give us, this is the drum roll part now
so 1 square root of 3 plus 3 square root of 3
and all that over 3 gives us 4 square roots of 3 over 3 plus 2
Where you can put the 2 first,
some people like to write the non-irrational part
before the irrational part
But we're done we figured out the perimeter
of this inner triangle BED, right there