Let's talk about the acid/base definitions for Bronsted Lowry and also Lewis. So we will start with Bronsted Lowry.
So a Bronsted Lowry acid is a proton donor
A Bronsted Lowry base is a proton acceptor
So lets really quickly review what these definitions mean by protons
So if we look at this diagram right here I am going to draw the hydrogen atom, the most common isotope
So hydrogen has one proton in the nucleus and one electron somewhere around our nucleus, a negative charge like that
And so we would say that this is hydrogen, right? and then we put its one valence electron right there
to represent the hydrogen atom, the most common isotope
If we were to
somehow take away this electron, we would only be left with the proton here, we would only be left with the proton in the nucleus
And so when we talk about a proton, we are talking about the
nucleus of a hydrogen atom which is equal to H+
So, no longer are we talking about the electron
Lets see how this applies to an acid base reaction
and so we start over here with water and then we have HCL over here on the right
Now in this bond between the H and the CL,right? One of those electrons came from the hydrogen and one that came from the chlorine, so let me just go ahead and
draw those in so the one from the hydrogen I am going to put in blue here
and that's this hydrogen, that's this electron from hydrogen right here
in blue
And then for chlorine, I am going to make that electron green
so right in here like that
and so for this acid base
reaction
a lone pair of electrons in the oxygen is going to take this proton, right
So just the nucleus of the hydrogen atom
leaving the electron in blue behind
and that electron in blue stays behind
and ends up on the chlorine
So lets go ahead
and draw what we would form from that
we would have oxygen here the oxygen had two bonds to
hydrogen and the oxygen just picked up another bond to hydrogen
so let me go ahead and mark
those electrons
so these electrons over here in magenta formed
a new bond with a proton
so thats this bond here
and then we had some electrons on oxygen
Let me go ahead and make those in red
So these electrons in red
on the oxygen didn't do anything so they're still there
right here
and that's going to give that oxygen a +1 formal charge
so this is the hydronium ion
H3O+
Our other product we would also make
we would have our chlorine, which had three lone pairs of electrons around it already
and then it picked up both of those electrons so lets go ahead and
mark that one in green that it had originally brought to the dot structure
and also the one in blue, the one it took from hydrogen like that,
so chlorine now has a negative charge
so its really the chloride anion
so this is the Cl-
like that
Lets identify our Bronsted Lowry
acid and our Bronsted Lowry base for this reaction
Lets go back over here and see what happens
the H2O (the water) acted as a proton acceptor
and it accepted a proton from HCL
so water would be