Hi, this is Dr. Mahadev of Stanford school of Medicine
I'm here with my good friend - Salman Khan
We're following up to our ealier discussions about
Cervical spine injuries or neck injuries
and we're going to talk about some of the things you might do
to manage a patient who might have a circular spine injury
in the case that you had to do something in basic;
like manage their airway.
Sal: Right. When we say "manage their airway" they may have something stuck
In their airway or blocking the airway
Dr. Mahadev: Usually the tongue falls back and blocks the airway
but you're right - if the airway's block, you can't get air to your lungs
And if you can't get air to your lungs, you die.
Sal: Right. And you said usually, your tongue falls back.
What is that?
Dr. Mahadev: When you're unconcious, the muscles that control your tongue
relax, because when you're unconcious, your tongue falls back