In the last video we talked a little bit about what inflation is in the Consumer Price Index
and i thought i will actually show you data and maybe point out a few interesting things right over here
so this right over here is the monthly press-release, there is a table from the monthly press-release
issued by the Bureau of Labor Statistics and this is Table A which is really a summary of all the important things
it's the changes in CPI for all urban consumers
the CPI-U
and they do it for non- or urban consumers and all the rest
but the CPI that is quoted is the one for urban consumers
the US city average
I always find that the details are much more interesting
than what you hear just on the news
when people say "oh, the CPI changed by 0.5 per cent"
and one thing I do wanna point out and this is true of the CPI
this is true of all government statistics,
and frankly this is true of any report that any company gives you,
it's very important to keep in mind
whether they're giving a sequential change
or whether they're giving a year over year change
so, for example, there might be a press release like this one
and the text of it or maybe the headline number when you look at your local newspaper
or your news report would say
"look, in June 2011 inflation on all items, on the entire basket of goods went down by 0.2 per cent"
and you might say "oh wow, look, there's no inflation, in fact the prices are going down,
"this would be minor deflation"
but it's important to realise that this is only the seasonally adjusted prices from May to June
and when I talk about seasonally adjusted is that
traditionally maybe people use a different amount of energy, a different amount of gasoline from May to June
and they try to factor that in when they compare the price of the basket of goods
from May to June, so that's what they talk about "seasonally adjusting"
but if you look over here, the prices went down from May to June
adjusting it for the season,
but the year over year changes are still up
if you compare June 2011 to June 2010, it is still up by 3.6 per cent
and in general, the monthly things are going to be a little bit more volatile,
obviously with the seasonal adjustments you have other short-term factors that might change it,
but the year over year one is a stronger signal for what is actually happening with inflation
although someone might wanna pay attention to the monthly one,
because that's obviously giving you kind of the most up-to-date of what's happening now
and what you'll often see is they'll give an inflation number for everything
and then they'll subtract out actually food and energy,
so this is all items less food, less energy
and as for food energy, they represent a good bit of the basket but the'yre very, very volatile
you can see it right here in this report
year over year energy has gone up double digits
20 per cent for energy generally
if you look at fuel oil - 35.6 per cent
at least in this report, it's been coming down more recently,
but year over year it's been up a huge amount
and that's actually the main driving factor for this 3.6 per cent
if you take food and energy out of the equation,
if you compare the basket of goods minus that,
inflation was only up 1.6 per cent
it is interesting, even within that you can look at which parts of the economy
or which products and services are getting a lot more expensive and which ones are getting cheaper
it is actually really interesting that used cars and trucks are up 5.1 per cent
that seems like a pretty strong price increase for used things