let ABC be a triangle
such that
angle ACB equals pi/6
this is A,B,C
and this angle over here is pi/6
assuming it is in radians
and they tell us a,b,c
denote the lengths of sides opposite to
A,B,C RESPECTIVELY
values of x for which a equals this thing
b equals this thing and c equals this thing
we need to find a relation between a,b,c
once we get the relation,we can substitute
with these expressions and solve for x
first i think is how to relate a,b,c with the angle here
what should pop out into ur brain is law of cosines
law of cosines
that tells us c squared equals
a squared plus b squared and it is essentially the pythagorean theorem
but this just is not a right triangle
minus 2a*bcosine of
c , now in this case
angle c right here is angle ACB
this over here is going to be
30 degrees,so what is cosine of 30 degrees
if just in case u forgot it
in iit-jee exam all u need in terms of time
this is 30 degrees
that is 1 this is one half,the side opposite to
30 degrees,this is 60 degrees,this gonna be a 30,60,90
this is square root of 3 over two,cosine is adjacent
over hypotenuse,so square root of three over 2 over one
so this in this example it is going to be
c squared equal to a squared
plus b squared minus
2ab and this whole thing is square root of 3 over 2
times square root of three over 2 and these
twos get cancel out,we get c squared equals
a squared plus b squared minus square root3 into ab
now the next thing i want to do is that
substitute this for a and substitute this for b
and then for c i want to substitute
this expression right over here,but i have to be careful
i want to make sure it is in the form something that i can simplify
i take this x squared plus xplus 1 if i
if i square this iam going to end in some fourth power and this b iam
going to end up in a 4th power,then in have a business of square root of 3
so let us see,atleast we can