In the last video, we talked about how the Serbians
were able to hold back the Austro-Hungarians
at the beginning of World War I.
But eventually they had to give in.
They were essentially –
They couldn't hold up against the combined forces
of the Bulgarians, the Austro-Hungarians,
and the Germans.
And they were able to roll through in 1915.
And then we have to wait until 1918
for the Allies to essentially recapture Serbia.
Now what is noteworthy –
There are many noteworthy things in World War I.
And, obviously, we can't cover all of them.
is just what a [devastating] loss World War I
was to the Serbian people.
Just as a little bit of context –
[Serbia was a] very small country.
We're talking 4.5 million people,
as we enter into World War I,
with a reasonably [large army].
I guess, relative to the size of the country,
it was a decent-sized army.
But with an army on the order of –
we're talking on the order of 400,000 soldiers.
And this was pretty much [everyone].
Everyone in the country who could be in the army
was, essentially, in the army.
Over the course of the Serbian campaign,
and the Macedonian Front, you, essentially,
have the Serbian army getting decimated.
60% of the Serbian army dies.
60% – roughly 60% of the Serbian army is killed.
And even from a population point of view,
the Serbian population is reduced by 16%.
16% of the Serbian population –
civilian and military –
is dead by the end of World War I.
So a lot of countries suffered horribly
during World War I –
there were many notable ones –
France – the Russian Empire –
We could go on and on and on.
But it would be hard to argue
that any country suffered more
than what the Serbians did.
60% of their military dead,
[as well as] 16% of their [overall] population.