Now this is our solution.
First, Alice and Bob agree publicly on a prime modulist
and a generator.
In this case, 17 and 3.
Then, Alice selects a private random number, say 15, and calculates:
3 to the power 15 mod 17, and sends this result
publicly to Bob.
Then Bob selects his private random number, say 13, and calculates:
3 to the power 13 mod 17, and sends this result
publicly to Alice.
And now the hard of the trick.
Alice takes Bob's public result and rasies
it to the power of her private number
to obtain the shared secret which in this case is 10.
Bob takes Alice's public result and rasies
it to the power of his private number, resulting
in the same shared secret.
Notice they did the same calculation, though it might not look like it at first.
Consider Alice. The 12 she received from Bob was calculated as 3 to the power 13 mod 17.
So her calculation was the same as 3 to the power 13, to the power 15 mod 17.
Now consider Bob. The 6 he received from Alice was calculated as 3 to the power 15 mod 17.
So his calculation was the same as 3 to the power 15, to the power 13.
Notice they did the same calculation with the exponents in a different order.
When you flip the exponent the result doesn't change.
So they both calculated 3 raised to the power of their private numbers.