So we talked about inhaling and exhaling.
And I mentioned that the key first step
for both of them is kind of
the change in volume: going up in volume
and going down in volume.
But I didn't really talk about how that happens exactly.
So, I'll kind of jump into that now.
And let me begin by telling you that
in the middle of your chess,
you have this enormous kind of bone that goes down.
I'm drawing it out of proportion
just to make it very clear
where the bone is being.
Go ahead and feel on your own body
this bone which we called
either the breast bone or the more
technical name is sternum.
Write that down here.
The sternum is this middle bone and
all the ribs on both sides attached there.
So, you've got a total of 14 ribs and 7 pairs of them.
Actually, I should say 14 pairs of ribs.
I don't want you to think there're 14 in total.
There are actually 14 in total and 7 pairs of the ribs.
So 14 ribs actually attached directly
to this bone, the sternum bone.
So in white, these are the ribs.
And between the ribs, you actually have muscles.
So I'm gonna draw some of these muscles
between the ribs.
And these muscles are all going to have
their own nerve
that allows them to contract.
So, these muscles are controlled
by your body or your brain.
And their name, let me just jot down here on the side,
is "intercostal muscle".
And "inter" just means "between".
So, this is the name of the muscle.
And "costal" refers to the ribs.
So, when you see that word "costal",
you'll know we're talking about the ribs.
So what's between the ribs is these muscles:
intercostal muscles.
And they're gonna start moving outwards
when your brain says,
"hey I want to take a deep breath!"
So, these muscles are going to contract
and the ribs are gonna move outwards.
So these go out. And you also have...
Let me just make a little bit of space on this xxx.
You also have another muscle
that kind of right down here.
And it has kind of a an upside down U shape to it.
So I'm drawing it kind of like a dome.
You can think of it as a dome.
And this dome is the floor. If you remember,
we talked about the floor of the thorax.
So this is of course, our diaphram muscle.
So, you've got a diaphragm muscle.
And this one when it contracts, it's gonna go...
instead of going out, it's gonna go down.
So it's gonna kind of flatten out.
And I can actually draw this if you just
stick with me for a moment.
I'm gonna erase this dome-like shape.
And I'm gonna draw it when it looks like as it's contract.
So when it contracts, this is actually
going to be more flat.
And this flat diaphragm, as you can see, is now
further down that it used to be.
And as it goes down, all of the structures
that are inside the space, so the two lungs,
and of course, I didn't draw the heart here,
but the heart would be this kind of this cardiac notch.
If you want me to, I can even draw that heart here.
This is our heart here.
They're all going to kind of physically moved down.
So this is our heart and our lungs.
They are physically gonna be kind of drawn downwards and out.
They're gonna also move out as
the intercostal muscles move out.
So you have expansion of these lungs,
that's basically the idea.
And if you kind of zoom in on this,
to kind of see exactly what this expansion looks like,
when I say, you know, you have more volume, the lungs,
really what I should be saying,
if I want to be more exact,
is that all the alveoli, if these are the alveoli,
let's say this is another branch,
this is another alveolar right here;
all these alveoli, they are actually expanding.
And you have about 500 million alveoli.
You can just kind of fathom how big a number that it is.
It's an enormous number of alveoli.
If I was actually drawing them here... drawing forever, right?
It'll take forever to kind of write out
this many different alveoli.
But basically what happens is that, when the ribs go out,
the diaphragm moves down.
These alveoli are actually being pulled out.
They are actually pulled outwards.
So they are actually gonna be getting larger in size.
They literally look like they've grown in size.
And, this is what they look like.
And actually, if you take even a closer look,
you'll see that these alveoli have around them,
a bunch of protein.
The cells around them have a bunch of protein.
And this protein is called "elastin".
And you can guess what elastin might do.
It has kind of a similar sound to the word "elastic".
Elastin is basically kind of like a rubber band.
So you kind of thinking of elastin as a rubber band.
And, when the muscles move down and out,
and the alveoli pulled open,
let me actually kind of scroll up,
because you can kind of go back to the idea of inhaling.
What is happening? Well, we have
a couple things happening.
One, you have muscles contracting. Muscles contract.
And when I say "muscles", you know I'm talking about
all those intercostal muscles in your diaphragm.
And as a result of the muscles contracting,
you have now the alveoli, alveoli are streched open.
So those rubber bands are elastin, protein,
are literally physically being stretched open.
So the alveoli are stretched open.
And keep that in mind, because
what's gonna happen then is,
when the muscles relax, which is
what happens when you exhale,
when the muscles relax,
what do you think is going to happen to that elastin?
Well, it's like a rubber band,
if that's what I'm saying, it's gonna be like,
then the alveoli are going to recoil.
They are gonna recoil.
And that's actually the driving force for
why the volume goes back down.
So if you have a bunch of rubber bands
that you're stretching out...
Let me actually bring up the picture
so you'll see really clearly.
If you're physically kind of using your muscles
to help pull this stuff open,
then the moment that you start pulling open,
the moment that you,
you know, stop contracting those muscles,
now you have a nice big volume.
What's gonna happen?
All these elastin molecules are gonna snap back.
We'll do it with a different color.
I'll do it with this color.
They are gonna snap back like this.
All that protein are gonna snap back into
kind of the original size.
And when they do, this thing gets smaller.
So my alveoli kind of goes back to its original size,
which is much smaller than this.
Let me actually show you that
even though contraction is what opens up things
it's the recoil that kind of brings things back down
to their normal size.
Let me erase this to make it kind of neater drawing.
So you can see it now, inhaling, the way that
we actually increase the volume,
is by pulling things open through contraction.
And this actually requires energy, right?
Remember, you can't contract a muscle
without spending chemical energy.
So this takes chemical energy.
And we usually think of this molecule ATP
as the specific type of chemical energy
we're gonna use.
And to exhale, when you reduce the volume,
it's gonna be driven by this elastic recoil.
So that's a type of elastic potential energy.
So, this process of kind of inhaling and exhaling
is really a little different from each other.
On the one hand, you're using ATP;
you're actually burning through these molecules.
And when you exhale,
you're actually not using chemical energy anymore.
You're just using that elastic potential energy,
kind of the same sort of energy that you can imagine
you would have if you snap a rubber band.
So, let's stop there. We'll pick up the next video.