Lets say I'm trying to judge how many years of experience we have at the Khan Academy
Or on average how many years of experience we have, and in particular, the particular
type of average we'll focus on is the arithmetic mean.
So I go and I survey the folks there, and let's say this is when, Khan academy was a smaller organization
when there were only five people in the organization, and I find, and I'm surveying the entire population
So years of experience, the entire population of Khan academy, because that's what I care about
Years of experience at our organization- at Khan Academy, and this is when we had 5 people-
And I were to go, we're now 36 people, I don't wanna date this video too much,
but let's say I go and I say "ok there's one person straight out of college
that one year of experience, or recently out of college, somebody with three years of experience,
someone with five years of experience, someone with seven year of experience,
and someone very experienced, or reasonably experienced with 14 years of experience
So based on this data point, and this is our population for years of experience, so I'm assuming that we only have
five people at the organization at this point, what would be the population
mean for the years of experience, what is the mean years of experience for my population
well we can just calculate that, our mean years of experience, and I'm going to
denote it with mu, because we're talking about the population now, this is a parameter
for the population, its going to be equal to the sum from our first data point,
so data point one, all the way to data point, in this case, data point five
we have five data points, of each of - so we're gonna take all five from the first data point,
the second data point, the third data point, all the way to the fifth,
so this is going to be equal to x1 plus, oh no I'm going to divide it all by the number of data points I have
plus x2 plus x3 plus x4 plus x sub 5
all of that over five, and as we said this is a very fancy way of saying "I'm going to sum up all
these things and then divide by the number of things we have," so let's do that
Get the calculator out, so I'm going to add them all up, one plus three plus five, plus seven plus fourteen,
so that's five data points and I'm gonna divide by five, and I get six
So the population mean for years of experience at my organization is six, six years of experience
Well that's, I guess interesting, but now I wanna ask another question, I wanna get some
measure of how much spread there is around that mean, or how much do the data points
vary around that mean, and obviously I can give someone all the data points
but instead I wanna come up with a parameter that somehow represents how much
all of these things on average are varying from this number right here, or maybe I
will call that thing the 'variance', so the variance
this is a population variance that I'm talking about, just to be clear, it's a parameter
The population variance I'm going to denote with the Greek letter Sigma, lowercase sigma squared
And I'm going to say, well I'm gonna take the distance from each of these points to the mean, and just
so I get a positive value I'm going to square it and then I'm gonna divide by the number of data points
so essentially I'm gonna find the average squared distance, now that might sound very complicated
but let's actually work it out, so I'll take my first data point, I'll take that data point and I will subtract
our mean from it, so this is going to give me a negative number, but if I square it's going to be
positive, so essentially it's going to be the squared distance between one and my mean,
and then to that I'm going to add the squared distance between three and my mean
And to that I'm going to add the squared distance between five and my mean,
and since I'm squaring it doesn't matter if I do five minus six or six minus five
when I square it I'm going to get a positive result regardless
and then to that I'm going to add the squared distance between seven and my mean, so seven minus six squared
all of this, this is my population mean that I'm finding the difference between
and then finally, the squared difference between 14 and my mean, and then
I'm going to find essentially the mean of these squared distances, so I have five squared
distances right over here, so let me divide by five
so what will I get when I make this calculation right over here.
Well let's figure this out, this is going to be equal to (1-6) is negative 5, negative 5 squared is 25
(3-6) is negative 3, if I square that I get nine
(5-6) is negative one, if square it I get positive 1
(7-6) is 1, if I square it I get positive 1
and (14-6) is 8, if I square it I get 64, then I'm gonna divide all of that by 5.
And I don't need to use a calculator but I tend to make a lot of careless mistakes when I do things
while I'm making a video, so I get: 25+9+1+1+64 divided by 5 so I get 20
So the average squared distance, or the mean squared distance from our population mean
is equal to 20, you might say "wait these aren't 20 away," remember it's squared distance away
from my population mean so I squared each of these things I like to because I made it positive, and
we'll see later it has other nice properties about it, now the last thing is - how can we represent this
mathematically? We already saw that we know how to represent a population mean and a sample mean
mathematically like this, and hopefully we don't find it that daunting anymore
but how would we do the exact same thing, how would we denote what we did right over here
Well let's just think it through, we're just saying that the population variance,
we're taking the sum of each, so we're gonna take each item, we'll start with the first item
and we're gonna go to the nth item in our population, we're talking about population here
and we're gonna take, we're not gonna just take the item, this would just be the item, but we're gonna take
the item and from that we're gonna subtract the population mean, we're gonna square it, so
the way I've written it right now, this would just be the numerator, I've just taken the sum of each of these things
the sum, the difference between each data point and the population mean and squared it
If I really wanna get the way I figured out this variance right over here, I have to divide the whole
thing by the number of data points we have, So this might seen very daunting and
very intimidating, but all it says is: Take each of your data points, well one it says figure out your population mean
figure that out first, and then from each data point in your population, subtract out that population mean
square it, take the sum of all of those things, and then just divide by the number of data points you have
And you will get your population variance.