Right, what I have right in front of me is the Khan Academy measuring angles,
measuring angles exercise. I have a small part of it in this screen right over here.
And it's a pretty cool exercise cause it has this little
virtual protracter that we can use to actually measure angles.
And I wanna give credit to the, the person who built
this protracter, cause I think it's pretty neat. Omar Rizwan,
who's actually a high school interim made this, made this
pretty neat module. And so in general, when you wanna
measure an angle, what you wanna do is you wanna put the
center of your protracter at the center of well actually,
I said the vertex of the angle at the center of the protracter,
and then, what you wanna do is, either rotate the angle or rotate the protractor
in this case you are going to rotate the protractor
you wanna rotate the protracor so that the zero angle
are look at the zero mark is at one of the sides
of the angle and the other side of the angle is within the protractor
so lets,try to do that so if may be ,if you wanna do that
this zero side it should be at this side of the angle
so lets,rotate it
lets rotate it that way,
its keep rotating it
i can keep it press thats better
alright ,thats looks about right so,
one side, is that zero mark and then my angle my other side
are if there is a way
points 2 looks like pretty cause to the 20˚ mark
so i would type the range of the screen you are seeing that
and that is the right answer
and we can get the other angle
so lets,try the measure this one right over here
so,once again place the center of the protractor
at the center at the vertex of an angle
we can place the zero degree the base of the protractor at this side of the angle
so we should rotate it a little bit
we want to do one more time that , looks about right
and the angle is now opening up
this is the other side of point to 110 degrees
is this larger than 90 degree its also an obtuse angle.
the last one is an acute angle,this is obtuse
angle 110 degrees more than 90 degrees,we typed in
i got the right answer
just do couple of more than these
so,once again put the center the protractor at the vertex of an angle
now i want to rotate it ,there we go, and this looks liking roughly
an 80 degree angle but,if i am really precise
81 or 82 degrees and 80 is my best guess
lets do one more of these. Vertex of my angle
at the center of my protractor.and I want to put one
side of my angle at 0 degrees. here are two ways
to do this, you could do just this, this is not too
helpful as the angle is outside the protractor.
So lets keep rotating it, so our other side points to
70 degrees, so it is an acute angle.
I will leave you with that.