In this video we will talk about what the chi squared distribution is. Chi squared distribution
sometimes called the chi-squared distribution. And in the next few videos, we will actually use it to test how well
theoretical distributions explain observed ones, or, how good a fit
observed results are for theoretical distributions. So lets just think about it a little bit, lets say
I have some random variables. And each of them are independent standard
normally distributed random variables. let me just remind you what that means, so lets just say I have
I have the random variable X. If X is normally distributed
we could write that X is a normal random variable with a mean
of 0 and a variance of 1 or you can say that the mean expected value of X is equal to 0
or in that the variance of our random variable X is equal to 1. Or, just to visualize it
is that we are sampling when we take an instantiation of this variable
we are sampling from a normal distribution a standardized normal
distribution that looks like this. Mean of 0 and then a variance of 1 which would also mean the standard
deviation of 1.
So this could be the standard deviation, or , variance, or the standard deviation that would be equal to 1
so a chi-squared distribution, if you just take one of these random variables
and you, let me just define it this way, let me take a new random variable
let me define a new random variable Q, let me define a new random variable Q that is equal to you essentially sampling
from this standard normal distribution and squaring whatever number you got.
so it is equal to this random variable X squared, it is equal to that random variable X squared
the dist for this random variable right here is going to be an example
of the chi-squared distribution, actually what we are going to see in this video is that the
chi-squared distribution is actually a set of distributions depending on how many sums you have
right now we only have 1 random variable that we are squaring so this is just one of the examples
that we will talk more about them in a second. This right here, this we could write that Q is a chi-squared distributed random variable
or that we could use this notation right here Q is, we could write it like this
this isn't an X anymore this is the greek letter chi although it looks alot like a curvy X
so its a member of chi-squared and since we are only taking one sum over here
here, we are only taking the sum of on 1 independent normally distributed standard normally distributed variable we say
that this has only 1 degree of freedom. and we write that over here
so this right here is our is our degree of freedom
we have one degree of freedom over there. now if we define
lets call this Q1, let's say we have another random variable - lets call it Q - we need a diff color, let me do Q2 in blue
lets say I have another random variable Q2 that is defined as, lets say I have 1 independent normally distributed variable I'll call that
X1 and then I'll square it. and then I have another independent standard or is guess you could call it standard normal
distributed variable X2 and then I square it. And you could imagine that both of these guys have distributions like
this and they are both independent and so to get to sample Q2 you essentially sample X1 from this distribution square that value,
sample X2 from the same distribution essentially square that value then add the two and then you are going to get Q2
this over here, here we would write Q1. Q2 here we would write is a chi-square distributed random variable with 2 degrees of freedom.
Two degrees of freedom and just to visualize the set of chi-squared distributions
lets look at this over here. So this, I got this off of wikipedia, this shows us some of the probability densities
functions for some of the chi-squared distributions. This first one over here for K of equal 1
that's the degrees of freedom so this essssentually our Q1. This is our probability density
function for Q1 and notice it really spikes close to 0 and that makes sense. If you were sampling just once from this standard norm dist
there's a very high likelyhood that your going to get something pretty close to 0
and then if you square something close to 0, remember these are decimals
they are going to be less than 1 pretty close to 0 its going to become even smaller
so you have a high prob of getting a very small value you have a high prob of getting
values less than some threshold, this right here less than is guess this is 1 right here
so then one half and then you have a very low prob of getting a large number. To get
a 4 you would have to sample a 2, you would have to sample a 2 from this distribution and we know that 2 is
actually its 2 variences or two standard deviations from the mean, so its less likely
and acutally thats - thats to get a 4 so to get an even larger numbers its going to be even less likely
so thats why you see this shape over here. now when you have 2
degrees of freedom it moderates a little bit this is the shape for, this blue line right here is the
shape of Q2 and notice that your are a little bit less likely to get values close to 0
and a little bit more liekly to get numbers further out
but its still kinds shifted of weightrd towards small numbers
then if we had another random variable and other chi-squared distributed random variable so then we have
lets say Q3 and lets deffing it as sum f three indipenedient variables
each of them would have a stand norm dist so X1, X squared plus X3 squared then all the sudden
our Q3, this is Q2 here, has a chi-squared distribution of 3 degrees of freedom so this guy right over here
that will be this green line. Maybe I should have done this
in green, this will be this green line over here and then notice that it is becoming a little more likely
that you get values in this range over here.
because you are taking the sum, each of these are going to be pretty small values, but you are taking the
sum so it starts to shift it over to the right. So the more degrees of freedom you have
the further this lump starts to move to the right. and to some degree
the more symmetric it gets and whats interesting about this
i guess its almost different than any other distribution,
we have looked at, although we have looked at others that have
this property as well, is that you cant have a value below 0
because we are always squaring these values each
these guys can have values below zero, they are normally distributed, they can have negative values
but since we are squaring and taking the sum of squares
this is always going to be positive.
The place that this is going to be useful, and we are going to see in the next
few videos is in measuring, essentially error from an expected value
and if you take the total error, you can figure out the probability of getting that error
from, if you hold some parameters, or if you assume some parameters
we'll talk more about that in the next video
Now with that said, I just want to show you how to read
a chi-squared distribution table. So if I were to ask you, if I were to ask you
if this is our distribution, let me pick this blue one right here
so over here we have 2 degrees of freedom for adding two of these guys right here
if i were to ask you, what is the probability
what is the probability, of, what is the probability of
Q2 being greater than, Q2 being greater than. Let me
put it this way. What is the probability of Q2 being greater than
2.41? And I'm picking that value for a reason.
so I want the probability of Q2 being greater than 2.41
what I want to do is, ill look at a, ill look at a chi-squared table
like this. Q2 is a version of chi-squared with 2 degrees of freedom
so i look at this row right here under 2 degrees of freedom
and I want the probability of getting a value
above 2.41 and i picked 2.41 because it is actually
at this table. And so most of these chi-squared
the reason why we have these weird numbers
like this instead of whole numbers
or easy to read fractions is its actually
driven by the p value its driven by the probability
of getting something larger than that value
so normally you would look at it the other way
you would say, ok if i want to say what, what chi-squared value
for 2 degrees of freedom there's a 30% chance of getting
something larger than that, then i would look up 2.41
buyt im doing it the other way just for the sake of this video
so if i want the probability of getting, of this random variable right here
being greater thaan 2.41, of being greater than 2.41 or its p value
we read it right here, it is 30% and just to visualize it on this chart
this chi-squared distribution, this Q2 the blue one
over here 2.41 is going to sit, lets see this is three
this is 2.5 so 2.41 is going to be someplace right around
here, so essentially what that table is telling us
is this entire area, this entire area, under, under this blue
line right here. what is that? and that right there is going
to be 30% of, well its going to be .3, or you can view
it as 30% of the entire area under this curve
because obviously all the probabilites have to add up to 1.
so that's our intro to chi-squared distribution. In the next video we are
actually going to use it to make some, or to test some
inferences