Let's say that f(x) is equal to x^2 + x - 6/x - 2.
And we're curious about what the limit of f(x)
as x approaches 2 is equal to.
Now, the first attempt that you might want to do,
right when you see something like this,
is just see what happens, what is f(2)?
Now, this won't always be the limit,
even if it is defined.
But it is a good place to start,
just to see if something reasonable could pop out.
So looking at it this way, if we just evaluate f(2),
in our numerator, we're going to get 2^2 + 2 - 6.
So, that's going to be 4 + 2, which is 6, - 6.
So you're going to get 0 in the numerator,
and you're going to get 0 in the denominator.
So, we don't have – the function is not defined at x = 2.
WRITING: f not defined.
So there's no simple thing there.
Even if this did evaluate, if it was a continuous function,
then actually the limit would be whatever the function is.
But that isn't necessarily the case.
But we see very clearly that the function is not defined here.
So, let's see if we can simplify this.
And we'll also try to graph it in some way.
So one thing that might have jumped out at your head is
you might want to factor this expression on top.
So, if we want to rewrite this,
we could rewrite the top expression –
(And this just goes back to your Algebra I.)
Two numbers whose product is -6 and whose sum is +3 –
Well, that could be + 3 and -2.
So this could be x + 3 × x - 2, all of that over x - 2.
So, as long as x does not equal 2,
these two things will cancel out.
So we could say this is equal to x + 3
for all x's except for x = 2, as long as x does not equal 2.
So that's another way of looking at it.
Now, another way we could rewrite our f(x) –
(I'll do it in blue, just to change the colors.)
– we could rewrite f(x) – this is the exact same function –
f(x) is equal to x + 3 when x does not equal 2.
And we could even say it's undefined when x = 2.
So given this definition, it becomes much clearer to us
how we can actually graph f(x).
So let's try to do it.
DRAWING: (So that is not anywhere near being a straight line.
That is much better.)
Let's call this the y axis.
We'll call it y = f(x).
And then let's, over here, let me make
a horizontal line that is my x axis.
So defined this way, f(x) = x + 3.
So if this is 1, 2, 3, we have a y-intercept at 3,
and then the slope is 1.
But it's defined for all x's except for x = 2.
So this is x = 1, this is x = 2.
So when x = 2, it is undefined.
So let me make sure I can –
So it's undefined right over there.
DRAWING: So it's undefined right over there.
So this is what f(x) looks like.
Now, given this, let's try to answer our question.
What is the limit of f(x) as x approaches 2?
Well, we could look at this graphically.
As x approaches 2 from lower values than 2 –
(So this, right over here, is x = 2.)
If we get to maybe, let's say this is 1.7,
we see that our f(x) is right over there.
If we get to 1. 9, our f(x) is right over there.
So it seems to be approaching this value right over there.
Similarly, as we approach 2 from values greater than it,
if we're at like – I don't know – this could be, like, 2.5 –
our f(x) is right over there.
If we get even closer to 2, our f(x) is right over there.
And once again, we look like we are approaching this value.
Or, another way of thinking about it,
if we ride this line from the positive direction,
we seem to be approaching this value for f(x).
If we ride this line from the negative direction –
from values less than 2 –
we seem to be approaching this value right over here.
And this is essentially the value of x + 3 if we set x = 2.
So, this is essentially going to be –
this value right over here is equal to 5
if we just look at it visually.
If we just graphed a line with slope 1, with a y-intercept of 3,
this value right over here is 5.
Now, we can also try to do this numerically.
So let's try to do that.
So, if this is our function definition –
completely identical to our original definition,
then we just try values as x gets closer and closer to 2.
So let's try values less than 2.
So, 1.99999 –
(This is almost obvious.)
1.999 + 3, well that gets you pretty darned close to 5.
If I put even more 9's here, and get even closer to 2,
we'd get even closer to 5 here.
If we approach 2 from the positive direction –
And then, once again, we're getting
closer and closer to 5 from the positive direction.
If we were even closer to 2, we'd be even closer to 5.
So, whether we look at it numerically,
or we look at it graphically, it looks pretty clear
that the limit here is going to be equal to 5.