Let A=(0,0) and B=(b,2) be points on the coordinate plane.
Let ABCDEF be a convex Equilateral hexagon.
So convex means it's not concave,a concave hexagon would look like this
so that's two sides, three, four, five, six,
this would be a concave hexagon,
this is going to be popped out
and all the sides are going to be equal,
so it's equilateral hexagon.
They're not telling us it's a regular hexagon,
so we don't know that all of the angles are going to be the same
but all the sides will be the same.
then they show us a bunch of sides that are parallel to each other
and that the y-coordinates of its vertices are
distinct elements of the set 0,2,4,6,8,10.
The area of the hexagon can be written in the form m square root of n
where m and n are positive integers
and n is not divisible by the square of any prime.
That's just a fancy way of saying that
we've simplified this radical as much as possible.
Find m plus n.
So really the first part let's just make sure
we can visualize this hexagon.
So let me draw, we know one point one vertex for sure zero zero,
so let me draw my x-axis, that is my x-axis right over there
and then my y axis, my y axis will look like that.
y axis, we know that the vertex A sits at the point (0,0),
that is the vertex A.
Now we know that all the vertices have y-coordinates that
are either zero two four six eight ten,
and they're distinct members of the set
which means no two of the vertices share the same y-coordinates.
They are not going to be on the same horizontal line.
So let me draw these words on lines.
With the x-axis is a zero
then you have Y is equal to two,
then you have four, and you have six, and then you have eight,
and then you have ten up here.
Now B we already know. So first we've already used up the zero for A,
A is already using up the zero.
B uses up the two they tell us, that the y-coordinate of B is two.
The y-coordinate of B is two, so we use that as well
let me see if I can draw a B over here.
Let me see if I can draw a B sits on the horizontal some place,
and we - the hexagon has side length s
we don't know what that length is but they're all the same,
so let's call this s, it can help me think about it,
now that I know that this is equilateral hexagon,
all the sides are going to be the same length,
and so we're going to go out here,
we're going to go out here the (b,2),
we don't know what b is but that is our vertex B.
Now F is the other vertex that is connected to A.
F cannot sit on this horizontal, cannot sit on y is equal to two,
it can't sit on y is equal to six
because this distance would be super far,
clearly much further than this distance over here
where actually you could have that,
but then you wouldn't be able to draw a really a convex hexagon.
so y,the next vertex is just going to have to sit on this horizontal,
so it's going to be s away,
so it's going to be s away, maybe it will be something like that,
something like that, so let me draw it,
so that is the next vertex, that is vertex F Right?
Because we're going ABCDEF and then back to A.
Fair enough, now what about vertex C.
well vertex C can't be on the four horizontal
so it gonna have to be on the six horizontal.
So vertex C is going to have to be some place like that,
Some place like that, that's vertex C.
Once again that length is s, this length is s,
now what about vertex E?
can't be on the six horizontal now already taken up by vertex C
so the four and the six are already taken up,
so has to be at the at the eight horizontal.
And so this is length s.
And we also know that we're going back to the origin now.
so this is vertex E right here,
we know that we're going back to the origin,
not to the origin we are going back to the same x value,
this is going to be on the y intercept
and the reason why we know that is this is length s,
and this is length s and they both have to,
both of these diagonals travel the same,
they travel the same vertical distance, this base is four,
this base is four,so you can kind of view this is two right triangles,
both of them have base four and hypotenuse s,
and so they share this side right over here
so they both - this one goes out to the left that distance
and this one is going to come back that distance.
Now by the same logic over here,
this guy's going to have to come back
so he's - we can now use the ten coordinate,
the ten y horizontal or the y coordinate of ten
that's the only one we haven't used yet for D,
and since we came out,
when we had a diagonal of length s,
traveling four up,
this time same logic, we had a diagonal length s,
it traveled up four over here and moved out this distance
then we go back at the other direction and traveling up four,
and you're gonna go back in the same direction
so this is going to be directly on top of B.
so the coordinate for D is actually going to be b comma ten,
the y coordinate here is ten.
And there we have our hexagon,
we're done drawing our actual hexagon.
and all this parallel line information they told us is that
AB is parallel to DE,
so AB is parallel to DE and this is kind of obvious here.
BC is parallel to EF,
BC is parallel to EF.
and they say CD is parallel to FA, so CD
is parallel to FA and the way we drew it looks pretty clear
that is the case.
Now we define the area,
we defined the area of this hexagon
and it seems like a good starting point,
would be to figure out what s is
and to figure out what s is,
it's really going to be a function of
how much we've inclined this thing. So let's -
let's draw, you can see that this is an equiangular hexagon
that this is kind of skewed, is kind of, we distorted a little bit
but all the sides are of the same length.
So let's just call this theta,
let's call that angle right over there theta,
and they tell us that the angle FAB is 120 degrees,
FAB is a hundred and twenty degrees
that is a hundred and twenty degrees.
So this angle over here on the left,
this angle over here on the left is going to be 180 minus one twenty,
minus theta. So 180 minus one twenty is sixty
So this single over here sixty minus theta.
The reason I did that is because we have some information,
we know that we traveled up four over here,
and we know that we traveled up two over here
and maybe we could use that information to solve for s
because s is the hypotenuse of both of these right triangles
that I just constructed. Let me draw them.
So this right triangle right over here I could draw like this,
I could draw like this. So I have s,
I have theta and I have 2,that's this right triangle right over here.
This right triangle looks like this,
it looks like this, this is,
this angle is sixty minus theta,
and this height over here is four
So let's see what we can do to solve for s.
This triangle on the left or is on the right over here,
this triangle says that
If we take the sine of theta,
the sine of theta is equal to the opposite over the hypotenuse,
is equal to two over s, this triangle tells us that the sine,
remember this hypotenuse over here is also s,
the sine of sixty minus theta,
the sine of sixty minus theta is equal to four over s.
And if you want set these equal to each other
we could multiply this guy two on both sides.
You can see two sine of theta is equal to four over s,
Sine of sixty minus theta is also equal to four over s,
we can set them equal to each other.
So we have two sine of theta, two,
we have two sine two sine of theta is
equal to sine of sixty minus theta.
and then we could use some of our trig identities
we know the sine of a minus b is the same thing,
the sine of a minus b this is equal to
the sine of a times the cosine of b,
or I should say theta in this case,
So sine of sixty cos theta, minus,
this is just a standard trig identity
So it's a difference, sum and difference identity,
minus cosine of sixty,
minus cosine of sixty times the sine of theta,
times the sine of theta and all this is equal to two sine of theta.
two sine of theta. well sine of sixty degrees
this is the square root of three over two,
square root of three over two.
Cosine of sixty degrees is one-half, is one-half.
So we could add one half sine theta to both sides of this
and what are we going to get.
So we are going to add one-half sine theta,
then this guy's going to go away
and then you add one-half sine of theta to two sine of theta
which is really four half sine of theta,
so that's going to be five halves sine of theta,
so let me add one-half sine of theta, that's five -
five halves sine of theta
is equal to square root of three over two cosine of theta,
square root of three over two cosine of theta.
right? I added one half sine of theta to both sides of this
to get this I can multiply both sides by two just to simplify it.
So I get five sine of theta
five sine of theta is equal to the square root of three cosine of theta
Now I want to use that identity sine squared theta plus
cosine squared theta is equal to one.
So let me just square both sides that
will also help us with this radical
So we'll get twenty five sine squared of theta is
equal to square three cosine squared of theta,
Instead of writing cosine squared of theta,
let's just write that's one minus sine squared of theta. Right?
cosine squared theta is one minus sine squared of theta
Just squared both sides.
So let me just write what I just did,
I just squared both sides and so we get twenty five sine squared theta
is equal to three minus three sine squared theta
and we can add three sine squared theta to both sides
we get twenty eight sine squared theta is equal to three,
or that the sine squared theta,home stretch,to three over twenty eight
Or we could even write that sine of theta,
sine of theta is equal to the square root of three over twenty eight.
So it's equal to the square root of three over twenty eight
now we can simplify that twenty eight is four times seven
so we can take it out,
but that's good enough for now that'll,
that may be you know we'll simplify it
later if we have to sometimes it's easier to deal with.
So let's see, over here we have we have the sine of theta
now we can relate that actually to s over here we know that,
we know that before I messed with this thing,
we know that the sine of theta is equal to two over s,
or that s over two is equal to one over sine of theta,
or that s is equal to two over the sine of theta.
Well we know what sine of theta is,
it is square root of three over twenty eight.
so s is equal to two divided by sine of theta,
that's like multiplying by the inverse of sine of theta,
so that's two times the square root of twenty eight over three,
twenty eight over three so that is we figured out our s,
two times this thing over here.
Now given that we know s let's see how we can figure out the area.
Well what immediately pops out
is that we have this triangle over here,
that has height or I should say maybe it's base
if you view it sideways, its base is eight,
its base is eight,
and this distance right over here we should be able to figure out,
we should be able to figure out using the Pythagorean theorem,
because we know that this distance right over here is four,
We know that this distance is four.
We know that this distance, the hypotenuse is s,
so we could call this the height of it right over here
we could say that h squared,
h squared plus four squared plus sixteen is equal to
the hypotenuse squared, equal to s squared.
S squared - s is this thing over here so if we want to square s,
it becomes four times twenty-eight,
four times twenty eight over three,
and we'd subtract sixteen from both sides so h is equal to
four times twenty-eight over three minus
if I want to write sixteen over three
or if I want to write sixteen something over three
it's going to be minus forty eight,
minus forty eight over three
let's see I don't wanna multiply,
I don't want to have to multiply four times twenty-eight,
so you can write forty-eight as four times twelve,
so this numerator is going to be
four times twenty-eight minus twelve over -
remember that's h squared I should say,
H squared is going to be
four times twenty-eight minus twelve over three
which is equal to four times sixteen over three,
which is equal to sixty-four over three, that's h squared
so h is going to be the square root of that which is eight
over the square root of three,
so h right over here is eight over the square root of three
so if I want to find the area of this whole thing over here.
well first let's find the area of the small thing right over here
that's just going to be h times four,
so it's going to be,
well,I could do it either way,
but let's just say this is h times four, times one-half,
so it's going to be two times so the area of this triangle,
Let me do it in blue right here,this triangle's area is going to be h,
which is eight, over the square root of three, times four,
times four times one-half,
so this guy right over here is this going to be
two times eight over the square root of three,
or that's going to be sixteen over the square root of three
so this guy over here is sixteen over the square root of three.
So that is sixteen over the square root of three.
Now we have a bunch that, we have
this guy and this guy is going to have
the exact same area right over there,
and then you have this guy
who's going to have the exact same area again,
same exact logic, same exact logic, same base, same height,
they're actually congruent,
so you have four of these triangles,
so you are gonna multiply by four
if you want the area of this
or this area I've already shaded in, four times this
where it's sixty four over
where it's sixty four over the square root of three.
now the only area we have left to figure out
is the area of this parallelogram,
the area of the parallelogram in the middle.
Now we know the base of the parallelogram,
the base of this parallelogram is eight,
the base of the parallelogram is eight.
We just have to figure out its height.
We just have to figure out its height
and once again we can use the Pythagorean theorem.
So I'll call this, I don't know, we've already used h,
I'll use h again but this is,
you'd have to remember this is a different height over here,
this base over here is of length two,
two and it's hard to read now,
so we can now write,
we can now write that h squared plus four plus two squared is equal to
is equal to s squared
now we already figured out what s squared was in the past,
it's four times twenty-eight over three,
four times twenty eight over three.
Let's subtract four from both sides.
Let's subtract four over there so minus twelve over three.
And now let's see twelve is the same thing as four times three,
so this is, this is equal to four times twenty-eight,
four times twenty-eight minus three,
so that's four times twenty-five over three,
which is equal to one hundred over three, that's h squared,
so this h is going to be equal to the square root of this,
which is ten over the square root of three.
This is ten over the square root of three,
so this distance right over here is ten over the square root of three.
So we want the area of this parallelogram is going to be
that height times the base of the parallelogram,
so the area of parallelogram is going to be
eight times ten square root of three, or eighty -
eighty square roots of three.
Eighty, oh no, let me be very careful.
Let me be very careful.
This was ten over -
this is ten over the square root of three is this height.
So the whole area this parallelogram is
eight times ten over the square root of three
so it's eighty over the square root of three.
So the entire area now, if we add everything together,
If we add everything together
we have sixty-four square root of three for these four triangles
plus eighty over square root of three, so let's add it together.
So we have eighty over square root of three for the parallelogram
plus the sixty-four over square root of three for the triangle parts,
and this is equal to one hundred forty-four
over the square root of three,
we can rationalize the denominator,
so times the square root of three over the square root of three,
and in the denominator now we're going to get a
three one forty-four over three is going to be,
what, that's forty-eight, right?
three times forty's a hundred twenty,
three times eight's twenty-four
so it's going to be forty-eight square roots of three
for the area of our entire our entire hexagon
and so we have in the form forty eight square roots of three,
so if you want to find m plus n,
it's forty-eight plus three which is fifty-one.
That was a tiring problem I just find my brain started to
fry near the end of that I had trouble keeping track of things,
anyway, hopefully you enjoyed that.