A function, f(x), is plotted below.
Highlight an interval where f(x) is less than 0.
So f(x), which is really being plotted
on the vertical axis right over here --
x is the horizontal axis.
f(x) being less than zero really means that
the graph is below the x axis.
So the function is negative in this interval right over here,
and in this interval over here.
So I could put this [slider control]
anywhere right over here,
or I could stick it anywhere right over here.
Let me stick it right over here.
There we go. Got it right.
Let’s do a couple more.
So, the function is plotted below.
Highlight an interval where f(x) is greater than zero.
So, I could do this area right over here,
where the function is above the x-axis,
or I could do this area right over here,
where the function goes way above the x-axis.
(Well, it even goes off the page.)
So let’s stick it right over here.
Let’s do one more.
So, highlight an interval where f(x) is greater than 0.
Once again, I can do this region right over here,
where the function is above the x-axis, or over here,
where the function is above the x-axis.
I’ll do it right here, just for fun.
There we go.