We are asked to approximate the principal root or the the positive square root of 45 to the hundreths place
and i'm assuming they don't want us to use a calculator cos that would be too easy
so lets see if we can approximate this
just with our pen and paper right over here.
so square root of 45 or the principal root of 45
45 is not a perfect square,it is definitely not a perfect square
let's see what are the perfect squares around it.We know that it is going to be less than the next perfect square above 45.
lets see it's gonna be 49 cos that is 7 times 7.so it's less than the square root of 49
and it's greater than the square root of 36,and so the square root of 36 or the principal root of 36 i should say is 6 and the
principal root of 49 is 7.so this value right over here is going to be between 6 and 7
and if we look at it it's only 4 away from 49 and it's 9 away from 36.so looks like the difference between 36 and 49 is 13
so it is a total 13 gap between the 6 squared and the 7 squared.and this is 9 of the way through it
so just as a kind of approximation maybe and it may not work out perfectly because we are squaring it.
this isn't a linear relationship but it is going to be closer to 7 than it's going to be to 6 and at least the square or the 45 is 9/13ths of the away
so we could try it looks about two thirds of the way so lets try 6.7 as a guess.just based on point 7 it's about 2/3 it looks about the same
and actually we could calculate this right here if we want.
so 9/13ths as a decimal is going to be what?it's going to be 13 into 9 we have to some decimal places over here
13 doesn't go into 9 but it does go into 90 .lets see does it go into it 7 times.it goes into it 6 times
this value is almost 0.7
so you get it's about .69
so 6.7 would be a pretty good guess.this is .69 of the way between 36 and 49
so lets go roughly .69 of the way between 6 and 7
so this once again is just to approximate it is not necessarily going to give us the exact answer we have to use that as a good initial guess
and then see how well it works.so lets try 6.7
and the real way to try is to square 6.7
so 6.7 times 6.7
so we have 7 times 7 is 49
7 times 6 is 42 plus 4 is 46
put a zero now we have now moved up a space to the left
so we now have 6 times 7 is 42
carry the 4
6 times 6 is 36 plus 4 is 40
so 9 plus 0 is nine
6 plus 2 is eight
4 plus 0 is four and we have a four right over here
and we have 2 total numbers behind the decimal point
1,2
so this gives us 44.89
so 6.7 gets us pretty close but we are still not probably right to the hundred.
we've only gone 10's place right over here
so if we want to get to 45 this 6.7 squared is still less than 45 or 6.7 is still less than the square root of 45
so lets try 6.71 and increase it a little bit see if we can get from 44.89 to 45
cos this is really close already
lets just try it out 6.71
so once again we have to do some arithmetic by hand
we are assuming they don't want us to use a calculator here
we have 4 numbers behind the decimal point
so when we squared 6.71
6.71 squared = 45.0241
so 6.71 is a little bit greater
let me make it clear now
we know that 6.7 is less than the square root of 45 and we know that is less than 6.71
cos when we square this we get something a little bit over the square root of 45
but the key here is when we square this
so 6.7 squared got us 44.89 which is a 11 hundreths away from 45
and then if we look at 6.71 squared we're only 2.4hundreths above 45 so this right here is closer to the square root of 45
so if we approximate to the hundreths place definitely wanna go with 6.71