Let's add these two mixed numbers
two and five thirteenths plus seven and six thirteenths
and the way I like to think about it in my head,
I like to separate out the mixed numbers in to the whole number component and the fractional component
so we can rewrite two and five thirteenths as,
two plus five over thirteen
and then, we can write that plus,
then seven and six thirteenths we can rewrite as
plus seven plus six thirteenths
so all I did is I rewrote this and
essentially expanded out, I broke up the mixed numbers in to their whole number parts and their fractional parts
and then what I like to do is I like to add the whole number parts
so this two plus this seven, so I'll do the two plus seven over here...
I'll add those up, and to that I will add the fractional parts
so to that, I will add the five thirteenths
to the six thirteenths
so if we add the whole number parts
two plus seven is nine
and the fractional parts, already having the same denominator
five thirteenths plus six thirteenths
your going to get eleven thirteenths, five plus six is eleven
so you get nine plus eleven thirteenths
well that's just the same thing as nine and eleven thirteenths
and we are done!