This right here is a fresco by Raphael of Plato hanging out with his best student Aristotle
And you may or may not know that these two fellows along with Plato's teacher Socrates
are considered the fathers of Western philosophy,
but that's not what this video is about.
This is actually just a small little video about different dates or better
different ways to specify dates or dating machinisms.
And so if you were to look up Plato's birth you might get either 428 or 427
but we'll go with 428 -
if you were to look up Plato's birth
you might see it written as 428 BC
or you might see it written as 428 BCE
and the natural question is: what's the difference here?
They both have BC but this one has an E and it's the same year right now.
And the answer is that these are referring to the exact same year in history
but the acronyms here do stand for different things.
BC literally stands for Before Christ
so the date is written 428 BC.
The implication is that this is 428 years before the birth of Christ.
We'll see in a second that that's not exactly right
but that's what the implication is. If someone writes BCE
they're saying something very different. The B still stands for before.
So the B still stands for Before. But the CE. The C in CE does not stand for Christ anymore. It now stands
for Common. And so the CE part is Common Era.
Even though it's not referring to Christ any more, there is kind of intention here
so that it is less religious than the term Before Christ
it is still kind of putting an importance on Christ's birth
because it is saying that the Common Era is the time period after the birth of Christ
which we'll see in a second isn't exactly right
but it's essentially the same exact dating sheme.
One not directly referring to Christ,
one that is directly referring to Christ.
Similarly, this right here is a painting of Christopher Columbus
and if you would look up in history books
you'd know what was his first voyage
and when did he first show up in the New World
fighting an island in the Bahamas you would see it written as
either 1492 or AD 1492
or 1492 CE.
And once again these are all referring to the same year
just using different acronyms.
One of them is a little bit more religious
or more directly refers to Christ
and one is a little less religious.
So AD some people think it refers to After Death --
it does not refer to After Death.
Because if you think about it if you have years before the Christ and
if you start numbering years after his death how would you number the years during his life?
So AD does not stand for After Death.
It stands for Anno Domini.
Which literally means -- Anno means year
and Domini means Lord or the Lord or the year of our Lord
and one anno domini 1 AD would be the year of Jesus Christ's birth
so not after death, it stands for Anno Domini
but literally Year of our Lord, so year since that Jesus was born.
With year one being the... implicitly starting with his birth.
And we'll see in a second that's not exactly right.
CE stands for Common Era.
Once again, 1 CE is the same thing as AD 1,
sometimes, we now write AD 1492 or we write 1492 AD,
all referrig to the exact same thing.
Now, all of these things refer to... you know, when we say 428 BC
it implies 428 years before the birth of Christ,
1492 AD that's in the Year of our Lord 1492
and it implies 1492 years since the birth of Christ,
but the reality is that we're not really quite sure
when Christ was born and so these aren't exactly.
You know, Columubus didn't sail across the Atlantic
exactly 1492 years after the birth of Christ.
Most historians put the birth of Christ at 7-2 BC or BCE
depending on how you want to view it.
Remember, BC is Before Christ, which is little ironic,
because we're talking about the actual birth of Christ,
BCE is Before the Common Era.
And they put his death at 30-36 AD which is 30-36 in the Year of our Lord,
that's what this stands for, Anno Domini,
or in the Common Era, CE.
Now, some people they obviously don't like the BC/AD naming mechanism
because it's explicitly referring to Christ and every year
it makes Christ the central figure in all of history,
so they'll say this is clearly too Christian
and they would prefer the less Christian naming scheme
where we use BCE and CE.
But lot of people would still say: hey look, ok, you changed... or, you know
first of all some Christians wouldn't like this
that you removed the direct references to the birth of Christ
or being the years since Christ's birth,
but even here some people would complain that
althought you've removed the direct reference
that this is saying Before the Common Era and the Common Era,
even though you've removed the direct reference, it still makes Christ's birth
the central thing in all of history.
But this is the convention whether people like it or not
in order to have the same reference point
and theologically it's difficult to switch it, this time,
every one has essentially settled on this.
So it's really just a matter of letters,
which naming scheme you pick.
The whole point of this video is that you don't get
confused between BC and BCE, that you don't think that
AD stands for After Death, it stands for Anno Domini,
the Year of the Lord or the Year of our Lord
and CE stands for Common Era.
This and this are referring to essentially the same count,
after the birth of Christ, or the theoretical birth of Christ
which we don't really know when it actually happened,
it probably did not happen at the beginning of 1 AD or 1 CE.
These two things both also refer to the same direction in the timeline.
One last thing I want to point out is that
there is no year zero.
So if you take either of these naming schemes, you have...
so let's go very close to the years one.
So there is at some point this theoretical birth of Christ
which is probably not the actual birth of Christ,
but at that theoretical point, right at that point
you have 31 December of the previous year,
all of sudden now you have 1 January 1 AD or CE
and the year before that was 1 BC or BCE,
depending on how you wanna refer to it.
So there is no year zero in this scheme.
And the last thing I want to emphasize,
and it might be obvious to you,
is the larger number you have here,
the further back you're going in time.
Because this is saying how many years
before this theoretical birth of Crhist,
and obviously, the larger numbers the further you're going off
into the future. And if you want to figure out
how many years passed between Plato's birth
and Columbus's sailing across the Atlantic to find the New World,
you would say: well, look at it, it took 428 years to go
form Plato's birth to this theoretical birth of Christ
and there is another 1492 years to wait until Columbus gets his ships together,
so the total number of years would be,
428 years to get to Christ from Plato's birth
and then you have another 1492 years to wait for Columbus,
so it's eight plus two, that is ten,
as you can see I just want to add a little arithmetic in this video,
so one plus two plus nine is twelve,
and then we have nine, one plus four plus four...
so 1920 years between the Plato's birth
and Columbus sailing across the Atlantic.