We are in the international gallery in Berlin
and we are looking at one of my favourite paintings
by Edward Manet "In the Conservatory".
Now, conservatory is like a greenhouse.
It would be attached to a home
and would allow for plants to survive the winter.
And the woman who takes up most to the painting
seems like a hothouse flower herself.
I mean, look at her dress and hat...
She was actually the owner of a butique
and so fashion was important to her
and it is a wonderful survey minder of the way which Paris become such a showplace for the bourgeoisie.
Being observed and observing
were crtically important activities,
especially for somebody like Manet.
She has that hair about her of things above it all.
She does seem too touched.
I read it as her aloofness and his desire for intimacy.
The center almost literally is their hands,
hers casually on the back of this bench
but his holding a cigar which seems to inch towards her.
She looks out past him and so you are absolutely right
she is the object of his attention, perhaps of his desire
and she seems to be elswhere completely.
That man is her husband, Jules Guillemet.
Typical of Manet we have this open brushwork,
this loose handling of paint.
You are right this is a kind of speedo
with which his hand
is moving across the surface of the canvas.
I love the way
that the bench functions as a barrier between them,
except of course at its top where the hands almost meet.
It's so often Manet does give us a sense of the momentary,
the sense of something cought by your eye
and I almost have that sense here,
though we were walking by and cought this moment.
Formally the painting is so interesting.
She looks of to the right
and although we don't have a sense
she is looking in something specific.
We do see her gaze at drawn area
that we don't have available to us.
The man is looking at her but we can't quite see his eyes.
In Manet's usual way, there is a kind of flattening,
that takes place here.
The figures are very close to the foreground
and the verticales of the back of the bench,
how to emphasise through their rythm
the dimensionality of the surface,
the relative lack of diferentiation in the greens in the background and even field and a kind of shallow space.
And it's this flatness
and it's also the problems in the narrative
that I think would if, upset nineteenth century viewers.
Most academic paintings were offer as a narrative.
There was entirely understanable and this one just isn't.
We can't firmly say what's going on with this figures.
We don't know what's just outside the frame to the right.
So this is kind of ambiguity, not only in the style of painting
but there's a kind of ambiguity in the relationship as well.
All of which was antithetical
to the strong narratives of the academy.
This illegibility is such a beautiful expression
of the ambiguity of modern life
and Manet was one of the first artist to recognize this
and make the central to his art.