the alternative form of the derivate of the function f of the number 'a'
denoted by f'(a) is given by ... this stuff ...
now this might look a little strange to you but if you really think about
what it's saying, it's really just taking the slope of the tangent line between
a, f(a) ... so let's imagine some
arbitrary function like this, let's say that is
I'll just write that's our function f, and so you could
have the point when x=a, this is our x-axis
this is the point: (a, f(a))
notice: a, f(a)
and then
we could take the slope between that and some arbitrary point, let's call that x
so this is the point: x, f(x)
and notice ...
this top, the numerator right here, this is just our change in the value of the function
or you could view that as the change in the vertical axis
so that would give you this distance right over here, so that's what we're doing up here, in the numerator
and then in the denominator we're finding the change
in our horizontal values, horizontal coordinates
that we'll do in a different color
that would give you
so the change in the horizontal, that's this right over here
and then they're trying to apply the limit as x approaches a, so as x gets
closer and closer and closer and closer to a what's going to
happen is is that when x is out here we have this secant line
we're finding the slope of this secant
line, but as x gets closer and closer the secant line gets
better and better and better approximated to the slope of the tangent line
where the limit as x approaches a but doesn't quite equal it
is going to be, this is actually the definition of our derivate or the alternate form of the derivate definition, and this would be the slope of the tangent line
that exists
so with that all out of the way, let's try to answer our question
with the alternate form of the derivates as an aid, makes sense of the
following limit expression by identifying the function f and the number
a. So right here they want to find the slope of the tangent
line at 5, here they wanted to find the slope of the tangent line at a
so it's pretty clear that a is
equal to 5, and that f(a)
is equal to 125
now what about f(x)? f(x)?
Well, here is a limit of f(x)-f(a), well here's the limit as x
x to the 3rd minus 125, and this makes sense
if f(x) = x to the third
then it makes sense that f(5)
f(5) is going to be 5 to the third
is going to be 125, and we're also taking up here the limit is x
approaches a which is x approaches 5
so this is the derivate of the function f(x)
is equal to x to the third, let me write that down in a green color
x to the third at the number x equals
at the number a equals to 5, so we can imagine
this, let's try to actually graph it so that we can image, actually I'll do it
out here, where we have a little bit better contrast with the colors
so let's say that is my y-axis
let's say that this is my
x-axis, I'm not going to quite draw it to scale, let's say that here
is a point 125 or y=125
this is when x=5 so they're clearly not at the same
scale. But the function is going to look something
is going to look something like this, you know what x to the third is going to look like
it looks something, something like, something like, let me draw a little bit, something like this
we know it's going to look something like this. So here our a
a=5. Our a=5. This point right here
is, is: (5, 125) .... (5,125)
and then we're taking the slope between that point and
an arbitrary x value, and an arbitrary, or I should say
an arbitrary other point on the curve, so this right over here would be the point
called: x comma x to the third. We know that
f(x) is equal to x to the third. Let me make it clear
that the graph of y is equal to, y is equal to
x to the third, and so this expression
right over here, all of this is the slope between two points
this is the slope between these two points. And as we take the limit
as x approaches 5, so right now this is our x
as x get closer and closer and closer to 5
as it gets closer and closer to 5 these secant lines are better and better
and better approximate the slope of the tangent line
at x equals 5. So let's look at the tangent line a little bit
looks something to be even more, looks something like
something like that.