We're asked to add 0.822 to 5.65.
So let me rewrite this. And when I rewrite it, I want to line up the decimals,
so that we add the right place to the right place.
And so, we can write either number first, although I like to write the larger number first.
So let's write 5.65, and remember, the important thing is that we line up the decimal points.
So if we write 0.822, so we line up the decimals - let me line up the decimals first -
so I'll write the decimal right below the other decimal,
and it is 0.822. And now we are ready to add. So let's see what's going on here.
So, I like to start in the smallest place, that way the carrying works out well.
So you might say, "Wait, I need to add this 2 thousandths to something. I don't see anything up here."
Well, you could say that there's just a "0 thousandths" right up here.
Then it makes it very clear. Well, 0 thousandths plus 2 thousandths, is going to be 2 thousandths.
Five hundredths plus 2 hundredths is seven hundredths. 6 tenths plus 8 tenths is 14 tenths,
Well, 14 tenths is the same thing as 4 tenths, and 1 one.
Another way of thinking about it, is that you're carrying the 1.
But really what you're saying is "Look, this is 14 tenths.". I could write that as 4 tenths and a one.
Or 1's place. Or 1 in the 1's place.
Then we have 1 plus 5 is 6. And, of course, you can not forget the decimal.
The decimal goes right there, and this is 6.472.