Welcome back.
We are now on section four of our third test,
and so we're on page 530.
And let's start with problem number one.
If s plus t is equal to 3,
what is the value of s plus t minus 6?
Well,we know that s plus t is equal to 3,
so they're just asking us what is 3 minus 6.
Well 3 minus 6 is minus 3.
And that is choice A.
Number two.
They have a box on the cube.
Let me see if I can draw this box.
So it looks like,and then the back side's like this,
and then let me draw a little dotted--
And then the sides are A--
let me do that in a different color--A,B,C,D,E,P,and Q.
And they say,on the cube in the figure above,
each of the following points is the same distance from
P as it is from Q except?
And these are all the choices.
A, B, C, D, and E.
So we want to look for a point that isn't the same distance
from P as it is from Q.
A is one edge from P and one edge from Q,so it's not A.
B is two edges from P no matter how you go.
And it is also two edges from Q no matter how you go,
so it's not B.
C is one edge from Q,
but to get to P you gotta go at least three edges.
1, 2, 3, to go to C. So it's going to be C.
C is much closer to Q than it is to P,
so it is not the same distance.
So our choice is C.C is C.All right.
Problem number three.
And I'll switch to a less tacky color.
Oh boy,there's all sorts of stuff to draw.
Maybe I won't draw it.
Let's see if I can get by without drawing.
The bar graph above shows
where fraud is committed on the internet.
Which of the following circle graphs
most accurately displays the same graph?
Well I'll try it.So they say websites.
Websites is this huge number.
Websites,that's 78%.
Let me say that that is this purple color.
Actually I should do this with the rectangle too.
The websites is a purple color,
and then let's say that email is,
well I'll do it this color,at 18%.
And then they tell us that news groups is 2%,
so it's a really small percentage,2%.
And then finally,they tell us that other is also 2%.
And then you want to see a pie graph that's the same thing.
So if this is the pie graph.
So 78% is going to be this purple,
it's going to be websites.
So that's a little bit more than 3/4,right?
78% is 3% more than 3/4.3/4 would look like this.
A little bit more than 3/4
is going to look something like this.
But a little bit more than 3/4
And then I can actually even fill it.
That's going to be a little bit more than 3/4.
And then the blue stuff,18%,
that's going to look something like 18%.
That's a little less than 25%,so it's going to be like that.
So we could fill that too.
The other pieces are going to be
these thin slivers like this,2% and 2%.
This is really just translating that into this.
And they're actually going to be even thinner
than the way I drew it.
And out of all the choices,
the one that has this purple region,
websites,the dark region on the graph.
The only one that has that,where it's more than 3/4,
are choices C and D,right?
That's the only one where it has more than 75%
is shaded the websites' color.
It's either going to be C or D.
And then when you look at the difference between C and D,
choice C has nothing for other in there.
Choice C just has news groups, no other.
So it has to be D,
because news groups and other are actually same size.
So they should be the same proportions.
So the choice is D.
Next problem.
Problem number four.
The numerator of a certain fraction is
5 less than the denominator.
So let's say that the denominator is x.
The numerator is 5 less than the denominator,
so the numerator is x minus 5.
The numerator is 5 less than the denominator.
And they say the fraction is equal to 3/4.
What is the denominator of this fraction?
So we just solve for x.
So let's cross multiply.
x times 3,so 3x,is equal 4 times x minus 5.
So 3x is equal to 4x minus 20.
And you can subtract.
So you get 20 is equal to,subtract 3x from both sides,
is equal to x,and that's the denominator.
So that is choice D.
The next problem has a bunch of drawing for me to do.
Let's see if I can finish it in time.
So we have the two axes.
Let me draw the two axes.
This is a big problem, so I'll draw it big.
I've got the two axes, and then it goes from k to 6k.
k, 2k, 3k, 4k, 5k, 6k.
6k, 5k, 4k, 3k,you get the point.
And then it goes from 1 to 6.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
And then the triangle looks like it goes from--
if I were to draw a line--
it goes from 2k to 6k,and then from 2 to 6.
They actually draw the line like this,2k it is.
This is a triangle.
I don't know if I'll have time to do it in this video,
but everything should work out.
The triangle goes from 2k to 5k,good thing I caught that,
and it's at point 2.
That's its base.
And then it goes up to 6,where it kind of is in the middle.
It goes up to here.
This is what the triangle looks like.
I have redrawn the problem.
And this is B, A, C.
And they say,in the figure above,the scale on the x-axis
is different from the scale on the y-axis.
If the area of triangle ABC is 18,what is the value of k?
The area is 18.
So area is equal to 1/2 base times height for a triangle.
We know that the area is 18.
So 18 is equal to 1/2.
What's the base?
Well we went from 2k to 5k.
So we went 3k.
We went 1, 2, 3. We went 3k.
So the base is 3k.
And what's the height?Well from 2 to 6.
So the height is 4, and we just saw solve for k.
So 18 is equal to 1/2 times 4 is 2 times 3k is equal to 6k.
k is equal to 3.
And that is choice E. And we are done.
You just have to know area is equal to 1/2 base times height
and then just put in the base, which is 3k,
and the height, and solve for k.
I'll see you in the next video.