Read the problem.
So just to visualize this a little bit.
Let me draw a triangle here, just so we know what b and h are.
This distance right over here is b, and this distance is height.
Now they want us to solve this for the height.
So the formula is A = 1/2bh. We want to solve for h.
We essentially want to isolate the h on one side.
It's already on the right, so let's get rid of everything else on the right. I'll do it one step at
a time.
You could kind of skip steps if you wanted to. The best way to get rid of 1/2 that's beging multiplied
by h is to multiply both sides by the reciprocal. Let's do that.
Let's multiply. Remember, anything you do to one side, you have to do to the other side.
The whole point of multiplying by 2 is 2 times 1/2 is one.
If we multiply on this side, we'll have bh. On the other side, we'll have 2A. We're almost there.
If we just want to isolate the h, we can divide both sides of the equation by b.
You are just dividing both sides by b. And then what do we get? Well, the right hand side, the b's
cancel out, so we get h is equal to
2A over b, and we're done. We have solved this
formula for the height. I guess this could be
useful if someone just gave you a bunch
of bases and areas and said just keep
giving me the height for those triangles.