What I want to do in this video is explain what parallax, what parallax actually is and then then
try to visualize what the parallax would be like in the context of observing relatively nearby stars, and then in the next video
we're going to think about how we can use the parallax of nearby stars to figure out how far they actually
are away from us. So parallax really is just the apparent change in the position of something based on
a different line of sight. So when you see that and you just look at, so while you are looking at a car
you are going to see that depending on how far different things are from you it looks like they're moving
relative to each other. Right now I am looking at my computer monitor and if I move my head around
or shake my head around it looks like the wall behind the computer monitor is moving relative to the
computer monitor. We've all experienced this. Let's think about what parallax means when looking at stars.
So let me draw, let me draw the sun here, and obviously none of this is drawn to scale. So let me draw
the sun here and let me draw the earth at some point in its orbit around the sun, and we're going to
pretend that we're looking from above the solar system. The earth will be rotating, the earth will be
rotating in this direction right over here; and let's say that the star we care about, the start that
we care about is right over here. The star that we care about is right over here. Obviously, clearly not
drawn to scale. And what we're going to do is we're going to wait until the point in the year, so the
point in our orbit around the Earth, so that right at dawn, so we're sitting right here on the surface
of the earth and to simplify things we're on the equator and let's say that this is the stars roughly
in the plane of our solar system. So we're sitting right here, we're sitting right here, on the equator, and
then right at dawn, right when the first light of the sun, right when the first light of the sun begins
to reach me; remember that right now the sun is lighting up this side of the earth. So right when the
first light of the sun is reaching me, I'm looking, I'm looking straight up. So if I look straight up