In the last video we had a little bit of a review of classical economics.
And why it might have made sense in the context of the great depression
where the economy was operating well below its potential.
What I want to do, and it may be true anytime that the economy is operating well below its potential,
but what I want to talk about in this video is how Keynesian thinking can sometimes be dangerous.
And one thing I do want to emphasize over the course of this video is
Keynesian policies are often associated with people on the left,
with policies on the left, the democrats in the United States, but the Republicans
also are for the most part, especially mainstream Republicans, especially the last several
administrations, they have practiced what are-what can only be described as Keynesian policies.
When the economy started to recede, they tried to stimulate it by shifting aggregate demand
to the right somehow. And we'll talk about that they tried to do it in a slightly
different way through tax cuts instead of government increases, spending increases
but it was Keynesian in its underlying thinking.
Now just as a bit of a kind of backup, I want to talk a little bit more a about that cycle
that we talked about in the last video.
So if you had person A, person B, person C, and person D and maybe their firms.
And B supplies A, A supplies D, D supplies C, and C supplies B.
And for the sake of simplicity we'll say that they're all supplying two units
of their good and service to each other. And let's just say that C has a bad dream,
feels pessimistic, ate something bad and all of a sudden isn't feeling good about the future
and wants to buy less just out of caution, maybe wants to hoard a little bit of cash and things
just in case C needs it.
And so he buys a little bit less from D, so he buys a little bit less than D.
But D says "gee my business is bad, now I can't afford as many goods and services",
buys less from A, A does the same thing from B, and then B's business is bad
so buys less stuff from C, goods and services from C,
and now C feels like they're psychic.
Even though we see that it was actually a self fulfilling prophecy,
that C's pessimism actually led to that reality actually occurring.