Let's think about the different use cases for credit default swaps,
so let's say that I have some company over here
and it's been, it's given a BB credit rating
and this rating of course comes from a credit rating agency
credit rating agency, sometimes called a ratings agency
or a rating agency, I've seen it every different way
so this would be like Moody's or Standards & Poor's,
or whatever else. And they say, they look at this company
and they look at it's business, look at it's balance sheet
and they say, "Okay, it's not super safe, but it's not super risky either,
we give it a BB rating."
and let's say that there's an investor over here
who wants to lend money to this company
so he might lend them some money and get some interest in return
but this investor doesn't like this level of safety
he wants to make sure that he's made whole
even if this company goes out of business,
so he can go to a writer of a credit default swap.
And the most famous of those credit default swap writers is, or was, AIG
And he'll say, "Hey AIG, I'm gonna pay you a little bit every year,"
-- you can do that as an insurance premium,
and in exchange, you are essentially going to insure
you are going to insure me in the case of a default by this company
Insurance. And what we already said, it's a little bit shady
because AIG, it was not regulated like insurance,
so AIG did not have to set anything aside,
and what was powerful here for AIG is that the rating agencies
continued to give AIG a very high rating.
So let's say it had a AA rating, so despite the fact
that it kept taking on all these liabilities
the credit rating agencies says, "Hey, we'll still give you a AA,"
so they're able to use this AA rating to keep writing these contracts
to keep writing insurance, not setting anything aside
and essentially just getting, almost you could view it,
free money with eventually having to pay the piper, eventually.
Now, this is one scenario, another scenario is
maybe an investment bank creates some type of special purpose entity
or some collateralized debt obligation right over here
and, they have their different tranches,
and maybe for the senior tranche over here
just so that they can sell them to pension funds
who can only buy AA rated debt,
pension funds, the investment bank goes to AIG and says,
"Hey, can this entity right over here buy credit default swaps?
"...can we enter into credit default swap agreeements on you? So that incase any
"... of this stuff were to default you will also insure that."
And once we do that, then, a rating agency,
so this is a security, this is a senior tranche of a collateralized debt obligation now
the senior tranche. And now that that senior tranche
is essentially insured by AIG, a credit rating agency
once again will assign this a AA rating
even though this thing might be made up of a bunch of subprime mortgages
and all of the rest, although it is the senior tranche
so it will be made whole first, but now pension funds
can buy this type of thing.
The last use case, is maybe you have a hedge fund out here
Hedge fund out here, who doesn't want to lend anybody
any money, but is convinced that about
a whole bunch of these companies, maybe this company over here
or maybe this company over here, that has some other rating
so this is another company. This hedge fund is convinced
that these companies are going to default on their debt,
that there's going to be a credit crisis of some kind,
well then this hedge fund can enter into a credit default swap agreements
Could enter into credit default swap agreements
to essential get insurance, but not having anything to insure
it's like getting car insurance on someone else's driving
or someone else's car, and you kind of are starting to hope
that they have a car accident.
And because now this guy has a credit default swap
on company, on this company right over here,
despite the fact that they didn't lend to them,
the hedge fund is going to pay a little bit every year and get the insurance,
and they're essentially going to hope that this company
goes out of business, because if it does,
then they're going to get the insurance payment
they're going to get the same payment that this investor would have
but they would have never had to lend the money
so you could use it as side bet, you could use it as a way of making
lower rated securities all of a sudden acceptable to pension funds,
or you could use it as a straight up way of insuring debt
that you're lending to someone else.