A cylindrical log has a diameter of 12 inches.
A wedge is cut from the log by making two planar cuts that go entirely through the log.
The first is perpendicular to the axis of the cylinder,
and the plane of the second cut forms a 45 degree angle with the plane of the first cut.
The intersection of these two planes has exactly one point in common with the log.
The number of cubic inches in the wedge can be expressed as n pie, where n is a positive integer.
Find n.
So lets think about it, so lets just draw what they're describing
So we have a cylindrical log that has a diameter of 12 inches so lets draw that
so we have a, let me draw it like this, so that is cross-section of the log
and it has a diameter of 12 inches
so this is 12.. 12 inches and it is a cylinder so it looks like this
and here is our log, that is the log in question
a wedge is cut from the log by making two plainer cuts that go entirely through the log
the first cut is perpendicular to the axis of the cylinder'
so it would go.. it really just cut it.. it would just cut it straight