500 years ago,
trans-oceanic travel became a reality.
Since the end of the last Ice Age,
farming societies have been absorbing their neighbors,
making populations more similar within continents.
That when people began to cross oceans, in large numbers,
the genetic and cultural differences
between people from different continents
also began to fade, though not disappear.
Many families relocated
Willingly,
or unwillingly
to very distant lands.
Sometimes, they found unoccupied lands,
and sometimes they found lands occupied,
and wished they weren't.
And sometimes they found land and labor,
and devised ways of exploiting both.
All over the world,
people separated by thousands of kilometers
for thousands of years
began meeting once again
and producing children.
Today, whole regions, like the Americas,
are populated by people
who can trace their ancestry back to multiple continents.
But some small groups
are more geographically or culturally isolated,
and remain genetically distinguishable.
As long distance transportation gets easier and easier,
and individual societies become more diverse,
languages are being lost,
and genetic distinctions across the globe are fading.
But these genetic distinctions,
are a relatively recent phenomenon in our history.
We haven't been separated for very long.