A squirrel is running across the road at 12 feet/s
It needs to run 9 feet to get across the road.
How long will it take the squirrel to run 9 feet?
Round to the nearest 100th of a second. Fair enough.
A car is 50 feet away from the squirrel.
Okay, this is a high stakes word problem.
Driving toward it at a speed of 100 feet/s
How long will it take for the car to drive 50 feet?
Round to the nearest 100th of a second.
Will the squirrel make it 9 feet across the road before the car gets there?
So this is definitely high stakes, at least for the squirrel.
So let's answer the first question.
Let's figure out how long will it take the squirrel to run 9 feet.
So, let's think about it.
The squirrel...let me write squirrel, squirrel right over here...
the squirrel, so the squirrel's got to go 9 feet and we want to figure out many seconds it's going to take
So, what would we...would we divide or multiply this?
by 12?
Well, to think about that, you could think about the units
where we want to get an answer in terms of seconds
we want to figure out time
So, it would be great if we could multiply this...times seconds...seconds per foot
then the feet will cancel out and I'll be left with seconds
Now, right over here, we're told that squirrel can run at 12 feet per second, but we want seconds per foot
so, the squirrel every second, so they go 12 feet/s
Then we could also say 1 second per every 12 feet
So, let's it write it that way
So, it's essentially the reciprocal of this because the units are the reciprocal of this
So, it's 1 second for every 12 feet
Notice, all I did was take this information right over here, 12 feet/s
and I wrote it as second per foot, 12 feet for every 1 second, 1 second for every 12 feet
What's useful about this is, this will now give me the time it takes for the squirrel in seconds
So, the feet cancel out with the feet
and I am left with 9 x 1/12, which is 9/12 seconds
and 9/12 seconds is the same thing as 3/4 seconds
which is the same thing as 0.75 seconds for the squirrel to cross the street
Now, let's think about the car
So, now let's think about the car.
And it's the exact same logic.
They tell us that the car is 50 feet away
So, the squirrel's trying to cross the road, like that
And the car is 50ft away coming in like that
and we want to figure if the squirrel will survive
So, the car is 50 feet away
So, it's 50 feet away
We want to figure out the time it'll take to travel at 50 feet
Once again, we would want it in seconds
so we would want seconds per feet
So, we would want to multiply by seconds per foot
seconds per foot
They give us the speed in feet per second
100 feet / s
And so we just have to realize that this is 100 feet for every 1 second
or 1/100th seconds per feet
this is once again just this information, this information, but we took the reciprocal of it
cause we don't want feet per second, we want seconds per feet
and if we do that, that cancels with that
and we're left with 50 over 100 seconds
So, this is 50 over 100 is 0.50 seconds
And so now, let's answer the question, this life and death situation for the squirrel
Will the squirrel make it 9 feet across the road before the car gets there
Well, it's going to take the squirrel 0.75 seconds to cross
and it's going to take the car only half a second
So, the car is going to get to where the squirrel is crossing before the squirrel has the chance to get all the way across the road
So, unfortunately for the squirrel, the answer is...no...