What I want to do in this video is talk about plate tectonics
You have probably heard the words before,
and you might be somewhat familiar with what it discusses.
It's really just the idea that the surface of the earth
is made up of a bunch of these rigid plates,
so it's broken up into a bunch rigid plates,
and this rigid plates move relative to each other
and take everything that's on them for a ride
and the things that are on them include the continents.
so the theory is talking about the movement of these plates.
Over here I have a picture I got off of Wikipedia of the actual plates.
And over here you have the Pacific Plate,
you have the Nazca Plate, the South Amearican Plate,
I can keep going on, we even have the Antarctic Plate,
obviously when you do a projection onto two dimensions of a surface of a sphere
the stuff on the bottom and the top look much bigger than they actually are, Antartica isn't this big
relitive to say North America or South America, we just had to streach it out to fill up the rectangle.
but that's the Antarctic Plate, North American Plate,
and you can see that they're actually moving relative to each other,
that's what these arrows are depicting.
You can see right over here the Nazca Plate and the Pacific Plate
are moving away from each other, new land is formed here,
we'll talk more about that in other videos.
You see right over here, in the middle of the Atlantic Ocean,
the African Plate and the South American Plate meet each other
and they're moving away from each other,
which means that more new land, more plate material,
I quess you could say, is somehow being created right here,
we'll be talk about that in future videos,
and pushing these two plates apart.
Now, before we go into the evidence for plate tectonics,
where we'll say some of the more details about how plates are created
and some theories as to why the plates might move,
but I want to get to a little bit of the terminology
of plate tectonics out of the way.
Because sometimes people call them crustal plates,
and that's not exactly right.
I want to show you the difference, two different ways
of classifying the different layers of the Earth
and to think about how they might rely to each other.
So what you traditionally see, and actually I made a video
that goes into a lot more detail of this,
is a breakdown of the chemical layers of the Earth.
When I talk about chemical layers, I'm talking about
what are the constituents of the different layers.
So when you talk within this term,
the tough most layer, which is the thinnest layer,
is the crust.
Then below that is the mantle.
Actually, let me show you the whole Earth where I can draw the scale.
So far we have drawn the crust,
the crust is the outer, the thinnest outer layer of the Earth,
you can imagine the blue line itself is the crust.
Then below that you have the mantel,
so everything between the blue and orange line is the mantle,
let me label the crust.
The crust you can literally view
as the actuall blue pixels over here.
And then inside of the mantle you have the core.
And when you do this very high-level division,
these are chemical divisions.
This is saying that the crust is made up of different types of elements.
Its make-up is different than the stuff that's in the mantle
which is made up of different things
than what's inside of the core.
It's not describing the mechanical properties of it.
When I talk about mechanical properties, I'm talking about ...
so mechanical properties
are whether something is solid and rigid.
Or maybe it's so hot-melted,
it's kind of a magma or plastic solid.
So this would be the most brittle stuff if it gets formed up,
if rock starts to melt a little bit, then you have something like a magma
or you can view it as like a deformable or plastic solid.
When I'm talking about plastic
I'm not talking about the stuff that the case of your cell phone is made up,
I'm talking about it's deformable, this rock is deformable
because it's so hot and it's somewhat melted
it kind of behaves like a fluid.
It actually does behave like a fluid, but it's much more viscous,
it's much thicker and slower-moving than what we would
normally associate with a fluid like water.
So this is a viscous fluid.
And then the most fluid would of course be
the liquid state.
This is what we mean when we talk about mechanical properties.
When you look at this division over here,
the crust is solid,
the mantle actually has some parts of it that are solid,
so the uppermost part of the mantle is solid,
then below that, the rest of the mantle is in this magma,
this deformable, somewhat fluid state,
and depending on what depth you go into the mantle
there are different levels of fluidity,
and then the core, the outer layer of the core is liquid
because the temperature is so high,
the inner core is made up of the same things
and the temperature is even higher
but also the pressure is so high, so it's actually solid.
So that's why the mantle, crust and core differentiation
doesn't tell you about mechanical stuff,
whether it's solid, whether it's magma
whether it's really liquid.
It literally tells you what the make-up is.
Now to think about the make-up, and this is important plate tectonics,
so we talk about these plates, we're not talking about just the crust,
we're talking about the outer rigid layer.
Let me just zoom it a little bit,
let's say we're zoomed in right over there.
So now we have the crust zoomed in,
this right over here is the crust.
And then everything below here, we're actually talking about the upper mantle.
We haven't gone too deep in the mantle right here,
so that's what we call the upper mantle.
Right below the crust the mantle is cool enough
that it is also in real solid form.
So this right here is solid mantle.
And when we talk about the plates, we're actually talking about the outer solid layer,
that includes both the crust and the solid part of the mantle.
We call that the lithosphere.
When people talk about plate tectonics,
they shouldn't say crustal plates.
They should call these lithospheric plates.
Below the lithosphere you have the least viscous part of the mantle
because the temperature is high enough for the rock to melt,
but the pressure isn't so big as in the lower part of the mantle
that the fluid can actually kind of move past each other.
Although it's still pretty viscous, it's still a magma.
So this is still kind of in its magma state,
and this fluid part of the mantle
we can't quite call it liquid yet,
but over large periods of time it does have fliud properties.
This that essetnially the lithisphere is kind of riding on top of
we call this the asthenosphere.
So when we talk about the lithosphere and asthenosphere
we're really talking about machanical layers.
The outer layer, the solid layer is the lithosphere,
the more fluid layer right below that is the asthenosphere.
When we talk about the crust, mantle and core
we're talking about chemical properties,
what are the things actually made up of.