Here's a simulations created by Khan Academy user Justin Helps
that once again tries to give us an understanding of why we divide by n-1
to get an unbiased estimate of population variance when we're trying to calculate the sample variance.
So what he does here is a simulation it has a population that has a uniform distribution
so he says "I used a flat probabilistic distribution from 0 to 200 for my population.
Then we start sampling from that population, we're going to use samples of size 50
and what we do is for each of those samples we calculate the variance based on dividing by n,
we calculate the sample variance based on dividing by n, by dividing by n-1 and n-2
and as we keep having more and more and more samples, we take the mean of the variances calculated in
different ways and we figure out what those means converge to
so that's a sample, here's another sample, here's another sample
if I sample here then now I'm adding a bunch and I'm sampling continuously
And you saw something very interesting happen. When I divide by n, I get my sample variance
is still (even when I'm taking the mean of many many many sample variances) that I've already taken I'm
still underestimating the true variance.
When I divide by n-1 it looks like I'm getting a pretty good estimate
the mean of all of my sample variances has really converged to the true variance
when I divided by n-2 just for kicks it is pretty clear that I overestimated
that I overestimated the.. with my mean of my sample variances I overestimated the true
variance. So this gives us a pretty good sense that n-1 is the right thing to do.
Now this is another interesting way of visualizing it
In the horizontal axis right over here we're comparing each plot is one of our samples and how far to the right
is how much more is that sample mean than the true mean and when we go to the left is
how much less is the sample mean from the true mean.
So for example this sample right over here it's all the way over to the right, it's the sample mean there is a lot more
than the true mean, sample mean here was a lot less than the true mean, sample mean here only a little
bit more than the true mean. In the vertical axis, using this denominator dividing by n, we calculate
two different variances: one variance we use the sample mean, the other variance
we use the population mean. And this the vertical axis we compare the difference between
the mean calculated with the sample mean versus the mean calculated with the population mean
So for example, this point right over here, when we calculate our mean with our
sample mean, which is the normal way we do it, it significantly underestimates
what the mean would have been if somehow we knew what the population mean was
and we could calculate it that way and you get this really interesting shape
and that's something to think about if you recommend something to think about why or what
kind of shape this actually is. The other interesting thing is
when you look at it this way it's pretty clear this entire graph is sitting below the horizontal axis
so we're always when we calculate our sample variance using this formula
what when we use the sample mean to do it, which we typically do, we're always underestimating
we're always getting a lower variance than when we use the population mean
Now this over here, when we divide by n-1 we're not always underestimating
sometimes we're overestimating and when you take the mean of all of these variances
you converge, and here we're overestimating a little bit more
and just to be clear what we're talking about with these three graphs
let me take a screen shot of it and explain it a little more in depth
so just to be clear, just to be clear, this red graph right over here
let me do this color close to at least, so this orange, what this distance is
for each of these samples we're calculating the sample variance
using the sample mean and in this case we are using n as our denominator in this case
right over here, and from that we're subtracting the sample variance
or I guess you could call this some type of pseudo sample variance
if we somehow knew the population mean, this isn't something you see in a lot of statistics
but it's a gauge of how much we are underestimating our sample, our our sample variance given
that we do not have the true population mean at our disposal
so this is the distance we're calculating. So you see we are always, always underestimating.
Here we overestimate a little bit, and we also underestimate, but when you take the mean
and average them all out it converges to the actual values
So here we're dividing by n-1 and here we're dividing by n-2