Now to recap,
we are checking if some number 'n'
is prime, by doing a trial division.
Here is the square root of 'n'.
And here is 3.
Starting at 3 and we are
hopping along by 2
up until the square root of 'n'
and at each point in the way
checking if that number divided 'n'.
Now so far, people have been trying
to reduce the number of steps we take
by perhaps starting later
and taking larger steps.
Now I just want to pause here.
And let's think about
what is the ideal case
for a trial division algorithm.
What is the best we could possibly do,
if we got very creative in our stepping?
Well, remember. Any number 'n'
has some prime factorization.
Right? And let's say
the square root of 'n' is here.
We actually only need
to step on prime numbers.
That would be the best we could do –
because we know if we step only on primes,
we will eventually find a factor
– a prime factor – if it's a composite.
The question now is
how efficient is this method,
because it seems like
we have a perfect solution now,
if we wrote a new algorithm,
which first just called the sieve.
Let's say the new algorithm
is calculating if 'n' is prime.
It could call the sieve
and generate a nice long list of primes for us.
And then, we would have our trial division
which would use this list of primes,
so it could hop along and hit only primes –
up until the square root of 'n'
– wherever that is.
So, what's wrong with this?
Well we can visualize the time complexity
or the number of steps taken.
And remember, I did so by...
I coded up this algorithm
and I put in a step counter inside each loop.
So, we have –
Let's just say step++ means step + 1 here.
And inside this other loop,
there's also a step counter...
step++
So, these are all constant operations
checking if – and marking.
So we just have a step counter
inside each loop.
And now, here is a comparison.
On the far left is our
old trial-division method.
In the middle is our algorithm,
just calling the sieve
to generate all primes up to 'n'.
And on the right is this proposal,
where we just call the sieve to generate
primes up to the square root of 'n' –
and then call trial division
just on those primes.
And let's see what happens with small input.
As we can see initially,
the sieve takes many steps.
So, even in the modified version
on the right,
is actually slower than trial division –
and as the input grows, the number of steps
in the sieve grows even faster.
So let's just forget the middle
and compare trial division
versus the sieve up to
the square root of n + trial division.
And here, we can see the old trial-division
method is much more efficient.
The number of steps in our sieve
to square root of 'n' + trial division
is growing much faster.
So, it is actually not an improvement.
And below, is the program I used
to do this comparison.
And there is a recording
explaining how I set it up.
But now you maybe wondering,
"Well, what if we calculated
the primes in advance?"
So, the first step would be to,
let's say, build an array of primes
and store it on a hard drive.
And then, our algorithm
would just do trial division,
and it would know how to hop on primes only,
because it would be reading
from this proposed prime list.
And perhaps our prime list stores all primes
up to 20 digits, or even 100 digits.
Why can't we do this?
Well, the problem
is limitations in memory
when we enumerate lists of numbers,
which we'll explore next.
And, just for example,
let's say we were doing this by hand.
We calculate 5 was prime.
We write 5 on a piece of paper
and we store it in a filing cabinet.
Then we get 7.
We store that in a filing cabinet.
and 9... or 11....Sorry.
...into the filing cabinet.
And then we have a filing
cabinet full of prime numbers.
This is our... Think of it as a prime array.
Now, how big would
this filing cabinet be if,
say, we wanted all primes up to 20 digits?
– or all primes up to 100 digits long?
Could we even store
this array on a hard drive?
And understand why this
actually isn't possible,
we have to dive a little deeper into
how large does this actually grow
– this prime array –
and what is the size limitation of modern-day
and even future computer hardware?