What I wanna do in this video is talk a little bit about maybe why the plates are actually moving in the first place.
And nothing I'm talking about in this video has been definitively proved,
this is just kind of the current thinking, the leading thinking on why plates are actually moving.
Although we haven't seen the definitive evidence yet
and there's probably a combination of a bunch of things.
Now before we even talk about plates, let's just talk about convection.
And you might already be familiar with the term,
but just in case you're not, let's do a little bit of review of convection.
So let's say I have a pot over here,
so that is my pot and it contains some water.
So I have water in my pot.
And let's say I only heat one end of the pot.
So I put a flame right over at that end of the pot.
So what's going to happen?
Well the water that's right overthe flame
is going to be warmed up more then any of the other water.
so this water is going to get warmed.
But when it gets warmed, it also becomes less dense.
when you have a fluid, if you warm it up,
the molecules are vibrating more, they have more kinetic energy,
they're going to bounce further distances away from each other,
they will become less dense.
and if you have something that's less dense
and it's surrounded by things that are more dense,
and we're dealing with a kind of fluid state right here,
that warm less dense water is going to move upwards.
When it moves upwards, something has to replace it,
so you're going to have cooler water from this side of the container
kind of replacing with that water.
Now, this water as it rises, what's going to happen to it?
Well, it's going to cool down,
it's going to get further from the flame, it's going to mix with maybe some of the other water,
where the other water transfers some of its kinetic energy to the neighboring water,
so it will cool down.
But once it cools down, what is going the water do?
Remember, in general, the closer you are to the flame,
so the water closer to the flame in general is going to be warmer,
so all of this stuff is going to be warmer
and all of this stuff up here, like the coldest water is always going to be furthest from the flame.
And so the coldest water is going to be over here,
but remember, the coldest water is also the densest water.
So this water over here is dense.
And so it will sink, it's denser than the water around it,
and it also helps to replace the water that's going here to get warmed up again.
And so you the cycle here:
warm water rises, moves over to the right right here
and then goes back down as it cools down and is denser, then it gets warmed up again.
So this process is essentially transferring the heat.
It's allowing the heat to be transformed from this warm spot throughout the fluid.
So we call this process as this is convection.
Now, the reason why we think the plates are moving
is because we think that there are similar types of convection currents
in the asthenosphere, in the mantle, in the more fluid part of the mantle.
Remember, most of the mantle you can view as the mushy, spongy,
not quite liquid but not quite solid state, kind of plastic,
kind of mush paste, it can kind of flow like a super super thick, you know...
like super-viscous fliud, so not quite solid, not quite liquid. But the same thing could be happening.
You have certain areas in the mantle that are hotter than others, in particular in the asthenosphere,
and those areas, that's where you're going to have the material of the mantle moving up
bacause it's hotter, it's less dense and it will move up
and maybe it will cause one of these divergent rifts where plate material and crustal material is forming.
And then as it moves up it cools down,
and eventually sinks.
Although here it get heated up again.
So it has these kind of circular motion just like we saw with the boiling water.
And so that process, remember this isn't completely liquid, it is rocky,
so it's going to potentially be able to take other things with it,
it could maybe drag the crust along with it and that would cause,
actually it could drag the lithosphere along with it, not just the crust,
it could drag all this rigid rock appear along with it
causing it to move in that general direction.
So you have the drag there, you can also imagine that this kind of suction effect,
where if you view it as a fluid you have a bunch of fluid coming down here,
so it kind of pull the lithosphere down at those points
and if will kind of push the lithosphere up at those points.
So you have these convection currents that are essentially dragging...
you know, these aren't going to be super-fast-moving fluid convection currents
like you would expect with boiling water or with heated water,
these would be slow-moving convection currents, but they're moving enough
and they're able to kind of put enough drag on the lithosphere to take the lithosphere along with it.
And so that's kind of the high level, the dominant theory as to why the're moving.
There's other one to talk about,
maybe these lithospheric plates they kind of thicken as they move further away from this area
where the ridge is forming if we look at this oceanic crust right over here,
and so over time they're denser over here
because there's more cooled down material at these points
and that's already a little bit lower because this is where a lot of the land has been created
and so there's some gravitational effect,
but the dominant effect we think is due to this convection in the upper mantle.