Let's talk about hypertension, I'll write that here: hypertension
And hypertension basically means high blood pressure
and we actually categorize it in different groups. So let's use my blood pressureof 115/75 as an example
And I had drawn thisfigure for where where I had blood pressure on this side
and I had time on this side.
And I said my blood pressure does something like that
where the peak is 115
this is the systolic blood pressure
and I said that the lowest point is 75.
And that was my diastolic blood pressure.
We know that everyone has a different blood pressure, so let's organize blood pressure
into groups. let's say what group goes where
so to do that I'm gonna draw a couple number lines.
So I have here in brown, I'll do my systolic blood pressure
on this side and I'll do the diastolic on the other side.
And we're going to actually put them next to eachother
and I'll try to make them about the same size
like that. So let's say this is really high pressure
This would be like 200, and this is all in millimeters of mercury (mmHg).
200 mmHg. and at the very bottom would be zero.
So let's make them kind of the same.
And that means that up here would be about 100
and this would be about 120, this about 140,
let's say this is maybe 160, and this is 180.
And I'm gonna do the same thing here, this is about 100.
Except I'm gonna go on the other side.
Let's say this is about 80, and this is 60, 40, 20
Maybe I didn't draw it as well, but I think you get the idea.
So this is my number line, and the reason I drew the systolic numbers higher
than the diastolic is that we know the systolic pressure is always going to be higher than the diastolic pressure.
So that is why I separated it out. But you can imagine that
these numbers go up and these go down
I'm just being lazy and not drawing it all out.
So let's say that my pressure is 115, this is my systolic pressure.
let's do that one first. Where does that fit?
Well on this number line, 115 would be about right here.
And actually anything below 120 is kind of in the green zone
and this goes all the way down to zero
So let's say my systolic was 97 or 103, that would all be in the green zone.
And what I mean by that is I would say that I do not have hypertension.
So that's kind of a nice, safe area to have your blood pressure in terms of hypertension.
Now for diastolic pressures, we know that diastolic pressures are
the low range of a blood pressure.
And so those numbers are going to be lower.
Here, anything below 80 is considered in that green zone
Below 80 is where you want to be.
And I want to be very specific, I don't mean to say that
a blood pressure of 5 would be good.
What I mean is that you don't have hypertension, so you don't have HIGH blood pressure.
And that's very different from having low blood pressure.
So just for right now the green zone in terms of high blood pressure.
Now let's say my systolic blood pressure was a little bit higher
say it's between 120 and 140, somewhere in here
then I'm in the yellow zone, and that yellow zone means that
I don't have hypertension, but I'm getting there, so I'm getting closer
and this would be "Pre-hypertension"
On the other side, on the diastolic side, we use 90 as a cut-off
I'll write in 90, and anything between 80 and 90 would be
kind of in that yellow zone, and that's your pre-hypertension zone
That's pre-hypertension, so you're still not there yet.
Now in terms of high blood pressures, again you don't want high blood pressures
but in terms of getting there, if you're above 140
you're in hypertension, this zone right here
140-160 in particular is considered stage 1 hypertension
and between 90-100 for diastolic is stage 1.
And now if you have something above 160 for systolic blood pressure
Above 160, even higher than 200, so let's say you have 201,
that'd be stage 2.
So you can see that the higher you go, the higher your stage number
and the same is true on this side(diastolic).
So let's say you have a really high diastolic, well above 100,
you'd have stage 2 hypertension
all the way down there, so this is stage 2.
So i'm just gonig to do a couple quick examples for you.
So let's say, I'll do them in yellow (different color).
So let's say that you have 145 as a systolic and your diastolic is, let's say, 87.
Well 145 is right here, and 87 (I'm gonna do it in the same color to be consistent)
145 is right here, and 87 is in here.
So you're systolic is stage 1 hypertension, and your diastolic is in pre-hypertension.
So when you're in different stages for the diastolic and the systolic, what you do,
the rule is that you go with the higher stage.
So in this case, stage 1 is higher, so this person would be considered stage 1 hypertension.
Now we can do one more example, just to make sure you get it.
So let's do a different color, I'll do the next one in red.
So let's say you have 126 over 101.
So this person, 126 is actually right here, and 101 is right above the 100 mark right there.
So this person is actually pre-hypertensive if you're looking at just your systolic value,
but they're actually in stage 2 hypertension if you're looking at their diastolic value.
So overall, they're going to be in stage 2.
Becaseu the rule, again, is that you go with the higher stage.
So that's how you figure out what stage of hypertension someone is in.