Let's say that we have capital f(x) is being equal to the definite integral from pi to x of cot^2t dt.
and what we're curious about finding is the derivative of this business
we want to figure out what f prime of x is equal to
well this is a direct application of the fundamental theorem of calculus
this is going to be the derivative with respect to x of all of this craziness
so let me just copy and paste that
so copy and paste
so this is going to be the derivative with respect to that
and the fundamental theorem of calculus tells us that this is going to be equal to -this is going to be equal to just this function
but it's not going to be a function of t anymore
its going to be a function of x
so it's going to be equal to cot^2x
and you'll often see problems like this is if you go to calculus competitions or things like that or maybe certain exams
and it's like "Oh my God I have to take the antiderivative of all of this business, evaluate it at the different boundaries
and then I've got to take the derivative." No! You just have to apply the fundamental theorem of calculus.
And it's actually very straightforward and a very fast thing to do.
Now, let's mix it up a little bit.
Let's say that you had the expression -the definite integral from pi -instead of from pi to x, let's say it's from pi to x^2.
Let me write that x^2 in a different color just to make it clear what I'm doing.
From pi to x^2 of cot^2t dt, and you wanted to take the derivative of this business.
So you wanted to take the derivative with respect to x -you want to take the derivative with respect to x of this business.
How would you do it? Well the recognition here is is that this is -capital f(x) was defined as this.
Now instead of an x you have an x^2, so this is the exact same thing as taking the derivative with respect to x of F of not x
that would be this, instead we have F(x^2) where we had an x here before we now have an x^2
you can verify, if you had F(x^2) every place you saw the x here would be an x^2, so it would look exactly like this.
And so we just have to apply the chain rule.
So this is going to be equal to -and this is going to be equal to the derivative of F with respect to x^2
so this is going to be -and this is straight out of the chain rule -it's going to be F prime of x^2 times the derivative of with respect to x of x^2.
This is the derivative of F with respect to x^2
and then times the derivative of x^2 with respect to x
This is just the chain rule right over here
So what's F prime of x^2 -the derivative with respect to x^2?
Well, if you evaluate F prime at x^2, instead of just being cot^2x, it's going to be cot^2x^2.
So this part right over here -this business right over here is going to be cot^2x^2, so this is the derivative of all this business with respect to x^2
And then you have to multiply that times the derivative of x^2 with respect to x, which is just 2x
So there you have it, the derivative of this, all this craziness, is equal to 2x cot^2x^2.