Let's see if there's a way to make a risk-free profit.
And let me just tell you right from the get-go
there's usually not that many way to make risk-free profit in the world,
so this is very theoretical.
If the spot price for gold was a thousand dollars...
So the spot price literally just means the market price.
If you were to buy or sell gold today and actually exchange hands,
then you would pay or sell the gold for a thousand dollars per ounce.
And let's also say that the 1-year forward settlement price is $1200 per ounce.
So if you want to buy gold one year from now,
you can agree right now to buy it for $1200.
Or if you want to sell gold one year from now,
you could agree right now to sell for $1200
by entering into a forward or futures contract.
And just, the other details, the interest rate to borrow money is 10%.
And the carrying cost of gold is $50 per ounce per year.
And the carrying cost means if I had an ounce of gold,
and I wanted to hold it responsibly,
I wanted to store it, maybe someplace in a safe at a bank,
and I wanted to insure it in case it got stolen or in case someone lost it,
that would cost me $50 per ounce per year.
So that's what we mean by carrying cost.
And let's say you could also invest money risk-free in this type of a market...
(I've just made up these numbers)
for 5% a year.
So how could you make the money?
Well, you could, and we're assuming you start with nothing,
so you could literally just borrow $1000.
And then you use that to buy an ounce of gold in the spot market.
So you buy one ounce of gold.
And you also agree to sell it in the future.
So you enter into that forward contract.
So you enter into forward as the seller.
So you are, on the spot market, you are the buyer.
And on the forward market, one year from now,
you agree to be the seller.
So let's just think about how this is going to play out.
So over the course of the year,
you will have some cost.
You will have to pay the interest on this $1000.
That's 10%.
So you're going to have to pay $100 in interest.
And you're going to have to pay the carrying costs.
$50 per ounce.
So, $50 carrying cost.
And so, when we end up a year from now,
you can sell, you will sell the gold for $1200.
One year from now.
And you know you can do that,
because you entered into the forward agreement.
And then you can pay back the $1000 loan plus $100 interest.
And let's say you had to pay the carrying cost at the end of the year to the bank.
So plus the $50 carrying cost.
So how much did we profit?
Well, we get $1200 and we had to pay back $1150.
So we make...
So, $1200 minus $1000 minus $100 minus $50...
We make a profit of $50.
So the big takeaway here is...
that these type of things here normally don't exist!
If they did, people would do it all day and all night.
And this price would go up because everyone would want to buy on spot...
and this price would go down because everyone would want to sell on the futures market.
Everyone would want to do this right here.
So the appropriate price is this one should not...
this price, based on these numbers right here, should not be any higher than $1150.
So the correct market price here,
if we didn't want risk-free profit,
or essentially what the arbitragers would make happen by kind of taking advantage of this...
it would eventually go to $1150.
So it's essentially the spot price,
plus the cost to borrow money at that spot price,
plus the carrying cost.
So that's essentially what would be the rational price for the futures contract,
Or the forward settlement price.