To see the difference between cash accounting and accrual accounting
I'm going to go through this little example
and first I'm going to account for things
using a cash basis of accounting
and then we'll do it with an accrual basis accounting
and just so you have some context,
the cash basis is:
anytime you get cash from a customer
you would count that as revenue
and anytime you have to spend cash
you would count that as an expense
you'll see that this is what most small businesses do
while most slightly more sophisticated businesses
would use accrual based accounting,
because that matches up, kind of,
your actual expenses and your revenue
a little bit better in each period
so let's just go through this example
using the cash basis first.
And we're gonna assume
that we start off with no money.
So in month one,
you cater an event where the cost to you was $100
The customer pays you $200 for your services
And maybe they pay your $200 ahead of time,
so that you have the cash to go buy
the food and the paper cups and paper plates or whatever.
So you get $200 in revenue
this is a cash basis of accounting,
and you have to spend $100 of that on supplies,
and maybe you have to hire some help,
and pay yourself a salary
so, if you got $200,
and you used $100 of that, your profit here,
I'll do profit in green as well
your profit is going to be
(that's not green)
your profit is going to be $100
And if you started with no cash
your cash at the end of period,
This is going to be the cash at the end of month one,
you will now have $100 of cash.
Now let's go to month two
You cater an event where the cost to you was $200
You and the customer agree that
they can pay you $400 the next month.
So in this month, we have to use $200
Maybe our bank lets us overdraft
So let's say, we
(I shouldn't write this as an expense),
So I'd have to write negative,
we're assuming this is going out,
I'll write it in red.
So, we're going to use $200,
But we don't get any revenue
because we're doing the cash basis accounting
The customer's not paying us in that month
They're paying $400 the next month
So we get no revenue that period
So it looks like we got no revenue,
We had $200 of expenses.
Our profit here is going to be negative $200
and when we look at how much cash,
we had $100 of cash entering into month two,
We're using $200 of that,
so now we've kind of overdrawn our bank balance.
Maybe we owe our bank now $100
Let's go to month two
Month two, you get $400
from the customer in the previous month
You also get $200 in advance
from a customer that you have to cater for next month
So we've done no catering this month
but we've gotten a lot of money
We've got $400 from the previous month's customer,
and $200 for a customer
you're going to cater for next month
So we've got $600 on a cash basis in revenue.
And we had no expenses in that month.
So we have $600 in profit,
and our cash balance increases by $600,
so the end of this month we now have $500.
Now, month four: You cater the last customer's event.
It costs you $100.
So once again, you just have to spend,
(I'm gonna do that in magenta)
You just have to spend the $100 in month four
to cater the actual event.
But you got no revenue in that month.
So it looks like you took a loss negative $100.
And then your cash balance will go down to
your cash balance will go down to $400
So this is a cash basis.
this is how a lot of businesses run it.
But you can see there's a problem here.
It looks like our profit is jumping all over the place.
Sometimes we're profitable. Sometimes we're not.
Even though our business is a little bit steadier
than that would seem to imply.