It was painted in 1821 and this painting in a a poll a few years back it was dubbed the number two most
loved painting in Britain.
So let's talk about why that might be. It's large, it is very large.
And, very British, in the sense that it shows what was intended to be quintessential
country sightseeing, It's painted in Suffolk which is an area of the country
which is very green, beautiful and rural.
Constable actually was the artist who was best known for painting these beautiful
pastoral scenes in the English countryside and something about it is unique
because what they are doing is reflecting the landscape back on to Britain
because before this everyone was always looking to Italy, abroad to that sense of
Arcadia, beautiful paradise that you wanted to go and capture.
People travelling around in Rome and copying people who had gone before like
Claude and their kind of ideas of light and colour
and what picturesque, beautiful places would look like.
What Constable is doing, is turning the lense back on the UK
and saying 'Hey' we have paradise here on our own, look at our wonderful countryside
and in addition this is, so it's the begining of the 1820's
The early 19th century was prime Industrial Revoulotion time in London
and this scene was actually painted not in the countryside
but in Constable's London studio.
He did a lot of preparation sketches out in the countryside
but he actually painted this in his studio.
He's looking at this Industrial Revoloution that's
eating up the British countryside.
He's sort of holding up this beautiful, green, still, peasant lifestyle
as something that's really in reaction to that industrialisation.
It's definitely got a homely and very nostalgic feel to it
and that's relevant to Constable because this land was actually owned by his father,
So although it's nostalgic for a sort of a industry before the
machination revouloution, before it came along, it's also
sort of nostalgic to his own childhood
and I think you can see that closeness to the land
that he's managed to capture his own pasion
and his own feeling.
There is a sense of fondness about the way this is painted,
I mean he's very careful with the brush strokes
to pay a lot of attention, you know that dog in the front
that's standing on the shore looking very attentively
at the man in the middle of the pond and
that's the hay wain, by the way, refers to this carriage,
right in the middle, the wain being a carriage carrying hay.
It's interesting because it's focussing on work,
they're crossing the river, they've got their horses,
the lady in the background there she seems to be
washing some clothes, or something in the river.
So there is a view of working life going on here,
but at the same time, it's very still and quiet
and Constable himself he was part of this
land owning, wealthier class.
He's not actually somebody who would be working
in this way, so at the same time there's kind of a
idealising of the peasant workers and also
not really showing them at work, this feels
much more still then it would if you were actually watching
a carriage forward across a stream.
If you were to listen to this painting, you can imagine
the noise of the river and the racking of the wheels on the
carriage and the dog I'm sure is not standing there quietly.
He's probably about to bark at the noise and the animals
going by. So there is a very concious choice that
Constable is making, to make this almost like a snapshot
of the beautiful English countryside and that
you could just stumble across this and it could be happening
anywhere, this painting itself, this type of painting in
Constable's paintings in general, but this one has been
reproduced many, many times and shows up
as the prime number one with a star illustration of
this sort of English landscape painting from the
beginning of the nineteenth century and I think
there is, the potential, to be over saturated with
reproductions and images of The Hay Wain so that when
you actually stand in front of it, you feel
like you already know it.
It's interesting that it's so popular now because, when it was
first exhibited, it wasn't popular, it wasn't a huge success
and he actually took his paintings to the salons of
Paris, where he had a little bit more recognition and then
came back to the UK. But the British public didn't
appreciate this in the first offer.
See how far they've come.