Solve p=2l+2w for l
So this right here, this is just a formula for
the perimeter of a rectangle.
Perimeter is equal to 2 times the length plus
2 times the width.
They just want us to solve this equation right here,
solve for l, so let's do that.
So we have p is equal to 2 times, 2 times l plus 2 times w
so we can solve for l.
Let's isolate all of the l terms on one side,
and the best way we can do that by leaving it here on the right
and then getting rid of this 2w, and the best way
to get rid of this 2w is to subtract is from the right
and if you're gonna subtract it from the right
you also have to subtract it from the left
if you want this equality to hold
so you have to also subtract if from the left
and so the lefthand side becomes p-2w, p-2w
and the right hand side you get, this 2w minus 2w, cancels out
you just have a 2l. And then if you want to solve for l,
you just have to divide both sides of the equation by 2!
If you just divide both sides of this equation by 2
and we have isolated our l.
We get l is equal to p-2w over 2.
Or if we wanted to write it the other way
we could write l is equal to p-2w over 2,
and we are done.