Deflation
Deflation is literally just a lowering of prices, or a general decrease in the level of the price for goods and services
Or another way to think about it, since deflation is an increase in the level of prices, you can just view it as
negative inflation. And so, let's say we're the folks at the bureau of labor statistics and we are trying to compute the CPI Index
And one period, let's call it Period 1 over here. We have our CPI index for Urban consumers that is quoted most often.
And we have one basket of goods and it will have housing in it.
It will have transportation in it. It will have fuel in it. It might has some proxy for entertainment in it whatever else inside of it
and that basket of goods, let's say in period One, and this is a simplification, runs that urban consumer on average
100 dollars, and then we go to Period Two, and we look at that same basket of goods,
maybe we're adjusting certain things, maybe some products became obsolete and we have to replace
or there has to be some adjustments for technology... given that, assuming that everything else is equal
that same basket of goods is now running at 98 dollars, and so, the total costs of goods and services
for this kind of average consumer has gone down by 2 dollars. or we can say, that we've experienced negative 2 percent inflation
which really just in another way of saying we have experienced deflation
now, deflation is not the norm, especially for growing economies, the way that our current economic systems run
although it does happen, Japan in particular is probably the most recent, most famous case of deflation
and the main reason why economist really don't like deflation, in particular why central bankers really don't like deflation
is that it makes it much harder to control the economy, or to fuel the economy which interest rates alone.
or actually just with printing money alone, and I'll go into a little bit more depth with that in future videos
One thing I do want to make clear, is although deflation is not what we normally see in the broader economy as a whole
it does happen very frequently in specific sectors and the most common one is in the technology sector,
specifically in hardware, we've all experienced buying a laptop, at one period..
so right now you buy a laptop for maybe 1000 dollars,and then 6 months later, you see the exact same
laptop for 500 dollars, and that's just because the rate of technological innovation is growing so fast,
that they can produce the same amount of memory and processing power for a lot cheaper now, or for the same amount of money,
you can get much more memory and processing power
laptops with big screen TVs and phones and all the rest.