In the last video we figured out that
given a takeoff velocity of 280 km/h
and if we have a positive value for any of these vectors
we assume that it's in the forward direction for the runway
Given this takeoff velocity, and a constant acceleration of 1 m/s^2
we figured out that it would take an Airbus A380 about 78 seconds to take off
What I want to figure out in this video
is that given all these numbers
how long of a runway does it need?
Which is a very important question
if you want to build a runway that can at least allow Airbus A380 to take off
you probably want it to be a little longer than that
just in case it takes a little bit longer than expected to take off
But what is the minimum length of the runway, given these numbers
so we want to figure out the displacement
or how far does this plane travel, as it's accelerating at 1 m/s^2
to 280 km/h...or to 78 m/s...I converted it right over here
as it accelerates to 78 m/s
how much land does this thing cover?
So we can say, so let's call this the displacement
is going to be equal to...
So displacement is equal to...you can view it as Velocity times Time
but the velocity here is changing
if we just had a constant velocity for this entire time
we could just multiply that times however long it's traveling
and it would give us the displacement
But here our velocity is changing
but lucky for us, we learned...
(I would encourage you to watch the video on average velocity for constant acceleration)
but if you have constant acceleration
and that is what we are assuming in this example
If you assume that your acceleration is constant
then you could come up with something called an *average velocity*
And the average velocity...if your acceleration is constant...
if and only if your acceleration is constant
then your average velocity will be the average of your final velocity and your initial velocity
and so in this situation, what is our average velocity?
well our average velocity, let's do it in m/s
is going to be our final velocity, which is
(let me calculate it down here)
so our average velocity in this example
Velocity_average in this example...
is going to be our final example...78 m/s
plus our initial velocity,. But what's our initial velocity?
We're assuming we're starting at a standstill
...plus 0...
all of that over 2
So our average velocity in this situation
78 divided by 2 is 39 m/s
and the value of an average velocity
in this situation, in any situation
the value of an average velocity
is that we could figure out our displacement
by multiplying our *average velocity* times the time that goes by
times the change in time
So we know the change in time is 78 seconds...
we know our average velocity here is 39 m/s...
(just the average of 0 and 78..39 m/s)
Another way to think about it
if you want to think about the distance traveled
this plane is constantly accelerating
so let me draw a little graph here
this plane's velocity-time graph will look something like this
so this is time...and this is velocity right over here
this plane has a constant acceleration starting with 0 velocity
it has a constant acceleration
this slope right here is its constant acceleration
it should actually be a slope of 1, given the numbers in this example
And the distance traveled
is the area under this curve, up to 78 seconds
because that's how long it takes for it to take off
so the distance traveled is this area right over here
(which we will cover in another video)
Or let me give you the intuition of why that works...
why distance is area under a velocity-time line
What an average velocity is, is some velocity
and in this case it's exactly right between our two...
our final and initial velocities
But if you take that average velocity
for the same amount of time
you would get the exact same area under the curve
or you would get the exact same distance
So our average velocity is 39 m/s times 78 seconds
and let's just get our calculator out for this
we have 39*78...gives us 3042
so this gives us 3042...
and then m/s times second just leaves us with meters
so you need a runway of over 3000 meters
for one of these suckers to take off
or over 3 kilometers, which is about 1.8 or 1.9 miles
just for this guy to take off
which I think is pretty fascinating