Problem number 6. Let f be defined by f of x is equal to, and we have two cases when x is less then or
equal to zero f is 1 minus two sign of x when x is greater than zero, f is e to the negative four x.
show that f is continuous at x equals zero. So for something to be continuous at x equals zero lets think
about what has to happen. So if I have a function here, so that is my x axis and lets say that this is
my y axis and we care about what happens at x equals zero, and lets say that this is our function. So
maybe our function maybe looks something like this. I dont know what it, well this one in particular probably
looks something like this. This one in particular, this one in particular might look, who knows, and then
it might look something like that. And the particulars aren't that important we just have to think about
what they're asking. In order for it to be continuous here, the limit as we approach from the left, the
limit as we approach zero from the left should be equal to the value of the function at zero. So the limit
of f of x should be equal to f of zero which should be equal to the limit as we approach from the right.
Which should be equal to the limit as we approach zero from the right, so that should be equal to the
limit as x approaches zero from the right of f of x. And the reason that this matters is if this wasn't
the case, if f of zero wasn't the same as a limit then we might have a gap right over there, so you could
have limits. So you could have a situation like this, where you have a gap right over there and looks something
like that. So the two limits from the left and the right both exist and the limit at that point would
exist, but if the function itself doesnt equal that value there, if it equals something else, then the function
would not be continuous. So thats why the limit has to be equal to the value of the function in order
for it to be continuous. So lets think about whether all of these things equal each other. First of all
lets just think about the value of the function there. So we're doing part A, F of zero is equal to, we're
going to use this first case cause thats the case for x is less than or equal to zero, so f of zero is
going to be equal to one minus two sign of zero. Sign of zero is zero, two times zero is zero, so this whole
thing is zero. 1 minus 0 is 1. Fair enough. Now, lets think about the limit as x approaches zero from the
left hand side of f of x. So as we approach the zero from the left hand side we're dealing with this first
case up here. So this is the limit as x approaches zero from the left hand side of 1 minus 2 sign of
x. Now sign of x is continuous its a continuous function so this is going to be the same thing as 1 minus
2 sign of zero which we've already figured out which is exactly equal to 1. So this is equal to one.
So the value of the limit as we approach from the left is the same as the value of the function. Now
lets do it as we approach from the right. As we approach from values of x greater than zero. So lets
think about the limit as we approach 0 from the right of f of x. So here we're dealing with values of
x that are larger than 0 so we're dealing with this case right over here so thats going to be the limit
as x approaches zero from the right of e to the negative 4x. And for the x's that we care about, or actually
in general, this is a continuous function. This is a continuous function, so this is going to be the same
thing as e to the negative 4 times 0, which is just e to the zero, which is just one. So this once again
is equal to one. So the function is equal to one, at that point the limit as we approach from the left
is equal to 1 and the limit as we approach from the right is equal to one. So the function is continuous
there.