For a long time the middle ages had a bad reputation
the general public regarded it as a gloomy dark interval
Just after the second world war however
the bleak middle ages suddenly changed color
In January 1948 the popular life magazine printed a nearly 600 year old calendar
in full color, for millions of readers
the colorful reproductions suddenly got a prominent place in many a living room
the images are now the icons of an era
we find them on postcards
in history books, on mouse pads, playing card and coasters
but however famous this artwork has become though many reproductions
its medieval creators remaine very obsuce
The hidden masters of the middle ages
the brothers Van Limburg
the work of the Limburg brothers wasn't meant for us
It was created for the private enjoyment of kings and princes
it stayed firmly behind the walls of castles and palaces for generations
no one elce ever lay eyes on it
or even knew about its existence
The Limburgs brothers masterpiece is called The Belles Heures of Jean de France, Duc de Berry
and it is the most valueable book in the world.
This manuscript is safely looked away in Chateau de ?? just north of Paris.
The parchment pages are extremely vulnerable and hardly ever shown to the public.
Very rarely will one of the earths rulers be allowed a gimps of this manuscript.
Only presidents like J.F. Kennedy and Richard Nixon have preceded you.
The work created by the Limburg brothers consists of a large number of miniatures
of unparalleled quality and detail.
These paintings however are smaller then an A4 page,
and are hidden away in a small number of books.
By combining archive material with new discoveries in old libraries and museums,
a clearer pictures of the lives of these obscure master painters emerges from the mist of time.
This is the story of Herman,Paul and Johan van Limburg.
Also known as the Limburg brothers.
The limburg brothers rose rapidly at the French court,
but very few people know that these medieval painters had their artistic base
in what is now called the Netherlands.
They have something magical, fairy tail like
yes, they emit something, and what they emit, for me is the authentic great artisty.
The smallness of it obviously is part of the excitement.
It's always has been one of the excitements,
very large things and very small things.
The small things are secret.
The three Limburg brothers painted landscapes and portraits with a precision that was unheard of at that time.
They gave us the first snowy landscape in the history of painting.
Smoke from a chimney.
Skies full of clouds,
A proper night scene.
Paintings with perspective
People of flesh and blood.
The Limburg brothers were way ahead of their time with these innovations.
There medieval art set the trend for modern painting.
Some painters make their career primarily because they can do one thing,
That was new or different and great and you focus on that primarily.
But the Limburg brothers did all of it.
Indeed their art is the great flowering the great ???
Like fireworks in the sky.
Huge shattering of some of the most beautiful art that was produced.
Some of these 600 year old painting are so realistic,
that we can still recognize them today.
The month December on the calendar
Shows the great don of Vincennes castle clearly in the background.
The Mont Saint-Michel hasn't changed much since the Limburg brothers lived.
Even back then the Burton monastery island fell dry at low tide.
Even though the farmers have left the city the Parisian Îll de La cité
Is clearly recognisible on the June page.
It is these pictures of proud castle that determine our impression of the middle ages.
The illuminations of the Limburg brothers certainly give us a window into the medieval world,
But its a window into a very rarerivied part of the medieval world.
It's the world of a royal prince.
You have to think of the times. These were extremely bad times.
Uhm. The king was mad.
This is the period of the 100 years war.
This wasn't an easy time to be alive.
Politically extremely unsettled.
When you look at the manuscripts however you don't have a sense of these peasants
that they are, let's say overtaxed. But yet they look extremly happy to be working out in the fields.
Mowing the hay and reaping the weath.
Of course it's very dirty work. But you wouldn't know it from the pictures.
It all looks as if every thing is sweet and humpty doory as we say.
The water of the river slowly passed under the arches of the bridge.
It was murky full of silt and dirt.
Only on the grassland and the fields outside the wall of Paris the work continued, regardless of the unrelenting heat,
it continue'd without pause.
The farmers wanted to bring the grain in before the destructive thunderstorms would roll in.
Out of the window's of Saint Paul and surrounding castles one could see the sowers run around the fields line little dots.
The sun cough the sickles and scythes.
Half naked, dripping with sweat, the men cleared the fields.