We are on number 11.
Sonia customized her bicycle by exchanging the front wheel
for a wheel that had 1/2 the diameter of the back wheel.
So this'll be a weird looking bicycle.
We're going to have a small wheel in front,
and then-- let's see if I can draw a bicycle.
Oh, it looks like it. I don't know.
Then you have a huge wheel in the back, right?
Because the diameter of this wheel
is 1/2 of the diameter of that wheel.
Now when Sonia rides the bicycle,
how many revolutions does the front wheel make
for each revolution of the back wheel?
All right.
When you do this problem,
how many revolutions does the front wheel make
for each revolution of the back wheel?
And let me just make sure it says that
the front wheel has 1/2 the diameter of the back wheel.
So let me ask you a question.
If the back wheel goes around-- well,
that's essentially what it was just asking.
Let's make up numbers.
Let's say that the back wheel's diameter--
or let's say it's radius.
Let's say the back wheel has a radius of 2.
So then, what's its circumference?
Its circumference, for the back wheel, would be 2 pi r.
So it would be, 2 times pi times 2,
which is equal to 4 pi, right?
The circumference of this has 1/2 the diameter,
so it would also have 1/2 the radius.
So the circumference will just be 2 pi r,
which would be 2 pi.
So this one, if you have 1/2 the diameter,
you also have 1/2 the circumference.
And so when this wheel does 1 revolution,
how far has the bicycle traveled,
assuming the wheel hasn't skidded or anything
Well, when this back wheel does 1 revolution,
the bicycle would have traveled 4 pi,whatever our units.
4 pi feet, if that's our units, right?
So if the bicycle's traveled the 4 pi units.
It's going to travel 4 pi units
on the front of the bicycle as well.
So if we've traveled 4 pi units,how many times does
this wheel have to turn around to travel 4 pi units?
Well, in one revolution,this wheel, it's 2 pi.
So this wheel actually has to turn around twice.
It turns around twice
for every 1 revolution of the big wheel.
Hopefully that makes sense.
You just realize that 1 revolution of the big wheel
is going to be twice the circumference of the front wheel.
And so the front wheel has to turn around twice
when the bike goes over that same distance.
So the answer to their question is,
how many revolutions does the front wheel make
for each revolution of the back wheel?
Well, the answer is, C.
That looks like an E, but the answer is C, 2.
Problem number 12. All right.
A list of numbers contains p positive and n negative numbers.
So p pos, n negative.
If a number is picked at random from the list,
the probability that the number is positive is 3/5.
What is the value of n/p?
OK, so the probability of getting a positive is 3/5.
So what is the probability of getting a positive?
Our probability of getting a positive
is going to be equal to p/n?
That's the probability of
the number of positive numbers we have
over the total numbers we have, right?
That's the probability of getting a positive number, right?
If this was red marbles and blue marbles,
the probability of getting a red marble would be
the number of red
over the total number of marbles,right?
So similar here.
It's the number of positive numbers over the total numbers.
And the total numbers
are the positive numbers plus the negative numbers.
And now, they are asking us for what is the value--
Well ,ok, I just want to make sure I'm doing it right.
If the number is picked at random from the list,
the probability that the number is positive-- right,
this is the probability that's positive is 3/5--
what is the value of n/p?
So now I'll solve for n/p.
So we could cross multiply here, right?
So we could say 5p is equal to 3 times this,
is equal to 3p plus 3n.
I just cross multiplied.
And then, let's see, subtract p from both sides.
You get 2p is equal to 3n.
And we want to figure out n/p, right?
So let's divide both sides by p.
So you get 2 is equal to 3n/p.
And let's divide both sides by 3.
And you get 2/3 is equal to n/p.
And we are done.
n/p is equal to 2/3,which is choice C.
Wasn't too bad.
Problem 13. Clear image, invert colors.
And I will do it in this tacky green.
Problem 13.
The total daily cost, c, in dollars,
of producing x units of a certain product
is given by the function.
All right, we've got a cost function right here.
c of x is equal to 600x minus 200 over x plus k.
And they're telling us k is a constant.
And x is less than,or equal to, 100.
Fair enough.
If 20 units were produced yesterday for a total cost of $640,
what is the value of k? So 20 units.
So they're essentially saying that c of 20,
the cost of producing 20 units,is equal to $640.
So we can just use this information to now solve for k.
So c of 20 is going to be equal--
put in 20 to this equation-- so it's 600 times 20 minus 200.
All of that over 20, right?
C of 20, right? All of that over 20. Plus k.
I can't forget the plus k-- plus k is equal to--
we know that equals to 640, right?
And what is this equal to?
Well, we actually don't even have to multiply it, right?
Because this is 600 times 20. And what's 200?
200 is 10 times 20, right?
So you can divide the top and the bottom by 20.
So you have 20, 20, 20.
So you're just left with 600.
I mean, you could multiply it out
if you don't understand what I just did.
But you get 600 minus 10 plus k is equal to 640.
So you get 590 plus k is equal to 640.
Subtract 590 from both sides. You get k is equal to 50.
And that is choice B.
So you really just have to
substitute the x into our cost function.
And then set that equal to $640.
And you've solved for k.
Problem 14.
For how many ordered pairs of positive integers x, y
is 2x plus 3y less than 6?
So these are positive integers, right?
We could figure them out.
The 0, we can't use 0.
So if x is 1, what can y equal?
So then we have 2 plus 3y is less than 6.
This is a case of x is equal to 1.
So then we'd have 3y is less than 4.
So we'd have y would have to be less than 4/3.
So the only situation where y is less than 4/3
is y would have to be 1, right?
Because that's the only positive integer less than 4/3.
If x is 2, then we have 4 plus 3y, right?
2 times 2 is less than 6.
And so you have 3y is less than 2. y is less than 2/3.
Well, I don't see any positive integers
that are less than 2/3.
So x can't even be equal to 2, right?
So neither of these numbers can get any bigger than 1 or 1.
So there's only 1 ordered pair of positive integers that--
positive integers, and that's the trick--
that satisfy this equation, 1 and 1.
And we know, because immediately,
when we just raise one of them above 2,
we get above 6, no matter what.
We can't find a positive integer that satisfies it.
So that's it. It's just choice A. Not too bad.
And I will see you in the next video.