In this video i want to clarify a little bit about why we calculate the percent
changes when we're thinking about elasticity the way that we do
so just to remind ourselves and we'll focus on the price elasticity of demand although we've
been exposed to other types of elasticiticies already but just as a review
the price elasticity of demand. So the elasticity of demand
is definied as the percent change in quantity
demanded over the percent change, the percent change
in price, so first i'll calculate the conventional way, the way that you would
in a tradional microeconomics class
and then i'll calculate it the way that you would just
based on how you would tradionally calculate percentages and we'll see why
microeconomists like to do it the way that they do, so first
we'll talk about it the correct way, i'll put it in quotes
cause correct is really just by definition really just by
convention.But we first think about the percent change in
quantity, percent change in quantity, were gonna assume
we're gonna calculate the elasticity of demand between point A over here
point A and point B over here
so what is our percent change in quantity? well our absolute change
in quantity from going to A to
B, we have increased by 2
so we have increased by 2, i'll write it down here. This is gonna be 2 over
and this is kinda the slightly
strange thing that we do when we calculate our percentages we don't say 2 over 4
we say 2 over the average of 4 and 6, 2 over the
average of our starting point and our ending point and the average of
4 and 6 is 5. So this is going to be, we have a
40 percent change based on how we calculate the percentages
in our quantity demanded and let's do our
percent change in price this is all going to be over our percent change in price so our absolute change in price is
negative 1 dollar, negative 1 dollar and then
instead of doing it over our starting point over 2
we do it over the average of the two, over
over 150, negative 1 over
150 is negative two-thirds or right about negative
negative 66.7 percent
if we say roughly, so this right over here. so based
on how we calculate our percentages and i want to make it clear this is kind of a strange way
that we do over the midpoint of the starting and ending point
but we're saying the percent change from a to b in quantity
so our percent change in quantity this right over here
we are saying it is 40 percent and than we are saying
that this percent change in price right over here is
negative 66.7 percent
now the reason why this is valuable and obviously if you do the math right here
40 percent over negative 66.7 percent your going to get
some lets see something in the 6's
but lets actually get out a calculator to calculate it
So it would be 40 divided by 66.7
gives you, its almost 60. So its roughly
.60 if we were to round. It is approximately
0.60. Its .597 something
I'll just leave it there, wait.
.60 Now whats cool about
this and whats useful about this, this is reason why we economists
do it, you would get the same answer if you were going from a to b
or whether your going from b to a. And this is the situation were going from
a to b but if we were going b to a
its the exact same thing. If we go from b to a
what is our change in quantity? Our change in quantity is
negative 2. It would be negative 2 over
and now you wouldn't do it over your starting point, you would do it over the average
and this is why we will get the same value regardless of which direction we go
in and so we get the average of 4 and 6 which is 5
and thats going to be over now going from b to a what is our
change in price. our change in price is plus 1
over the average of our starting point
and our ending point. Over 150 now these are
exact same quantities both are going to be a negative number here the negative is
on the bottom and here the negative is on top. Either way
your going to eventually, this is a negative .60 because of positive divided by a negative
and this is too when you evaluate it is gonna turn out to be
exact same thing. negative zero point
.60. now if you calculate percentages in the traditional way
you would not get the same value for price elasticity of demand
whether you go from a to b and b to a. and just to
show that to you and i'll put this in quotation marks
because its not the wrong way to do this in general in fact this how you would calculate
price changes traditionally, but its not how you do it
the microeconomic sense and so if you do it the wrong way
if you said from a to b you have a
you have your absolute change in quantity is plus 2
and your base this
remember this is the way its done outside of microeconomics
your base is 4 and then your change in price went down 1 and your base started at A and your base is 2.
This is the way you do it outside of an economics class.
And so you get, this would be equal to 50 percent plus 50 percent over negative 50 percent.
And you would essentially get 1, going from A to B. Using a traditional way of calculating percent change.
What happens when you go from B to A?
Well now all of a sudden your change in quantity is negative 2 and your base starting point is six and your change in price, is once again increasing your price by 1 from B to A and this is plus 1 and your base is now 1.
So you will get negative 33 percent roughly over 100 percent.
So this will be equal to negative negative .33.
Notice when you calculate percentages in the traditional way you get a different answer going from A to B or whether your going from B to A.
The whole reason why we take the percentages over the averages of our starting and ending point.
So we get the same value for the elasticity of demand along this portion of the curve.
You could really view as the average elasticity of demand of this portion of the curve.