Compare 156.378 to 156.348
so i assume they are asking which of these are greater
So let me write this 156.378 we want to
compare that with 156.348
I will go through it step by step even if you know it
Lets go to the hundreds place first
The 1 in the hundreds place represents this many hundreds
We have 1 in the hundreds place in both the numbers
Lets go to the tens place, we have 5 tens which is 50
In both the numbers we have 5 tens which is equal
Lets go to the ones place. we have 6 ones in both
the numbers which is equal again
Lets go to the tenths place, 3 tenths in both the numbers
lets go to the hundreths place. We have 7 hundreths
in one number and 4 hundreths in the other number, which
has lesser hundreths.Lets go to the thousandths place
It is equal and does not matter if they are different
as in the hundreths place it is different.
7 > 4 , so 7 hundreths is greater than 4 hundreths.
So 156.378 > 156.348