So let's imagine that I'm here,
and this is me, at the age--
actually I'll do this right now,
--let's say at the age of 31.
And then, then I go into the future.
So this is a line from the present.
And then I go into the future,
and this is me again,
and this is now at the age of 71.
So I've-- I've got fourty extra years
I even picked up a --a cane,
to help me walk around.
And finally I go even further in the future
and -and being very optimistic.
I'm gonna go ahead and say
this is at the age of 101
I live to be a centenial
and sitting in a wheelchair at the age of 101
and I'm gonna wave out at you.
So, that's me in a wheelchair
and we're gonna apply that formula
we've been talk about so much
delta P equals Q times R
so as I said Q is cardiac output
and we got R is Resistance
so we got this formula
and let's say I go to the doctor's office
and I go today, and I go when 40 years,
and I go again when I'm a 101
And today they tell me
my boold pressure is 120/80
and actually I went not too long ago
and that's pretty much what they told me it was.
and I go in the future,
and in 40 years they tell me it's actually gone up
my blood pressure's now 150/90
an in fact I go again mhen I'm 101
and they say it's 180/ --let's say /105.
So, the blood pressure is raising
and that's bawically what I'm told.
And they say, well-- you know,
you gotta make sure you eat well,
and excersice, and--
and that should help your blood pressure.
And I'm left to wondering
what the connection is between the two.
So, let's figure out what the connection is exactly
So, my blood pressure I just said it's 120/80
and if I wanna figure out my mean arterial pressure
so my [mean arterial pressure]
meaning the average pressure in my arteries
I've actually used my blood pressure
to keep me a guess as to what it's gonna be.
So I know that I spend about 1/3 --
my mean arterial pressure is gonna equal
1/3 times my systolic
'cause I know I spend about 1/3 of the time--
my heart does, anyway--
it spends about 1/3 of this time beating
and it spends 2/3 of the time relaxing
and the relaxing pressure is the diastolic pressure,
that's 80.
And so that works at about 95
and so that's how I came up with that 95 number
and that's also why it's not exactly 100