Convert log base 4 of 2 equals 1/2 into an exponential equation
So logarithm literally tells you
so if we were to just look at this part over here.
A logarithm is just saying tell me the exponent
that I would have to raise my base to
that I would have to raise 4 to to get to 2.
So tell me the exponent that I would have to raise it to, to get to 2.
And so this equation written as a logarithmic equation
says: I need to raise 4 to the 1/2 power in order to get 2.
So if I wanted to write it as an exponential equation,
I could literally just say: well if I raise 4, and that's this 4 right over here, that's my base,
To this exponent, to the 1/2 power,
then that is going to be equal to 2.
And we're done. We've written the same equation as an exponential equation.
The value of a logarithm, this is to think:
What do I get if I raise 4 to the 1/2 power?
I get 2 if I raise 4 to the 1/2 power.
This is saying: What power do I have to raise 4 to to get to 2?
And then that is equal to 1/2.
So logarithm is saying: What power do I have to raise the base to
to get what's inside the logarithm.
This says: what do I get to when I raise 4 to the 1/2 power.