Before we do some alkene nomenclature, let's look at two famous alkenes.
So, over here on the left we have (R) - limonene.
So, the -ene ending gives away the fact that limonene has double bonds in it.
So, (R) - limonene smells like oranges.
So, it's the molecule that gives oranges its smell.
So, even if you've never heard of the limonene molecule you've definitely smelled it before.
Over here on the right we have another alkene called alpha-pinene, so the -ene ending tells you that
there's an alkene or double bond present in the molecule.
Alpha-pinene is one of the main constituents of turpentine,
which most people know is a solvent used in oil painting.
And, some people think that turpentine has a bad smell to it,
and that's incorrect there are definitely some bad forms of turpentine but if you get some high-quality turpentine
alpha-pinene has a very, very nice smell.
So limonene and pinene two molecules with great smells to them.
Let's take a look at some simpler alkenes and see if we can name them...
So if I were to look at an alkene, and it looks like this... let's go like that,
put our double bond right here...
And how would I name this according to IUPAC nomenclature?
Well, when we named our alkanes the first thing we did was found our longest carbon chain.
And we're going to do the same thing for alkenes,
Except this time we're going to find our longest carbon chain that includes our double bond.
So the longest carbon chain that includes our double bond...
it could go like this.
So that would be our longest carbon chain including our double bond.
And how many carbons is that?
One, two, three, four, five, six.
Six total carbons.
When we were naming alkanes we called our six carbon alkane, we called that hexane.
Obviously we can no longer use that name.
We do have six carbons,
We do have six carbons but we have a double bond present.
...in the molecule so it is an alkene instead of an alkane.
And we've just seen how the -ene ending is used to identify alkenes.
So instead of an -ane ending for an alkane we're going to use an -ene ending.
So instead of hexane we're going to call this hexene.
When I go to my next step I'm going to need to number my carbon chain.
And I'll number it to give my double bond the lest number possible.
So I have two options, I could start with this carbon on the right... I could make that carbon number one,
Or I could start with this carbon down at the bottom I could make that carbon number one.
You want to give your double bond the lowest number possible.
So I'm going to start with the carbon at the top right,
to be carbon one.
So if this is carbon one, this must be carbon two,
carbon three, four, five, and six.
So my double bond starts at carbon two so I'm going to
go ahead and put a 2 in front of this and make it 2-hexene.
So it's implied that the double bond finishes at the next carbon.
So the double bond spans the distance between carbon two and carbon three.