So I'm going to write out a number
then we're going to think about
how we could say
or actually write that number.
So...I'm just going to write it out.
I'm going to have to resist the temptation
to actually speak it out
'cause that's normally how I operate,
but I'm not going to do that right now.
I'm not gonna do that right now.
So there's several ways that we can
pronounce this, and I encourage you to pause it
and try to pronounce it yourself.
You might not even need to pause it!
Well, the first thing that jumps out -
well we've got twenty thousand and then some.
So maybe we should write it that way.
So we've got, we've got...
...twenty thousand...twenty...
Actually let me write it out as numbers first,
to really decompose it.
So we have twenty thousand,
and then what do we have on top of that?
Well we have five tenths.
This is the tenths place,
so we can literally rewrite that as
five tenths...five tenths...
then we have zero...zero hundredths.
I'll write that as a hundredths place
just so that we can keep track of it,
and then finally we have seven thousandths.
That's the thousandths place,
so we can write that plus seven thousandths.
So if we were to write down
everything I just...that I just spoke out loud,
we would just say that this is twenty
(let me write that a little bit neater)...
...this is twenty thousand...
...twenty thousand and five tenths...
...and five...
Let me write out the word...
...and five tenths and seven thousandths...
...and seven thousandths...
Now this isn't the only way to say this.
Another way of thinking about it
is to try to merge the five tenths and
the seven thousandths in terms of thousandths.
So let's think about this.
So we could write this as...
...so once again we would have
our twenty thousand...twenty thousand...
...but instead of five tenths and seven thousandths
let's write our five tenths in terms of thousands.
And the easiest way to do it is to multiply
the numerator and the denominator both, here...
...by a hundred. So then we will have...
...so this five tenths is the same thing as
five hundred over a thousand.
And this seven thousandths is still
seven thousandths,
and these two combined are
five hundred and seven over a thousand.
Five hundred seven over a thousand.
So we could just call this: twenty thousand
and five hundred and seven thousandths.
So let's write that down.
So we could just say this is
twenty thousand...
...twenty thousand...
...and...and...
...five hundred...
...and seven...
...five hundred and seven thousandths.
Thousandths...thousandths, thousandths
this is one over a thousand,
while this right over here (thousand of course),
actually represents one thousand.
So we've got twenty thousands
(that's that right over there)
and five hundred seven thousandths.