We're on problem 12
0.1 plus 0.1 squared plus 0.1 to the third
So that's the same thing as 0.1
What's 0.1 squared?
It's 1 times 1 with 2 numbers to the right of the decimal
so it's 0.01
And then to the third power
You're just going to end up 1/10 of that, right?
0.01 times 0.1
Well that's 1 with 3 numbers to the right
of the decimal point
If I'm going to add them all up, I get 1, 1, 1
And that is answer B
They're making sure you can multiply your decimals
Problem 13
If you have trouble with decimals
you might want to get on the Khan Academy--
the actual application, it's free--
and just work through the basic arithmetic
because we have actually a bunch of things on multiplying
decimals and stuff
You have to start at 1 plus 1
but it makes sure you don't have any holes in your knowledge
It eventually gets to algebra and trigonometry and calculus
You might find that useful
Anyway, question 13
A carpenter constructed a rectangular sandbox
with a capacity of 10 cubic feet
If the carpenter were to make a similar box twice as long--
2 times length-- twice as wide-- 2 times width--
and twice as high as the first sandbox
what would be the capacity
in cubic feet of the second sandbox?
So you might want to visualize it, right?
The best way to visualize it is probably
how many of the old ones could fit?
So if this was one of the old ones
and now I'm going to make a new one that's 2 times the size
in every dimension, right?
That's 2 times the height
So essentially, I could increase the width by 2
Increase the depth by 2, or whatever you want to call it
Right?
And then I'm going to increase the height by 2
And I'm going to have trouble drawing
So how many of the original sandboxes--
that's what they want to know--
how many of the original sandboxes essentially
could fit into the new one?
Well, 2 in 1 direction times 2 times 2
So 2 times 2 times 2 is equal to 8
So another way to think of it
you could view the old sandbox as almost a unit
like one cubic unit sandbox
And now we're going to go 2 in every direction
So we could fit 8 of the old sandboxes into the new one
So 8 times that is equal to 80 cubic feet
which is choice D
Question 14
And these, at least so far
I think these are on the easier end
They'll probably get harder
but so far they're a lot
faster than the data sufficiency ones
Which of the following cannot be a value of 1
over x minus 1?
And I think this is one of the ones
where we have to look at the choices
Negative 1
So can we pick x so this is negative 1?
Well sure, if x is equal to 0
1 divided by negative 1 is negative 1
So it's not negative 1 because that can be a value for that
Well, this is interesting
How can we ever make this equal to 0?
The only way we can get this close to 0 is
if the denominator becomes a really huge number, right?
But it'll never be equal to 0
It'll just be a really, really, really small fraction
This approaches 0 as x approaches infinity
But this will never equal 0
So the answer is B
All of the other things are completely possible
You just have to realize, you should just see choice B
and is like, how could this ever equal 0?
Because the numerator is never equaling 0
This can only approach 0
if the denominator gets really really, really big
It will just become a really small fraction
But it'll never, ever equal 0
And you could even try
1 over x minus 1 is equal to 0
You can try to solve it
If you multiply both sides by x minus 1
you get 1 is equal to 0
It's impossible
Undefined
A bakery opened yesterday with a daily
supply of 40 dozen rolls
Half of the rolls were sold by noon
1/2 by noon
And 80% of the remaining rolls were sold between noon
and closing time
80% remaining, noon and closing
How many dozen rolls had not been sold
when the bakery closed yesterday?
OK, half sold by noon
So 20 sold by noon
And 20 left
Right?
And they said 80% of the remaining rolls were sold
between noon and closing time
So we could view it two ways
If you wanted to do it really fast, you're like, OK
20% of the remaining rolls will not be sold
Right?
So you could say 20% of the remaining rolls--
so times 20-- don't get sold, right?
If 80% get sold, 20% don't get sold
And that equals what?
We could say 20 times 20 is 400
Two spaces behind the decimal point
And that makes sense
20% is 1/5
So 1/5 of 20 is 4
So 4 rolls don't get sold when it closed
You could do it the other way around
You could say, OK, how many sold between
at this time 80% of 20 is 16 more sell
16 sell
And then you can say, OK, how many total were sold?
Well, 20 plus 16, 36
And then 40 minus 36 is also 4
It takes a little bit more time
but it gets you the same answer
Eventually time is what you'll have to focus on
Once you are confident that you can get every problem right
What is the combined area in square inches of the front
and back of a rectangular sheet of paper
measuring 8.5 by 11?
So it's essentially going to be 2 times 8.5 times 11
If you just multiplied 8.5 times 11
that would give you the area of one side
So we want the area of both sides
It's going to be 2 times that
And I want to do this first
just so I can get rid of this mixed number
So 8.5 times 2
That's 17, times 11, which is going to be what?
17 times 11 is 170
Because that's 17 times 10, plus 17
So that's 187
That's choice E
Let's do problem 17
150 is what percent of 30?
So 150 is equal to x percent of 30 times 30
Or another way we could write that is--
well, let me just write it as a variable
Let's figure it out as a decimal
And then once you know a decmial, it's easy to convert that
So 150 is equal to x of 36 or 36x
This is some number times 36
Divide both sides by 36
You get x is equal to 150/36
Let's see, I think we can divide the top and the bottom
Definitely we can divide them by 6
6 goes into 150 25 times
And it goes into 36 6 times
Right?
Oh wait, what am I doing?
It's 30
My own handwriting got me caught up
This is a much easier problem than what I was doing
They're saying 150 is what percent of 30, right?
So it's x times 30
This is easy
You divide both sides by 30
I mistakenly wrote 36 there
Divide both sides by 30, you get 5 is equal to x, right?
If you wanted to write 5 as a percentage
you just multiply both sides by 100
So you could say x is equal to 500%
And that makes sense
150 is 5 times 30
100% of 30 is 30
200% of 30 is 60
And so forth
So 500% of 30 is 150
That took me too long I think
E
Got to make sure your handwriting is good
Next question
The ratio 2:1/3 is equal to-- Well, 2 divided by 1/3 is
equal to 2 times 3/1, which is equal to 6/1
So 2:1/3 is the same thing as the ratio of 6:1
which is choice A
Right?
2:1/3 is equal to 6:1
Another way to think about it is 2 is 6 times 1/3
And 6 is 6 times 1
Same thing
So 18 is A
Next question
Running at the same constant rate
6 identical machines
can produce a total of 270 bottles per minute
At this rate
how many bottles could 10 such machines produce in 4 minutes?
OK, so how much does each produce per minute?
So 1 machine will produce 270 divided by 6 bottles per minute
Right?
That's one machine
I just divided both sides by 6
6 machines produce that
So 10 machines would produce 10 times as many per minute
So 10 times this is 2,700 divided by 6 bottles per minute
And if they want to know how much 10 machines
are going to produce in 4 minutes
you just multiply this times 4
So this is how much they produce in 1 minute
so the answer's going to be 2,700 times 4 divided by 6
So let me see if I can do this math fast
So 6 is equal to 2 times 3
If you divide 2,700 by 3, that's 900
And 3 divided by 3 is 1
And then 4 divided by 2 is 2
So 900 times 2 is equal to 1,800
And that is choice B
And I'm all out of time
See you in the next video