What I thought I would attempt to do in this and the next few
videos is just to give a scaffold of American history, I'm clearly
going to glaze over a lot of the details, but hopefully it will
give you a sense of how at least everything fits in together
and at least the major events in American history,
now when I talk about American history I mean United States
history, and so the first real successful settlement in what's
now the United States was at Jamestown, and that's Jamestown
Virginia, right over here in 1607, and it was set up as a kind of
a commercial settlement, and then shortly after that, and we always
learn this in school with you know the pilgrims on the Mayflower
sailing the oceans blue and all the rest, they were kinda the next
major settlement in the new world, I guess we should say the
next major English settlement, there were obviously the Spanish
and the Portuguese were already settling the New World with
a good bit of success at this point, but we're talking about the
English settlements, and so the pilgrims settled Plymouth in what's
now Plymouth, Massachusetts, in 1620 and at, obviously from 1620 until the mid 1700s
you just had a huge influx of people, migrating and cities
developing, but I'm going to fast forward all the way to the mid -
1700's, so this is actually a huge amount of time that I'm
just not providing any details over because I'm just going
focus on the major events in American history, so this is 130
year period where things were just getting built out more, they were getting more developed
and I'm going to fast forward to 1754 because at this period,
you had essentially the entire east coast of what's now the US
these were the thirteen colonies of the United States, well they're not the United States, yet.
They are the 13 British colonies, but these are English settlements
and then if you go a little bit to the
north-west, from there you have all the French settlements
and obviously still in these parts, you know, in Quebec and Canada people speak French
but you had the french settlements up in this area, up in this area
over here, I'm not going to go into the details, each of these can
be a whole series of videos, and hopefully in the future I will make
them a whole series of videos, but you fast forward to 1754
and you start having the French and the British start getting into
squabbles over territory where Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania is right now.
In 1754, and that starts the French and Indian war,
and I want to be very clear here, because this is one of the biggest
points of confusion when people learn American history,
Since it's called the French and Indian war they think its between the French
and the Indians, but its not its. It was the French and the Indians against, against
the British and the colonists so in this war the British and the
colonists were on the same side against the French and the Indians, and then obviously
there were some Indians who were also on the side of the British,
but its called the French and Indian war because these were the people
that the British were fighting against, now if anyone outside of the
United States talks about the French and Indian war they'll not call it the French and Indian war, they'll really just call that
the American theater of the Seven Years War, because it eventually evolves
into a much bigger conflict, between Great Britain and France
that is going on in Europe, and the French and Indian war was really
just the American theater of it. So between, between 7 -- the French and Indian war starts in
1754 based on these disputes over Pittsburgh, but that wasn't the only
thing there were all of these other things, and other tensions
that were developing and the thing that starts the war is never the only
factor it is always just the tipping point, but that leads to a
bigger war in Europe, and that's the Seven Years War, that starts in 1756 and ends
they both end because they are really the same war
in 1763 with the Treaty of Paris, Treaty of Paris in 1763 and the big take-away of that
is that really most of what France had in the new world now becomes
essentially a part of the British Empire now becomes British colonies
or British territories, and even Louisiana goes over to Spain, at this point
and you'll see it goes back to France for a little bit in 1800
and then it goes back to the United States, in 1803 but we'll see
that in a second, so 1763 the British with this huge costly war
that they were able to win, and at least from the point of view of the
British they felt that the main beneficiaries of this war were the Americans
because they were able to get all this new territory all of this new area
that they can now trade with, so that they can now potentially settle,
and so the British decide to start taxing the Americans for at least some portion
to recoup some portion of the cost of the war so they pass in 1765 they
pass the Stamp Act and this wasn't a tax on stamps what this was is
that they essentially declared that a whole set of paper that had to be
used in the new world so the stuff for legal documents, stuff that maybe even
newspaper that that paper had to be produced in Great Britian and it had
to have a special stamp on it in order for the contracts or whatever was on top it
in order to be legitimate, so essentially it was a huge tax on paper,
and on documents and essentially this is what societies ran on so it was
just a way to extract money from the colonists in order to I guess help pay back
some of the cost that the empire felt that they had incurred on behalf of
of the colonists you can debate whether who was the main beneficiary
but regardless you can imagine that this this whole period
over here the colonists weren't happy, especially because they didn't have representation
in Parliament, this was done without anybody from the colonies saying
"Hey wait, I don't think that's fair or this is fair" or whatever so you fast forward, 1773
you have the Boston Tea party where, you have a bunch of people who
for what ever reason and there's multiple interests here, but there was three ships
in Boston harbour full of tea, and the tea was owned by the East India Tea
Company, and they decide in protest, and there was a whole series of
acts and other taxes that went back and forth but once again we're not
going to go into the details here, but in revolt they dumped the tea
and they dressed up as Indians, American Indians, and they dumped the tea
into Boston Harbor, and you can imagine that that was a very exciting
act for the colonists, but it didn't make the British very happy, and then after that they passed the
Coercive Act, they essentially did a blockade of Boston, so things started
to get really really really tense in the early 1770s,
than if you fast forward to 1775 you have essentially the first
conflicts of the American Revolutionary War and we're going to do
a whole series of videos on really the whole Revolutionary War,
1776 you have the Declaration of Independence, this is them right
here drafting the Declaration of Independence and thats really just saying
"Hey you know we've had enough of you Great Britain. We are now
declaring ourselves as an independent country. No more of this colonies
business", and so all the way untill 1783 you have the American
Revolutionary War, and once again you can do a lot of videos on this but I'm
just going to go over just so that you have a sense of when everything
happened and when everything ended, and we can later dig deeper
into the scaffold and it ends with the Treaty of Paris, and the US
becomes a free, independant state and then you fast forward --
until this point the US is being governed by Congress and the Articles
of Confederation, but the constitution that we have now, it was drafted
in 1787, it was ratified it had to get at least 9 of the states to ratify
it that happend in 1788 and then it went into effect in 1789.
so it depends on what you consider the birth of the country well it would
definitely the Declaration of Independence, but the country in its
current form with its current institutions, with its current constitution started in 1789 and that
was also the beginning of Washington's first of two terms as President
and those ended in 1797. And then John Addams comes into the picture
and the reason why I put this is that it was actually, this is the only president that I show, very important that
he decided to step down after two terms, he was hugely popular and if he
wanted to he probably could have become one of these characters that
stick around maybe a little bit longer than some people would want
so it was really good that he set this example of stepping down after
two terms and that he wasn't this kinda power hungry dude.
You fast forward a little bit more, 1803, and I mentioned after the
French and Indian war what's Louisiana, and I want to be clear
Louisiana isn't just what's the current state of Louisiana it's this whole
region that includes the state of Louisiana, but all the way up to roughly
what the United States's current border with Canada
And after the French and Indian war all of this business over here went to Spain.
Then in 1800 it went back to France.
But then in 1803 Napoleon had a bunch of stuff that he had to worry about; his naval fleet was destroyed,
he had suffered some defeats in the West Indies, I guess we could call it.
In particular, in Haiti, and he said "I probably won't be able to control this territory anyways."
So he sold it to the United States for what turned out to be a very, very, very cheap price.
But it's kind of like, you know, It's not like he could of protected it anyways.
The United States might have been able to take it from him, without him being able to do anything.
So he might as well get some money for it so he can fund his battles in Europe.
So in 1803, the United States almost doubled in size.
It went from these territories that had after the American Revolution for independance
Now it got all this region over here in 1803.
Then you fast forward a bit, you fast forward a bit. The war of 1812 it was an interesting one
because there weren't any really serious outcomes from it.
What was interesting about this whole time period even after independance,
the British continued to harass America,
they continued to arm Native Americans who would maybe revolt, or cause trouble for settlers
They would impress American seamen, when I say impress, I don't mean they were doing something special.
It meant that they were impressment of seamen meant they were
kind of taking over these boats, taking the sailors and forcing them to become part of the British military.
So they are doing a whole series of things that was really kind of antagonizing the United States.
In 1812, the United States declares war on Great Britain.
You have the war of 1812. It ends in 1815 with the battle of New Orleans.
But there wasn't any real transfer of territory or anything like that over here.
What was good, some people call it the second war for American independence.
It really asserted America's, that America was here to stay, I should say,
that the United States was here to stay.
That the revolution wasn't just some fluke, that it isn't just some just flybynight country.
It was able to defeat one of the greatest empires in the world again.
So it was kinda here to stay.
Now, you fast forward a little bit more,
this part of what we call Texas, this area right over here.
It was before 1836, it was part of Mexico,
but the Mexicans actually encouraged, actually encouraged English speaking settlers.
These would be the American English speaking settlers into the area just because it was sparsely settled.
But these English speaking settlers a lot of them were slave owners
And then as we kinda go up to 1836 the state of Mexico,
that all this was kind of governed by - they were thinking about abolishing slavery.
So you can imagine that the settlers there didn't like this idea.
So in 1836, you have the war for Texas independence.
And that's where you "Remember the Alamo" and all of that.
The first President of Texas is Sam Houston, that is why Houston is named Houston.
Then you fast forward all the way to 1845;
In this time period you have this whole talk in the United States
of manifest destiny, that, you know, it is a part of our God given destiny as Americans
to one day extend our territory all the way to the Pacific ocean.
So people were already eyeing a lot of the territory,
remember all this territory, this was Texas
and Mexico still viewed it as their territory, even though,
it was being governed independently by the people that called themselves Republic of Texas.
And all this territory, that was Mexican territory,
so that people were trying to eye and saying wouldn't it be nice to get a little bit of that.
So in 1845, and this was in agreement with the settlers in Texas, with the Republic of Texas, the United States annexed Texas.
So the settlers there wanted this to happen. So this wasn't a forced annexation of Texas.
But Mexico was not so happy about this, because Mexico still viewed, still viewed Texas as a part of their territory.
And America, to some degree depends on how you view it, seams like they kind of wanted to goad Mexico into war.
So they sent military really close to the border of Mexico,
even into some territory where that Mexico had better claims to it, but I'm not going to take sides on this.
But it seemed like there was some instigation going on,
some debate on the actually course of events.
In 1846, you have war actually breaking out between Mexico and the United States.
And by 1848, the United States essentially trounces Mexico.
Most of the war actually does go on on Mexican land.
Because of that, because of that, Mexico cedes over all this area,
so California, and all of the rest of, you know, Nevada, Arizona,
and with the part of New Mexico that didn't come along with the United States, didn't already have.
Along the same amount of time you both have the British and the Americans that were eyeing this territory,
Oregon terriory, the territory up here. It even included part of Canada.
Eventually, they were able to resolve it relatively peacefully.
And what they agreed is, is that the Americans would get all of this territory.
And the British would get everything north of this line, right over here.
That's why Vancouver and British Columbia and all of that is, is Canada now.
It stayed part of the British empire a little bit longer.
So by 1848 the manifest destiny essentially had happened.
We, the United States had gotten everything from
California all the way from the Pacific coast to the Atlantic coast.
And then, you know, and clearly, I'm really just covering the high levels
just 30,000 level, of foot view of American history here.
This whole time you have this tension developing,
from the birth of the country through, through the election of Abraham Lincoln.
You have this tension over slavery.
A lot of people in the North didn't like it on moral grounds.
A lot of people in the South didn't like it, well they wanted slavery regardless of their,
of their, of what they thought of it morally.
The South's economy to a large degree was based on slavery
and so all of this, you know, the tipping point kind of happened in 1860.
where Abraham Lincoln who was pretty vocal about his, about the fact that he did not like slavery.
He wanted to curb the spread of slave states.
You know, up to this point you had all these compromises,
every time a state came into the Union, the slave states wanted it to be another slave state,
the free states wanted it to be another free state.
So you always had this, people kinda jockeying for whoever could have the most states on their side of the camp.
But all this kind of, pro slavery and anti slavery, hit a tipping point in 1860,
when Abraham Lincoln, who was fairly vocal about not extending slavery, he was elected.
Then, a bunch of what are now,what we consider southern states seceded from the Union.
And then 1861, in South Carolina, South Carolina said, "Hey, we are not part of the United States anymore."
but there was still a United States military garrison there, so they attacked it, that started the Civil War.
So during the Civil War, it lasted until 1865.
Abraham Lincoln makes the Emancipation Proclamation in 1863,
which essentially proclaims, all the slaves should be free.
This lays the groundwork for the Thirteenth Amendment to the Constituition.
And then unfortunately, he dies, two months before the end of the Civil War.
But in 1865, the South surrenders, so they are not able to secede.
Essentially, we no longer have slavery in the United States.
So I'm going to leave, and it's fascinating. Just to give you a sense of things, here's the map.
The navy blue are the Union states, the Northern States,
the light blue are the territory controlled by the Northern States.
This orange color are the states that seceded from the Union, the Confederacy.
This light orange, these are kinda territories that they controlled, but they were disputed.
And these yellow states, right here were members of the Union,
they did not secede from the Union, they didn't join the Confederacy, but they were slave states.
Probably the most fascinating thing about the American war, the Civil War,
other then the fact that it ended slavery in the United States, that was probably the biggest thing,
It was also the bloodiest war that ever happened in the United States history.
During the Civil War, during the Civil War, and these are unbelievable numbers.
18% of white males in the South, white males in the South, in South died.
18%, almost one out of five white males in the South died during the Civil War.
And for the North, it was slightly better. It was 6%.
But still it was a huge percentage of the men in the United States died fighting the Civil War.