I wanna do a quick refresher on medians of triangles
also explore interesting property of them that would be useful,
think,to a future problem so let me just draw an arbitrary,
an arbitrary triangle over here, now that's good enough
Now a median of the triangle, and we'll see the median,
a triangle has 3 of them, it's just a line that connects
a vertex of a triangle with the midpoint of the opposite sides,
so the opposite sides midpoint looks like right about there,
this length is equal to the length, and so this is a median,
close enough
And of course we have 3 vertexes, we'll have 3 medians
if start at this vertex, we wanna go to the midpoint
of the opposite side, it looks like it's right about there
so this blue line over here is another median
It's not a completely straight line but you get the idea
And we can also do it from this point, right over here,
draw a line from this vertex to the mid point of the opposite side
let's see the midpoint of the opposite side is there
And we draw a line, each of these;
I can draw a straighter "line" than that
We draw, well think you get the idea
These are all medians of this triangle
And what's next about medians,
is that all 3 medians always intersect in one point
And that by itself is a pretty neat property
That one point that they intersect is a called a centroid
It's called a centroid, it's called the centroid
And if this was a physical triangle, let's say you made it out of iron,
and if you were to toss it, or even before you toss it,
the centroid would actually be the center of mass
Let's say this is an iron triangle,
lets say right here this is an iron triangle,
that has it's centroid right over here,
then this iron's triangle center of mass would be the centroid is,
assuming the uniform density, and if you would have thrown,
it would have rotate, it would have rotate around this points,
around, around, assuming it had some a rotational motion
around that centroid, around the center mass
But anyway the point of this video is not to focus on physics
and throwing iron, triangles
The point here is, I wanna show you a neat properties of medians
and the property is the distance from, if you pick any median
the distance from the centroid to the midpoint of the opposite side
so this distance is gonna be half of this distance
So this distance right here is A, then this distance right here is 2A
Or another way to think about this,
this distance is 2/3 of the length of the entire median
And this distance right here is 1/3 of the length of the entire median
And let's just prove it for ourselves,
just so you don't have to take things, take things on faith
And to do that I'll draw an arbitrary triangle,
I'll do a 2 dimensional triangle, I'll even do a 3 dimensions,
at least in my mind it makes the math,
it makes the math a little bit easier
In general whenever you take a,
Whenever you have N dimensional
that you embed on an N +1 dimension,
it makes the math a little bit easier
That actually tetrahedron problem we did,
you can actually embed a four dimension
that would make the math easier,
it's much harder to visualize because I didn't do it that way
So lets just have an arbitrary triangle,
let's say it has a vertex there, a vertex there and a vertex there
I'm not making any assumptions about the triangle
I'm not saying its an isosceles and equilateral, anything,
its just an arbitrary triangle
8And so lets say its coordinate, lets say its coordinate right over here is,
I call this the X-axis, this is the X-axis, this the Y-axis and the Z-axis,
I know some of you are already used to swapping these two axis
but it doesn't make a different so lets call this coordinator right here
A, 0, 0 so it's A along the X-axis
Let's call this coordinate 0, B, 0
Let's call this coordinate up here 0, 0, 0, C
So if you connect the points, you're gonna have a triangle
You're going to have a triangle just like that
Now the centroid of a triangle especially in 3 dimensions
the centroid of is going to be the average,
the average of the coordinates of the vertexes
or the coordinate of the centroid, the coordinate of the centorid here
its just gonna be the average of the coordinates of the vertexes
So the coordinate right this over here is gonna be,
so for the x coordinate we have 0, 0, 0 + A
so we have 3 coordinates they add up to A so we have to divide up by 3 so its
A over 3
The Y coordinate is gonna be B+0+B+0 they add to B, but we have 3 off them
And the same thing we do it for the for the Z coordinate,
the average is gonna C, it's C over 3 and
I'm not proving anything to right here, you can verify it for yourself,
but its going to be the average, figuring out what this line is,
this ine is and this line is
This centroid or the center of this mass of this triangle,
if it had some
mass is just the average of these coordinates
Now what we wanna do is use this information,
let's just use this coordinate
and compare just using the distance formula,
lets compare this distance, lets compare this distance
up here in orange to this distance down here, down here in yellow
And remember this point down here, this is the point
the median of this, of this bottom side right over here, so the median of this bottom side
Is just gonna be the average of the these two points
and so the X coordinates 0 plus A
B + 0 over 2 is gonna be B over 2
And then it has no Z coordinates so it's just gonna be 0
0 + 0 over 2 = 0
So we know the coordinates for this point, that point and that point
so we can calculate the yellow distance
and we can calculate the orange distance
So lets calculate the orange distance
So that is gonna be equal to the square root of, square root,
The orange disntace is going to be the square root of,
which we'll take the difference of each of these point square
so it's A over 3 minus 0 squared,
that's gonna be A square over nine over 9
so that's gonna plus B over three minus 0 square over 9,
plus C over 3, minus C which is negative 2/3, that's negative 2/3
and we want to square that, so we're gonna have positive
4 over 9 positive C square, did I do that right?
C over 3, so 1/3 minus 1 is negative 2/3, so this is negative 2/3 C,
you square it, you're gonna get 4 9 C squar
So that's the orange distance, now let's calculate,
and if we wanna do it we can actually,
we can express it a little simpler than this ,
this is the same thing as a square root
of A square + B square + 4 C square over the square root of 9,
which is just, that's just equal to that's just, the equal to 3
So lets do the same thing with the yellow distance
so if gona be equal to have A over 2 - A over 3
so 1/2 minuses 1/3 that's the same thing
as 3/6 minuses 2/6 so 1/6 A square over 36
B over 2 minus B over 3 is B over 6, you square it,
you got plus B square over 36
An then finally you have 0 minus C over 3
over square, that's gonna be a C square over nine
that's when we get a common denominator
C square over nine is the same things as plus 4 C square over 36
and we can rewrite this as a square root of
A + B square + Four C square over 9
So you can see this distance right here,
if you multiply this orange distance by 1/2
you're going to get, so if you multiply by 1/2
or you divide it by 2, so if you multiply by 1/2
you get the yellow distance
So this is always gonna be twice the disntsaces
So we do this in the most general possible way,
we assume nothing about this triangle
Remember that little property the centroid,
the if the intersection of the medians,
if the intersection happens 2/3s along every median
2/3s away from the vertex or 1/3 away
of the length of median away from the midpoint of the opposite side
We can use this property in,
well we can use it in a bunch of problems
Anyway, I hope you found that interesting