Factor 8k squared minus 24k minus 144.
Now the first thing we can do here, just eyeballing each of these terms
if we want to simplify it a good bit is
all of these terms are divisible by 8.
Clearly 8k squared is divisible by 8, 24 is divisible by 8,
and 144, it might not be as obvious is divisble by 8,
but it looks like it is. 8 goes into
144- 8 goes into 14 one time, 1 times 8 is 8
subtract, you get a 6 (14 minus 8 is 6),
bring down the four- 8 goes into 64 8 times.
So it goes into 144 18 times. So let's just
factor out an 8 of this, and then that'll simplify
our expression, it'll actually give us a leading one coefficient.
So this will become 8 times k squared minus
24 divided by 8 is three k minus 18.
Now we have to factor this business in here,
and remember if anything has the form
x squared plus bx plus c, where you have a
leading one coefficient (this is implicitly a
one, we have that here in this expression in
parentheses), then we literally just need a
(and we can do this multiple ways) but we need
to find two numbers whose sum is equal to the
coefficient on x, so two numbers whose sum is equal
to negative three, and whose product is equal
to the constant term, and whose product is
equal to negative 18. So let's just think
about the factors of -18 here, let's see if we
can do something interesting. So it could be
one, and since it's negative one of the numbers
has to be positive and one has to be negative.
1 and 18 is if it was positive, and one of these
could be positive and one could be negative,
but no matter what, we're either going to have
pos- we're either- if you, if this is negative
and this is positive, they add up to 17; but
if you switch them then they add up to negative 17,
so those won't work. So either (you can write
it this way) positive or negative 1 and then
negative or positive 18 to show that they
have to be different signs. So those don't work.
Then you have positive or negative 3 and then
negative or positive 6, just to know that they are
different signs. So if you have positive 3 and
negative 6, they add up to negative 3, which
is what we need them to add up to. And clearly,
they- positive 3 and negative 6 their product
is negative 18. So it works! So we're going to go with
positive 3 and negative 6 as our two numbers.
Now, for this example, just for the sake of this
example, we'll do this by grouping. So what we
can do is we can separate this middle term right here
as the sum of 3k and -6k, so I can write the
negative 3k as plus 3k minus 6k (let me write the
rest of it)- so we have k squared up here, plus 3k
minus 6k, which is the same as this thing over here,
and we have minus 18. And then all of that's being
multiplied by 8. Now we're ready to group this thing-
we can group these first two terms, they are both
divisible by k, and then we can group these second
two terms. So then we have 8 times (let me write
brackets here, since we're using double parentheses
- brackets are really just parentheses that look a
little bit more serious)- OK, now let's factor
out a k from this term right here (using a different
color)- let's factor out the k here. So this is k
times k plus 3, and then we have a plus, and over
here it looks like we could factor out a negative 6.
So let's factor out (let me use a different color)
-let's factor out a negative 6 over here. So
plus negative 6 times (k plus 3). So now it looks
like we can factor out a k plus 3; there's a k plus 3
times a k, and then we have a k plus 3 times the
negative 6. So let's factor that out- so we have this 8
out front, that's not changing (let me write that and
the brackets)- we're factoring out a k plus 3, so then
we have a k plus 3 that we factored out, and then inside
of that we just have left this k (instead of writing
plus negative 6, I could just write k minus 6).
We factor out the k+3 and we're done! And then we
can rewrite this- this, the way we wrote it here
is 8 times the product of k plus 3 times k minus 6,
but we know from the properties of multiplication that
this is the exact same thing as 8 times k plus 3
times k minus 6. And we are done.