In many ways the artist's materials are what the musical notes are for a composer
the artist brings together a desperate group of materials, assembles them into a composition
and what we see of that composition is on the canvas
and just the same way as the conductor's job is to take the set of notes and make some sense of the unruly orchestra
a restorer's job is to take the set of materials which has gone through a lot
of transformations since it was applied by the artist and make some sense of it
as conservators we have a variety of tools that have been adapted to tell us about
to give us clues about what the author may have had in mind when he was creating a particular image
This is 'The Farewell of Telemachus and Eucharis'
which was painted by Jacques-Louis David in 1818 when he was working in exile in Brussels
We're looking at the detail of the painting with a technique called infrared reflectography
which involves taking a camera that has been equipped with an infrared sensitive tube
and seeing the reflective abilities of different materials, different pigments in the infrared light range
If we take a close look at this area of the painting when we look at it with infrared
what we see is that David went to the trouble to block in the figure in the nude underneath the drapery and deliberately clothed him
David was trained as an academic painter, academic painters in France were trained from a very young age
to draw and study the nude and one of the reasons you do that is so you can get a real sense of form
not just the surface of the skin but the bone and the muscle that's underneath
When you walk through the galleries there are couple of things that you are not aware of
One is the fact that the picture has a history, it has a history from the time that it left the easel
when all sorts of things began to happen to it
This is a painting by an early 19th century German painter named Caspar David Friedrich
who is an extremely rare artist in this country
When I first saw the painting at the auction house it was in a somewhat disheveled state
it had a fairly discolored varnish on the surface and more importantly it had a large hole in this part of the painting
What I did do was to repair the hole from the back, glue some new pieces of fabric just to the edges of the painting
which allowed me to re-stretch it onto the strecher
and then I have prepared the stretcher with yet another piece of fabric and then the whole package was put back together
so from the front you really can't tell that anything has happened
So the challenge in the restoration was to take care of the structural anomalies, this hole in the sky
but to do the work in such a way that my presence would be as invisible as possible
so that all that was left in the end was the artist's voice speaking to you directly
We have been able to look at this painting with infrared reflectography
and underneath the surface is an extraordinarily elaborate plan
These trees in the distance which have a kind of misty quality, were laid in in very elaborate, precise detail
and then the paint actually played the role of the mist
Imagine a late afternoon, early evening when the mist begins to rise from the fields
Friedrich literally laid in the mist, laid in the paint
the same way that the mist would have travelled into the field
and that's one of the reasons that this illusion of a tree in the mist in the distance
compared to the clarity of tree in the foreground is so successful
because he's used the paint almost to imitate the natural progression of the atmosphere
What appear to be the essence of simplicity and purity is often the result of a tremendous wrestle and struggle with materials
Paint is a very unruly and a difficult substance to handle and it's very hard to make it do what you want it to do
and one of the reasons that artists are such geniuses is because they are able to take a virtually unmanageable material and make sense of it
make it speak, make it say something reflect some inner beliefs and feelings that they have
and that's a tremendous skill and talent and gift which is why we appreciate these things today