Thrill Soda hired a marketing company to help them promote their brand against Yummy Cola.
The company gathered the following data about consumers' preference of soda:
So they have, year by year, percentage of respondants who preferred Yummy Cola,
percentage of respondants who preferred Thrill Cola,
and these are people who had no preference.
So, in 2006, 80% liked Yummy, only 12% liked Thrill, and 8% didn't like either one or
didn't have any preference.
And so actually just from here you see that many many more people liked Yummy Cola
than Thrill Cola, actually every year over year.
So, Thrill Cola definitely has something -- they have an uphill battle.
Then they said the advertising company created the following two graphs to promote Thrill Soda.
And so, let's see what's happening over here.
And let's think whether this is misleading or not.
So if we look at this graph over here, in 2006, sure enough, 80% liked Yummy Cola, then in 2007, 76%, a