Welcome to the presentation on finding the equation of a line.
Let's get started.
Say I had two points.
Let's say I have the point one comma two, and I have the point three
comma four, and I want to figure out the equation of the
line through these points.
So let's at least figure out what that line looks like.
So one comma two is here, and two, three; three, four.
three comma four is here, and if I want to draw a line
through them, it'll look something like that.
So what we want to do is figure out the equation of this line.
Well, we know the form of an equation of a line is y equals
mx plus b, where m is the slope, and that tells you how
steep the line is, and b is the y-intercept.
And I don't know why people chose m and b.
We'll have to do some research on that.
b is the y-intercept and the y-intercept is just where does
it intersect the y-axis.
And this problem, you could actually look at it and
figure it out, but let's do it mathematically.
So the equation for the slope m: it's rise over run.
Another way to view that is for any amount that you
run along the x-axis, how much do you rise?
Well, let's do that numerically.
Rise is the same thing as change over y, and run is the
same thing as change over x.
Delta, this triangle, means change, change in y.
Well, change in y, let's take the starting
point to be three comma four.
Let's say we're going from three comma four to two comma one.
The change in y is four minus two.
We just took this four minus this two over three minus one.
My phone was ringing.
And that's just this three minus this one.
So if we just solve for it, we get four minus two is two, and three
minus one is also two, so we get the slope is equal to one.
And that makes sense because when we move over one in x,
we go up exactly one in y.
When we move to the left one in x, we move down exactly one in y.
So now we know the equation is y equals onex plus b because
we solved the m equals one.
And this is, of course, the same thing as
y equals x plus b.
Now, all we have left to do is solve for b.
Well, how do we do that because we have three variables here.
Well, we could actually substitute one of these pairs
of points in for y and x, and that makes sense, because
these points have to satisfy this equation.
So let's take this first pair. y is equal to two.
two is equal to x, which is one plus b.
It's a pretty easy equation to solve.
We get b equals one, so that tells us that the equation of
this line is y equals x plus one.
That's a pretty straightforward equation, and it makes sense.
The y-intercept is one, which is exactly here, zero comma
one, and the slope is one, and that's pretty obvious.
For every amount that we move to the right, we move the same
amount up, so the slope is one.
Let's do another problem.
Let's say I wanted to find the equation of the line between
the points negative three comma five and two comma negative six.
Well, we do the same thing.
m is equal to change in y over change in x.
So let's take this as the starting point.
So say negative six minus five.
So we just took negative six minus five over two
minus negative three.
You've got to be real careful to get the signs right.
So it's two minus negative three.
Negative six minus five is minus eleven, and two minus negative three, well,
that's the same thing as two plus plus three, so that's five.
So we have the slope is equal to negative eleven / five.
And notice that if on the numerator we use negative six as
the starting point, that in the denominator, we have to use
two as the starting point.
We could have done it the other way around.
We could have said five minus negative six over negative three
minus two, in which case we would have gotten-- this would have
been eleven over negative five.
So as long as you-- if you use the negative six first, then you
have to use the two first, or if you use the five first, then
you have to use the negative three first.
I hope I'm not completely confusing you guys.
Well, anyway, we know the slope is negative eleven / five, so the
equation of this line so far is y equals minus eleven / fivex plus b.
Now we can take one of these pairs on the top and substitute
back and solve for b.
Let's take the first pair.
So five is y.
So we say five equals negative three, so it's negative eleven / five
times negative three, right?
I just put the x in for x plus b.
So just simplifying that, I get five is equal to thirty-three / five plus b, or b
is equal to five minus thirty-three / five, and this equals twenty-five minus thirty-three / five.
twenty-five minus thirty-three is minus eight / five.
So the equation of this line, and this one wasn't as clean as
the other one, obviously, is-- let me do it in another color
for emphasis-- y equals minus eleven / fivex minus eight / five.
Hopefully, those two examples will give you enough of an idea
to do the figuring out the equation of a line problems.
And if you have problems with this, you might just want to
try just the slope of the line problems or the y-intercept
problems separately.
I hope you have fun.
Bye.