What I want to do in this video is introduce the idea of a universal set or the universe that we care about
and also the idea of a complement, or an absolute complement.
If we're doing it as a Vien Diagram, the universe is usually depicted as some type of a rectangle right over here.
It itself is a set and it is usually denoted with the capital U
U for universe, not to be confused with the union set notation
and you could say that the universe is all possible things that could be in a set
including farm animals, and kitchen utensils, and emotions, and types of Italian food or even types of food
but then that just becomes somewhat crazy because you're literally thinking of all possible things.
Normally when people take about a universal set, they're talking about a universe of things that they care about.
So the set of all people, or the set of all real numbers, or the set of all countries
whatever the discussion is being focused on
but we'll talk about it in abstract terms right now.
Let's say you have a subset of that universal set, set A.
Set A contains everything that I have just shaded in.
What we're going to talk about now is the idea of a complement, or the absolute complement of A.
The way you could think about this is this is the set of all things in the universe that aren't in A.
We've already looked at ways of expressing this.
The set of all things in the universe that aren't in A.
We could also write as the universal set minus A.
Once again this is the capital U, this is not the union symbol over here.
Or we could write this as U slash A.
How do we represent that in the Vien Diagram?
It would be all the stuff in U that is not in A.
One way to think about it is as the relative complement of A that is in U
but when you're taking the relative complement of something that is in the universal set
you're really talking about the absolute complement.
When people talk about the complement, that's what they're saying.
What's the set of all the things in my universe that are not in A?
Let's make things a little bit more concrete by talking about sets of numbers.
Once again, we could have been talking about sets of TV personalities, or animals, or whatever it might be
but numbers are a nice simple thing to deal with
and let's say that our universe that we care about is the set of integers.
Our universe is the set of integers.
I'll write captial U is the set of integers.
This is a little bit on the side, but the notation for the set of integers tends a bold Z.
It's Z for "zol" from German for integer.
The bold is this kind of weird looking "blackboard bold".
it's what mathematicians use for different types of sets of numbers.
I'll do a little on the side here.
They might write R like this for the set of real numbers.
They'll write a Q in that blackboard bold font (it looks something like this), this is the set of rational numbers.
You might say, "Why Q for rational?"
Well, there's a couple of reasons:
One, the R is already taken up
and Q for quotient, a rational number can be expressed as a quotient of integers
and we just saw the Z for zol or integers, the set of all integers.
So our universal set, the universe that we care about right now is integers
and let's define a subset of it, let's call that subset C (a letter that I haven't been using a lot).
The set C is equal to -5, 0, and +7.
I'm obviously not drawing it to scale
the set of all integers is infinite while the set C is a finite set
but just to draw it, that is our set C right there.
And let's think about what is a member of C and what is not a member of C.
We know that -5 is a member of our set C.
This little symbol right here denotes membership, it looks a lot like the Greek letter epsilon, but it is not
it just means membership of a set.
We know that 0 is a member of our set, and 7 is a member of our set.
We also know some other things.
We know that the number -8 is not a member of our set.
We know that the number 53 is not a member of our set.
53 is sitting some place out here.
We know the number 42 is not a member of our set, 42 might be sitting some place out there.
Now let's think about C complement, or the complement of C.
C complement, which is the same thing as our universe minus C
which is the same thing as universe relative complement C.
These are all equivalent notation.
What is this in our diagram? It's all the stuff outside of our set C.
And now we know that -5 is a member of C, so it can't be a member of C complement
so -5 is not a member of C complement.
0 is not a member of C complement. 0 sits in C, not in C complement.
53 is a member of C complement. It's in the universe, but outside of C.
42 is a member of C complement.
Hopefully that helps clear things up a little bit.