Snakes, lots and lots of snakes. These snakes are just writing with potential.
Similar parts linked together, they move in a specific and limited way. Part of the potential of things
is how they break, these snakes break fantastically into these snake modules. You can put them back together
too, allowing the existence of the super snake. Super snakes are obviously desirable for many reasons,
besides being inherently awesome, you can wear them and put them on things and drop them which I find
amusing for some reason. You can arrange them into a space-filling fractal curve if that's what you like.
Which I do. You can even jump snake. But let's not forget you can make mini snakes too.
Which enables the snake-stache, and starting from mini snake gives you room to grow.
[snakex12] They like to bend into this angle, who cares what it actually is besides about 90 degrees
but it begs the question, how many ways can I fold this snake if it has 10 segments?
I can notate the way it slithers back and forth from tail to head. I'm gonna call this string of letters
a slither. This is a valid slither, this is an invalid one. Since anyone who's played snake knows that
a snake isn't allowed to run into itself. Given a slither, how can I tell whether it's-
Of course snake lets you go straight too, so you can do another version of this that allows going straight
and notate it like this and wonder whether this snake is a loser snake or not.
[snakex16] Don't forget to try putting the snake modules together in ways they were never meant to go.
You can mix colours, so in theory I could be hiding a secret message in the colour pattern of this snake.
But I'm not, because I'm lazy so it's just the digits of the binary expansion of pi.
Even better you can attach more than one segment at a point, I can have a two-headed serpent.
I can play the game where I cut off the heads of a hydra, adding two more in the old head's place.
And see how far that gets me. I can put the snake modules on my fingertips and have snakey fingers.
That's cool too. I can even do super snakey fingers. [snakex5]
[snakex20]