In a regular tetrahedron, and that is just a 4-sided polyhedron, and it's regular so all of its sides
and all of its faces will be the same. The centers of the 4 faces are the vertices of a smaller tetrahedron.
The ratio of the volume of the smaller tetrahedron to that of the larger tetrahedron is m over n where
m and n are relatively prime, positive integers. Find m plus n. So let's just draw this regular tetrahedron
first. So this is a regular tetrahedron. So in order to have 4 equal sides, or 4 equal faces I should
say in 3 dimensions it needs to look like this, essentially needs to be 4 triangles. So we have 1 triangle,
just like that. And we have another triangle like that. Then we have another triangle in the back, so
this is another triangle in the back, and we have a triangle as the base. This is a regular tetrahedron
where each of these faces are going to be equilateral triangles. Each of these faces are equilateral
triangles. So if you look, so this length is the same as that length, fair enough. So that is our regular
tetrahedron. Now they say that the centers of the 4 faces, so let's look at the centers of the 4 faces.
Let's say that this is the center of one face. This is the center of another face. Back here is the center
of the face that we can't see, that's behind these two faces, and that this is the center... this right
here let's say is the center of the base. The center of the 4 faces are the vertices of a smaller tetrahedron.
So we can connect them to get a smaller tetrahedron, so along. So we have this one going along the center of
this face to the center of the base. Going from the center of the base to the center of this face over
here. We have this line, you connect those. We have one of the face of the smaller tetrahedron you go
like that. You have kind of the top, if you flipped it over you would have the base
of the smaller tetrahedron. If you connected those in the back.
You would have the two faces that you can't see, that face and that face.
Now they want us to essentially figure out the volume of the smaller
tetrahedron, this magenta tetrahedron, to this yellow one over here
And you might already be racking your brain how do you figure out the volume
of a tetrahedron and what not and all of that,
But the important thing to realize, the important thing to realize
if you take two similar, really two similar objects
and if you just know the ratio of one of their dimensions
and assuming that all of their dimensions have the same ratio
And it is the case in this right over here. Then the volume
will be the cube of the ratios of one of their sides.
So let me show this to you right over here, let me depict it.
So if we let's say let's say that this length right over here, let's call that
length big, for the big tetrahedron. And let's find the corresponding edge
of the small tetrahedron. So let's say that we have
another side of this small tetrahedron. Let's call that length small.
If we know the ratio of length big to length small. If we know,
if we know the ratio of length big to length small we could figure out
the ratio of the big tetrahedron, we can figure out the ratio of the
big tetrahedron to the small tetrahedron
to the volume of the big tetrahedron to the volume of the small tetrahedron
by just cubing this ratio, by just cubing this ratio.
And we can do that because these are completely similar in every direction and every dimension.