I've been asked to calculate the probability of winning
The Mega Millions Jackpot
So that's what I thought I'd do this video on.
So the first thing is to make sure we understand what winning the jackpot actually means.
So there are going to be two bins of balls.
One of them is going to have 56 balls. So 56 balls in one bin.
And then another bin will have 45 balls in it.
So 46 balls in this bin right here.
So they are going to pick 5 balls from this bin right here, and you have
to get the exact number of these five balls. It can be in any order, so let me just draw
So its one ball, all shaded so it looks like a ball.
two balls, three balls, four balls
and five balls
And you just have to get the numbers in any order. And this is from the bin of 56
From a bin of 56.
And then you have to get the megaball right.
and they're just going to pick one ball from there, which they call the megaball.
They're going to pick one ball from there. And obviously this is going to be one of 46
So, from a bin of 46.
So to figure out the probability of winning is going to be one of all the possible
all of the possibilites of the numbers you can pick
Its essentially all the combination of the white balls times the 46 possibilites for the mega ball
So, think about the combinations about the white balls
There are couple ways you could do it
if you are thinking in combinatorix terms
it would essentially be like saying
out of a set of 56 things, I am going to choose
I'm going to choose 5 of them
Literally, you could do this as
56 choose 5
Or, if you want to think of it in more conceptual terms
the first ball I pick there is 56 possiblities
Since we're not replacing the ball
The next ball I pick
There are going to be 55 posibilites
the ball after that there is going to be 54 possibilities.
The ball after that there will be 53 possibilities
The ball after that there is going to be 52 possiblites.
52, because I've already picked 4 balls
Now this number right over hre
when you multiply it out is the number of permutations
if I cared about order
If I got that exact combination
But to win this, you don't have to write it down in the same order
You just have to get those numbers in any order
So what you want to do is want to divide this by the number of ways that five things can actually be
ordered.
And if you're ordering five things
The first of the five things could take five different positions
And the next one will have 4 positions left
And the one after that will have 3 positions left
and the one after that will have two positions
And the fifth one will be completely determined because we've already placed the other four.
So it will only have one position
So when we calculate this part right over here
This will tell us all of the combination of just the white balls
So let's calculate that
So just the white balls, we have 55
sorry, 56 x 55 x 54 x 53 x 52
and we're going to divide that
by 5 x 4 x 3 x 2 x 1
but we don't have to mutiply by one, but I'll do that just to show what we're doing
And that gives us about 3.8 million
So let me put that off screen, and let me write that number down
So this comes out to 3 million 8 hundred and 19 thousand
3,819,816
So thats the number of possiblities here
So just your odds of just picking the white balls right
are one out of this
assuming you only have one entry
and then there are 46 possibilities for the orange balls
so you're going to multiply that by 46
And so that's going to get you
So when you multiply it times 46
Bring the calculator back
so we're going to multiply our previous answer
times 46
Ans just means my previous answer
Times 46, I get a little under 176 million
A little under 176 million
So that is, let me write that number
So that gives us 175,711,536
So your odds of winning it, with one entry
because this is the number of possiblities
And essentially for $1, you are getting one of those possibilities.
Your odds of winning is going to be one over this
And to put this into a little context
I looked it up on the internet of what your odds are of actually getting struck by lightning in your
lifetime
And your odds of getting struck by lightning are 1 in 10,000
1 in 10,000 chance of getting struck by lightning in your lifetime
And we could roughly say that the odds of getting struck twice in your life time
Or another way of saying it, the odds of you and your best friend
both independently getting struck by lightning when you're not around eachother
Is going to be 1 in 10,000 times 1 in 10,000
and so that will get you 1 in - I have now eight zeros
one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight.
So that gives you one in one hundred million
So you actually twice, almost this is very rough
You're roughly twice as likely to get struck by lightning twice in your life
than to win the MegaJackpot!