Lets say we have one ray over here that starts at point A and then goes through point B, and so we could
call this ray (we could call, let me draw that a little bit straighter) we could call this ray AB. Ray AB
starts at A or has a vertex at A and lets say that there is also a ray AC. So lets say that C is sitting
right over there and then i can draw another ray that goes through C, so this is ray AC. and what's interesting
about these two rays is that they have the exact same vertex. (they have the exact same vertex at A)
and in general what we have when we have two rays with the exact same vertex, you have an angle. and
you've probably, you're probably already reasonably familiar with the concept of an angle which i believe
comes from the latin for corner, which makes sense this looks a little bit like a corner right over
here that we see at point A and, but the geometric definition, or the one you are more likely to see
is when two rays share a common vertex. and that common vertex is actually called the vertex of the angle.
so A is vertex. Not only is it the vertex of each of these rays, ray AB and ray AC, it is also the vertex
of, of the angle. so the next thing i want to think about is how do we label, how do we label an angle
you might be tempted to just label it angle A, but i'll show you in a second why that's not going to
be so clear to someone based on where, where our angle is actually sitting. so the way that you specify
an angle, and hopefully this will make sense in a second, is that you say ANGLE, (this is the symbol
for angle) and it actually looks strangely similar to this angle right over here, but this little pointy
thing almost looks like a less than sign, but it's not quite. its flat on the bottom right over here.
this is the symbol for angle, you would say angle BAC, BAC, or you could say angle CAB, or angle CAB.
and either case there kind of specifying this corner, or sometimes you could view it as this opening
right over here. and the important thing to realize is that you have the vertex in the middle of the
letters. and you might be saying why go through the trouble of listing all three of these letters, why
can't i just call this angle A. and to see that, let me show you another diagram. and although the geometric
definition involves, two rays that have the same vertex
in practice, you are going to see many angles
made of line and line segments
Lets say I have one line segment like that, let me
label it DE, and lets also have line segment, FG
and lets say the point where the two line segments interact
is H, how could we specify this angle right over here
can we call it as angle H, if we say it as angle H,
it could be this angle, that angle or this angle over here
it could be this angle over here. The only way to specify
which can we are talking about is to give 3 letters
if you want to talk about this angle, you will call it
angle EHG, or could call it angle GHE,
if you wanted this angle over here, you could call it
angle DHG, or angle GHD. i think you get the point.
this angle is angle FHE or EHF and this is angle FHD or
DHF. now are are clear which angle you are referring to.
So now we have a general idea what an angle is and how
we denote it with symbols, it does not look like
all angles look the same. Some are more open than others
So for example, let us take two angles here,
angle BAC, and let's say over here, I have angle XYZ
when you look at these angle XYZ is more open
while this angle is more closed, compared to the other angle
when we measure angles, we must measure it on how open
or closed they are. The measure of angle XYZ, is greater
than the measure of the angle ABC.
Any measure of angles, is based on how open, or closed
they are which we will see in the next vidoes