Every year this apple farmer produces one million pounds of Apples
1 million pounds of Apples
But he's got a problem
Every year the apple prices jumps around
a bunch... sometimes it sells the harvest for over
30 cents and this guy makes a tonne of money per pound
and then sometimes it drops down to ten cents per pound
and this guy cant even cover his cost.
And on the other side of equation, you have this pie chain right over here
they... they specialize in making apple pies,
and when the price of apple goes super high,
these guys cant cover their cost and while running on loss
an when the price goes low, they have real bonnazza,
but neither party here likes this scenario.. They dont like the unpredictability of
one year having a feast and one year having a famine
so what they can do is...
Let's say we have the harvest coming up
pie farmers kind of afraid... What if the price of pie
goes down to ten cents per pound? Then he is gonna go broke
pie chain is afraid... What if the price of pie goes up to 30 cents
a pound... then these guys are gonna broke..
what they can do
is agree ahead of time... regardless of what the actual market price of
pies ends up being after the harvest
They could agree to
transact at a specified price... So they could set up a little contract here,
So they could set up a contract, where the chain
The chain agrees
agrees to buy
One million pounds at a
a specified date.. Lets just say after the harvest
at the harvest
for 20 cents a pound
this works out well
for the chain, because they can ensure, regardless of what the market price ends up being
they can ensure they pay 20 cents a pound, which is a good
price where could make a decent profit and atleast they have a decent predictability
and they can plan on
things...
and it works out for the farmer because he knows that for 20 cents a pound
he can cover his costs, pay his rent and pay his employees
and feed his family and it also takes out the unpredictability
volatility for him... for him as well
So what we have set up here is actually called a forward contract
This is a forward contract
and what it is as you can see.. It is an agreement
an obligation for both parties to transact in future
at a specified price... So at the time of the harvest, they would specify
when they write this contract, they would specify this date
I dont know what it might be... November 15th and on November 15th
This farmer is obligated to deliver a million pounds of
Apples and then this pie chain is obligated
to produce some money to pay 20 cents a pound
or essentially produce 200,000 dollars
and that way they both are essentially able to avoid
the volatality and make sure they can survive.