We're in the Brera, in Milan and we're looking at an important early Raphael
Raphael is in his early twenties when he paints this and the subject is the marriage of the virgin
and it's taken from a book called the Golden Legend
now, this is a medival book, it basically tries to fill in all the missing stories in the Bible
Now, when you think about this deeply religious Christian culture
they looked at the Bible to understand the secret story but there're so many omissions
there're so many things that are missing that people created the glue that tied the stories together.
And that's what's collected in the book we know today as The Golden Legend.
So this story is about the marriage of the virgin Mary to Saint Joseph
and that story says, that there're number of people that want to marry Mary
..many suitors.. and each of these suitors had a rod
and that she would be married to the one whose rod flowered,
miraculously flowered, needless to say.
And so they went to the temple and the man whose rod flowered was Joseph
and we can see that in this painting - Joseph who's got that wonderful yellow drape over his shoulder and
around his waist is putting a ring tenderly on the virgin Mary's finger
and he holds in his left hand a rod that indeed has leaves at its end
and there are other suitors behind him, you can see, have rod without flowers on the end.
And one suitor in front is annoyed, decided to brake the rod on the knee.
There's wonderful human narrative quality here. This is not just sacred event, that really is an acting it before us as a kind of performance.
And so right in center we have a priest marrying Mary and Joseph
and the painting is so symmetrical in so many ways with that temple behind and this rationally constructed perspective space
and that priest is in the middle between Mary and Joseph, tits his head little bit so he's just off centre.
In fact there's little bit of the chaos of the crowd that people're moving this way ahead
The people're refocusing here and there.
This painting is often compared to an early renaissance painting by Raphael's teacher Perugino "The Giving of the Keys to Saint Peter"
and you can begin to see here in this early work by Raphael indications of what we understand now
as the high renaissance style as opposed to the kind of stiffness of the 15th century of the early renaissance.
Raphael I guess has figures who seem to move very easily and elegantly.
So, make no mistake, this is painting that is to clearly ??? to Perugino, why?
I think you're absolutely right, Raphel is beginning to step out of his master shadow.
He signed the painting, if you look very closely the front of temple it says "Raphael vrbinas" - Raphael from Urbino.
And there is a beautiful sense of elegance, especially in the version of Mary,
she is painted so tenderly and she stands in a lovely counterpose though, tilts her head down.
It's that typical Raphael's sweetness. So whereas the early renaissance so often was trying to reveal
the truths of what we see of the world that we live in, here there's an attempt to perfect
to create that kind of balanced harmony as representation of ideal heavenly place.
Ideal beauty, perfection, harmony are qualities associated with the high renaissance
and we see that in background of this painting. If we follow the linio perspective system
and we track the ??? created by those paving stones behind the freezed figures in the front
we see a centrally planned temple in the background a form that was considered ideal
by the architects and artists of the high renaissance, we can think of ??? for example and his Tempietto.
It's a spectacular building and I love the way that the lining perspective leads her eye back, they passed the freezed figure in the foreground
and then our eyes are allowed to move around that arcade
that's occupied by those smaller figures, but then my eye goes back
to the doorway and then through the building to the doorway on its far side
and to the sky that's revealed beyond even that
and there is that diminishment of the scale of the one doorway and then the further doorway
giving us a real sense of the completeness of this space.
There's real love of creating an illusion of space an the way that the sizes of the figure shift
as we move further back in the space we have this real harmony here that I think is really typical
of the high renaissance between the architecture and figures, where one ennobles and the other were
one as ideal and perfect as the other, it's this high renaissance moment,
although very beginnings. And of course we're looking with high insight to what will happened.