Now ready for part B, and I've wiped all the salt off of my fingers
and I've had a glass of water, so I'm ready for some business.
Find the second derivative of w with respect to t in terms of w
Use the second derivative to determine whether your
answer in part a is an underestimate or overestimate
for the amount of solid waste that the landfill contains at time t equals one-forth
so let's do the -- first thing's first--
Let's find the second derivative in terms of w
Now, we already have the first derivative over here
in part a I re-wrote it just with slightly different notation
but I'll just use this because I need to write down here
and I can still refer to this thing.
So let's just take the derivative of both sides of this
of this differential equation with respect to t.
So you take the derivatative of this left-hand side with respect to t
you get the second derivative of w with respect to t
as a function of t is equal to-
now you take the derivative of this with respect to t
This is the same thing as 1 over 25 w t minus 12.
And so when you take the derivative, that constant part drops off
and you're just left with 1 over 25 times the derivative of w t
Let me make that clear;
this is the same thing as 1 over 25 w.
1 over 25 w as a function of t minus 12
one-twenty-fifth of 300 is 12.
You take the derivative of this, you get one-twenty-fifth
times the first derivative of w and then the derivative of this
with respect to t is just 0
A constant, obviously, does not change with respect to t.
And so we get this right over here
now this is the second derivative in terms of the first derivative,
But the question asks us, "Write the second derivative
in terms of w" but lucky for us, we know how to express this
we know how to express this as a function of w.
They gave that to us in the problem. This was given.
This is just me rewriting this in a different notation.
So this is going to be the same thing as 1 over 25
1 over 25 times the derivative of w.
And the derivative of w is this. This is--
the differential equation (inaudible)
the derivative of w is this over here.
So 1 over 25 times -- 1 over 25 times w t
the function w as a function of t minus -- minus 300
And so we can say the second derivative-
let me write a little smaller so I don't waste space-
the second derivative of w as a function of t
is equal to 1 over 625 times w as a function of t
which is a function of t minus 300.
So we've done the first part.
We've found out the second derivative of w in terms of just w
Now let's try to adddress the second part of their question.
So we did the first part.
Now use what we just figured out to determine whether your answer
in part a is an underestimate or an overestimate
of the amount of solid waste that the landfill
contains at time one forth.
So in part a we found the slope.
We found the slope of the tangent line at time equals 0
and we use that slope to extrapolate out to 3 months
or time equals one-forth -- one forth of a year.
Now, if the functions' w's slope over that forth
was exactly the same slope of the tangent line
or if that slope did not change
then our extrapolation would be exactly right.
If w's slope is increasing over that time
then our -- then our estimate would be an underestimate of the correct thing
and if the slope is decreasing over that time
then our estimate would be an overestimate of
of the actual amount in the landfill.
And to figure out whether the slope is increasing or decreasing
we just have to look at the value of the second derivative.
If the second derivative is positive
that means our slope is increasing
which means that our extrapolation would be an understatement.
Let me just be clear here.
Let me draw this.
Let me make it very clear.
So, let me just draw a random function.
So let's say that's w.
So this is a case where w's slope is increasing faster
or w's slope is increasing from that starting point.
So our starting point -- this was our slope
and then w's slope keeps increasing from there.
And in this case, our estimate is going to be an underestimate
of where w actually is after a forth of the year.
If w's slope is exactly the same as the function
over the course of the year
over the course of the first 3 months,
so it would look something like that
maybe it diverges later on.
And in this case, our approximation would be really good
it would probably be exact for w.
And if w's slope for whatever reason goes negative after that point
and they already tell us that it's an increasing function
so that is, um, that is not likely