I want to do the same problem that I did in the last video, but I want to show you there's multiple
ways to solve these problems that, should hopefully, give you the right answer, if you do them
the right way. So, once again, 1 pipe can fill a pool 1/2 times
faster than a second pipe. If both pipes are open, the pool
can be filled in 6 hours. If only the slower pipe is open, how
long will it take to fill the pool. So, as I said
in the last video whenever you do these problems
its very important to think in terms of rate,
the rate that the slower pipe can fill a pool
and the rate that the faster pipe can fill a pool.
Now right over here I'm going to define
that the slower pipe, the slower pipe, can fill a pool in
R, so its rate is R pools per hour, R pools per hour.
So if its rate is R pools per hour,
and R for rate, what is the faster pools rate? The faster pools rate