Some people use the letters FOIL as a strategy for making sure they have multiplied all the terms.
Use the FOIL approach to multiply (3x + 2)(5x - 7).
I'm actually not one of those people who like to use the FOIL letters,
because it's just a form of memorization as opposed to realizing
that you're just using the distributive property, twice.
but with that said, let's actually use FOIL,
so that you'll see that it actually is the same thing
as using the distributive property twice.
So just to remember FOIL,
it literally stands for:
so F.O.I.L.
The F in FOIL stands for First
The O stands for Outside
The I stands for Inside
and the L stands for Last.
So not only do you have to remember FOIL,
but you have to remember what each of these
letters actually stand for.
But let's see how that applies to this
to multiplying these two binomials.
So we have (3x + 2)(5x - 7)
So we're starting with the first,
we're starting with the F
we have to multiply the first terms
in each of the binomials
So that's going to be 3x*5x
Then we do that outside terms,
so that's going to be the 3x times the -7
so this is going to be plus 3x times -7
then we want to do the inside terms
we want to do the things in green.
so that's the 2 and the 5x
so that's plus 2*5x
and then we want to do the last terms
which are 2 and -7
so plus 2 times -7
and we end up getting
3x * 5x is 15x^2
plus, or I should say minus
because there's going to be a negative sign here
so 3x * (-7) is -21x
then we have 2 * 5x is
plus 10x
and then 2 * (-7) is -14
now it's minus 14
and we can these two middle terms together
if we have -21x and we add 10x to that
that gives us -11x
and then these other terms over here
we have 15x^2-11x-14
so we just used FOIL
what I want to do is show you that this
is the same as using the distributive property twice
so if we have, I'll rewrite the problem
(3x + 2)(5x - 7)
what we can do is distribute the (5x - 7)
we can multiply that by the 3x
and we can also multiply that -
let me make it clear when I say 'that'
I mean this whole (5x - 7) -
we can multiply it by the 3x and also by the 2
we get 3x (5x - 7) + 2 (5x - 7)
and then this gives us 3x * 5x is going to be 15x^2
3x * -7 is going to be -21x
then, remember this step we're just applying
the distributive property again,
so then we have 2 * 5x is just going to be 10x
and then we have 2 * -7 is -14
so we actually got exactly the same result
that we did when we applied FOIL
and when you simplify it, you get this answer again.