Use less than or greater than for this little brackets thing to write a true sentence.
So they essentially want us to say whether 45.675 is greater than or less than 45.645.
So let's look at each of these numbers.
I'm just going to write them on top of each other.
So the first a number is forty-five and six hundred and seventy-five thousandths.
and the second number is
forty-five and six hundred and forty-five thousandths.
Now when you look at everything, here, the only place,
where these two numbers are different is in the hundredths place.
We have 7 hundredths here and
we have 4 hundredths here.
Everything is the same, so this number is going to be greater.
This number is a greater than 45.645,
or six-hundred and forty-five thousandths.
Let me write that down just to make sure,
we know what we're doing.
Forty-five and six hundred and
seventy-five thousandths,
or 45.675, is definitely greater than 45.645,
or forty-five and six hundred and forty-five
thousandths.