The normal distribution is
arguably, the most important
concept in statistics.
Everything we do or almost
everything we do in inferential
statistics which is
essentially, making inferences
based on data points, is to
some degree, based on the
normal distribution.
So, what I want to do in this
video, in this spreadsheet, is
to essentially give you as deep
an understanding of the normal
distribution as possible.
For the rest of your life if
someone says, we're assuming a
normal distribution you can
say, oh I know what that is,
this is a formula and I
understand how to
use it et cetera.
So this spreadsheet, just so
you know, is downloadable at
www.khanacademy.org/downlads/
and if you just type that part
in you'll see everything
that's downloadable.
Then download/normalintro.xls
and you'll get this
spreadsheet right here.
I think I did this in
the right standard.
Anyway, if you go onto
Wikipedia and if you were to
type in normal distribution or
were to do a search for a
normal distribution -- let me
actually get my pen tool going
-- this is what you would see.
I literally copied and pasted
this right here from Wikipedia.
I know it looks daunting, you
have all these Greek letters
there, but this is just -- this
sigma right here -- that is
just the standard deviation
of the distribution.
We'll play with that a little
bit in this chart and
see what that means.
You know what the standard
deviation means in general but
this is the standard deviation
of this distribution, which is
a probability density function.
And I encourage you to rewatch
the video on probability
density functions because it's
a little bit of a transition
going from the binomial
distribution, which
is discreet.
The binomial distribution will
say, what is the probability of
getting a 5, and you just kind
of look at that histogram or
that bar chart and say oh,
that's the probability.
But in a continuous probability
distribution or a continuous
probability density function,
you can't just say what is the
probability of me getting a 5.
You have to say what is the
probability of me getting
between, let's say
a 4.5 and a 5.5.
You have to give it some range.
And then, your probability
isn't given by just
reading this graph.
The probability is given by
the area under that curve.
It be given by this area.
For those of you who know
calculus, if p of x is our
probability density function --
doesn't have to be a normal
distribution although it often
is a normal distribution -- the
way you actually figure out the
probability, let's say between
4 and a half and 5 and half.
What is the probability, the
odds of me getting between 4
and a half and 5 and a half
inches of rain tomorrow?
It'll actually be the integral
from 4 and a half to 5 and a
half of this probability
density function or of this
probably density
function, the x.
So that's just the
area of the curve.
For those of you who don't know
calculus yet, I encourage
you to watch that playlist.
But all this is saying is
the area of the curve
from here to here.
It turns out for the normal
distribution, this isn't an
easy thing to evaluate
analytical and so you
do it numerically.
You don't have to feel bad
about doing it numerically
because oh, how do I take
the integral of this?
There's actually functions
for it and you can
even approximate it.
One way you can approximate it
is you could use it the way you
approximate integrals
in general.
You could say well, what
is the area of this?
Well it's roughly the
area of this trapezoid.
So you could figure out the
area of that trapezoid, taking
the average of that point and
that point and multiplying
it by the base.
Or you can just take the level
of -- let me change colors
because I think I'm overdoing
it with the green -- or you
could just take the height of
this line right here and
multiply it by the base.
You'll get the area of this
rectangle, which might be a
pretty good approximation for
the area under the curve.
Right?
Because you'll have a little
bit extra over here but you're
going to miss a little bit
over there, so it might be a
pretty good approximation.
That's actually what I do in
the other video, just to
approximate the area under the
curve and give you a good sense
that the normal distribution is
what the binomial distribution
becomes essentially, if
you have many trials.
What's interesting about the
normal distribution -- I don't
know if I mentioned this
already -- this right
here, this is the graph.
This is just another word,
people might talk about the
central limit theorem.
But this is really kind of one
of the most important or
interesting things about our
universe, central
limit theorem.
I won't prove it here but it
essentially tells us, and you
could kind of understand it by
looking at the other video
where we talk about
flipping coins.
If we were to do many flips of
coins -- those are independent
trials of each other -- and if
you take the sum of all of your
flips, if you were to give
yourself one point -- if you
got ahead every time -- and if
you're take the sum of them as
you approach an infinite number
flips, you approach the
normal distribution.
What's interesting about that
is each of those trials -- in
the case of flipping the coin,
each trial is a flip of the
coin -- each of those trials
don't have to have a
normal distribution.
So we could be talking about
molecular interactions and
every time compound x interacts
with compound y what might it
result doesn't have to have
to be normally distributed.
But what happens is, if you
take a sum of a ton of those
interactions, then all of a
sudden the end result will
be normally distributed.
This is why this is such an
important distribution.
It shows up in nature all of
the time and if you do take
data points from something that
is very complex and it is the
sum of arguably, many almost
infinite individual independent
trials, it's a pretty good
assumption to assume the
normal distribution.
We'll do other videos where we
talk about when it is a good
assumption, when it isn't
a good assumption.
But anyway, just to digest
this a little bit and let
me actually rewrite it.
This is what you'll see on
Wikipedia but this could be
rewritten as 1 over sigma times
the square root of 2 pi times
x is just e to that power.
So it's just e to the, this
whole thing over here, minus
x minus the mean squared
over 2 sigma squared.
This is the standard deviation.
Standard deviation squared
is just the variance.
Just so you know how to use
this, you're like, oh wow,
there's so many Greek
letters here, what do I do?
This tells you the
height of the normal
distribution function.
Let's say that this is the
distribution of people's
heights above 5'9.
Let's say that this
was 5'9 and not 0.
What this tells you is, if you
wanted to figure out what is
the probability of finding
someone who was roughly 5
inches taller than the average
right here, what you would
do is you would put in this
number here, this 5 into x.
And then you know the standard
deviation, because you've
taken a bunch of samples.
You know the variance, which is
the standard deviation squared.
You know the mean, and you just
put your x in there and it'll
tell you the height
of the function.
And then you have to
give it a range.
You can't just say how many
people are exactly 5 inches
taller than average.
You would actually say how
many people are between 5.1
inches and 4.9 nine inches
taller than the average.
You have to give it a little
bit of range because no is
exactly, it's almost infinitely
impossible to the atom
to be exactly 5'9.
Even the definition of
an inch isn't defined
that particularly.
So that's how you'd
use this function.
This is so heavily used in,
one, it shows up in nature
but in all of inferential
statistics, I think it behooves
you to become as familiar with
this formula as possible.
I guess to make that happen.
Let me play around a little bit
with this formula just to kind
of give you an intuition of how
everything works out et cetera.
If I were to take this -- I'd
like to maybe help you memorize
this -- this could be rewritten
as, if we take the sigma into
the square root sign, if we
take the standard deviation in
there, it becomes 1 over
the square root of 2
pie sigma squared.
I've never seen it written this
way but it gives me a little
intuition that sigma squared,
it's always written as sigma
squared, but it's really just
the variance and the variance
is what you calculate before
you calculate the standard
deviation, so that's
interesting.
And then this top right here,
this could be written as e to
the minus 1 half times and both
of these things here are
squared so we could just say x
minus the mean over
sigma squared.
And this kind of clarifies
what's going on here
a little bit better.
Because what's this?
x minus sigma is the distance
between whatever point
we want to find.
Let's say we're here.
x minus mu is the mean so
that's here so that's this
distance, and this is the
standard deviation which
is this distance.
So this in here tells me how
many standard deviations
I am away from the mean.
That's actually called the
standard z score, I talked
about it in the other video.
And then we square that
and then we take this
to the minus 1/2.
Well let me rewrite that.
If I were to write e to the
minus 1/2 times a, that's the
same thing as e to the a to
the minus 1/2 power right?
If you take something to an
exponent and take that to
an exponent you can just
multiply these exponents.
So likewise, this could be
rewritten as, this is equal to
1 over the square root of 2
pi sigma squared, which
is just the variance.
And I'm just playing around
with the formula because I
really want you to see all
the ways, maybe you'll
get a little intuition.
I encourage you to email me
if you see some insight
on why this exists.
Once again, I think it is cool
then all of the sudden we have
this other formula that
has pi and e in it.
So many phenomenon are
described by this and once
again pi and e show up together
just like e to the i pi
is equal to negative 1.
It tells you something
about our universe.
Anyway, I could rewrite this as
e to the x minus mu over sigma
squared and all of that
to the minus 1/2.
Something in the minus 1/2
power, that's just 1 over
the square root which is
already going on here.
So we could just rewrite this
over here as 1 over the square
root of 2 pi times the variance
times e to essentially,
our z score squared.
If we say z is this thing in
here, z is how many standard
deviations we are from the
mean, z score squared.
And all of the sudden
this becomes very clean.
We just say 2 pi times our
variance times e to the number
standard deviations we are away
from the mean and
you square that.
You take the square root of
that thing and invert it and
that's the normal distribution.
Anyway, I wanted to do that.
I thought it was neat
and it's interesting to
play around with it.
Then that way if you see it in
any of these other forms in the
rest of your life your won't
say what's that, I thought the
normal distribution was this or
it was this and now you know.
With that said, let's play
around a little bit with
this normal distribution.
So this spreadsheet,
I've plotted the
normal distribution.
You can change the assumptions
that are in this kind
of green, blue color.
So right now it's plotting it
with a mean of zero and a
standard deviation of 4.
I just write the variance here
just for your information,
the variance is just the
standard deviation squared.
And so what happens when
you change the mean?
So if the mean goes from 0
to let's say it goes to 5.
Notice, this graph just
shifted to the right by 5.
Right?
It was centered here, now
it's centered over here.
If we make it minus
5, what happens?
The whole bell curve just
shifts 5 to the left
from the center.
Now what happens when you
change the standard deviation.
The variance is the average
squared distance from the mean,
the standard deviation is
the square root of that.
So it's kind of, not exactly,
but kind of the average
distance from the mean.
So the smaller the standard
deviation the closer a
lot of the points are
going to be the mean.
We should get kind of a
narrower graph and let's
see if that happens.
When the standard deviation
is 2, we see that.
The graph you're more likely
to be really close to the
mean than further away.
If you make the standard
deviation, if you make it 10,
all of the sudden you got a
really flat graph and this
thing keeps going on forever.
And that's a key difference:
the binomial distribution
is always finite.
You can only have a finite
number of values while the
normal distribution is
defined over the entire
real number line.
So the probability, if you
have a mean of minus 5 and a
standard deviation of 10, the
probability of getting a
thousand here is very low but
there's some probability.
There's some probably that all
of the atoms in my body just
arrange perfectly that I fall
through the seat
I'm sitting on.
It's very unlikely and it
probably won't happen in
the life of the universe
but it can happen.
And that can be described by
normal distribution because it
says, anything can happen
although it could
very unprobable.
The thing I talked about at the
beginning of the video is when
you figure out a normal
distribution you can't just
look at this point on the graph
-- let me get the drop pen tool
back -- you have to figure out
the area under the curve
between two points.
So if I wanted to say -- let's
say this is our distribution
-- and I said what is the
probability that I get 0.
I don't know what phenomena
this is describing
but at 0 happened.
If I say exactly 0, the
probability is 0 -- I shouldn't
use 0 too much -- because
the area under the curve,
just under 0, there's no
area, it's just a line.
You have to say
between a range.
So you have to say the
probability between -- and
actually I can type it in here
-- between minus .005 and plus
.005 is -- well it rounded -- it
says they're close to 0.
Let me do it, between
minus 1 and between 1.
It calculated at 7 percent
and I'll show you how I
calculated this in a second.
So let me get the
screen draw tool.
So what did I just do?
Between minus 1 and 1 -- and
I'll show you the behind the
scenes, what excel is doing --
we're going from minus 1, which
is roughly right here, to 1.
And we're calculating the
area under the curve.
We're calculating this area or
for those of you who know
calculus, we're calculating the
integral from minus 1 to 1 of
this function where the
standard deviation is right
here, is 10 and the
mean is minus 5.
Actually, let me put that in.
So we're calculating, for this
example, the way it's drawn
right here, the normal
distribution function, our
standard deviation is 10 times
square root of 2 pi times e to
the minus 1/2 times
x minus our mean.
Our mean is negative right now.
Our mean is minus 5 so it's x
plus 5 over the standard
deviation squared which is the
variance, so that's
100 squared dx.
This is what this number is
right here, this 7 percent
or actually .07 is the
area right around there.
Now, unfortunately for us in
the world, this isn't an
easy integral to evaluate
analytical, even for those of
us who know our calculus.
So this tends to be
done numerically.
And kind of an easy way to do
this is -- well not as easy way
-- a function has been defined
called the cumuluative
distribution function that is a
useful tool for figuring
out this area.
So what the cumulative
distribution function is
essentially -- let me call it
the cumulative distribution
function -- it's
a function of x.
It gives us the area under
the curve, under this curve.
So let's say that this is x
right here, that's our x.
It tells you the area
under the curve up to x.
So another way to think about
it, it tells you what is the
probability that you land
at some value less
than your x value.
So it's the area from minus
infinity to x of our
probability density function.
When you actually use the Excel
normal distribution function,
let me say norm distribution.
You have to give it your
x value, you give it the
mean, you give it the
standard deviation.
And then you say whether you
want the cumulative
distribution, in which case you
say true or you want just this
normal distribution,
which you say false.
So if you wanted to graph
this right here, you
would say false in caps.
If you wanted to graph the
cumulative distribution
function which I do down here
-- let me move this down a
little bit, let me get out of
pen tool
so the cumulative distribution function is -- right over here
then you say true when you make that Excel call.
So this is a cumulative
distribution function for the same... for this
This is a normal distribution,
here's a cumulative
distribution.
Just so you get the intuition.
If you want to know, what
is the probability that I
get a value less than 20?
So I can get any value
less than 20 given
this distribution.
The cumulative distribution
right here, -- let me make it
so you can see -- if you go to
20 you just go right to that
point there and you say wow,
the probability of getting
20 or less is pretty high.
It's approaching 100 percent.
That makes sense because
most of the area under this
curve is less than 20.
Or if you said what's the
probability of getting
less than minus five.
Well minus 5 is the mean
so half of your results
should be above that and
half should be below.
And if you go to this point
right here you could see that
this right here is 50 percent.
So the probability of getting
less than minus 5 is
exactly 50 percent.
So what you do is, if I wanted
to know the probability of
getting between negative 1 and
1 what I do is -- let me get
back to my pen tool -- I figure
out what is the probability
of getting minus 1 or lower.
So I figure out
this whole area.
And then I figure out the
probability of getting one or
lower which is this whole area
-- well I'm going to give it
a different color -- 1 or
lower is everything there.
And I subtract the yellow area
from the magenta area and I'll
just get what's ever
left over here.
That's exactly what I did
in the spread sheet.
Let me scroll down.
This might be taxing my
computer by taking the
screen capture with it.
So what I did is I evaluated
the cumulative distribution
function at one to
be right there.
And I evaluate the cumulative
distribution function at minus
1, which is right there.
And the difference between
these two, I subtract this
number from this number and
that tells me essentially
the probability that I'm
between those two numbers.
Or another way to think about
it, the area right here.
I really encourage you to play
with this and explore the excel
formulas and everything.
This area right here
would be minus 1 and 1.
Just so you know this graph,
the central line right
here, this is the mean.
And then these two lines I drew
right here, these are 1
standard deviation below and 1
standard deviation
above the mean.
Some people think what's the
probability that land within
one standard deviation
of the mean?
Well that's easy to do.
What I can do is I'll
just click on this.
And I'll just call this, what's
the probability that I land
between 1 standard deviation --
the mean is minus 5 -- one
standard deviation below the
mean is minus 15 and one
standard deviation above the
mean is 10 plus minus 5 is 5.
So that's between 5 and 15.
So 68.3 percent.
That's actually always the case
that you have a 68.3 percent
probability of landing within
one standard deviation of the
mean, assuming you have
a normal distribution.
So once again, that number
represents the area under
the curve here, this
area under the curve.
And the way you get it
is with the cumulative
distribution function.
I'll go down here.
Every time I move this I have
to get rid of the pen tool.
You evaluate it at plus
5, which is right here.
This is 1 standard deviation
above the mean, that's a
number right around there.
It looks like it's like 80
something percent, maybe
90 percent roughly.
And then you evaluate it at
1 standard deviation below
the mean which is minus 15.
And this one looks like roughly
15 percent or so, 15, 16, maybe
17 percent, I'll
say 18 percent.
But the big picture is when
you subtract this value
from this value you get
the probability that you
land between those two.
And that's because this
value tells the probability
that you're less.
So when you go to the
cumulative distribution
function you get
that right there.
It keeps crawling
back and forth.
So when you go to five -- and
you just go right over here --
this is essentially tells you
this area under the curve, the
probability that you're
less than or equal to
5, everything up there.
And then when you evaluate it
at minus 15 down here, it
tells you the probability
that you're back here.
So when you subtract this from
the larger thing you're just
left with what's under
the curve right there.
Just to understand this
spreadsheet a little bit better
because I really want you to
play with it and see what
happens if I make this
distribution, the mean was
minus 5 now let me make it 5.
It just shifted to the right.
It just moved over
to the right by 5.
Whoops.
Let me use the pen tool.
It just moved over
to the right by 5.
If I were to try to make the
standard deviation smaller
we'll see that the whole thing
just gets a little bit tighter.
Let's make it 6.
And all of a sudden this looks
a like a tighter curve, we make
it 2, it becomes even tighter.
I really want you to play with
this and play with the formula
and get an intuitive feeling
for this, the cumulative
distribution function and think
a lot about how it relates to
the binomial distribution and I
cover that in the last video.
To plot this I just took
each of these points.
I went to plot the points
between minus 20 and 20 and
I just incremented by 1.
I just decided to
increment by 1.
So this isn't a continues
curve, it's actually just
plotting a point at each
point and connecting
it with the line.
Then I did the distance
between each of those
points and the mean.
So I just took 0 minus 5,
this is this distance.
So this just tells you
the point minus 20 is
25 less than the mean.
That's all I did there.
Then I divided that by the
standard deviation and this
is the z score, the
standard z score.
This tells me how many standard
deviations is minus 20
away from the mean.
It's 12 and a half standard
deviations below the mean.
Then I use that and I just
plugged it into essentially
this formula to figure out
the height of the function.
Let's say at minus 20
the height is very low.
Let's say at minus 2 the
heights a little bit better,
the heights going to be
some place, it's going
to be right there.
And so that gives
me that value.
But then to actually figure out
the probability of that, what I
do is I calculate the
cumulative distribution
function.
Well this is the probability
that you're less than that.
So the area under the curve
below that which is very small.
It's not zero, I know it
looks like 0 here but that's
only because I round it.
It's going to be 0001,
it's going to be a
really small number.
There's some probability that
we even get minus a thousand.
Another intuitive thing that
you really should have a sense
for is the integral over this
or the entire area of the curve
has to be 1 because that
takes into account all
possible circumstances.
And that should happen if we
put a suitably smaller number
here and a suitably
large number here.
There you go, we
get 100 percent.
Although, this isn't
a 100 percent.
We'd have to go from minus
infinity to plus infinity to
really get a 100 percent.
It's just rounding
to 100 percent.
It's probably 99.99999 percent
or something like that.
And so to actually calculate
this, what I do is I take the
cumulative distribution
function of this point and I
subtract from that the
cumulative distribution
function of that point.
And that's where I got
this 100 percent from.
Anyway, hopefully that will
give you a good feel for
the normal distribution.
I really encourage you to play
with the spreadsheet and to
even make a spreadsheet
like this yourself.
In a future exercise we'll
actually use this type of
spreadsheet as an input
into other models.
If we're doing a financial
model and if we say our revenue
has a normal distribution
around some expected value,
what is the distribution
of our net income?
Or we could think of a
hundred other different
types of examples.
Anyway, see you in
the next video.