It was pointed out in the comments for the last video where
I defined this insertion sort that I didn't necessarily
have to do this break, the logic, and this is one of those
examples that sometimes when you just program something and
the way that your brain is at least thinking about it
you don't always do it in maybe the most elegant way
and that commenter was right. There was a slightly more,
or a lot more elegant way to do this insertion sort.
So, over here if we go into the WHILE loop,
I have this WHILE loop
happening WHILE I is greater than or equal to zero
But then, I want to essentially BREAK out of that WHILE loop
if the variable value is not less than the I-th element in list
So, one way to do this, cause I'm just defining the parameters
on when to do this WHILE loop. Instead of this IF the value is
less than the I-th element, do this, otherwise
BREAK, what I could've of done, and is actually the more
elegant way to do this, WHILE I is greater than or equal
to zero AND value is less than than I-th element in list
so now I know that value is less than the I-th element of the
list, and I will execute this code over here, so I know that this
is going to be true. I know that this is going to be true and I can
I can auto take all of these one level back and then I don't have
to do an ELSE and I don't have to BREAK out of the loop anymore
so that should simplify the program a good bit. But, let's verify
for ourselves that this actually works, so let me save it. And then
let me run it, looks like its...let me define a list, so let me call
it, I'll just call it C is equal to one, five, six, seven
two, four, fourteen and two. So let's just define that and let's try
our insertion sort. Insertion sort on C, let's see what we get.
So let's see, let's print C now and there you go.
It sorted it. So thank you for the comment.
I think this does simplify it a little bit and
it shows that sometimes you always have to question
especially if you have a WHILE statement, is there a better
way instead of using a BREAK because I'm putting a condition
on a reason to BREAK out of the WHILE loop, why don't I
implicitly just put it up here.