So, first let's step back,
and think about what we mean when we say
'make an algorithm more efficient'
We have to think abstractly, meaning we don't care about
the machine running our algorithm anymore –
whether we wrote it to run on this little old Nintendo,
or on an ENIAC, which is much slower.
Both of these computers could run our algorithm.
We don't want to think about the machine anymore.
What we do want to focus on is two things:
we need to understand what we mean by 'size',
what is the size that our algorithm requires,
and time, how long it takes to solve a problem.
We really need to nail down these two concepts.
Now, to do so, I want to convince you that
a computer is equivalent to what you could do
with a pencil, a large stack of paper,
and a very simple calculator.
A modern computer is very similar to this.
Instead of paper, it uses digital memory,
and it has a Central Processing Unit
which contains something called an 'ALU' –
which I'll explain in a second –
which is its calculator.
And it can access a calculator, say,
a billion times per second,
and basically run though very simple steps.
And that's all a computer is.
There's no magic.
Now lets quickly cover time or, you might call 'speed',
how quickly our algorithm executes,
and we need to develop a very abstract measure for this,
because every computer runs at different speeds –
as you know.
Remember, a computer is reading
from some list of very basic instructions.
And it has access to a really primitive calculator
which you can use,
and it is called the ALU, and the ALU is inside
the CPU, and the ALU is the Arithmetic and Logic Unit.
So it can do very basic things, like 'Add',
or it can subtract, if you provide it.
It can also do very basic logic operations, like
'AND', and 'OR'.
So the ALU is that tiny calculator that
the computer has access to
and think of it as basically
answering very simple questions.
That's all the little calculator can do, and
here is a instruction set list, to give you an example,
this is from a micro-controller, but it applies to anything.
On the left hand column you see 'ADDWF', and the description tells us what that operation does.
It takes f and d, and it adds W to f.
And here is 'DECF', that's 'decrement f', so 'subtract 1 from f'.
Or 'MOVF', that is going to move 'f' into a new location.
Now, what's the most important here is this column, 'Cycles'.
Notice these operations, these primitive operations, they all take aproximately
one or two cycles. Another way of saying this
is that all of these operations
take a constant amount of time,
so they'll never hang or
repeat over and over and over.
You can send any of these insctructions and
you'll get an answer in one cycle.
Ok, 'cycle'
is not 'seconds'.
'Cycle' is relative. for example:
'Cycle', in the ENIAC, the computer could do
5,000 operations per second.
And remember, a computer is
powered by a clock,
which is basically a toggle going back
and forward, back and forward,
and however fast they can do that toggling
that's how many cycles I can operate on.
So, a modern computer could do much faster,
let's say 10 to the power of 10 per second,
or it could even do a trillion cycles per second.
So know we can summarize, when we talk
about time or speed of an algorithm,
we are not talking about 'seconds', we refer
to 'number of primitive steps'.
We say 'primitive steps' because we assume
each primitive step takes a constant amount of time.
So, simple calculations will take,
let's say, one step.
But when we have a computer running complex steps,
such as our algorithm we wrote, it's going to take
many steps, right? There is no 'Tell me
if it's Prime' operation in the computer chip.
The compute chip can only do those very simple things
like you do on a piece of paper.