We're standing in Munich,
looking at the House of Art,
which was once called
"The House of German Art."
It was built for Adolph Hitler, and
was a place to promote a very specific idea
of German art.
This is thought to be the very first building
that Hitler commissioned for the Nazi state,
and this was to be the first of many buildings
that were to be constructed around the nation
that were the embodiment of National
Socialist ideology.
As we look at this building,
it's hard not to notice the Nazis
were drawing on the classical tradition of
ancient Greek and Roman architecture.
Yes, but by way of 19th century classical
revival traditions, especially in Germany,
we might think of the work of Schinkel,
up in Prussia, in Berlin especially,
and we might think of the work of
Klenze here in Munich.
These were artists who took the ancient
tradition and appropriated them for their age.
This building is a little bit different.
It is even more spare.
It is even more stripped down.
But we can see this long Doric
colonade on either side
giving a sense of order and power.
And I think timelessness is another word
that we should use about this architecture.
There was an aspiration toward the eternal
or timelessness that Ancient Greek architecture
stood for those very values that the
Nazis wanted to embody
as opposed to what they considered
"degenerate" art or "sickly, unhealthy" art
that was actually exhibited just
a few blocks away.
There were two major exhibitions of art
that were opened in 1937
that were meant to be seen in opposition
to each other,
and they were only about a block and
a half from each other.
The great exhibition of German art
opened here at the House of German Art,
but then in a temporary exhibition space
was the first iteration of the Entartete Kunst exhibition,
the "Degenerate Art Exhibition."
We use that word, "degenerate," and what
it really meant for the Nazis was an art
that was sickly and unhealthy, the art that
today we hold as most dear.
If you go to modern art museums, you'll be looking
at the art the Nazis considered degenerate,
artists like Schmidt-Rutloff or Paul Klee
or Max Ernst, Kirchner,
all of the great early modernists,
and those artists were drawing
on so-called primitive art.
They deformed the human body.
They used extreme colors.
They distorted space.
These were all things that Hitler
rejected.
He was looking for an art that was
ideal and beautiful and perfect
and that represented a kind of timelessness.
So this architecture, and the art that
it was meant to house,
were tied up in National Socialist ideology.
Germany had gone through a very rapid industrialization,
and the National Socialists, the Nazis,
looked back to a kind of invented,
agrarian past that they romanticized.
And so the contemporary ills that came with
industrialization and that came with urbanization
were villified.
And art that was representative
of those changes, a kind of international character,
a kind of risk taking, all of the aspects
that we associate with modern art
is something that was villified.
And this building was built specifically as
a kind of antidote.
And you could say that another aspect of
modern art is that it's constantly changing.
There is cubism and futurism and dadaism
and all of these movements,
always trying to stay contemporary as
opposed to what Hitler was wanting for the Third Reich
which was timeless.
In fact, Hitler spoke to this directly.
In the speech that Hitler gave on the opening
of the first exhibition, he said:
So when HItler says a "German Art,"
make no mistake.
What he means by that is eradicating
another kind of art
and denying those artists the ability
to make art,
sending some of them off to
concentration camps.
The artist whose work appears on the cover
of the Entartete Kunst exhibition
was sent to a concentration camp
and murdered.
This was serious, frightening, propaganda.
So the kind of art that was being exhibited here
was really an art of exclusion.
And it really was a kind of propaganda.
And it reminds us of just how powerful
the visual arts can be as a tool of the state.
And the person who embodies this most
is a man named Adolph Ziegler,
who was a painter,
and the man responsible for putting
together the first exhibition
of "Great German Art" here in the House
of German Art.
And also organizing the Entartete Kunst
exhibition.
And Zeigler was a favorite of Adolph Hitler.
In fact, his painting, "The Four Elements,"
was hung in the Reichs Chancellery
in Hitler's own office in Berlin.
Characteristic of Ziegler's work, and characteristic
of much of the painting and sculpture
that was exhibited in this first exhibition
in the House of German Art,
is a classicism.
We see an emphasis on eternal properties
like the four elements, like the four seasons.
And we see an emphasis on a particularity,
a kind of hyperclarity that we might associate
with 15th century northern art.
And the art that was exhibited in the
degenerate art exhibition
was hung with art by people who were
mentally and physically handicapped.
So that was art that was associated
with all that the Nazis were eradicating,
literally murdering.
And it was wildly popular.
Estimates put the attendance to the Entartete
Kunst exhibition between two and three million people.
And you know what?
Even now, in the beginning of the 21st century,
there is still real controversy about modernism.
People still get upset.
And I think it's important to understand
our uncomfortableness,
but also the kind of historical dimensions
by which intolerance of art can become dangerous.
Very dangerous.
Maybe this is a good time to read
a little bit more from Hitler's speech
at the inauguration of that first exhibition:
Those are chilling words.
And of course, Hitler did with people
what he also did with the art.
It's interesting to note that the motto
of the Austrian avant-garde,
and Hitler was, after all, Austrian.
And he was a would-be artist.
The motto was "To each age its art,
and to art its freedom,"
the very opposite of the ideals Hitler
was trying to promote.