Let's take a look at this capital.
It's what would be referred to as historiated capital
which is to say that it's a capital that actually has a narrative carved into it.
The most obvious and recognizable and decorative element
a non-narrative element are the representations of acanthus leaves
which come out of Greek and then Roman architecture
but this is later, this is medieval, this is 13th century.
And one of the things one notices about them immediately
is how deeply carved they are.
So you have those lovely dark shadows forming the edges of the leaves.
One of the first elements that you see is the story of the original sin,
story of Adam and Eve both of whom look really terrified.
They do look terrified and they're both covering themselves
that tells us what specific moment in the story it is.
They know their nakedness and God is probably at this moment
confronting them and asking them why they hide from him.
I love how their eyes are drilled with these deep holes
and then they have these large oval shapes around them
so they just look like their eyes are bulging out of their heads
from that terrible recognition of what they've done and how they've betrayed God.
They've actually seem to have plucked one of the leaves of acanthus from the capital next to them
in order to cover themselves and that's what they are hold between their hands.
Eve especially, she rips the top of that leave to her chest
and her hair fans out like a flame.
She's just a really powerful image of the knowledge
of what they've done and the consequences
of what their actions are gonna be are already present here.
It's widely emotional in that sense
and I think that in the 21st century we would even say psychological now.
There's another Old Testament scene that's represented on this capital.
If we move to the right we actually have a pretty complicated image
of a large arching figure, an angel.
You can see the angel's wings.
She's got her hands around two figures, Abraham and Isaac.
And these figures are stumpy and not in correct proportions
in that we that we kind of think [of them] as Medieval
and they are indicated by lines, as opposed to form.
So this is Abraham obviously about to kill Isaac, his son
and the angel who stops him from doing this terrible thing
and you know this story is a prefiguration of the story of the crucifixion of Christ.
It's also critically important story in terms of the necessity
of one's absolute obedience to God.
The protectiveness of the angel, of her arms,
her wings covering the figures and the way that her head forms the corner of that capital,
I think it's very powerful.
It is interesting that the anger's face is not looking down to Abraham and Isaac
but in some more direct way looking out to us.
In fact they all seem to be looking out to us.
It's beseeching us to follow this example.
The portals of many romanesque churches were decorated
with scenes of the last judgement and the idea was
as you walked in you were reminded of the price of sin.
The price of sin was eternity in hell.
These are the choices that we face as humans
about what we can do with our lives.
Nobody is going to accuse romanesque sculptors of being subtle.
And they are very powerful and very emotional
and they have taken us a few moments to decode
and visitors to the museum they have to look at the label
but there is no doubt that anyone in the romanesque church in the 12th or 13th century
would have been able to read these stories very easily.
Yes, this is what have been very direct messages and constant reminders.