in the last video we left off with the
assassination of Franz Ferdinand
archduke Franz Ferdinand, of Australia, the heir
the Austro-Hungarian empire.
And so you could imagine
the austro-Hungarian empire did not take
that well.
They already did not enjoyed
the kingdom of serbia trying to
essentially provoke
this nationalistic movement
and they view them as this small little
week country right below them.
And so they use this to essentially
issue an ultimatum. Esentialy say,hey, look
immediately
bring all the people who did this to
justice all the people who might have
conspired with
the Gavrilo Princip's
to create to allow this assassination
attempt occur and, and, and and do it
or else and except full responsibility.
And actually the serbians where, the
kingdom of Serbia wasn't no meed
was in no mood to to get into a
war with Austro- Hungary and so they
tried their best to comply.
But their best wasn't enough, so then
July twenty-eight, a month later,
you have the austrians declaring war on
the serbians.
Austria
declares war
on Serbia.
Now, up until this point Austria, the
Austro-Hungarian empire, the ok, serbia's
a small kingdom here,
and has some ties, and obviously it's a
slavic nation, so it has some
linguistic ties with the Russian empire.
The Russian empire also had some
political ties to it,
but Russia's not going into a war with
the sort of this
where justified in attacking them, they
just killed the heir to our throne.
So we're going to go in there. Russia's
probably not interested in actually
creating a a larger
a larger skirmish year.
And that was a severe miscalculation on
the part of the Russian, on the part of
the austrians. The Russians were not
happy about this. They felt close ties to
the Serbians, and they felt the need to
protect the serbians, or you could argue
that maybe the were, they were they
wanted to mobilize just to scare
the Austrians. Whatever it might be weather
was russia wanted to get into a war
whether they were really looking to
protect the serbians
or whether they were looking to mobilize
to a scare the austrian from actually
attacking
the russians began to mobilize.
So russians began to gather
their troop
so the russians
russians mobilize
mobilize. And now, this is where all of
the alliance's start to come into a fact.
If you go if you remember about the
alliances we talked about
several videos ago,
if you go to eighteen seventy nine you
have dual alliance treaty between
Germany and Austro- Hungary
to protect each other from Russia's attacks,
and actually if Russia attacks,
or mobilizes. So now Germany is like, hey, maybe i am obligated to protect
Austro-Hungary from Russia. You also
have to remember eighteen ninety two,
the franko russian military convention,
military assistance both ways
in the event of attack.
So, the Germany's thinking, look you know we've
sign this treaty,
and, we to some degree, are maybe eager for
war, because you've been militarizing
so much,
and,
I can't just fight Russia, I also know that
France and Russia have this alliance
right over here, so Germany in quite
surprising quickness, decides to declare
war on both.
So on August first,
on August first,
Germany
declares war on Russia
on...
Russia
on Russia,
and then on August
and then on August third,
August,
August third, Germany declares war
on France, 'cause they know, or at least they
feel that they can't declare
war only one of them. And they want to
do it very quickly, because they didn't
want to Russia a chance to mobilize too
much.
And the fact that they will do this so
quickly, I mean we're talking three
witnesses three days after Austria
declares war on Serbia, and another two
days declare war in France,
kind of shows that Germany was already in a
war footing. It's not a joke to all of a
sudden invade or to declare war on
country, so Germany was essentially
preparing for this. And this this ,right
over here, gave them
the excuse
to essentially declare war.
So they declare war on both of these
characters, Germany against Russia,
Germany's declaring war on France. Now,
the easiest way for them to move into
France, so they're literally going on the
offense here,
is for them to go through Belgium is for
them
is for them too
go through Belgium.
But the germans were where?
There where, that there's a seventy
five-year-old treaty, the treaty of
London, in eighteen thirty nine, article
seven said, that Britain
was to protect the neutrality of
Belgium.
And Germany was a no interest to get
into a war
with the British. the British had a
powerful military, especially a very
powerful, a very powerful navy.
The German said hey let's just take on
the russians and the french from now, for
now, and so that she reached out to the
british and said, hey you know this
little treaty that you got here from
eighteen thirty nine, the seventy
five-year-old treaty, you don't really take
this seriously, right? I mean if we have
to go through Belgium you're not really
going to kind of hold true this
treaty? And, and the british said no, we, we
actually take that very seriously.
Obviously,
the british had didn't want them, the
germans to be aggressive you did the
british didn't want the germans to be
able to invade France.
And, so when
in August
in August forth, on August fourth,
August fourth,
when Germany essentially rolls through
Belgium
Germany invades Belgium,
to get to France, this gave the legal
justification for the british to declare
war on Germany.
British
declare
war on
Germany.
And so, in a matter of only, I mean not
even, and we're talking in a few months here
from the assassination of
Franz Ferdinand of Austria,
you essentially have all of the major powers
of Europe, and that's will see because
they had these empires
and and and and and not too long most of
the world as it
war with each other.