(music playing)
We're at the Getty Villa in Malibu with Francesca Tronchin and Beth Harris. This is Stephen Zucker.
And we were going to look at a gorgeous little Roman statue - well, sort of Roman.
Yeah, sort of Roman. This is actually what I would call a Roman reproduction of a Greek work of sculpture.
And that word reproduction is a particularly thorny one and we can talk about that later.
But, just generally speaking, the Romans were absolutely crazy about Greek art.
Well, so am I. Right. As we all are.
They made many, many reproductions of works of Greek sculpture as well as Greek painting, usually putting their own little finishing touches on it so to speak.
And in some cases there were slight variations, so we can't really think of it as a photocopy or an absolutely perfect 1-to-1 reproduction.
Obviously, it tells us alot about the Greeks at a particular moment in time.
But, does it tell us a little about the Romans also?
Oh, absolutely.
There's alot that you can tell about Roman taste by looking at the kinds of Greek works of art that they reproduced.
And it seems that there are a number of criteria for copying and reproducing a work of - let's just keep it on sculpture for the moment.
And one of those disiderata, so to speak, one of those motivations for copying a Greek statue would be that the original Greek statue was famous in some way,
that there was some kind of notoriety associated with it.
Or, if the sculptor of the original was significant in some way.
And, this piece that we're looking at here really packs a one-two punch. It's got both.
It's got both. Absolutely.
First of all, the original sculptor was Praxiteles, who worked in the 4th century B.C.E.
And the reproduction that we're looking at here, the copy, is probably from the late 2nd century C.E.
So about 600 years. That gives you a real sense of something must of have been really special about this original
if 400 years, 500 years, 600 years later they're still making reproductions of it.
Just in the same way like if you go to the Louvre, you can buy your mousepad and your coffee cup with the Mona Lisa, you know, something that is 500 years old.
So, the original would have been life-sized? Would have been lifesized. Absolutely. Maybe 3 feet?
This is about 3 feet tall, and I think judging from the size of it, judging also by the subject matter
which we should say is a depiction of Venus, the Roman version of the Greek goddess Aphrodite the sexy goddess of Love.
So judging by subject matter, scale, material and so forth, I think it's relatively safe to say that this would have been in a domestic context, that is to say it was on display in a house.
So, this would not have been in a temple.
It really would have been something that you would have had a more personal relationship with?
A more intimate sculpture? Sure.
Would it have been decorative? Would it have had a religious function, given that it is a goddess?
Well, if it's a depiction, if it's a statuette that was in a house, I would say that it was really decorative in function.
But, it had also a certain function, almost like how we show our travel slideshows to our friends.
These are the beautiful works of art that we saw on our trip to Paris, or whatever. A keepsake.
I think that this was something that was decorative, but also functional, in the way that it showed off the Roman homeowners erudition,
his knowledge of Greek sculpture, as a way, as a kind of a pretentious way of collecting and showing art.
Art still functions that way. Oh, absolutely.
And, I think among art historians, looking at what books they keep in their living room on view, I think that's another similar sort of pretention.
That's exactly right.
So, this sculpture has changed over time.
We're looking at this very pristine, white marble.
And, marble is this beautiful, soft material, that's translucent. It glows, almost skinlike.
But, is that the way that this sculpture would have been represented originally?
No, and as you can see if you look very closely; for example, in the folds of the drapery, around her eyes, and also in her hair there is a headband there.
There are several traces of paint. And, this is something that's very important to remember about ancient sculpture from the classical world.
That all of that sculpture that today we really appreciate that beautiful, white crispness.
All of that would have been painted in antiquity.
I'm not so sure about the flesh part of this nude Aphrodite.
But, certainly as I mentioned the drapery and the hair. It was painted with something called encaustic,
which was pigment that was melted into beeswax.
And so, it had kind of a glistening quality to it as well.
There are a couple of other things that are missing when we look at this statuette, that would have been there in the original.
Not only are we missing that original paint, but we're also missing her eyes, which probably would have been inlaid in some material.
Perhaps glass, stone, bone. There are lots of different options for inlaying the eyes.
And, would there have been some jewelery perhaps?
Absolutely. that was the third thing I was going to mention.
You can see she has pierced ears.
And, so we can imagine maybe little dangly, gold earrings.
So, in a way she would have looked so much more alive than she does now.
Absolutely.
And, if you read some of the ancient testimony, ancient descriptions about sculpture, in general,
there are lots of cases of Romans and Greeks thinking that statues were so lifelike that they actually could come alive.
And there are stories about statues that were chained down to their bases so that they wouldn't just walk off the base and walk out of the sanctuary.
So, why is Venus always coming out of the bath and feigning a kind of modesty?
I think we probably have to tell the story of why the statue was so important in antiquity to get to that story.
But, certainly this pose that she's in, with one arm, one hand picking up some drapery that she had draped over a water jar down by her left foot
with the right hand over the lower part of her body, ostensibly shielding her genitals; but in reality drawing our gaze right to it.
So, it's absolutely a kind of false modesty.
But, she is Aphrodite. She's meant to be sexy.
She doesn't mind that we're looking there.
A goddess like Artemis, on the other hand, would be horrified. I can't even think of a nude Artemis in antiquity.
And, if I remember correctly, she punished several people for simply looking at her.
But, not Venus. Not Venus.
But, to tell a little bit about the story of the original 4th century statue of Aphrodite by Praxiteles.
Praxiteles in the 4th century was commissioned by the citizens of the island of Kos, which is off the coast of western Turkey.
They said "we need a statue of Aphrodite for our temple."
And, so Praxiteles said, "no problem." And, in fact, he made two statues of Aphrodite.
One showed her fully clothed.
And, then really this one was the other option.
Nowadays, especially looking at ancient art or even Rennaisance art, we've really become accustomed to nudity in art.
But, in the 4th century B.C.E., this was something really brand new. To see a nude female goddess rendenered lifesize was something incredibly shocking.
And, so the residents of the city of Kos, when they were presented by Praxiteles with these two options - naked Aphrodite, or clothed Aphrodite.
Their sense of propriety took hold of them.
And, they said "We want the one with her clothes on."
The nude Aphrodite was just something too radical.
So, the nude Aphrodite, which of course was the second choice, went to the city of Knidos, which is on the western shore of modern day Turkey.
So, really just right across the water from Kos.
It's interesting to know that we have many written descriptions of people traveling to Knidos to see Praxiteles' nude Aphrodite.
We have scores and scores of reproductions of that statue, including the one that we're looking at here.
We have no idea what the clothed Aphrodite looked like. What a surprise. Yeah.
I think that tells us alot about Greek art, about Greeks, about Romans, about travel, about us.
Absolutely.
Yeah, little has changed.
That's terrific. You've really brought this sculpture alive for us. Thanks.
(Music playing)