We are on problem number 12. Problem 12.
OK,what is the greatest of five consecutive integers if
the sum of these integers is 185?
So what is the greatest?
Let's assume x is the greatest.
And they're consecutive integers,
so what's the second greatest?
Well,that would be x minus 1.
The third greatest would be x minus 2.
x minus 3. x minus 4,right?
These are five consecutive integers
where x is the largest,right?
If x was 150,x minus 4 would be--
these numbers would be 150,149,148,147,146 like that,right?
So these are consecutive integers,x is the largest.
And they're telling us that the sum is 185.
So the sum is equal to 185.
So what is this sum? How do sum these up?
So we have five x's,right? So get 5x.
And then what's minus 1,minus 2,minus 3,minus 4?
So 1 plus 2 is 3,3 plus 3 is--
this is where I always mess up--
3 plus 3 6,6 plus 4 is 10,right?
So you get 5x minus 10 is equal to 185.
Add 10 to both sides. 5x is equal to 195.
And you could eyeball this,you could say well,
how many times does 5 go into 200,
and it's going to be 1 less than that,right?
Five goes into 200,what,if it goes into it 40 times,
it'll be 39 or you can divide.
If you didn't want to do it that way,
you could say 5 goes into 195,3 times 5 is 15. 45,39.
So that's our answer,x is 39.
It's the largest of the consecutive numbers.
So those numbers are 39,38,37,36,35.
Those are our five consecutive numbers.
Next problem. Problem 13.
A salesman's monthly gross pay consists of $1,200 plus 20
percent of the dollar amount of the sales.
So plus 20 percent of the sales,s I'll say is for sales.
If his gross pay for one month was $2,500,
what was the dollar amount of the sales for that month?
Well when I read it,I essentially set up this equation,right?
His compensation is $1,200 plus 20 percent of the sales.
And we know that that equals $2,500 in this month.
So let's subtract $1,200 from both sides.
So you get 0.2s is equal to $1,300,right?
And so s is equal to $1,300 divided by 0.2.
And the way I like to think about this,0.2,instead of
having to do this decimal,
which you could do,is I could have rewritten this.
20 percent is the same thing as 1/5,right?
So it's also 1/5 s is equal to $1,300.
And now this is easy.
Multiply both sides by 5,
you get s is equal to $1,300 times 5,which equals what?
Thirteen times 5 is 65,and add the two 0's.
So s is equal to $6,500.
So that's the monthly sales that month.
I was a little redundant with the word "monthly" just now.
Next problem. Problem 14. OK,so they've drawn a circle.
And then,let's see,they've told us that this is,let's see.
They tell us that this is 40 degrees.
Let's see,Naomi makes silver jewelry.
For one style of earring,
she cuts wedges from a silver disk,
which I guess is depicted here,as shown in the figure above.
Each wedge makes a 40-degree angle at the center of the disk.
If the weight of each uncut disk is
a uniformly distributed 2.5 grams--
that's how much this whole silver disk--
I should've done it in grey instead of magenta
because it's silver,but anyway--
how many grams does each wedge weigh?
So we essentially just have to figure out what fraction of
the entire circle is each wedge?
Well,each wedge is 40 degrees.
How many degrees are in the entire circle?
Hopefully it's second nature to you right now,
but there's 360 degrees in an entire circle,right?
So the wedge is what fraction of the entire circle?
Each wedge is 40 over 360 of the entire circle.
And that's what? That's equal to 1/9.
Divide the top and the bottom by 40,right?
Four goes into 36,right,9 times.
So each wedge is 1/9 of the entire circle,
and I just did that based on the fact
that it's 40 degrees over 360 degrees.
So if each wedge is 1/9 of the entire silver piece and
the silver piece weights 2.5 grams,
then each wedge will weigh 1/9 times 2.5 grams,right?
And if we want to write 2.5 as a fraction,how do we do that?
That might be convenient right now.
Well,I'll tell you,that's the same thing.
And you could multiply it out,and that's all fine,but you
could also recognize that 2.5 can also be written as 9/4.
Oh no,no it can't,sorry. 2.5 can be written as 5/4.
No. I'm pathetic. 2.5 can be written as 10/4,right?
Because four goes into 10 two times.
Why am I even writing 10/4?
See,my brain is malfunctioning.
2.5 can be written as 5/2,which is 10/4.
I was somehow thinking of the number 9,
and I'm not going to make excuses for my deficits. Anyway.
So what's 1/9 times 5/2? It's 5/18.
So each wedge is going to weight 5/18 of a gram.
The other option is you could have divided 2.5 by 9
and you would have gotten another answer with decimals.
Either one would have worked
because these are free answer questions. Next problem.
Can you actually use a calculator on the SAT these days?
If you can,that would've been an option as well. Problem 15.
If x squared minus y squared is equal to 10
and x plus y is equal to 5,what is x minus y?
Before I even read the rest of the question,when I saw this,
it should be like your knee-jerk reaction
when you take the SAT.
When you see x squared minus y squared equals 10,
well that's the same thing as x plus y times x minus
y is equal to 10.
You just factor this difference of squares immediately.
You almost can do that
before you read the rest of the question.
And they tell us what's x plus y? x plus y is 5.
So 5 times x minus y is equal to 10.
Divide both sides by 5,you get x minus y is equal to 2.
That's it. Next problem.
So they draw us--let me color.
So they draw us a rectangle.
And then within that rectangle there is another rectangle.
It looks like this. Another square,really.
And what I've drawn doesn't look that much like a square,
but it's close enough,I think. You get the idea.
And this is,I see,a right angle,right angle,
right angle,right angle.
They tell us that this distance is 2,this distance is 3.
In the figure above,what is the area of the shaded square?
So this is a bit of a trick.
And actually,let me do it in the next video
so I can kind of delve deeper into the trick.
I'll see you in the next video.