I want to make a quick clarification to the last video and then think about
what friction up to when the block is actually moving
In the last video, we started off with a block being stationary
We knew that the parallel component
of the force of gravity on that block was 49 N downwards, down the slope
I went on the block was stationary so there must be an offsetting force
then we said, that's the force of friction and it must be 49 N upwards
and so they completely net out in that direction
Now what we said is keep applying a little bit more force until we can budge
this block to start accelerating downwards
I said I kept applying a little bit more force until I get to 1 N
and then the block started to budge
So at that point, when it started to budge, I am applying this 1 N right over here
There is already 49 N of force or the component of gravity in this direction
Combined, we're providing 50 N to just start budging it
to just overcome the force of friction
The one thing I want to clarify here is that
at the whole time the force of friction was not constant at 49 N
When I wasn't messing with this block and the parallel component of force was 49 N
then the force of friction was 49 N
When I started to press on it, apply a little bit force
maybe I applied 1/10 N on top of that
then the force of friction was 49.1 N
because it was still providing enough force so that this block was not moving
Then I applied maybe 1/2 N
and so the total force in the downward direction would have been 49.5 N
But if it still was not moving
then the force of friction was still completely overcoming it
So the force of fiction must be 49.5 N
All the way up to the combined force in the downward direction being 49.999999 N
and then the force of friction was still 49.999999 N
All the way until I hit 50 N and the block started to budge
which tells us that the force of friction, or at least the force of static friction
all of a sudden now couldn't keep up and it started to accelerate downwards
So in that static scenario, the force of friction
changed as I applied more or less force in this downward direction
With that out of the way, let's take a different scenario
Let me just redraw that same block
since all this is getting messy
So we have the same block
As we said in the last video, we're now assuming wood on wood
So this is the wedge
This is the block right over here
We know that the component of gravity that is parallel to the plane right there is 49 N
We know the component of gravity that's perpendicular to the plane--
we figured it out about 2 videos ago--
is 49 square root of 3 N
We know that this block is not accelerating in this normal direction
So there must be some force counteracting gravity in that direction
And that's the normal force of the wedge on the block
So that is going in that direction
at 49 square root of 3 N
And now instead of assuming that this block is stationary
let's assume that it's moving with a constant velocity
So now are dealing with a scenario where the block has a constant velocity
And for the sake of this video, we assume that constant velocity is downwards
The constant velocity v is equal to--let's say--5 m/s down the wedge or down the ramp
or in the direction that is parallel to the surface of the ramp, in this direction
right over here. So that's the constant velocity
So what are all the forces at play?
And be very careful here
There might be temptation to say, OK, you know there's a net force here. We're moving
So maybe that's the net force causing the movement, but member, this is super important
This is Newton's 1st law
If you have a net force, if you have an unbalanced force, it'll cause it to accelerate
And we are not accelerating here; we have a constant velocity
We are not accelerating here
So if you're not accelerating in that direction
then that means that the force in that direction must be balanced
So there must be some force acting in the exactly opposite direction
that keeps this thing from accelerating downwards
And so it must be exactly 49 N in the opposite direction
And as you can imagine, this is the force of friction
This right over here is the force of friction
And the difference between this video and the last video is last time friction was static
even at 49 N, the box was stationary
You keep nudging it until you get to 50 N, then it start moving
Here we're just jumping into this picture where
we just see a box that's moving down the slope at 5 m/s
So we don't know how much force it took to overcome static friction
But we do know
that there is some force of friction that is keeping this box from accelerating
keeping it at a constant velocity
that is completely negating the parallel component of the force of gravity
parallel to the surface of this plane
So given this, let's calculate another coefficient of friction
but this is going to be the coefficient of kinetic friction
because now we're moving down the block. I'll do a video on why
sometimes a coefficient of static friction can be different
than the coefficient of kinetic friction
So the coefficient of kinetic friction, we'll write it as the Greek letter mu
with a little k here for kinetic where it's a kind of moving friction
It's going to be equal to the magnitude of the force of friction
over the magnitude of the normal force
And you can derive this experimentally
You just observe this whole thing going on and you do the math with this block
You knew the a component of gravity that's going in this direction
you could figure out this coefficient of kinetic friction
What's cool about this is, this is in general going to be true
For any two materials that are like this. So you know, maybe this is
a certain type of wood on a certain type of wood
or a certain type of sandpaper on a certain type of sandpaper
whatever you're talking about, and then you can use that to make predictions
if the incline was different or the mass was different
or even if you are on a different planet
or someone was pressing down on this block would change the normal force
So given this right here, let's figure out for the sake of doing it
the coefficient of kinetic friction here
The force of friction here completely offsetting the force of gravity parallel to the surface
is 49 N
And the normal force here, the force of contact between these two things
this block and this wedge, is 49 sqrt of 3 N
So we get one over the square root of 3
Let's get the calculator out to get the accurate number here
So we have one divided by the square root of three
which gives us .58
0.58 and there's no units here, because the units cancel out. It's a unitless measurement
And the interesting thing here is that the coefficient the way I've set up this problem
the coefficient of kinetic friction is lower, if we assume the same materials
than the coefficient of static friction
And for some materials, they might not be that different
but for other materials, the kinetic friction can be lower than static friction
You never see a situation where the coefficient of static friction is lower than
the coefficient of kinetic friction
but you do see situations where the coefficient of kinetic friction is lower
than the coefficient of static friction that
once something is moving for some reason--
we'll theorize why that might be--for some reason
friction has a little less potent than when something is stationary
So we can say this generally
coefficient of kinetic friction is less than or equal to the coefficient of static friction
It's a little bit easier, or friction provides a little less, or less than
or equal to the force when something's moving than when something is stationary
I'll think about that a little bit deeper in the next video