In this video,we are going to take the definition of bronsted-lowry acids and bases that we define
in the last video,and we're gonna use it to explore concepts of
Keq,Ka and also pKa,and see how
they are important when you're talking about acid-base chemistry
so here we have a generic acid-base reaction that uses the bronsted-lowry
definition.So,HA is our generic acid
it's going to donate a proton to H2O
H2O IS A bronsted-lowry base,if H2O accepts a proton
h2o becomes h3o+,and if HA
donates a proton,so it's left with,uh,if it loses
proton it's left with A- the conjugate base,like that
so when the reaction reaches equilibrium,the rate of the forward reaction is
equal to the rate of the reverse reaction,and from general
chemistry,the position of the equilibrium is described by what's called a
Ka/Keq expression,which is defined as the concentration
of the products over the concentration of the reactants
so if I were to write a Keq expression for this generic
acid-base reaction,I would take the concentration of the products
so I go ahead and put H3O+ times A-
and I put that over the concentration of my reactants,so it should be
HA AND H2O.Now the concentration
of water is constant,and so you can
think about it just being removed from the Keq expression,or you can think about
combining the concentration of water with the Keq to give you what's called
a Ka expression.So a Ka expression would have
the concentration of H3O+times the concentration
of A- over the concentration of
HA,since we've taken out water from our expression.
Now the useful what of Ka expression
I think it's much more obvious when you apply it to an actual
reaction,so the one we talked about in the last video,right,
had H2O and HCl
where HCl donated a proton to
H2O.This reaction is technically at equilibrium,but the
equilibrium lies to the right here,so H2O
will become H3O+,so gained a proton
and if hcl loses its proton,it will be cl-
so we talk about the equilibrium line to the right,which will mean
that we'll get ,uh, way more products than reactants
and so if we go ahead and write the Ka expression for this
acid-base reaction,let's go ahead and do it,the Ka
expression is equal to the concentration of my products over my concentration of the reactants
so for this reaction,the Ka will be equal to H3O+
times the concentration of Cl-
right,all over the concentration of HCl
and since HCl is a strong
acid,the equilibrium lies
to the right,which means we're going to get a extremely high concentration
of our products,compared to our reactants
and so the actual number turns out to be approximately
ten to the seventh for the concentration of my product
using my Ka expression over one,so
ten to the seventh over 1,so ten to the seventh is a extremely large number
which again makes sense because HCl is so strong
what what a very high concentration of products to reactants
that's what the Ka expression does,it tells you a relative idea about the strength of the acid
and in this case HCl is very strong,so HCl is strong
we know this just by looking at the Ka expression getting a value
of 10^7/1
that is a very large number ,and usually when you are doing Ka values,you get extremely
large numbers or extremely small numbers,which can be kind of annoying,when you're
doing math or when you are just talking about the acidity of a compound
so since that's annoying,chemistry takes what's called
the pKa value instead of the Ka value,especially organic chemistry
will tend to favor pKa values over Ka values
the way to calculate a pKa value it's like finding the pH of
something,so if you remember from what the pH is equal to the negative
log of the concentration of the hydronium ion,right?That's a way
of giving you numbers that are easier to work with,that's the exact same concept
here.So if I were to find the pKa,right,the pKa
would be equal to the negative log of the Ka.
the negative log of the Ka,so for HCl
we will plug in our number here,so we will plug in 10^7
so let's go ahead and do that calculation,so if we
plugged in 10^7, the pKa would be equal
to the negative log of 10^7
,which is equal to -7
so you could say that the pKa of HCl
is equal to -7,which is again the number is easier
to work with than 10^7
and so using the pKa way of doing
it,you are gonna get a range of pKa's approximately -10 to approximately 50,and so
of the compounds that you discuss,you are usually gonna be in this range
so once again it's just much easier to work with
now mathematically the higher this number is,right,so this number
right here 10^7 the lower the value
you're gonna get for your pKa,and so that allows
you to realize that mathematically the
stronger the acid is ,the lower the pKa value that you
are going to get,and so conversely the weaker the acid
, the higher the pKa value that you will get.So when you are trying
to compare two molecules in terms of acidity
if you look at their pKa values the molecules with the lower
pKa values is going to be the stronger acid,so let's go
ahead and do an example
you are gonna see how to apply this
skill.If we took the ethane molecule,so ethane
would be c2h6 ,so go ahead and put in
these hydrogens here like that
we were comparing ethane to ethanol,let's go ahead and draw
an ethanol now.So ethanol is a very similar molecule
the only difference is there is gonna be an oxygen and
there is going to be an hydrogen on that oxygen here.
Here are two dot structures and if you are thinking about the acidity
of these two molecules if you look at the molecule on the left for ethane
all these hydrogens are equivalent,so in terms of donating a proton I could
say that thid could be the proton that is donated.When you look at ethanol
all the hydrogens are not equivalent.
In the acid-base chemistry,this is going to be the acidic proton.
And the measured pKa values for this molecules,ethane turns out to have a
pKa of approximately 50 and ethanol
has a pKa value of approximately 16.
So thinking about the math,remember the lower the
pKa value,the stronger the acid ,and so
ethanol is a stronger acid
than ethane.In terms of how much more acidic is ethanol than ethane,it might be
tempting just using subtract those numbers.So 50
-16 gives you 34,so you might be tempted to say that ethanol 34
times acidic than ethane.It's 34 orders of magnitude more acidic than ethane
is.So in reality ethanol is ten
to the 34th times more acidic,which
is an extremely large number,and so for all practical
purposes,ethanol is
acidic but ethane is not acidic at all.That gives you these relative values,so ethanol
is much more acidic than ethane,but ethanol is not
anywhere near as acidic as HCl is,so HCl is considered
to be a strong acid,ethanol is not considered to be a strong acid.
and ethane is not considered to be an acid at all.But remember these values are
all relative,but these pKa values are extremely
improtant and you'll see them come up several times in organic chemistry course.
The next video we will talk about the difference,uh,why
there's large difference in acidity between ethanol and
ethane.