What I want to do in this video is talk about the difference
between vectors, vectors and scalars.
And they might sound like very complicated ideas
but we'll see over the course of the videos
but they're actually very simple ideas.
So first, I'll give you a little bit of a definition
and then I'll give you a bunch of examples
and I think the examples will make things super clear.
Hopefully they'll make things super clear.
A vector is something that has magnitude
a magnitude, or you can kind of view that as a size
and it has a direction. So, and it has a direction.
And it has a direction.
A scalar only has a magnitude or size.
And if that doesn't make sense to you,
it will hopefully make sense to you in a second when I show you an example.
For example: Let's say that I have a...
Let's say that's the ground right there
Let me do the ground in a more appropriate ground-like color.
So,this is green right over here...
And lets say that I pick and I have a brick here,
I have a brick here on the ground.
And I pick up that brick, and I move it,
and I move it over to this place right over here.
So I move the brick right over there,
and I take a ruler out and I say, "Wow! I moved the brick,