In the last video we did some examples
were we had one digit
repeating on and on forever
and we were able to convert those into fractions.
In this video,
we want to tackle something a little bit more interesting
which is multiple digits repeating on and on forever.
So let's say I had 0.36 repeating,
which is the same thing as --
since the bar is over the three and the six,
both of those repeat: 3 6, 3 6, 3 6...
and it just keeps going on and on like that forever.
Now the key to doing this type of problem is
instead of multiplying --
like we did in the last video:
we said "this is equal to x".
Instead of just multiplying it by 10,
ten would only shift it one over
We want to shift it over enough
so that we can kind of...
so that when we line them up,
the decimal parts will still line up with each other.
And to do that,
we want to actually shift the decimal space
2 to the right.
And to shift it 2 to the right,
we have to multiply it by 100, or 10^2.
So, 100x is going to be equal to what?
We are shifting this two to the right:
One... two...
So 100x is going to be equal to...
The decimal is going to be there now,
so, its going to be 36.36...36...36...
and on and on forever.
And then let me rewrite x over here,
we are going to subtract that from the 100x.
X is equal to 0.363636... repeating on and on forever.
And notice when we multiply it by 100,
the 3's and the 6's still line up with each other.
When we align the decimals,
you want to make sure that the decimals
line up appropriately.
And the reason why this is valuable
is that now, when we subtract x from 100x,
the repeating parts will cancel out.
So, let's subtract.
Let us subtract these two things.
On the left-hand side we have 100x - x,
so that gives us 99x.
And then on the right-hand side,
this part cancels out with that part,
and we are just left with 36.
We can divide both sides by 99,
and we are left with x = 36 / 99
and both the numerator and the denominator
is divisible by 9, so we can reduce this.
If we divide the numerator by 9 we get 4,
and the denominator by 9, we get 11.
So 0.363636 forever and forever repeating
is four elevenths.
Now let's do another interesting one.
Let's say we have...
- and I will just set it equal to x -
let's say we have the number
the number 0.714,
and the 14 is repeating.
so this the same thing,
so notice the 714 isn't going to repeat,
just the 14 is going to repeat.
So this is 0.714, 14, 14... on and on and on.
So lets set this equal to X.
Now you might be tempted to multiply this by 1000,
to get the decimal all the way clear of 714.
But you actually don't want to do that.
You want to shift it just enough
so that the repeating pattern can be
right under itself, when you do the subtraction.
So again in this situation,
even though we have 3 numbers
behind the decimal point,
because only two of them are repeating
we only want to multiply it by 10^2.
So once again, you want to multiply it by 100.
So you get 100x = ...
- we're moving the decimal two to the right -
One..., two...
So, it's going to be 71.414141 and on and on.
And then let me rewrite x below this.
we have x = 0.1714, 14, 14 ...
And notice: now, the 14, 14, 14's
are lined up right below each other.
so it is going to work out when we subtract.
So, let's subtract these things:
100x - x = 99x,
and this is going to be equal to...
these 14, 14's are going to cancel those 14, 14's
and we have 71.4 - .7
we can do this in our head
or we can borrow if you like:
this could be fourteen, this is a zero,
so you have 14 - 7 = 7
and then 70 minus 0.
So, you have 99x = 70.7.
And then we can divide both sides by 99;
you could see that also something strange is happening
because we still have a decimal,
but we can fix that up in the end.
So, lets divide both sides by ninety-nine:
You get x = 70.7 / 99.
Now, obviously, we have not converted this
into a pure fraction yet.
We still have a decimal in the numerator.
But that is pretty easy to fix:
you just have to multiply the numerator
and the denominator by ten
to get rid of this decimal.
So lets multiply the numerator by ten
and the denominator by ten.
and so we get 707 / 990.
Let's do one more example.
Let's say we have something like
3.257 repeating,
and we want to covert this into a fraction.
so once again, we set this equal to X,
and notice: this is going to be
3.257, 257, 257...
The 257 is going to repeat on and on and on.
Since we have three digits that are repeating,
we want to think about a thousand x,
10 to the 3rd power times x
and that will let us shift it just right
so that the repeating parts can cancel out.
so 1,000x is going to be equal to what?
We're going to shift the decimal to the right,
1, 2, 3...
so it' s going to be 3,257 point...
and then the 257 keeps repeating:
257, 257, 257 keeps going on and on forever.
And then we are going to subtract X from that.
so here is x;
x is equal to 3.
- You want to make sure
you have your decimals lined up -
3.257 257 257 . . .
keeps going on forever.
Notice when we multiply it by 1,000
it allowed us to line up the 257's
so that when we subtract,
the repeating part cancels out.
So let's do that subtraction.
On the left-hand side
a thousand of something minus One of that something,
You are left with 999 of that something.
is equal to
- this part is going to cancel out with that part -
is going to be equal to..
Let's see, 7 - 3 = 4,
and then you have this 5 and the 2 and the 3.
So you have 999x = 3,254.
And then you can divide both sides of this by 999.
And you are left with x = 3,254 / 999.
Obviously this is improper fraction
the numerator is larger than the denominator.
You could convert this to a proper fraction if you like,
You could just try to figure out
what the 0,257 repeating forever part is equal to
and have 3 being the whole number part
of the mixed fraction,
or you can just divide 999 into 3254.
Actually we can do that pretty straightforward:
it goes into it three times,
and the remainder, ...
well let me just do it to go through the motions:
999 goes into 3254...
it will go into it 3 times,
we know that because this is originally 3.257
so we are just going to find out the remainder.
So, 3 x 9 = 27,
we add the 2's, so we have 29
3 x 9 = 27,
so we are left with,
if we subtract,
if we re-group, or borrow,
however we want to call it,
this could be 14,
this could be a 4,
(I'll use a new color)
this would be a 4,
and then the 4 is still smaller than this 9,
so we need to re-group again
so this could be 14 and this could be 1,
but this is still smaller then this 9 right over here,
so we re-group it again,
this would be 11 and then this is a 2,
14 - 7 = 7,
14 - 9 = 5,
11 - 9 = 2,
so we are left with
did I do that right? - Yep
so this is going to be equal to
3 and 257 over 999.
And we are done.