What I wanna do in this video is give an introduction to the language
Or some of the characters that we use when we talk about geometry
and I guess the best place to start is even think about
what geometry means
As you might recognize the first part of geometry right over here
You have the root word geo
The same word that you see in things like Geography and Geology
And this comes this refers to the earth
This refers
My E looks like a C right over there
This refers to the earth
And then you see this Metry part
And you see Metry in things like Trigonometry as well
And Metry or the metric system and this comes from measurement
This comes from measurement or measure
Measurement
So when someone's talking about Geometry,
The word itself comes from earth measurement
And that's kind of not so bad of a name
Because it is such of a general subject
Geometry really is the study and trying to understand
How shapes and space and things that we see relate to each other
So you know when you start learning about Geometry,
You learn about lines and triangles and circles
And you learn about angles
And we'll define all of these things more and more precisely
As we go further and further on
But also encapsulated things like patterns
And three dimensional shapes
So it's almost everything that we see
All the Math- visually Mathematical things that we understand
Can in someway be categorized in Geometry
Now with that out of the way, let's just start from the basics
So basic starting point from Geometry
And then we can just grow from there
So if we just start at a dot
That dot right over there
It's just a point
It's just that little point on that screen right over there
we'd literally call that a point
And I'd call that a definition
And the fun thing about Mathematics is
That you can make definitions
We could've called this
We could've called this an armadillo
But we decide to call this a point which I think make sense
Because it's just what we would call it in everyday language as well
That is a point
Now what's interesting about a point is that
it is just a position; that you can't move on a point
If you moved if you were are at this point
And if you moved in any direction at all
you would no longer be at that point
So you cannot move on a point
Now there are differences between points
For example that's one point there
Maybe I have another point over here
And then I have another point over here
And then another point over there
And you want to be able to refer to the different points
And not everyone has the luxury of a nice colored pen like I do
Otherwise, they could refer to the green point,
Or the blue point, or the pink point
And so in Geometry to refer to points we tend to give them labels
And the labels tend to have letters
So for example, this could be point A;
this could be B; this would be point C;
and this right over here could be point D
So if someone says hey circle point C- you know which one to circle
You know that you would have to circle,
You would have to circle that point right over there
Well that so far it's kind of interesting
You have these things called points
You can't really move around on a point
All they do is specify a position
What if we wanna move around little bit more?
What if we wanna get from one point to another?
So what if we took
We started at one point and we wanted we wanted all of the points
including that point that connect that point in another point
So all of these points right over here
So what would we call what would we call this thing?
All of the points that connect A and B along a straight
And I'll use everyday language here
Along kind of a straight line like this,
Well we'll call this a line segment
In everyday language you might call it a line
But well call it a line segment coz we'll see in ge
When we talk in Mathematical terms
A line means something slightly different
So this is a line segment
And if we were to connect D and C,
This would also be another line segment
A line segment
And once again, because we always don't have the luxury of colors
This one is clearly the orange line segment;
This is clearly the yellow line segment;
We want to have labels for these line segments
And the best way to label the line segments are with its end points
And that's another word here
so a point is just literally A or B
But A and B are also the end points of these line segments
Coz it starts and ends at A and B
So let me write this A and B
A and B are end points
Another definition right over here
We, once again, we could've called them aardvarks or end armadillos
But we as mathematicians decide to call them end points
Because that seems to be a good name for it
And once again, we need a way to label these line segments
With that have the end points
And what's a better way to label a line segment than
With its actual end points
So we would refer to this line segment over here-
We would put its end points there
And to show that it's a line segment,
we would draw a line over it just like that
This line segment down here, we would write it like this
And we could've just as easily written it like this:
CD with a line over it
Would've refer to the same line segment
BA, BA with a line segment with a line over it
would refer to that same line segment
And now you might be saying well I'm not satisfied
Just travelling in between A and B
And this is actually another interesting idea
When you were just on A, when you were just on a point
And you couldn't travel at all;
you couldn't travel at all in any direction without,
while staying on that point,
That means you have zero options to travel in
You can't go up or down, left or right, in or out of the page
And still be on that point
And so that's why we say a point has zero dimensions
Zero dimensions
Now all of a sudden, we have this thing: this line segment here
And this line segment
we can at least go to the left and the right
along this line segment
We can go towards A or towards B
So we can go back or forward in one dimension
So the line segment is a one dimensional
It is a one dimensional idea almost or one dimensional object
Although these are more kind of abstract ideas
There is no such thing as a perfect line segment
Because everything a line segment you can't move
You can't move up or down on this line segment while being on it
While in reality anything that we think is a line segment
Even you know, a stick of some type-
a very straight stick or a string that is thought
that still will have some width
but the geometrical pure line segment has no width
It only has a length here so you can only move along the line
And that's why we say it's one dimensional
A point you can't move at all;
a line segment you can only move in that back and forth
along that same direction
Now I just said to you that it can actually have a length
How do you refer to that?
Well you refer to that by not writing that line on it
So if I write AB with a line on top of it like that
That means I'm referring to the actually line segment
If I say that
let me do this in a new color
If I say that AB is equal to five units
It might be centimeters or meters whatever
I just the abstract unit is five,
That means that the distance between A and B is five
That the length of line segment AB is actually five
Now let's keep on extending it
Let's say we wanna just keep going in one direction
So let's say that I start at A
Let me do this in a new color
Let's say I start at A and I wanna go to D
But I wanna I want the option of keep on
I wanna keep on going
So I can't go further in A's direction than A
But I can go further in D's direction
So this little this idea that I just showed;
This essentially a cycle line segment
But I can keep on going past this end point
we call this We call this a ray
and the starting point for a ray is called the vertex
Not a term that you'll see too often
You'll see vertex later on in other context but it's good to know
This is the vertex of the ray
It's not the vertex of this line segment
So maybe I shouldn't label it just like that
And what's interesting about a ray is
once again its one a dimensional figure
But you could keep on going in one of the direct-
You can keep on going toward past one of the end points
And the way that we would specify a ray is we would say
We would call it AD and we would put this little arrow over on top of it
To show that is a ray
And in this case it matters the order
That we put the letters in
If I put DA if I put DA as a ray
This would mean a different ray
That would mean we're starting at D and then we're going past A
So this is not ray DA, this is ray AD
Now the last idea that I'm sure you're thinking about is
What if I could keep on going in every, in both directions?
So let's say I can keep going in
My diagram is getting messy
So let's let me introduce some more points
So let's say I have point E and then I have point F right over here
And let's say that I have this object that can
That goes through both E and F
but this keeps on going in both directions
This is, when we talk in geometry terms, this is what we call a line
Now know this a line never ends;
you can keep going in either direction
A line segment does end
It has end points; A line does not
And actually a line segment can sometimes be called just a segment
And so you would specify line EF
you would specify line EF with these arrows just like that
Now the thing you're gonna see most typically
When we're studying Geometry are these right over here
Because we're gonna be concerned
With sides of shapes, distances between points
And we're talking about any of those things;
Things that have finite length;
things that have an actual length;
Things that don't go off forever in one or two directions,
Then you're talking about a segment or a line segment
Now if we go back to a line segment
just to kind of keep talking about new words-
That you might confront in Geometry
If we go back talking about a line
That's I was drawing a ray
So let's say I have point X and point Y
And so this is line segment XY;
so I could specify it, denote it just like that
If I have another point
Let's say I have another point right over here
Let's call that point Z
and I'll introduce another word
XY And Z are on the same they're all lined on the same line
If you would imagine that a line
could keep going on and on forever and ever;
So we can say that XY and Z are collinear
So those three points are co- that they are collinear
They all sit on the same line or
And they also all sit on the line segment XY
Now let's say we know, we're told that XZ is equal to ZY
And they are all collinear
so that means
This is telling us that the distance between X and Z
is the same as the distance between Z and Y
so sometimes we can we can mark it like that
This distance is the same as that distance over there
So that tells us that Z is exactly half way between X and Y
So in this situation we would call Z the midpoint
The midpoint of line segment XY coz it's exactly half way between
Now to finish up,
we've talked about things that have zero dimensions, points
We've talked about things that have one dimension-
a line, a line segment or a ray
you might say well what has two dimensions?
Well in order to have two dimensions
That means I can go backwards and forwards
in two different directions
So this page right here or this video
or the screen that you're looking at is a two dimensional object
I can go
I can go right left that is one dimension;
or I can go up down
And so this surface of the monitor you're looking at
Is actually two dimensions
Two dimensions
You can go backwards or forwards in two directions
And things that are two dimensions, we call them planar
Or we call them planes
So if you took a if you took a piece of paper
Then extend it forever; just extended in every direction forever
That, in a Geometrical sense was a plane
The piece of paper itself; the thing that's finite
And you'll never see this talked about in a typical Geometry class
But I guess if we were to draw the analogy
You could call a piece of paper, maybe a plane segment
Because it's a segment of an entire plane
If you had a third dimension then you're talking about kind of
A three dimensional space
In three dimensional space,
not only could you move left or right along the screen
Or up and down,
you could also move in and out of the screen
You can also have this dimension that I'll try to draw
You could go into the screen
or you could go out of the screen like that
And as we go to higher and higher Mathematics
Although it becomes very hard to visualize,
you'll see that we can even start to study things
That have more than three dimensions