Now that we have a decent understanding of
how to figure out many significant figures that we are dealing with
lets take a situation where,
significant figures will or might become relevant.
So let's say that I have a carpet here
and I'm using a may be a meter stick to measure the carpet to nearest centimeter.
And so I get the carpet as on to the the nearest centimeter I get to be 1.69 meters.
So this is 9, obiviously this is to the nearest centimeter.
This 9 hundredths of a meter as the same thing as 9 centimeters.
And let's say I'm able to measure the width here as 2.09 meters.
I use the same meter stick and you were to ask me:
"Sal, what is the area of your carpet?"
So - you know - just to the straight up calculation:
the area is going to be the length times the width,
so it would be 1.69 meters times 2.09 meters.
We could do this by hand, but let me just get the calculator out
to make things move along a little bit faster.
And so we have 1.69 times 2.09 and they gives us 3.5321.
Let me write that down 3.5321.
So let me write this in a new color. So this gives us 3.5321,
and we have a meters times a meters which gives us meters squared or square meters.
I might very proudly to tell you that
"Hey the area is 3.5321 square meters.
And the problem here is that it when I give you this thing
that has all of these numbers behind the decimal point
and all of these are significant figures
that implies that I had a really precise way of measuring the area.
But in reality I only was able to measure the area to the nearest centimeter.
So the way we would do this we don't...
so I don't make it look like my measurement is more precise than it really is.
So this calculation is derived from my measurements.
I make sure that it has no more significant figures then either of the numbers that I multiplied.
So in this situation I have 3 significant figures here,
and over here I have 3 significant figures.
And so in general you multiply or devide the significant figures in your product
or the divisor, divident, the quotient , the quotient!
The numbers, the significant figures in your product or your quotient can not be any more than
the least number of significant digits,
or whatever you are using to come up with that product quotient.
So over here both of these have 3 significant figures.
So I can only have 3 significant figures in my product.
If one of these had 3 significant figures and this have 2 significant figures,
I can have only have 2 significant figures in my product.
So in order to be kind of legit here,
I have to round this to 3 significant figures.
I have to round it to 3 significant figures,
I need to round it to the nearest hundredth here
and so this 2 will round down, so we got
this gets us to 3.53 meters squared.
Now we're cool with the significant figures.
Let's do another situation with division!
Let's say that I'm...
Let's say that I'm laying tiles down in my bathroom,
and so the diagram will look very similar,
and I measure... I measure the...
I measure the width of my bathroom to be,
let's say it is 10.1 feet now. 10.1 feet.
And this is the precision that I'm able to measure.
So I'm able to measure the 10th of a foot.
And let's say that the length of my floor is ...
The length of my floor - I just make up a number - is 12 point...
And for whatever reason I was able to measure this with slightly higher precision
So 12.07 feet. And let's say...
Let's say that I have tiles... I have tiles.
And the tile has an area, so someone else measure for me, it has an area of...
Let's say that the area of this tile is 1.07 feet squared.
What I want to do is to figure out how many tiles can fit on this bathroom floor.
So what I would do I would figure out the area of this bathroom floor,
and then divide by the area of the tiles.
So the area of the bathroom floor, so floor area...
Floor area is going to be equal to 10.1 feet times 12.07 feet,
so that will give us, let's calculate it.
It is 10.1 times 12.07 feet, it gives a 121.907.
So this equal to - let's scroll over a little bit to the right -
this is equal to - a little bit more over the right -
this is equal to 121.907 feet squared, or squared feet.
Now, we are not done with our calculation,
but there might be a temptation right here,
say look, I have 4 significant figures here,
I have 3 significant figures over here,
there would be a temptation to say,
"Look, my area should not have more then 3 significant figures."
And that temptation would be OK, if this is all you are looking for.
If the final answer you are looking for was the area of the floor.
But we are not done with our calculation,
we want to figure out how many of these tiles will fit into this area.
So the general rule of thumb,
because you don't want to loose information,
the general thumb is:
don't round the significant figures until you are done with the calculation.
Especially if you are just doing a bunch of multiplying and dividing
because otherwise if you round here,
you actually will introduce more error into your calculation than you'd want to.
So what you do is you keep it as kind of a full number.
Now you do the division. So let's do the division.
So the tiles per floor... tiles per floor.
I guess we could say my bathroom or tiles in the bathroom,
tiles fitting in bathroom, on the floor of this bathroom.
It would be the area of the bathroom, so 121.907 feet squared,
divided by the area of the tile,
divided by 1.07 feet squared.
And ones again, let me get the calculator out.
So we have 121.907 divided by 1.07,
and you get this crazy thing with all of these digits,
but this is going to be our final answer,
so here we do care about significant figures.
So tiles fitting in the bathroom,
we get something that is actually just keeps going,
so it's... Let me write this in a new color.
We got 113.931775701 - and actually it just keeps going - feet squared.
And this is the final answer.
We cared about how many tiles will fit onto this bathroom floor,
now the significant figures come into play.
And the way to think about this:
I have 4 significant figures over here, I have 2 significant figures here,
I have 3 significant figures over here,
and since we did just a bunch of multiplying and dividing, in general...
Since we did a bunch of multiplying and dividing we have to have the minimum,
whatever is the minimum significant figures of the things we computed with,
that's how many significant figures we can have in our final answer.
We'll make this clear: this has 2 significant figures, but this is 3: the 1, the 0 and the 1.
So our final answer can only the 3 significant figures.
3 significant figures.
So we need to round to the nearest foot. The next digit over is a 9, so we need to round up.
So we are going to round up.
So this would get us to 114. Actually this units aren't squared feet, this is in tiles.
This is feet divided by feet, and so this is going to be 114, 114 tiles.
Obviously it is not going to be exactly 114 tiles,
but based on the precision of the measurements we have done,
we can say 114 tiles.
Now what I have just showed you right here what we multiply and divide measurements
that has a certain number of significant figures.
The general rule of thumb is whatever the minimum number of significant figures
in any of the numbers calculated, that is how many significant figures...
that is the least number is the number of significant figure
in your final quotient or product or answer.
When you do addition and subtraction, it's a little bit different and we will cover that in the next video.