We're in the Italian city of Ravenna standing outside the Church of San Vitale. This is a really important 6th century church, it's just really old.
And it's unusual in that it's essentially a planned church.
That means its focus is on its centre instead of a basilica which has a long or longitudinal axis.
Right. When we think about a church we generally think about a building shaped like a cross
and it has that long hallway, the nave. This doesn't have that.
Instead it has an ambulatory or aisle that surrounds its central space.
In this particular case on the east side of the church
there is also an extension with an apse at the end.
Looking at the outside of San Vitale we see that it has eight sides,
so it's an octagon and within that octagon there's a smaller octagon that rises higher.
The exterior of the church is brick. Those bricks were
taken from ancient Roman buildings and were reused here in the 6th century.
The walls are pierced with lots of windows and that's especially important because the interior
is covered with some of the most magnificent mosaics that survive
from the early Medieval period.
And of course you'd want that light glistening on the gold and beautifully coloured mosaics let's go inside and have a look.
We've walked into the church and the centre towers over us.
And yet these apse-like shapes that are supported by columns
undulates and moves around us.
There are massive pillars that support the building, but there's also a real delicacy. Look for instance at the way the columns
are doubled, that is the stacking of one set of columns
above the next. And they move in and out back into
the space of the ambulatory on the ground and up into the gallery above. But the real
gem in this church can be seen on the east end. Let's walk over there.
The eastern end of San Vitale is completely covered in
dense mosaic. These tiny pieces of glass and
glass sandwiched in gold that reflect the light. We're walking up
towards the apse now: this semi-circular space. There are three large
windows and just above that, a large apse mosaic. And in the
centre we see Christ dressed royally in purple sitting on orb
the orb of the Earth, of the Universe. Below flow the four rivers
of Paradise, and on either side of him an angel.
Christ is holding the Book of the Apocalypse with the Seven
Seals visible, and in his right hand he's handing a crown
to San Vitalus, who was adopted as the primary
martyr of this city. And on the other side we see Ecclesius who founded and
sponsored the building of this church and we see him handing
the church to the angel beside Christ. Every
surface here in the apse is covered with imagery with figures
with decorative patterning. The only surfaces that really are
stone are of a very decorative marble, cut to pair
and create wonderful abstract designs. It is this
lush, glorious space, here in this city that's distant perhaps
from the capital of the Empire, but that speaks to its importance.
Right above the altar we see an image of the Lamb
of God, and the Lamb of God refers to Christ. He's wearing
a halo. This ideas of Christ as the sacrificial
lamb sacrificed for the redemption of mankind.
The lamb is surrounded by a wreath of victory, in this case
the idea of the triumph of Christianity itself, and that wreath is held in place
by four angels who stand on globes that refer
to the globe on which Christ in the apse sits.
And then we see Christ again, but this time older, in the archway
at the beginning of the chancel.
Right the triumphal arch has Christ in the centre. It's really a kind of bust-length portrait, and his
body is surrounded by a mendorla kind of rainbow-coloured halo,
and then moving down the arch on either side
are fourteen figures, including the Apostles.
We see scenes from the Old Testament specifically the ones that prefigure the life of Christ
and Christ's sacrifice, and we see scenes from the New Testament.
There are also fabulously decorative columns, made out of a high-quality marble that
was brought from the east. What's most remarkable about these columns for me
is that we've really left behind the Classical Orders. These are
not Doric, they're not Ionic, they're nor Corinthian. They are
the early Christians trying to invent a new iconography for their architecture.
And on top of the capitals we see
something called impost blocks, that help make the transition up to the arches.
The two most important important mosaics in San Vitale flank the apse.
And those show the Emperor Justinian and
his Empress Theodora. Now Justinian and Theodora never actually came to Ravenna.
And they're in the mosaics
we think, to reassert their control over the city.
For much of the 400s, Ravenna was under the control
of a Goth, Theodoric. And Theodoric was an
Arian, that is he didn't follow the Orthodoxy, the Orthodox doctrines of the Church.
And basically the Arians
believed that Christ was the creation of God
the Father, and therefore was subordinate in the hierarchy of the Trinity.
Christ wasn't co-equal with God the Father the way he
is in Orthodox Christian belief, and so,
Justinian, the Emperor in Constantinople in the early 500s,
sends his general Bellesarius to conquer Italy
to reconquer Ravenna, and re-establish Orthodox Christian belief here in Ravenna.
And the Arian belief was suppressed, and so what we're seeing here
is the reassertion of eastern Imperial control, that is Justinian
is in Constantinople, in the East, and he is saying I'm in
charge, even here, in Ravenna, in Italy.
Spiritual power goes hand-in-hand with political power, with the power of the Emperor.
We see Justinian in the centre,
wearing purple, the colour that is associated with the Throne.
He's surrounded by his court, but there are also religious figures,
representing the Church, and there are soldiers;
three centres of power: the Church, the Emperor, and the military.
And we can see that some of the figures are treated more individually than others.
Justinian, Maximian, are more individualised, and it's possible that
people of the time would have looked up and recognised the other figures who are
lost to us today, but the figures from the army are a lot more anonymous.
Justinian the Emperor's authority is divine, you can see a halo around his head,and he holds
a bowl associated with Eucharist, which is handing in the direction of Chris, in the apse.
Right this is a bowl that would have contained the bread for the Sacrament
of the Eucharist. He's in the centre of the composition he's frontal,
but really all of the figures in this mosaic are frontal.
There are schematic, abstracted, medieval. We've left the Classical tradition of Naturalism behind.
And so if we look closely at the figures we can see that there's no real concern for
accurate proportions. Their feet don't really seem to carry the
weight of their bodies, they seem to float in an eternal
space and not in an earthly space. Next to
Justinian we see the bishop, Maximian, with his name above
him although that was added later, and beside him are the clergymen.
Maximian holds a beautiful jewelled cross, and he wears the same purple the Emperor wears associating
him with the power of the Emperor in Constantinople.
The figures next to him hold a jewelled Book of the Gospels, and the
figure at the far right holds an incense burner. What we're seeing here is
the Emperor leading a procession for the
enactment for the Sacrament of the Eucharist.
And in fact, the Eucharist would have been performed the the Sanctuary. The figures stand in
front of a field of gold, which is very much a Byzantine tradition.
And when we say Byzantine we are referring to the capital of the Empire which is Constantinople.
Which we now call Istanbul. You'll notice that the tesserae,
that is these small pieces of coloured glass, many of them with gold
leaf that is actually fused, almost like a sandwich, in between two pieces of
clear glass, are set into the wall at angles so that
the light reflects off them in a way that is complicated and beautiful
and creates a sense of the liveliness of the surface, and that would have
been especially true when it was illuminated by candles and by
lanterns. Let's walk around to the other side and take a look at the panel
devoted to Theodora, Justinian's wife. To the right of the apse
windows, we see the panel of the Theodora the Empress, and it mirrors the panel with Justinian.
So we have an idea that Theodora, Justinian's Empress, ruled
as co-equal to Justinian, that she was a very powerful woman, even
though she was reputedly of lower class, that she was
an "entertainer", apparently.
There are some colourful descriptions of her past.
She's wearing incredibly elaborate clothing and jewellery, with
rubies, with emeralds, with sapphires, and very large pearls
and in back of her head just like Justinian, is a halo, which
speaks not to her own divinity, but to the divine origin of her
authority.
Like Justinian, whose carrying a bowl that
held the bread for the Eucharist, Theodora is carrying the chalice
for the wine for the Eucharist, and like Justinian too, she is surrounded by attendents
that symbolise the Imperial court. A curtain is raised as
though she is about to take part in a ceremony related to the Eucharist.
I'm really taken by the elaborate Byzantine costume.
There's a sense of trying to bring the richness of the Imperial court in Constantinople here to Ravenna.