Let's do another ratio problem that's a bit of a classic.
So, let's say that I start off with a certain number of fruit.
So, I have some number of fruit.
But I'll get back to that in a second.
But we know that the ratio.
We know that the ratio -- we know that the ratio of apples
-- I'll do apples in this reddish color.
The ratio of apples to oranges.
To oranges, those colors are very similar.
Let's say, it is equal to -- let's say it is equal to five:eight.
So it's equal to five:eight.
five:eight.
Or I could also write it as five:eight, just like that.
That's the ratio of apples to oranges.
Now, the next thing that I know about this problem is that when
I take away fifteen -- when I take away fifteen apples.
So, take away fifteen apples, and the ratio becomes 1 to 4
The ratio of apples to oranges becomes 1 to 4
How many apples -- let me write it this way. how many total, how many total not how many apples
how many, How much, let me say how much total fruit do I have, I have after taking away the fifteen apples? he fifteen apples
How much total fruit do I have?
So let's do a little bit of algebra.
Let's say that x is the number, x is equal to the number of
fruit that we start with.
How much fruit are we going to end up with at the end?
We're taking away fifteen apples. We're not doing anything to the oranges.
So we know that x minus thirty, I'll do that in a different
color, x minus oh x fifteen, we take away fifteen apples, xminus 15 is equal
to the number of fruit we end up with.
We know these two things are true.
And now, we know that we start off with a ratio of five:eight.
So we know that the ratio of apples to oranges is equal to
five:eight that we start off with.
Or, that's just another way of saying that for every group --
assuming that we can divide our group of fruit into even -- or
I can divide it into a set of groups, and every group
has the same number of apples and oranges.
That means that for every group of, what, thirteen fruits, thirteen fruits,
there are five apples and eight oranges.
That's what this tells me. For every group of thirteen fruits, there are five
apples and eighteen oranges.
And how many groups of thirteen fruit are there?
Well, I have x total fruit.
So if I divide x divided by thirteen, if I take x divided by thirteen,
that is equal to -- this is thirteen thirteen right here, this is the thirteen
at thirteen fruits per group, I have x total fruit.
So this is the total number of groups, So this is equal to the number of groups.
Now, for every group, I have five apples.
So how many apples am I starting off with?
There is a number of groups.
For every group, I have five apples.
So I'm starting off with five times that apples.
fivex over thirteen apples.
5 x over thirteen apples
Now, for every one of these groups, I also have eight oranges.
So, how many oranges do I have?
I have eight times that.
Because for every one of these, I have eight oranges.
So eight times that is eightx over thirteen oranges.
Fair enough.
That's what I start off with.
Now, when I'm done we said that the ratio, the rato of apples to oranges
the ratio of apples to oranges becomes 1 to 4.
Becomes 1 to 4
Or, another way of saying that is that, for every five -- right,
if you add these two numbers together, for every five fruit
there are one apple and four oranges.
Fair enough.
So, how many groups of five fruit do we have?
Well, this is the total number of fruit we're left with
after we took fifteen away.
So how many groups of five do we have?
We take the total number of fruit.
x minus fifteen.
Divide it by how many fruit we have per group.
And this is how many groups of -- this is equal to
the groups of five fruit.
Of five fruit.
Now, for each of these groups, I'm going to have
one apple and four oranges.
So how many apples and oranges do I now have after I took
away fifteen of the apples?
I took away fifteen fruit?
Let's think about this a little bit.
How many apples am I going to have?
I have one apple for every one of these groups.
So, that's how many -- so the number of groups is the
number of apples I have.
So, I'm going to have x minus fifteen over five apples.
And then how many oranges am I going to have?
For every one of these groups, I'm going to have four oranges.
So, I'm going to have four times this many oranges.
So we can write that as 4 over 5 times x minus fifteen oranges, right
That's just five times the number of groups of five fruit.
Now, what doesn't change?
I'm messing with the number of apples, but I never changed
the number of oranges.
So, this number which is the number of oranges we
started off with, has to equal this number.
The number of oranges we ended up with.
There's many ways to do this problem, but this is the way that's popping out of me that might be straightforward.
So let's see if we can solve for x.
This has to be equal to that.
That never changed.
So you could say 8 x over 13 is equal to 4 fifth times x minus fifteen.
And, maybe, the best way to do this, let's multiply both sides
of this equation times five / four.
So, times five / four times five / four.
These cancel out. That just becomes one.
What does this become?
This becomes, you see you get a four, divide it by four you get a two there.
This becomes tenx over thirteen.
tenx over thirteen, that's the left-thand side, is
equal to x minus fifteen.
Now, let's subtract x from both sides.
And we get tenx over thirteen minus x is equal to minus fifteen.
Let me scroll down a little bit.
And so, what is this?
This is the same thing as tenx over thirteen minus thirteenx over thirteen, all right
That's just x.
Is equal to minus fourteen.
And then, ten minus thirteen, this is equal to -- so this is minus threex
over thirteen, is equal to minus fifteen.
Now, we can just multiply both sides of this equation
by minus thirteen over three.
Multiply this side by minus thirteen over three.
I picked that number so that this and that cancel out.
And that and that cancel out, and the negatives cancel out.
So I'm just left with x on that side.
And then, the right-hand side becomes what?
The negatives cancel out.
I can divide the fifteen and the three by three, so that becomes a five.
And then this becomes a one.
And I'm just left with five times thirteen.
This was just, times plus thirteen, I wrote that just to make sure
that you understood that the negatives canceled out.
So, five times thirteen is what?
five times twelve is sixty, so x is equal to sixty-five.
But that is not our answer.
Remember what x was.
x was the number of fruit we started with.
We just figured out that this is equal to sixty-five.
But what the question asked, the question wanted to know is,
how much total fruit do I have after taking away the fifteen apples.
So the question wants to know, how many after taking the fifteen apples.
If I started with sixty-five, I give away fifteen of the fruit, all of
them are apples, then I'm left with sixty-five minus fifteen,
which is equal to?
fifty apples, oh not, fifty pieces of fruit.
fifty pieces of fruit.
That's what they're asking for.
If you want, you can go on and figure out how many apples you
started with, you finished with, the number of oranges, or
whatever else, but this is what they're asking.
How much total fruit, not the number of apples, total fruit,
do I have after taking away the fifteen apples?