in this video we will see how to synthesize alcohols using a grignard reagent.
so first we have to learn how to make a grignard reagent
so you start with an alkyl halide over here on the left and you add
magnesium metal and you need to add something like
diethyl ether. you can't have any water present
because water will react with the grignard reagent. And so this is
what you make over here on the right, you end up with a carbon atom bonded to
a metal, so carbon is bonded to magnesium. This is called an organo
organo-metallic bond. And you can do this with other metals.
You can do this with lithium for example, but Grignard reagents are
one of those things that are always talked about in undergraduate organic chemistry class
and you can see that these two electrons here, these red ones,
I've drawn it like a covalent bond, a bond between carbon and
magnesium, but in reality it is more ionic
than covalent, so it is equivalent to this second structure down here
Now in terms of electronegativities, carbon is actually more electronegative than
than magnesium, so the two electrons in red
are actually going ot be closer to the carbon atom itself, giving the carbon
a negative charge and forming a carbanion
And this is a carbanion that is formed. And this is unique
because this carbanion can now act as a nucleophile
in your mechanism to make alcohols, so this is the preparation
of a Grignard reagent, it's proved to be a very very useful thing.
in organic synthesis, so much so that Grignard won the nobel prize
for his research into this chemistry.
Let's take a look at the mechanism to form a Grignard reagent.