Now that we have setup the parameterization let's try to evaluate the integral.
The next thing we need to do is express ds in terms of du and dv.
We have seen this before ds is going to be equal to the magnitude of the cross product
of partial of r with respect to u crossed with partial of r with respect to v du dv .
First lets take the cross product and we will do that with a 3 by 3 matrix , we will do that right over here
we set up and fill in r of u and r of v in the actual determinant over here. So first we have our components i , j , and k.
First think about r sub u is. The partial of r with respect to u. Well it's i component
is going to be 1 the partial of u with respect to u is 1 so it's i component is 1 , it's j component is going to be zero
partial of v with respect to u is zero , v doesnt change with respect to u , so this is going to be 0 , partial of (there have
to be brackets around here partial of this with respect to u is just going to be 1 again , this is the partial of v squared respect
to u is just zero , so this is just 1 again and then r sub v the partial of r with respect to v , the i component is going to be zero
j component is going to be 1 and the partial of u plus v squared is going to be 2v , so this is pretty straight forward determinant
so lets try to evaluate , so i component i so we cross this column and this row , so this be 0 times 2v minus 1 times 1 , so essentially
it is just going to be negative 1 times i so we are going to have negative i this is equal to negative i and then the j component
we have to put a negative out front. And remember we have to check out board pattern.
So cross out that row, that column.