In this video I'm gonna use words like
eras, periods, and ages to refer to segments of time
in the human or in the pre-human past
What I wann clarify, right from the get-go
cause thats something that's confused me in the past
archaeologists will refer to eras periods and ages
in the human past, and they usually refer to
periods of tens of thousands of years or thousands of years
but these are differents eras periods and ages
than the ones that geologists would refer to
when they are talking about geological time.
In geological time ERA means several hundred millions of years
periods and ages mean millions of years
when an archaeologists, when we are studying the human past
they are just generally talking about the long segments of human time
but not in the millions of years, usually in the thousands or ten thousands of years.
So what I wanna do, with that out of the way
is talk about what has happened in the distant human past
or the distant pre-human past, and also
touch on some of the classifications for these segments of time,
because they actually tell us about the interesting developments
that happened to humanity over the 200,000 years
that Homo sapiens have been on this planet
or that we believe that Homo sapiens have been on this planet
So the longest period of time in the human past
or the category of human time, and there are different ways we can categorize,
is the Paleolithic era right over here.
And what really makes that period of time -
so this begins even at pre-history or pre-human history
before Homo sapiens even existed
you have the beginning of the Paleolithic era
that really began with the development of stone tools
And as we learned in the video on Human Evolution
there were pre-Homo sapiens species that were using stone tools.
So the Paleolithic Era is really kind of signified by 1 of the stone tools,
but even more that either the pre-humans
or once you go about 200,000 years ago
the humans showd-up is kinda distinguished by
humans being hunter-gatherers.
Which essentially mean, to survive
we used to walk around a lot, you know,
if we couldn't see something obvious to hunt,
maybe a wooly mammoth or something
If we didn't see something obvious to hunt
we would look around for snails or mushrooms or whatever else,
and that how we would survive, that's how we would live.
And because we were constantly adapting to our environment based on the seasons,
we would be maybe following animals as they migrated,
hunter-gatherers were fundamentally nomadic,
which means that they never settled in one place for a long time,
they were always ready to kind of pick up,
probably their tents, and follow the herd,
or follow whatever animals they were hunting,
or follow the seasons so that they could go to
warmer climates maybe where there is more likely
to find something in the ground to eat maybe during the winter, who knows?
So the Paleolithic era is really distinguished
by that huge swath of time in human history
and it doesn't come to an end
until you get to the advent of FARMING.
So the Paleolithic Era, we are literally talking about
over 2 million years ago, it's when it starts,
before Homo sapiens even existed as a species
and it goes all the way to the advent of farming
that we believe first came about around 11,000 to 7,000 years ago.
And this abreviating right here, this BP
This does not stand for Brithish Petroleum,
it stands for "Before Present", or before the present time
so, one more acronym to kind of have in your toolkit when you see things.
And obviously, if we are 11,000 years before the present,
that's the same thing as 9,000 before Christ,
or before the common era
because Christ was, we believe, born 2,000 years ago.
Now, it may or may not be obvious to you,
but the advent of agriculture is a SUPER big deal.
Argueably the biggest deal in the development of human civilization.
Or in all of the human history!
And you might say,"Hey, what's the big deal about agriculture?"
These characters over here look pretty happy,
they are able to walk around a lot, they are able to hunt.
What's the big deal of all of the sudden people
plowing fields and domesticating cattle
and having chickens to lay eggs and whatever else?
And the big deal about that, besides the fact
that it would change peoples diet,
is that for the 1st time it allowed them to NOT be nomadic,
it allowed them to, and you could've probably had
some hunters who were somewhat settled,
maybe living near the ocean, fishing and all the rest
but for the most part, the development of agriculture,
it forced people to stay in one place
so you have the Paleolithic Era,
all the way to the advent of agriculture
which was about 11,000 - 7,000 years ago
and besides the fact that it changed people's diet
it allowed them to settle.
So agriculture allowed human beings to settle down in one area.
It wasn't just that they were settling in one area
but because they were able to control their enviroment
the were able to increase the density of things
of crops that humans could consume,
and animals that human could consume
and lower the density of crops that humans can't consume
and animals that they can't consume,
or that they don't want around, like pests of some type.
What it allowed them to do is also settle in more dense environments.
You can imagine, when you just have people walking around
you need a lot of land to support
even the calory requirements of 1 human being.
But all of a sudden, if you are able to develop agriculture,
you are able to domesticate animals,
and so in the same amount of land you can have
more calories being generated,
and because you have more calories being generated
in a smaller amount of land, people can settle
and they can settle in a denser environment.
So agriculture was really this necessary requirement
for people to kind of develop civilization or to develop villages and cities.
And maybe also giving them free time to start thinking about:
"Hey, maybe we wanna think about how we can record what we know,
how we can develop even more technologies."
And so just to give us a sense of the categorization
that an archeologist would use for this different periods of time,
I told you we're still in the Paleolithic Era,
with the advent of stone tools, pre-humans
most of human time on this planet,
and then about 11,000 years ago the development of agriculture,
and it developed independendtly in different places around the world,
which was by itself an interesting phenomenon
and people think that climate might have warmed up a little bit
so that maybe naturally there were some human-edible crops
that would exist in a little bit denser environment
and humans learned optimise that slowly
and they did that independently.
It's an interesting question of why did it develop
just then, after 180 or 190,000 years,
why did agriculture all of the sudden happen.
But just to get to terminology, the Paleolithic Era
is that period before agriculture,
and then once agriculture starts to develop,
we are now in the Neolithic Era.
And some archeologists would describe a transition period
between the Paleolithic and the Neolithic era,
called the Mesolithic.
And just to know what these words mean, because they actually
make sense when you know what they mean.
"Paleo" means "Old",
and "lithic" means "stone" or "old stone",
so they really talking about the Old Stone Age.
"Neolithic", as you can imagine, means "New stone",
so it's kind of the New Stone Age.
And "Meso" means "Middle". So it is the Middle Stone Age.
So another way of thinking about this whole period
from when people were hunter- gatherers all the way
to about 11,000 - 7,000 years ago when they developed agriculture,
this whole period is called the Stone Age.
And the Stone Age is kind of the biggest age
and there are different ways of describing it.
Bacause if you just call it the Stone Age,
you are really making the importance out of the actuall tools
that people could shape, they weren't able to use matal at this point.
When you refer to Paleolithic and Neolithic,
you are maybe referring a little bit more,
and there are other ways to think about it,
you are refering a little bit more to the lifestyle of the human beings,
Paelotihic being hunter-gatherers,
Neolithic having actually settled, starting to develop
kind of primitive villages and even cities
and of course Mesolithic is in between.
And just a word about a pop-culture reference,
you might have heard of the Paelolithic diet that some people are going on now,
and those are people who try to live like hunter-gatherers.
Their belief is that most of human evolution occured
while we were hunter-gatherers, and so that's what our bodies are most accustomed to,
so they like to eat meat and they like to eat a lot of nuts
and I've even met someone who used to eat only raw meat,
and I don't know if that's easy to justify
or if that's even somehow valid by the archeological records,
these people probably did cook their meet.
Now, the end of the Stone Age we would have, I would say
the number 2 most significant development in human history,
and now we're talking about 3,000 BC
which is about 5,000 years ago.
And this is the development of wiriting.
So we were hunter-gatherers, about 9 - 11 thousand years ago
people started developing argiculture,
allows them to settle in more dense environments
it also gives a little bit more free time
because they don't have to hunt and gather all the time
and then you go and once again, we'll probably discover things
as we go forward in time that maybe these days
need to be pushed back or whatever else,
we'll discover new civilizations, who knows,
but our best sense is: you have these villages and civilizations developing
and by about 5,000 years ago,
so this will be 5,000 before the present
or 3,000 BC, Before Christ,
you have people saying: hey, why don't we
start trying to write down what we know, so it doesn't...
you know, when I tell someone orally it does actually
lose information there, so let's slowly collect
all the knowledge we have and maybe accelerate,
we know they didn't explicitly think of these,
but let us write down what we know.
And so at about that period of time you have as far as we can tell
the first development of kind of a pictogram-based system of writing.
And the earliest system of writing we know
is cuneiform which is from the Sumerian civilization
which is now in present-day Iraq.
I was a really big deal. This is on some level
the beginning of recorded history.
We can talk about the world history, you can say the history
is all of the past and we can use the archeological record
to figure out stuff before people started to write things down
but when they started to write things down
now it was recorded, now we're actually getting
actuall accounts of what poeple know, of actuall people's knowledge.
And the reason why this is a big deal,
I mean, argiculture hopefully you now appreciate
that it was a pretty big deal,
but the reason why writing was a big deal
is that now civilization could collect its knowledge
it could build upon it, generation after generation,
without having to worry about people forgetting it
or information getting distorted verbally from ancestor to descendant.
And with that you also have the beginning of the Bronze Age.
The Bronze Age is kind of known from this beginning
even though it's referring to a material which comes from
the first time that people started using bronze
as a tool or using using bronze for their tools and weapons
and bronze, as you know, is a mixture of
mostly copper and a little bit of tin.
But the Bronze Age, at least in my mind, the biggest deal
of what started the beginning of the Bronze Age
really was the writing.
So once again, just as a review, because I actually find this kind of confusing.
Most of our current understanding, most of human pre-history
and even pre-human pre-history we spent as hunter-gatherers
using stone tools until about 11,000 years ago,
and then we became a little bit more settled,
we became farmers essentially using stone tools
and then you fast forward another about 5-6,000 years
and then we started to become farmers who started
to write down the things that we knew
and we started to use bronze tools.