Let's draw a diagram of the human breast
and talk about some of the amazing functions of this organ.
Now, the human breasts in both males
and females contains mammary glands.
And in females, around the time of puberty,
these mammary glands develop; in males, they usually remain
remain undeveloped and the main function of this gland,
I'll just write in the name over here, these are called the mammary glands.
Mammary glands, and the main function of this gland is to secrete
milk to nourish the human infant. Now
these mammary glands, each of them drains towards the nipple
by a little duct called the lactiferous duct
and I remember I was expecting my first baby and I remembered thinking,
"Where is the milk gonna come out from? I don't see a hole there!"
And the answer is, there isn't a single hole there. Many tiny holes
that are so small you can't actually see them with the naked eye.
And so these lactiferous ducts, and I'll just
label them for you here, these are the
lactiferous ducts
and the lactiferous ducts empty, or drain,
towards the nipple and towards that darker area of skin
that we see when we look at the human breast and that area
of skin is called the areola and the reason
the areola exist is because when the newborn first
comes out, areola, the newborns
actually don't see very well and in order to help them find their source
of food, we have this darkened area of the breast that actually gets
quite a bit darker during pregnancy.
Ok, so now these mammary glands are lined with
what we called myoepithelial cells and let me just break
down that word for you. "Myo" is-is a
prefix that we use when we're talking about anything that has to do with muscles.
or anything that contracts. So these are
we know contractile cells
and they're also epithelial cells and epithelial cells in the body
are the cells that line things. So these cells, these red ones,
these myoepithelial cells
are cells that both line the
mammary glands and have the ability to contract, to eject
the milk out through the lactiferous ducts.
Now all of these structures are supported by quite a
bit of connective tissue and we're usually talking about in the breast.
The main ones are collagen and elastin
collagen... and... elastin
And all of these connective tissue
kind of this connective tissues framework, comes together
in these ligaments, strong ligaments, that anchor the breasts
to the chest wall and these ligaments are called
Cooper's ligaments. Cooper's...
ligaments. In medical school, we used to
remember this by saying the phrase, "Cooper's Droopers"
but after having had 3 children and breastfed for a
long time, I don't think that's so funny anymore. Anyway,
the only other thing in the breast that makes it kind of a soft and squishy organ
is the adipose tissue that also sort of
forms part of the framework or the structure and
supports actually all of the glands along with the connective tissue,
the collagen and elastin. So this is our adipose tissue
adipose...
and, we'll see in our next video
what happens how the body knows when to cause the
these myoepithelial cells to contract, to eject
the milk out of the mammary glands.