You might be wondering why the exchange might be willing to
take on counter party risk for people exchanging
these kind of standardized future contracts
and tthe first reason is that exchange actually.... to make a lot of money
what he can do is, tell these people who want to buy apples in the future
Say for example... Hey...
You can enter into a futures contract with a settlement price of 22 cents per pound
So thats what they are going to have to come to the table with.
That's 22 Cents per pound...
And he can tell the people who are going to deliver the apples that
When you deliver the apples the settlement price is 20 cents per pound
And so essentially when the settlement occurs,
he is going to be able to make a 2 cent profit
he is going to make, a 2 cent profit
Let me review that again,
He only has to pay these guys 20 cents per pound for the apple,
and these guys are paying 22 cents per pound for the apple,
and, may be I should let this arrow go in this direction, cos this is the actual flow of the money
if these guys are gonna pay 22 cents for the apple
and as the exchange, he is gonna give only 20 cents to the farmer,
he is going to make 2 cents profit, on future contracts,
on.. on thousand pounds of apple...
That's going to be 20 dollars for each of those contracts
So thats gonna be 20 dollars....
20 dollars... per... 20 dollars per contract
and he is going to be doing this night and day,
trading with all of the different farmers and all of the different customers
and even some speculators, who might want to do this
so may be if the, spread... if he can maintain this 2 cent spread,
he'll keep making 20 dollars, every time one of these future contracts exchange hands,
Now the other way he is going to protect himself against losses,
is, he is going to make each of these parties set aside some money,
in case... In case the future contracts price moves against them,
and this money that they have to set aside is called margin...
I'll explain this in more detail in future video
but what it essentially is, the amount of money that this guy,
or the amount... the largest amount that this guy...
thniks that the future price might move by,
the contract price move by on any given day,
so he has a cushion, he can actually use margin as kind of insurance.
So he can make sure that on the settlement day, both parties
will kind of be able to meet their obligations
And I will go into more detail about that in next video,
on exactly how margin works.