Let's say you and I are playing a game
where we're trying to figure out how
far a ball is being thrown into the
air, or how fast we're throwing
that ball into the air, and what we do
is one of us has a ball, and the other
one has a stopwatch over here
so, this is my best attempt, it looks
more like a cat than a stopwatch,
but I think you get the idea.
So what we do is one of us throws the
ball, and the other one times how
long it's in the air.
Now, what we do is we're going
to use that time in the air to figure
out how fast the ball was thrown straight
up, and how long it was in the air
and how high it got.
There is going to be one assumption
I make here, and in fact this is an assumption
that we're going to make in all of these
projectile/motion type problems, is that
air resistance is negligible.
And for something like – if this is a
baseball or something like that –
that's a pretty good approximation,
so we're not going to get the
exact answer and I encourage you
to experiment on your own – or even
to see what air resistance does
relative to your calculations,
but we're going to assume for this type of
projectile/motion, and really all of the
future ones, or at least in the
basic physics playlist, we're going
to assume that air resistance
is negligible.
And what that does for us, is that we can
assume that the time up – that the time
for the ball to go up to its peak hight –
is the same thing as the time
that it takes to go down.
If you look at this previous video,
where we plotted displacement versus
time, you see after two seconds,
the ball went from being on the ground,
or, I guess, the thrower's hand,
all the way to it's peak hight,
and in the next two seconds,
it took that same amount of time
to go back to the ground, which
makes sense: whatever the
initial velocity is, it takes half the
time to go to zero, and then
it take that same amount of time to
now be accelerated in the downward
direction, back to that same magnitude
of velocity, but now in the downward
direction.
So let's play around with some numbers
here, just so we get a little
bit more of a concrete sense.
So, let's say I throw a ball in the air,
and you measure, using the
stopwatch, that the ball
is in the air for five seconds.
So how do we figure out how fast
I threw the ball?
Well, the first thing we can do
is that we can say, look, if the
total time in the air was five seconds,
that means that the time, let me write it,
well, that means that the
change in time to go up during the
first half of, I guess, the ball's time in
the air, is going to be 2.5 seconds.
And which tells us that over this
2.5 seconds, we went from our
initial velocity, whatever it was,
we went from our initial velocity
to our final velocity, which is the
velocity of zero meters per second.