I mentioned in the last several videos
that the coefficient of kinetic friction tends to be less
sometimes little bit roughly equal to the coefficient of static friction
but this might lead you to at least a question
that I have had in my mind and I still have to some degree
that why is the coefficient of kinetic friction lower or why can it be lower?
And the current best theory that I
can visualize in my head and based on the readings that I have done is the difference between--
so let's think about it this way
Look at a regular human level
maybe we have a block, so this is the static case. Let me draw like this
I will draw this static case over here
So I have a block that is stationary on top of a surface in a different color
On top of some type of surface right over here
and over here I am going to have a block
moving at some at a constant velocity relative to the same surface
Let me draw out. So this is moving at some constant velocity
and so the interesting thing here is assuming that these are the same masses
These are the same surfaces
is why should the coefficient of friction here
why should the coefficient of static friction--
so this is here, this is stationary what's under place of coefficient of static friction
why should that be larger than the coefficient of kinetic friction over here?
Another way to think about it, you would need to apply
more force to overcome the static friction here and start to get this accelerating
than you would need to apply to get this already moving body to accelerate
because there would be less of a responsive friction force. So let's think about it little bit
So what I am going to do is zoom in into the atomic level. So when you zoom into the
atomic level, almost nothing is completely smooth
So the surface over here might look something like this
So, let me draw the molecules that make up the surface
So, the best to my ability
So the molecules when you zoom up really close for the surface might look
something like this and when you--you know we are really really zoom into the atomic level
unimaginably small, much smaller than that boxes. But I am trying to look it
what's happening with the atoms/molecules where they contact
and the box's molecules look something like this
They aren't completely smooth and hopefully this video also emphasizes
that all of this forces and contacts we are talking about in this video --it's actually
interesting philosophical, nothing is ever really in contact with each other. You really
just have atoms and that are repulsing each other because they are electrons
The electromagnetic force of repulsion between them is
not allowing them to get any closer together
So that's all when you push something
it's just the electrons in your hand pushing on the electron or the electron clouds
in your hand pushing on the electron clouds of say the pen you are holding
or the key on your keyboard or the mug
so that it repulses and causes it to go in the other direction
So there is never this thing like real what we imagine in our head real contact
and if you really want to blow your mind
and watch the chemistry videos if you want to understand this
is that most of this atoms are actually free space themselves
as the electron cloud is huge relative or I guess where most
of the probability of finding the electrons is huge compared to the size of the
electron or the size of the nucleus. So it's kind of just a lot of free space pushing on
lot of other free space through the electromagnetic force
But anyway we are talking about friction here
So if you would really zoom in here when this thing is stationary
you have the surfaces aren't actually
even and so you can imagine this molecules that you have sometimes when they sitting
stationary, they might be kind of fit in to each other
they kind of slit into these little ruts over there
and so if you are trying to move this object, if you trying to accelerate it to the
left with some force, you have to overcome essentially either
for example this part right over here either has to somehow break off
or the whole things to be shifted up a couple of atoms or a couple of molecules
or may be this part over here has to be broken off or has to be shifted down one atom
You wouldn't notice these things
we wouldn't notice the shifting of a block; you wouldn't notice it
by the width of a molecule or the diameter of the molecule, but that's essential
what you have to do or you have to rip them off entirely in order to start this thing moving.
Once something's already moving, and this is at least I think about it
a lot of--it doesn't have a chance to settle into these little ruts. So
let me draw something that already moving and I will try to draw a similar surface
So I am trying to draw the surface that looks essentially like the one I drew
So maybe it looks like that this is supposed to be the same surface
But once it's moving, it's not sitting in the ruts anymore
The whole thing is moving, so it's kind of sliding across the top
So now it looks something like this. I will try my best to draw it
Maybe this is been shifted up a little bit so that it can start slide
you've overcome the static friction
So now it is--something draw the same, I am trying to draw the same surface here
so give or take
So now it's moving; it doesn't have a chance to really settle in
It has to kind of bounce along the top
So that's the best understanding and so the real force of the friction here
there will be still you know as it's moving along it still might
bounce into little ruts here and there
but you also have any type of chemical
bonds that form between the atoms temporarily that keep breaking and forming
in order to keep this thing--if you want to accelerate it
you are going to have to keep breaking these bonds
So that's essentially the force of friction that you are overcoming
Here you might have those same bonds and not only you have those same bonds
but you also have to overcome these ruts or these little parts that have a time to settle in
to little looks that you have to overcome even more. So that's the intuition
you know this is actually still an area of research. It's not this cut and dry thing
so fun thing to think about what's happening in the atomic level
but this is the general intuition of why the coefficient of static friction
is higher than the coefficient of kinetic friction