We are on problem number six.
If there is no waste,
how many square yards of carpeting is needed
to cover a rectangular floor that is 12 feet by 18 feet?
So I can just draw it like that. And it's 12 feet by 18 feet.
And the trick here is, they're not asking how many feet,
they're asking how many square yards of carpeting.
So the easiest thing to do really at this point,
is to convert the dimensions of the room to yards.
And they tell us 3 feet make a yard.
So 18 feet, that's the same thing as what?
Divide by 3, and you get, that's 6 yards. 6 yards is 18 feet.
And you divide by 3, you get 4 yards.
I always find the arithmetic the hardest part.
4 yards is equal to 12 feet, right? 4 times 3 is equal to 12.
So now this is a 6 by 4, so 6 yards times 4 yards is equal to
24 square yards. That's choice C.
And the mistake, if you got this wrong, you might have just--
well one, you might have multiplied 12 times 18
and gotten a very large number and said,
oh, that's the answer.
But then your answer would've been in feet.
Then the other mistake you might have done is
you might have multiplied 12 times 18--
you might done this, 12 times 18 divided by 3.
Because you said, oh well, 3 feet is equal to a yard.
And that is a mistake
because you're now converting square feet to square yards.
And it's actually-- you should have divided by 9
because there's actually 9 square feet per square yard.
Why is that? Because if I had--
let's say this is a 1 square yard, right?
That means it's going to be 3 feet on that side,
3 feet on that side. So it's actually 9 square feet.
So if you figured out the area in feet first,
you had to divide by 9, not by 3.
That probably was the most common mistake,
assuming that you realized that you had to convert units.
Next problem.
Problem seven. A certain scale only registers weights
that are greater than 6 pounds. OK, fair enough.
A person who wanted to know the weights of a puppy,
a kitten and a bunny-- very cute-- weighed them in pairs
and got the following results.
Kitten plus bunny weighed 7 pounds.
Kitten plus puppy is 8.
And bunny plus puppy is 9.
This is by far the cutest problem I've ever done.
What is the weight of the puppy? So we want to solve for P.
Well, if we're going to solve for P, the best thing
we could do is we want to use these two equations.
But we have three-- if we just look at these two equations,
we have three unknowns with two equations.
So let's use this equation to substitute into this equation.
So let's say we want to replace this K.
So we can use this top equation to say that
K is equal to 7 minus B.
So if we substitute that into this equation, we'll get--
so let me just-- this is 7 minus B, so we'll get 7 minus B--
and I'm just rewriting this top equation, that's this--
plus P is equal to 8.
And then this bottom equation still is B plus P is equal to 9
I could add the 7 or subtract 7 from both sides right now,
but I'm just going to actually add the equations,
because I like how these B's are going to cancel out.
I get excited about canceling variables.
So-- actually, no let me subtract 7 from both sides first.
So if we take 7 from here, than this 8 becomes a 1, right?
I just subtracted 7 from both sides.
So negative B plus P is equal to 1.
Now I just add these two equations.
And what's minus B plus B?
It's 0 plus P plus P is 2P is equal to 1 plus 9 is 10.
2P equals 10. P is equal to 5. Choice D.
5 pounds, that's how much the puppy weighs.
Which shows us the bunny weighs 2 pounds,
and the kitten weighs 3 pounds. Which is--
it looks like they actually thought about how much a puppy,
a bunny and a kitten would actually weigh,
which I have to give them credit for.
Next problem. Problem eight.
On a blueprint, 1/4 inch represents 16 feet in real life.
If a driveway is 40 feet long,
what is its length in inches on the map?
So a driveway-- that's a driveway, I don't know,
that's my driveway. And it's 40 feet long.
So how many of these units is it going to be?
Well, actually-- we could do it a bunch of different ways.
We could say 1/4 of an inch is equal to 16 feet.
If we multiply both sides of this relationship by 4,
you get 1 inch is equal to 64 feet. 1 inch--
I just multiplied both sides of this relationship by 4.
So if you want to figure out
how many inches this would represent,
you would say, well, x is how many inches it would represent
over 1 inch is equal to this length, 40 feet, over 64.
It's the same fraction.
And of course, if you divide by 1, this cancels out.
So you're left with x, which is its representation in inches,
is equal to 40/64.
Well you could divide the top and the bottom by 8,
so that becomes 5/8. 40 divided by 5. 64 divided by 8.
x is equal to 5/8. And that is choice B. Next problem.
There's a bunch of ways you could have don e it.
This is the way that occurred to me.
Next problem, problem nine. In the xy-coordinate system,
p comma 0 is one of the points of intersection of the graphs-
OK, so they're giving us two graphs.
y is equal to minus x squared plus 9,
and the other graph is y is equal to x squared minus 9.
If p is positive, what is the value of p?
So they're saying that the coordinate
where they intersect is p comma 0.
So we want to figure out the x-coordinate
where they intersect. So the easy way--
you know, they're tempting you to add these equations
and do all sorts of things,
but we know that they intersect at the point y is equal to 0.
They're telling us that,
so we don't have to do all this fancy stuff.
We don't have to figure out where they intersect.
They tell us it intersects at y equals 0.
So y equals 0, what's x in either of these situations?
Well, let's take this second equation.
0 is equal to x squared minus 9.
Add 9 to both sides, you get x squared is equal to 9.
I added 9 and switched the sides.
You get x is equal to plus or minus 3.
And they tell us, that if p is positive,
what is the value of p? Well, it has to be plus 3 then.
And that is choice A.And you could have used the top equation
You could have said 0 is equal to negative x squared plus 9.
You would've gotten the same thing.
You would've gotten x squared is equal to 9,
x is equal to plus or minus 3.
You would've gotten the same thing either way. Next problem.
I don't know if I'm going to have time to do it in this video
I might have to do it in the next. Problem ten.
The Smith Metal Company's old machine makes
300 bolts per hour. 300-- I'll call it b per h.
Its new machine makes 450 bolts per hour.
If both machines begin running at the same time,
how many minutes will it take the two machines
to make a total of 900 bolts? So how many minutes?
So let's say m for minutes.
So the total number of bolts they're going to produce--
so bolts is going to be equal-- so this is per hour, right?
These are both per hour. So let's figure it out minutes,
because they're asking us how many minutes will it take.
So if you make 300 bolts in an hour,
you're going to make 1/60 that in a minute.
So what's 1/60 of 300?
Well, 300 divided by 60 is 5 bolts per minute.
And this one-- what's 450 divided by 60?
Actually, I'm going to run out of time.
I'm going to do this problem in the next video.
I'll see you soon.