What I want to do in this video is familiarize
ourselves with the notion of a set
and also perform some operations on sets.
A set is really just a collection of distinct objects.
For example, I can have a set
let's call this set X.
I'll deal with numbers right now,
but a set could contain anything.
It could contain colours, people,
other sets, cars, farm animals
but numbers will be easy to deal with
just because they're numbers.
So let's say I have a set X.
It has the distinct objects in it
the number 3, 12, 5, and 13.
That right there is a set.
I could have another set,
let's call that set Y.
I didn't have to call it Y
I could have called it A, I could have called it Sal,
I could have called it a bunch of different things
but I'll just call it Y.
And let's say that set Y is a collection
of the distinct objects
the number 14, 15, 6, and 3.
So those are just two set definitions.
The way that we typically do it in mathematics
is we put these little curly brackets around the
objects that are separated by commas.
Now let's do some basic operations on sets.
The first operation that I will do is called "intersection".
We would say X intersect Y, the intersection of X and Y
X intersect Y.
The way I think about it is this is going to yield another set
that contains the elements that are in both X and Y.
I often view this intersection symbol here as "and".
So all of the things that are in X and in Y.
What are those things going to be?
Let's look at both sets X and Y.
The number 3 is in set X, is it in set Y as well?
Sure, it's in both, so it will be in the intersection of X and Y.
The number 12 is in set X but it isn't in set Y
so we're not going to include that.
The number 5 is in X but not in Y
and then we have the number 13 that is in X but not in Y.
And so the intersection between X and Y
is the set that has only has one object in it
it only has the number 3.
So we are done. The intersection between X and Y is 3.
Another common operation on sets is "union".
You could have the union of X and Y.
People often view this as "or".
We're thinking about all of the elements that are in X or Y.
You can imagine that we're bringing
these two sets together.
The key here is that a set is a collection of distinct objects
and the way we're conceptualizing things
right here, this is the number 3
this isn't someboy's score on a test
or the number of apples they have
so there you could have multiple people
with the same number of apples
here we're talking about the object of the number 3
so we can only have a 3 once.
But a 3 is in X or Y, so I'll put a 3 there.
A 12 is in X or Y
a 5 is in X or Y
13 is in X or Y
and just to simplify things, we really don't care
about order if we're just talking about a set
I've just put all of the things that are in set X here
and now let's see what we have to add from set Y.
We haven't put a 14 yet, so let's put a 14.
We haven't put a 15 yet
we haven't put the 6 yet
and we already have a 3 in our set.
So that's the union of X and Y.
One way to visual sets and visuals intersections
and unions and more complicated things
is using a Vien Diagram.
Let's say this whole box is the set of all numbers.
We have set X, I'll just draw a circle here
and I can even draw the elements of set X
so you have 3, 5, 12, and 13.
And then we can draw set Y.
Notice that I drew a little overlap here
because they overlap at 3.
3 is an element in both set X and set Y.
Set Y also has the numbers 14, 15, and 6.
When we're talking about X "intersect" Y, we're talking about where the two sets overlap.
So that's this region right over here.
The only place that they overlap is at the number 3
so that's X intersect Y.
Then X union Y is the combination of these two sets
so X union Y is literally everything
right here that we are combining.
Let's do one more example just so we make sure we understand intersection and union.
Let's say that I have set A and set A has
the numbers 11, 4, 12, and 7 in it
and I have set B and it has the numbers
13, 4, 12, 10 and 3 in it.
First of all, let's think about what
A "intersect" B is going to be equal to.
It's the things that are in both sets.
I have an 11 here but I don't have an 11 there so that doesn't make the intersection.
I have a 4 here and I also have a 4 here so 4 is in A and B.
I'll put a 4 here.
The number 12 is in A and B, so I'll put a 12 here.
Number 7 is only in A and the numbers 13, 10
and 3 are only in B so we're done!
The set of 4 and 12 is the intersection of sets A and B.
If we wanted to, we could even label this as a new set.
We could say set C is the intersection of A and B
and it's this set right over here.
Now let's think about union.
Let's think about A union B.
What are all the elements that are in A or B?
We can just put all the elements in A
11, 4, 12, 7
and put the things in B that aren't already in A.
So 13, (we already put the 4 and the 12), 10, and a 3.
I could write this in any order I want, we don't care
about order if we're thinking about a set.
So this right here is the union.