Let’s see you don’t like company A B C D very much and you convince that the stock is going to go down.
So, in that situation, you can actually short,
you can actually short the stock which in very high level is bet the stock is going to go down.
And the way you do that mechanically is that you borrow the stock.
You borrow the stock, from someone else who owns it.
And you immediately sells that stock that you don’t even know, you sell the stock borrow from someone else.
And you will sell at current price
So, for example,
at this situation, you’ll sell it, you’ll sell it at current trading pricea, of 50 dollars
You then hope that stock price goes down
So, in this situation, let’s think about this situation where the stock price goes down
So if you shorted it, right over here you borrow the stock and you sold it for 50 dollars
And then the stock actually go down. Iets go all the way down to 20, you think that’s about how far it’s gone go down
Then, you can buy back the stock
You can buy the stock, you can buy the stock for 20 dollars
In this situation, and then give it back to the owner you had borrowed the stock and now you can hand back the stock to the owner
So, you can give it back you’ve centrally unwanted it. What allow you to do is allow you to do the buying and selling in revise order
Normally, before you sell something you have to buy something
But here you are able to sell it and buy it later for a lower price so the situation were the end prices 20 dollars
You have sold it for 50, so that 50 dollars and you have to use 20 of it to buy it back
So in that situation, you’ve shortening the stock you would have made, you would have made 30 dollars
Let me wirte this columns here, this is shorting, this is the short option
You sold it 50, you borrowed and sold 50, then when it went down 20 you bought is back, you bought it back for 20
So you have 50 dollars processed, and you have used 20 of it to buy back ,so you have 30 dollars profits
but that’s only good scenario ,what happens if your band is wrong what happens, if the stock price goes up to 80 and over here
you get so scared like oh my god, I have to buy this stock back by 80, what if it’s keep going up, I will lose unlimited lots of money
So, over here, you get scared and you unwilled your situation. You say :OK, I’ll go and buy the stock for 80 dollars
So ,I can give it back, So, in this situation, stock goes up, you actually can loose a lot of money
You had sold for 50, so, you only have 50 dollars that you have from transaction, but now you have to buy the stock for 80
So if you sold for 50, and you’ll buy for 80. You now lost 30 dollars, 30 dollars in a whole
So, now, you are negative, negative 30 dollars, really shorting is the riskiest of all of things you can do
Because a stock price goes unbelievably high. What happens suppose stock goes 800 dollars, suppose 8000 dollars
All of a sudden, you’ve, you’ve sold something for 50 and you have the obligation it’s some point of future,
because you have to get the stock back of paying 500 dollars, 800 dollars, 8000 dollars you don’t know how much you’ve go to lose
So it’s the really the riskiest thing you can do , but it is one way to bet that stock price will go down or profit from the stock price going down.