Plot (4,-1) and select the quadrant in which the point lies.
So 4, the first number in our ordered pair, that's our x coordinate.
That says how far to move in the horizontal or the x direction
It's a positive 4 so I'm going to go 4 to the right
and then the second coordinate says what we will do in the vertical direction or in the y direction.
It's a negative one so since it's negative we'll going go down
and it's a negative one so we'll going go down one.
So that right over there is the point (4,-1)
So I've plotted it, but now I have to select which quadrant the point lies in
and this is just a naming convention.
This is the first quadrant.
This is the second quadrant.
This is the third quadrant,
and this is the fourth quadrant.
So the point lies in the fourth quadrant.
Quadrant IV
and I guess you have to know your Roman Numerals a little bit to know that--
--that's representing Quadrant IV.
Let's do a couple more of these.
Plot (8,-4) and select the quadrant in which the point lies.
Well my x coordinate is 8 so I move 8 or I go 8 in the positive x direction.
And then my y is -4 so I go 4 down,
and this is sitting again in, not the first, not the second, not the third, but the fourth quadrant.
In Quadrant IV.
Let's do one more of these.
Hopefully we get a different quadrant.
So we want to plot the point (-5,5)
So now my x coordinate is negative, it's negative 5.
So I'm going to move to the left in the x direction.
So I go to negative 5,
and my y coordinate is positive so I go up 5.
So (-5,5)
and this is sitting not in the first quadrant, but the second quadrant,
and of course this is the third and fourth.
So this is sitting in the second quadrant, which I answer and we got it right.