We already know that 2 to the 4th power can be view as starting with number 1 and then multiplying by 2, 4 times
so, let me do that. so, time 2, times 2, times 2, times 2. and that will give us...16
Now i will ask you a more interesting question. What do you think 2 to the negative 4th power will be?
I encourage you to pause the video and think about that
You may be tempted to say maybe is negative sixteen or something like that, but remember
what the exponent operation is trying to do. This is one way of viewing this. This is telling us is how many time are we going to
multiply 2 times negative 1, but here we are going to multiply negative 4 times? What negative traditionally mean?
Negative traditionally means the opposite. So here is how many times you are going to multiply.
Maybe when we make it negative this says how many time, are we going to starting with the 1, are we going to divide
by 2, so let think about that a little bit. So this can be view as one times
and we are going to divide by 2, 4 times. We are dividing by 2 is the same thing as multiplying by 1/2
so we can say that this 1 times 1/2 times... so 1 time 1/2, times 1/2, times 1/2 times 1/2
notice, multiplying by one half 4 time is the exactly the same thing as dividing by 2, 4 times
and in this situation, this will get you
1 time 1/2 is 1/2, time 1/2 is 1/4, times 1/2 is 1/8, times 1/2 is 1/16
and so you probably see the relationship here
this is essentially...you starting with the 1 and you divide by 2, 4 times
you could also say...that 2 to the - 4 is the same thing as 1/(2^4)
let me color code nicely so you realize what is negative doing
so this negative right over here
let me do it in a better color...magenta, something that jumps out
.