This sculpture's not usaully up, but it's a great Hesse
It's wonderfully awful
What do you mean by wonderfully awful?
Well, now
She's so pushng boundaries in so many improtant ways. I think in order
to really appreciate what her
what the ovengaurd was doing at this moment. She was hanging around people
like Ad Reiheadt with a whole series of artists that were involved
in a kind of high conceptualism, where there was an attempt to create a kind of
perfection in the physical world that represepented a kind of
ideal, a kind of purity, that was incredibly cerebral, it was incredibly
geometric. And, it has a sense that, when you look at that kind of work
that anything that anybody can make, that Ad Reinhardt can make, for instance
be just sort of a patonic shadow of