Find the area of rhombus ABCD
giving that the radii of the circles circumscribed
about triangles ABD and ACD are 12 5 and 25 respectively
So let's draw ourselves rhombus ABCD
So let's draw a rhombus!
So let me draw it, and here we go!
That's a decent rhombus right over there;
we know that the all sides of a rhombus are equal
So let's name, let's label the vertices, so vertex A, B, C, D
So there we go rhombus ABCD
And then they say the radii of the circles circumscribed
about triangles ABD, so triangle ABD, that's ABD
That is triangle ABD so let's draw the circle,
let's draw it's circumcircle, its circumscribed circle
or the circle that passes through the vertices A, B and D
So, let me draw, do my best job at that
this is not a trivial thing to do, it's not always easy
So let's, let's do it like that there we go, that's it,
It's circumscribed circle or it's the circle,
circle circumscribed about ABD right over there
Now they're telling us, they're telling us that its diameter is 12 5
so they're saying that this diameter right over here
So if I were to draw a diameter of this circle right over here
it is 12 5
Now there other circle, circumcircle for triangle ACD
so let's draw ACD; A, C, A, C, D
So let's draw a circle that can go through the these 3 point
it looks like it would have to be something,
something like this, something like this
It looks like somewhat bigger circle,
and that that gels with the information that they gave us,
the way I drew it
So the circle would look something like that
I don't wanna spend too much trying, time trying to draw that circle
but they're telling us that it's I should be very careful
They're saying that the radius is 12 5 not the diameter,
so there we make it very clear,
Actually let me delete that circle
since it's just so messy
I can delete that 12 5 too, let me get
There you go, so the 12 5 is the radius the radii of the circle,
so this first circle ABD around a triangle ABD
This distance right over is 12 5
and this distance over here is also 12 5
So let's focus on triangle ACD
Let's focus on that triangle
Its circumcircle -- will look something like this,
there you go something like that
The whole point here is we're trying to draw circumcircle
but it's a point it's a circle
that will go through those three points
And it has a radius of 25,
so if you draw if you had its center
or if I were to draw a diameter of it is 25, fair enough
Now we need to figure out the area of rhombus A, B, C and D
Now if you've been seeing the video that I've been uploaded lately,
actually I've been uploading a few of the prerequisites for this
Because there is a formula, we proved the formula in the geometry
and in the competition math playlist
We proved the formula that relates
the area of a triangle to it's to radius of its circumcircle
And let me just rewrite the formula right over here
The formula is the radius of triangles circumcircle
is equal to the product of the triangles,
the product of the triangles' sides all of that over four
times the area of the triangle
So let's see if we can use this formula
then we have proved in a previous video
to figure out the areas of triangle ABD or express them somehow
and triangle ACD
and see if we can use that information
to figure out the area of the entire rhombus
So let me let me redraw it, let me redraw it a lil' bit
cause I think my diagram's got kinda messy
So I'll redraw the rhombus,
if you want you don't have to draw the circumcircles
or the circumscribed circles
because we know this formula right of here
So this is A, B, C and D now let's think first of about triangle ABD,
Actually let me just draw the diagonals here
BD is one of the diagonals AC
is another one of the diagonals AC is the other diagonals
We know that the diagonals of a rhombus are perpendicular bisectors
we know that that's a right angle,
And we know, that this length is equal to this length
and we also know that that length is equal to that length
Now, if we knew this green length here
and this blue length here we would be able
to figure out the area of the rhombus
Let's label them, let's call this let's call this right over
here let's call this lower case a
and let's this length over here lower case b
A times B times one half would be
the area of this triangle right over there
A time B times one half times 2 would give us this area
and to that area or other way to think about it
This triangle is completely congruent;
it has sides AB and this side right over here
All of these four triangles have those three sides
So, all four of these triangles are congruent
so you could take the area of this triangle multiply it by four
you will have the area of the rhombus
Let me write this down, the rhombus the rhombus area
is equal to four times one half AB
One half AB gives us just this triangle
right over here four times that which will be
so four times one half AB is two AB
is gonna be the area of the rhombus
We can tell more we can figure out A and B,
we can figure out A and B we can figure out the rhombus' area
So let's focus on this first piece of information,
let's focus on triangle let's focus on triangle A, B, and D
They tell us that it's circumradius s 12 5
so let's just use this formula right over here we get
12 5 is equal to its circumradius
12 5 is equal to the product of length of the sides
So what's the length of the sides here?
So we have this side right over here side BD
that's just gonna be 2A right?
That's an A so A plus an A
So it's gonna be 2A times this side right over here
What's this side which is one of the sides of the rhombus?
Well that's, this is a hypothesis of this
right triangle right over here, right?
This is a right angle,
so it's going to be the square root of A squared plus B squared
But all of the sides are going to be like that,
it's a rhombus all the sides are the same
A squared plus B squared they're all going
to have the exact same length
So the product of the sides,
you have 2A that's the length of BD times
the length of BA which is going to be the square root of A
squared plus B squared time the length of AD
which is the square root of A squared plus B squared
all of that over four times
the area four times the area of ABD
So all of that is four times,
so what's the area of A, B, and D
Well ABD is just two of these triangles right over here
This guy over here is one half AB
This guy also is one half AB
So the entire the entire area is going to be two
of these guys right over here which is gonna be A times B
A times B it gives you the area
of both of these triangles each of more than one half AB
So, instead of writing the area right here I can write AB
So, let's see this simplifies to 12 5 is equal to
divide the numerator and the denominator by twos
so it becomes one becomes a two becomes a one
That becomes a one, square of A squared plus
B squared times square of A squared plus
B squared is just A squared plus B squared
A squared plus B squared and the denominator were just with 2b
So this first piece of information the circumradius for ABD 12 5
gives us this equation right over here
Now let's just do the same thing for triangle ACD
Its circumradius is 25 is equal to the length of this side
This is a B this is also a B so it's going to be 2B,
2B times the length of the side
which is the square root of A squared plus B squared
times the length of this side which is again
just square root of A square plus B squared
all of that over four times four times the area four times the area
Now the area once again it's just this triangle
which is one half AB plus this triangle which is another one half AB
you add them together you just get AB, you just get AB
Two divided by two you get one there,
you get a two here divide by B, get a one
that just has becomes an A
and so you get 25 is equal to the numerator squared
of A squared of B squared times itself
it's just gonna be A squared plus B squared over 2A
So that second triangle its circumradius being 25
gives us this equation right over here
We can use the both of this;
we have two equations with two unknowns
Let's solve for A and B if we know A and B
we can then go back here to figure out the rhombus' area
So, over here we get over here we get
let's multiply both sided by 2B
we get 25B is equal to A squared plus B squared
Over here if we multiply both sides by 2A
we get 50A is equal to A squared plus B squared
So 50A is equal to A squared plus B squared,
25B is equal to A squared plus B square
so 25B must be the same thing as 50A
they're both A squared plus B squared
So we get 25B must be equal to 50A
they're both equal to A square plus B squared
Now divide both sides no with by 25
you get B is equal to 2A B
I wanna do that in magenta
B is equal to B is equal to 2A
So we can take this information
and then now substitute back into one of these equations
to solve for B so we can solve for A
So let's go back into this one
so we get 50A
I have to solve for A first
50A is equal to A squared plus B squared instead of writing B squared,
we know B is the same thing as 2A
so let's write 2A squared
So we get 50A is equal to A square plus four A squared
or we get 50A is equal to 5A squared divide
both sides we can divide both sides by 5A
If we divided this side by 5 we get 10
and if we divide this side by 5 we get A
So A is equal to 10 and we can just substitute
back here so we can figure out B
Two times A is equal to B,
B is equal to two times 10 which is equal to 20
So we now A is 10 B is 20 we just have to go right back
here to figure out the area of the rhombus
The area of the rhombus is equal to
2 times A was 10, 2 times 10 times 20
This is 20 times 20 this equal to 400 and we're done
The area of the rhombus ABCD is 400