I got this problem here form the 2003 AIME Exam, that state to American Invitational Mathematics Exam, and this is actually the first problem of the exam.
The product N of three positive integers is 6 times their sum, and one of the integers is the sum of the other two.
Find the sum of all possible values of N.
So we have to deal with three positive integers.
So we have three positive integers write over here.
So we just think about three positive integers, just call them a,b, and c.
They are positive and they are integers.
The product N of these three positive integers.
So a times b times c is equal to N, is 6 times their sum.
This is equal to 6 times their sum.
Let me just use another color.
So this is their product.
So the product N of three positive integers is 6 times their sum.
So this is equal to 6 times their sum of those integers.
a plus b plus c, and the one of the integers is the sum of the other two.
One of the integers is the sum of other two.
Let we just pick c to be the sum of a and b.
It does not matter. This is just a name.
We have to set one of them is larger or less than the other one.
So we just set that a plus b is equal to c. The one of integers is the sum of other integers.
c is the sum of a plus b. Find the sum of all possible values of N.
We just try to little bit of liquidation of the information that we have here.
Maybe we can get some relationship or some constrains on the numbers that we can kind of go through the possibilities.
We know the a plus b is equal to c.
So we can replace c, replace c everywhere with a plus b.
So this expression write over here becomes ab which is a times b times c.
But instead of c, I am gonna to write a plus b over here. a+b.
And then that is equal to 6 times a plus b plus c.
And so, once again.
I will replace c with a plus b.
And then what does this simplify to.
So on the right hand side, we have 6 times a plus b plus b plus a plus b.
This is the same thing 6 times 2a plus 2b, just add the as and bs.
And we can factor 2. This the same thing as if you take out the 2.
6 times 2 is 12 times a plus b.
The left hand side, write over here, is still a times b or ab times a plus b.
So ab times a plus b is gotten to be equal to 12 times a plus b.
So this is pretty interesting here.
We can divide both sides by a plus b.
We know the a plus b won't be equal to, can not be equal to 0.
So all of these numbers have to be positive numbers.
So we divide both sides and the reason why I say that is if it was 0.
Dividing by 0, it will give a undefined answer.
So we divide both sides by a plus b, we get a times b is equal to 12.
So all the constrains that they give us boil off these down to this write over here.
The product of a and b is equal to 12.