Let's go little bit into how we can tell whether our body is processing glucose properly
And whether or maybe we have diabetes
And I want you all to take all of this with a huge grain of salt
because I am not a doctor, this is not medical advice
My goal here is to kind of just explore this subject with you
and try for all of us to get a better understanding of things
So let's think about what might happen after we have a meal
So we draw a little chart over here
So let's call this "hours"
And then on the vertical axis, I'm going to talk about our concentration of sugar in the blood
--so "blood sugar concentration"
sugar--actually you can call it "glucose concentration"
"blood sugar", we are talking about glucose
So let me draw a couple of points on this chart
So maybe this is 50, and our unit is going to be milligrams per decilitre (mg/dL)
Actually let me just do it this way, let me just say that everything is in milligram per decilitre
and we will talk in future videos about how we can relate this unit to everyday terms
But let's say that this right here is 50, this right here is 100
this right here is 150, and let's mark it right here at 200
So let's think about what will happen for a normal person
Let me mark some hours over here
so hour 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8; that's probably good enough
So the normal person, when they haven't eaten anything for a long time, let's say greater than 8 hours
So their fasting blood sugar, will be right around 80 mg/dL, give or take a little bit
There's a range around that, but I just want to show you what would happen to a normal person
So 80 mg/dL, their blood sugar should hopefully be right around there
And sometimes this fasting blood sugar, maybe we are assuming this is in the morning
maybe this hour 1 is 7am, so they haven't eaten for a while
that's fasting blood sugar
This is also, you'll hear in, sometimes your doctor
I heard my wife say this word without knowing what it meant
they sometimes say "preprandial"
Which is a very fancy word, which just means "before a meal"
"preprandial" is literally "before eating"
After the meal, you'll talking "postprandial"
A very fancy word, for a very simple idea, eating
So let's say at hour 2, this individual eats breakfast
So this is when the individual is going to eat breakfast
Now a normal person, when the person eats breakfast there'll be some carbohydrates in that breakfast
And it will be broken down into glucose, and glucose will enter the blood stream
And so their blood glucose will go up
it will slowly go up
And I was reading some studies, they say it kind of spikes 45 minutes into a meal
So let's see, 45 min is over there
so maybe it will go up to about there
And in a normal individual, the blood glucose level really shouldn't go above 120 mg/dL
And you know, there's obviously exceptions to all of these
we're just kind of saying that the normal breakfast, the normal person
not, you know, they're not eating a pint of honey, doing something crazy
Let's say 120 would be right around there
A normal person, you wouldn't, someone who does not have diabetes
it'll be unlikely that it'll go above that
And actually about after 2 hours, they're getting pretty close to normal
they're getting back under 100 mg/dL
And then you go beyond 2 hours, they just kind of get close back to their baseline
to the 80 mg/dL
So once again, this is normal
and of course, don't freak out if you were to take a blood test one morning and you're like 85 mg/dL
you're still not far off from normal, so obviously there's some variation from person to person
Now, if someone has diabetes, if either they have Type I, they don't have enough insulin
to actually process the glucose
or, if they have enough insulin, but their body is desensitised
the insulin is not being processed, so they can't process the glucose
We'll see that the glucose concentration will go up
And so in general, if you were to wake up one morning after not having eaten for more than 8 hours
and you were to prick your finger with little glucose monitors you can get at the drug store
And in your finger, the blood sugar levels, if you're to find them to be
let's say you're to find them to be at 140 mg/dL
it's a good indication, you shouldn't freak out, you should do multiple tests
and make sure that it wasn't a false reading or any of that
And you should definitely see a doctor
Once again, don't take this as any type of medical advice
that is not the purpose of this. The purpose of this is to understand a little bit of what's going on
Don't change your lifestyle based on any thing I tell you
Alright, but if you do experience that, it looks like, at least just from that one data point
that your body is not processing sugar properly
because you had over 8 hours to process the sugar
for insulin to go into your blood steam, and allow glucose to be taken up
and get back down to normal level
but it still hasn't gone there
So if you were to test a value like that, you should be concerned.
In general, the threshold--I've seen multiple thresholds here--
are between--I've seen high, and kind of middle one--120-130 mg/dL
So you're fasting, blood sugar is around this line right here
remember, the fasting blood sugar, not after you've eaten
Preprendial, before meal
if it is above that threshold right over there, then you should definitely at least see a doctor
and make sure they can see if you have diabetes
but this will be cause for concern
Another thing is that after a meal it spikes well beyond that
if we're talking it gets above 180
you know, once again, these are just thresholds that, you know, doctors have come up with
and researchers have come up with
and say, "hey this is a good indication that somehow you're not processing glucose properly"
so 180, 180 is up here, I'm drawing this is a squiggly line 'cause it's kind of a range
you know, it's not like if your blood glucose is 124 you're safe
and all of a sudden 125 you have diabetes
you know they're not that different from each other, but they have to set up some thesholds
so that, just to kind of have a threshold I guess
so if your blood sugar, after eating a meal, were to spike up to 200
once again, that would be cause for concern
In general, if someone has diabetes because they're not processing the glucose properly
their blood glucose might look something like this
So maybe their fasting glucose is right around 125-130, they can move around
then they have a meal, that it might spike up
obviously they can process some of the glucose, otherwise they would die
but it's not being processed properly
so the glucose levels don't go down to where they should
And maybe some glucose gets taken up from the blood
obviously they're living, so the cells are metabolising something
but it never gets to the normal 80 mg/dL
it might settle down back to something in the 120 range, to something like that
which would be cause for concern
And in general if you're some place, I've seen the threshold if you're above 100 on a fasting basis
that's cause for concern, you should maybe adjust your lifestyle
And if you're above 120-130 after a meal, once again, you should also be slightly worried
that you might be prediabetic, or you might have some risk of developing diabetes
So if someone has blood sugar like this, they're probably diabetic
and if someone has blood sugar like this, they should be worried
Once again, I'm not a doctor, don't take any of this as an advice
This is really just our attempt to understand things a little bit better