Where we left off in the last video we were beginning to try
to figure out what the 24 roots of
1 were and then we're going to square those 24 roots, take the absolute value of their
imaginary part and then sum them up. So let's once again, let's just think about the
roots that matter. So this over here we figured out this is pi over 12
so let me, this is pi over 12...
it's the angle, I guess I should say, that's either the pi over 12i
let's just focus on the angle here, this over here is 2pi over 12
or pi over 6. This over here is 3pi over 12, or
pi over 4, this over here is 4pi over 12
4 pi over 12, or pi over 3, and this right over
here is 5pi over 12. This is 5pi over 12.
5pi over 12. And then this obviously
is just 6pi over 12 or pi over 2. We could keep going, but before we keep going
and this will really just simplify the math a little bit. Remember we're going to have to
square these roots. So let's just think about if we have some complex number, a + bi
If we have some complex number a + bi
Let's think about what happens when we square it. This is going to be equal to a^2 + 2abi - b^2
Or we could rewrite it as a^2 - b^2, which will be the real part, and then plus 2abi
2ab is the imaginary part.
And the reason why I even took the trouble of writing it this way is to realize that the complex
what we're going to do is square all these complex numbers, and then take the absolute value of the imaginary part.
So really all that matters is the absolute value of 2ab
Or really, 2 times the absolute value, 2 times the absolute value of ab
Now, these guys all have analogs where either a or b would be negative
So if this guy is, if this guy, this right over here, let's call this a + bi
If you had a - bi, you would be down here. You would be down here, so if this guy is a + bi, a -bi is going to be over here
Or you could have -a - bi is going to be over here. -a - bi is going to be over there.
Or you could have -a + bi over here. -a + bi over here.
But the reason why I did this is we showed you just over here
all of these guys, when you square them and you take the absolute value
of the imaginary part of that squared value, it's all going to be the same
when you take, it's going to be ab, the absolute value is just going to be ab
the absolute value is just still going to be ab, so they're all going to be the same
So what we can do is, and each of these guys is going to have the same analog
so what we can do is just find the values for these guys, 1, 2, 3, 4, for these 5 guys
over here. And then just multiply whatever we get by 4, because they each have
I guess there's 4 of these around the unit circle and that'll save a lot of our
work. Now the other thing we want to think about. We already said
ignore 1, because we added that root, but even if we didn't remember to ignore it it wouldn't matter
because 1 doesn't have any imaginary part, 1^2 is still 1, 1 does not have any imaginary
part. We can also ignore an angle of pi over 2, or 90 degrees
because this has no real part
and you see over here, when you square it it's actually going to take you
over here and it won't have an imaginary part. When you square it, it's
2 times the real times the imaginary part. This has no real part, so this is going to
be zero. So this guy will also not contribute. So we really just care
about these angles, right over here, and then we'll square them,
find the absolute value of their imaginary part, and then multiply
everything by 4 because that will correspond to these other,
if you took the imaginary and real parts and made them negative
and it would take us all the way around the unit circle.
so let's think about it a little bit, so let me just write these over here, so the
z's that we're going to think about right now are going to be
e to the pi over 12, e to the pi over 6, e to the pi over 4,
oh e to the pi over 12i, I should say, pi over 6i, pi over 4i,
e to the pi over 3i, and then we have e to the 5pi over 12i.
Now we're going to square each of them, and it's nice to leave them in this
exponential form when you square it, as it's much easier to square these values
if you square this you're just essentially multiply the exponent times 2
so this is going to be e to the pi over 6i, this will be e to the pi over 3i
We're just squaring them.
Just taking the square of each of these values
Each of these roots
So e to the pi over 3i, and in here you're going to have e to the pi over 2i,
then over here you'll have e to the 2pi over 3i
and then finally over here you'll have e to the 5pi over 6i.
Now these are the squared values of these roots here
Now let's just think about their imaginary parts.
So this guy right over here can be rewritten
as cosine of pi over 6 plus i-sine of pi over 6.
so his imaginary part is sine of pi over 6
This guy's imaginary part, if you expand it out with Euler's formula
cosine of pi over 3 plus i-sine pi over 3
So this imaginary part is just going to be sine of pi over 3
Here's going to be sine of pi over 2,
here's going to be sine of 2pi over 3,
and here's going to be sine of 5pi over 6
Now we just have to evaluate these guys
and take their absolute value, and then take the sum
and then multiply everything times 4, and we're essentially
in the home stretch. So pi over 6 is 180, actually let me draw
another unit circle over here just so we can visual these angles
so now we have sine of pi over 6, which is the same thing as 30 degrees,
so it looks like this. and we know that the sine of 30 degrees is 1/2
square root of 3 over 2, but this right over here is 1/2
sine of pi over 3 is the equivalent of 60 degrees, the sine over here is
square root of 3 over 2, you can figure that out from 30-60-90 triangles
then you have sine of pi over 2
pi over 2 is that right over there. Well the sine of that is just 1.
The imaginary part of this, or I guess this would evaluate just to i
but the imaginary part which is viewed as the coefficient on the i, which is kind of
nonintuitive, you kind of think it's the whole thing, but when people say
the imaginary part, so this will just be 1.
and then sine of 2 pi over 3. So pi over 3 is 60 degrees, so you can view that as
120 degrees. So it's 120 degrees, so it's right over here. So it's going to have
the same sine value as pi over 3.
so it's going to be square root of 3 over 2.
and then sine of 5pi over 6. pi over 6 is 30 degrees, so this is sine of
150 degrees, so it's going to be just like that.
And it's going to have the same sine value as pi over 6, it's going to be 1/2.
and lucky for us, these are all positive values
so let's just take the sum. We have 1/2 plus
1/2 is 1, plus another 1 over here is going to be 2, plus
the square root of 3 over 2 is square root of 3.
Now remember, for this quadrant over here, we have to do it for all of the
quadrants, so we just need to multiply everything times 4.
so the sum of the absolute value of the imaginary parts of the squares of
the roots is 8 plus 4 square root of 3. and going back
to the original problem. we got the answer here
This is 8 plus 4 square roots of 3. I wanna make sure I didn't mess it up, right
so if we want to find m + n + p, it is 8 plus 4 plus 3,
which is equal to 15
and we're done.