Define a good word as sequence of letters
that consists only of the letters A, B and C
some of these letters may not appear in the sequence
and which A is never immediately followed by B
B is never immediately followed by C
and C is never immediately followed by A
How many seven-letter good words are there?
So let's just think about this a little bit.
So there're letters which're As, Bs, and Cs
and then it could be all As all Bs all Cs
because some letters might not appear
and A is never immediately followed by B
so A could only be followed by another A or another C
B is never immediately followed by C
which means that B could only be followed by
an A or another B
and C is never immediately followed by A
so C can only be followed by another C or a B.
So how many seven-letter good words are there?
So let's just think about the places
we have seven letters
one, two, three, four, five, six, seven letters.
now there's no contraints on this first letter
since it's not following anything
so it could be an A, B or a C,
So there's three possibilities for this first letter
Now there's three possibilities for this first letter
but no matter what letter this is
how many possibilities are there
for this second letter over here?
Well if this was an A
the second letter could only be an A or a C
because it can't be followed by a B.
If this was a B
the second letter could only be a B or an A
because it can't be followed by a C
if this was a C
the second letter could only be a B or a C
So no matter what letter this first letter is
the second letter can only have two possibilities
Another way to think about it is
there's one letter
no matter what letter this is
there's one letter that's being ruled out here
so it can only be two possibilities.
The same thing is here
we're gonna stick some letter here
and no matter what letter there is over here
it's going to rule out one possibility over here
so we're gonna have only two possible letters
that we can put here
no matter what letter is there
and use the same logic:
only two possibilities there
So how many total possibilities do we have?
well 3x2x2x2x2x2x2
this is one, two, three, four, five, six 2's
so this is equal to 3x2 to the sixth power
which is 3 times 2 to the sixth, is 32x2, is 64
which is equal to 180 + 12, is equal to 192.
There're 192 possible seven-letter good words
or good words as defined above.