Rewrite the following expression as the product of positive exponents, and then evaluate
the expression when x=2.
So they give us x to the negative 3 times 5 to the negative 2 times
x squared.
So the main thing to realize here is if I had something to a negative
exponent, this is the exact same thing as 1 over that same base,
to the positive version of the exponent.
So x to the negative a is equal to 1 over x to the a.
So using this knowledge just supply it over here.
So x to the negative 3,
power,
We can rewrite as 1 over x to the third power.
And then 5 to the negative 2, we can rewrite as 1 over 5 squared.
And then finally we have times x squared.
So we can multiply this out and the numerator we have 1 times 1 times x squared.
Which is just equal to x squared.
And the denominator we have x to the third times 5 squared.
5 squared is 25, and here you could say implicit there is a 1.
This is the same thing as x squared over 1.
So the denominator we have 25 times x to the third.
So this is going to be 25, times x to the third.
And then we can simplify this even more because
both the numerator and the denominator is divisible by x squared.
x squared divided by x squared is 1.
x to the third divided by x squared is just going to be equal to x.
And you can use other exponent properties
you can say x squared over x to the third is the same thing as
x to the 2 minus 3 power which is x to the negative 1 power,
But x to the negative 1 power we know it is the same thing as 1 over
x.
Any way you do it as long you do it any reasonable way,
you should get the same result.
So when we simplify it,
we get 1 over 25 x.
Now, they want us to evaluate it when x=2.
So if x is equal to 2, we get 1 over 25 times 2 which is equal to 1
over
50. And we are done.
We rewrote the expression as a product of positive exponents.
That's right over here.
We made all the exponents positive.
And then we evaluate it.
We got 1 over 50.