The equation of a circle c is x plus three squared plus y minus four squared equals forty-nine.
What are its center (h,k) and its radius r?
So let's just remind ourselves of what a circle is.
You have some point, let's call that (h,k).
A circle is a set of all points that are equal distance from that point.
So let's take a set of all points that are say r away from that point.
So let's say that this distance right over here,
is r, so we want all the set of points that are exactly r away from
so all the points (x, y) that are r away.
So you can imagine you can rotate around and all of these points are going to be r away.
I'm going to try my best to draw at least a somewhat perfect-looking circle,
I won't be able to do a perfect job on it,
but you get a sense.
All of these are exactly r away, at least if I were to draw it properly,
they are r away.
So how do we find an equation in terms of r and (h,k)
and x and y that describes all these points?
Well we know how to find the distance between two points on a coordinate plane
and in fact, it comes straight out of the pythagorean theorem.
If we were to draw a vertical line right over here that essentially
is the change in the vertical axis between these two points,
up here, we're at y, here, we're at k,
so this distance is going to be y minus k.
We can do the exact same thing on the horizontal line,
This x coordinate is x while this x coordinate is h,
so this is going to be x minus h, is this distance
So this is a right triangle because we're measuring vertical distance here,
We're measuring horizontal distance here, so these two things are perpendicular.
So from the Pythagorean theorem, we know that this squared plus this squared must be equal to
r distance squared, so this is where the distance formula comes from.
So we know that x minus h squared plus y minus k squared
must be equal to r squared.
Any x and y that satisfies this equation will sit on this circle.
Now with that out of the way, let's go answer the question.
The equation of the circle is this thing.
And this looks awfully close to what we just wrote,
we just have to make sure we don't get confused with the negative.
remember, it has to be the form x minus h and y minus k.
So let's write a little bit differently.
Instead of x plus 3 squared, we can write that as x minus negative three squared,
and then plus y minus 4 squared is equal to
instead of 49, we can just call that seven squared.
So now it becomes pretty clear,
that our h is -3, and our k is positive 4,
and that our r is 7.
So we can say (h,k) is (-3,4).
You might say hey, there's a negative four here
but no, look it's minus k, so k is 4.
Likewise, it's minus h, you might say, hey, maybe h is a
positive three, but no, you're subtracting the h,
so you'd say minus negative three.
And similarly, the radius is 7.