Now, let's do something pretty interesting, this
in some degree will be one of the easiest functions to find
the maclaurin series representation of
let's try to approximate e^x
f(x) is equal to e^x
and what makes this really simple
is when you take the derivative
and frankly this is one of the amazing things
about the number e
is that when you take the derivative
of e^x, you get e^x
so this is equal to f ' (x)
this is equal to f 2nd derivative of x
this is equal to f 3rd derivative of x
this is equal to the nth derivative of x
it's always equal to e^x
that's the first mind-blowing thing about e
you can just keep taking it's derivative
the slope at any point on that curve
is the same as the value of the point on that curve
that's kind of crazy
with that said
let's take its maclaurin representation
so we have to find
f(0), f ' (0), the 2nd derivative of 0
and when we take e^0
e^0 is just equal to one
and so this is going to be equal to f(0)
this is going to be equal to f ' (0) it's going to be
equal to any of the derivatives evaluated
the nth derivative is going to be valued at zero
and that's what makes the Maclaurin series
fairly straightforward
if I want to approximate
e^x using a maclaurin series
so e^x
and I'll put a little approximately over here
and we'll get closer and closer
to the real e^x and as we keep adding more and more terms
especially if we add an infinite number of terms
it would look like this:
f(0) and we do it in
what colors did I use for cosine and sine?
pink and green
I'll use the yellow here
f(0) is 1
plus f ' (0) times x
f ' (0) is also one
plus x
plus this is also one
so x^2 / 2!
all of these things are going to be one
this is one
when we're taking about e^x
so you go to the third term
this is one
you just have x^3 / 3!
plus x^3 / 3!
and I think you see the pattern here
we just keep adding terms
x^4 / 4!
plus x^5 / 5! plus x^6 over 6!
and something pretty neat is starting
to emerge
this is just really cool
that e^x can be approximated by
1 plus x plus x^2 / 2!
plus x^3 / 3!
once again, e^x is starting to look like
a pretty cool thing
this also leads to other interesting results
like if you want to approximate e
you just evaluate this as x is equal to one
so this is, well, so you just say e is e ^ 1
and this is going to be approximately equal
to this polynomial evaluated at 1
if x is 1 here, then we make x equal to one
over here
so it will be, one plus one
plus one over 2!
plus one over 3!
plus one over 4!
and so on and so forth all the way into infinity
and you could also do this as one
over 1 ! as well
but what's really cool is that
this is another way to represent e
it shows that e
once again shows up as
kind of 2 + 1/2 + 1/6
if you keep doing this, you get close
to the number e
but that by itself isn't the only
fascinating thing
if we look back at the Maclaurin Representation
of these other functions.
cosine (x)
let me copy and paste cosine(x)
so, cosine (x) right up here
let me do my best to copy and paste the whole thing
so that is cosine(x) and let's do the same thing
for sine(x) that we did last video
so the sine of x
let me copy and paste that
so do we see any relationship between
these approximations?
so before, you probably would have
guessed there's some relationship
between cosine and sine
but what about e^x?
so what you see here
is that cosine(x) looks a lot like this term
plus this term, although we probably want
to put a negative out front here
so we have a negative version of this term
right here
plus this term right here
plus a negative version of this term
right over here
and sine (x) looks just like
this term plus a negative version of
this term
plus this term
plus a negative version of the next term
so if we could somehow reconcile the
negatives in some interesting way
it looks like e^x
at least the polynomial representation
of e^x
is somehow related to a combination
of the polynomial representations of
cosine of x and sine of x
so this is starting to get
really really really cool
we're starting to see a connection
between something related to
compound interests
or a function whose derivative
is always equal to that function
and these things that come out of the unit circle
and oscillatory motion and all kinds of things
there starts to seem a kind of pure
connectiveness there. but i'll leave you
there on that video and in the next video
I'll show you how to reconcile these three
fascinating functions