So, we thought we'd talk about Picasso's
great painting, called "Guernica,"
which actually, I remember seeing very many times,
because it used to be in the Museum of Modern Art
before it was sent back to Spain.
- Yeah, it was. I kind of feel like I grew up with this painting.
- Yeah, me too.
- It was always such a powerful presence at MOMA.
- Yeah. And it was in a very small little room, so it was very intense.
- It was. It was. You know what was interesting is that actually,
in Picasso's will, he lent it to MOMA
until such time as Spain became a democracy again.
And remember, Franco lived for a very long time.
And this painting was made as a response to Franco -
- Well, to a specific event, the Spanish Civil War -
- A terrible, terrible event -
and this is such a loaded and powerful painting
and has had such an impact, both when it was made
and long afterwards.
- Yes, we can talk about two . . .
So, maybe we should talk about the historical circumstances
in which it was made.
It's a gigantic painting, and it was made by Picasso in Paris
at the request of one of two Spanish governments
that existed at that moment.
Remember, there was a civil war going on in Spain,
and on one side were the Fascists, led by Franco,
who would win the Spanish Civil War.
But on the other side were what were called the Republicans.
It has nothing to do with American
Republicans versus Democrats.
But these were people who wanted a democracy,
and they tended to be a bit more on the left,
whereas Franco tended to be very much on the right
of this political spectrum, in a much more extreme sense
than we have today. And what happened was that
Franco was trying to intimidate the population.
You have to remember, this is . . . we're talking about 1937 now.
This is before the second World War.
There had been the horrors of the First World War,
and there had been the rise of Fascism in Spain,
in Italy, in Russia -
-and Germany.
-and Germany, absolutely.
-and what happened was, was that Franco decided
to unleash violence directly on a civilian population
in order to really cow that population,
and to assert his power.
- and to consolidate his power.
- Absolutely. And so what he did is,
he actually was in touch with Hitler in Germany,
and he allowed Hitler to test out some of his bombers
on the city of Guernica.
-Hard to believe.
-It's really incredible. And Picasso was so horrified by this-
- the world was horrified by this - by the bombings,
and the mass civilian casualties that resulted.
Guernica was not a military target.
-Guernica's a little town.
-It's a little town. And this is a painting that was Picasso's
sort of, visceral response to this, that was made
specifically for an international exhibition in Paris,
a kind of World's Fair.
So, maybe we should talk about what we see.
-Yeah, it's a . . . it's a very powerful image against
the horrors of wars, I think in the tradition of
Goya's "Third of May."
- or David's "The Oath of the Horatii."
But you know, those were really old paintings.
And when you think about the 20th century,
when this was made, history painting,which is
what we were just referring to,
it didn't exist, really, anymore.
So a lot of people have credited Picasso with
almost single-handedly re-establishing the importance
of grand history painting. And I think for him,
this event required that kind of solemnness, that kind of import.
-Of the tradition of history painting. There are so many things
that remind me of Goya.
The figure in the foreground, for example, who's all
splayed out with a knife in his hand,
like the Spanish peasants in Goya,
Christlike in their martyrdom.
-The other thing that really reminds me of Goya here
is Picasso's choice to do this painting in black and white -
- black, white and grays, right.
- and, you know, Goya's painting is in color,
but it's all so starkly lit that it might as well be -
- Right, and it's about the forces of darkness,
and the forces of good.
- It is, and the contrasts between light and darkness,
both in this painting and in the Goya, I think
it's very consciously Picasso, another Spaniard
recalling that great example of history painting. Yeah, yeah.
And that image of the mother and the child on the left,
- That's so effective.
-I look at this painting and I can almost hear the bombs,
and the sirens, and the screaming. It's so palpable.
-On the extreme right, you have the woman
who's fleeing the burning building, her burning home.
And of course this painting is full of symbolism.
There's the horse, of course, screaming
There is the broken sword as you had mentioned,
And then, I think, really potent and really curious and
interesting is the light source itself, that lamp.
You know, people have said it looks like a human eye.
Perhaps the eye of God.
But you have an electric light bulb there.
And also it could function as an explosion.
That could be the explosion of the bombs.
-I think that's always sort of how it felt to me,
looking at that, was like the lights flickering on and off,
and explosions, and lights, and the way that lights . . .
you know, explosions sort of make lights flicker,
and it has this feeling of the chaos of that moment.
- It really does. It really does.
It also kind of vilifies modernity, in the sense of
the possibility of having airplanes drop bombs.
You know, because it's an electric light bulb, after all.
Something else that I find really interesting here
is the cross-hatching. Do you see that,
especially in the body of the horse?
Some art historians have talked about that
as a reference to the newsprint that Picasso
used to put into his paper collages.
But here, it's actually painted to look like
a little hatching, as if it might be print.
But it's not. So it's sort of self-reference.
But also, a reminder that this is a current event.
Like Gericault's "Raft of the Medusa,"
this is a tragedy that has just taken place.
And it's a pretty extraordinary painting.
And we know that when Colin Powell went to the UN,
to make the case for the war in Iraq,
by saying, claiming that, he believed at the time
that Saddam Hussein had weapons of mass destruction,
or the Bush administration believed it, and Colin Powell went to make that case at the United Nations
they didn't want to take pictures in front of this image.
-Well traditionally, the press sessions are in front of
a tapestry that was donated to the UN.
-It's a copy of this image.
And you're right, he did not want to be seen
in front of that.
-Right, because he was making a case for war.
And here we have this very, you know -
-Stark reminder of the price of war.
-Right, and I think it's really important to say
that this is represented in a sort of abstract,
Cubist kind of representation that, I think,
makes it more powerful.
I think if this had looked photographic,
I don't think it would have the power that it does.
I think the ways that the forms are exaggerated,
the hands moving up, and across, and all of the ways
that we have a kind of exaggeration here
are there to serve the emotional point of the image,
of the horrors of war.
-And because was brilliant, I think
at doing that.
- That formal language of expressing
those emotions.
- Yeah, but it form that is used, that
is folded into such a powerful political
and sort of humanistic message.
- Yeah, and it's interesting also because so
much of the history of the 20th century
and of art history is really looking at art
in a way that is very separate
from the political arena.
- A sanitized formalism.
In fact, much of Picasso's other work is
really dealing with the way vision
can be represented in a very, very
kind of formal way.
And it's so interesting to see such a
powerful statement.
I mean, there were other examples of Picasso's work,
but here is sort of the great example of the 20th century,
of a deeply political painting from an artist who
spent a good deal of his career, you're absolutely right,
really focusing on the way we see and the way we
represent what we see.
And art historians have written art history
very much in that way for much of the 20th century.
- So here is a really successful marriage that does
not separate ...
- Art that is engaged, right?
- In the world, in the most direct way.