We're in the Atraskan museum
in the Vatican Museums in Rome, and we're looking at my favorite
pot in the entire world. I can see why it's your favorite
pot. Seems to almost glow. The thing that makes it so fabulous
is we have these two heroes and we have a very simple image, but it's
giving us so much information. The heroes are
Achilles on the left and Ajax on the right, two of the great Greek
heroes featured in Homers Iliad and Exekias
is the potter who signed only two pots as the potter
and the painter, has identified these two figures by including
their names above them. He's also telling us what's happening
between the two. Achilles on the left is saying
the word four. You can see Tesra. And on the right
we see Ajax saying three; tri.
We know immediately that Achilles is winning the game that they're playing.
But this is of course a metaphor for the way that this myth will unfold
On either side, we see their shields. Achilles
still has his helmet on, although Ajax has taken his off - so a moment of relaxation between battles.
They are on the battlefield of Troy. Exekias has given us even more information in this.
not just the rolls of the dice and in larger sense - their fate.
Look at the way for example that while both figures are hunched over and focused at the game at hand,
and remember, these two men are really close friends,
so there is an intimacy here, brotherhood. Nevertheless Achilles, who has the higher role,
is holding his spears loosely, you can see the way the points are actually separating.
At the bottom you can see from the lines they're not as parallel.
But look at the figure at the right - Ajax, whose spears are held in a more parallel way,
so that we know that he is actually clinching with his fist,
he's tense. I even sensed a little bit of that tension in his brow.
Well, that's right, if you look at his brow really closely, you can see that Achilles has a single incised line to represent his brow.
But Ajax has a double line and it is a sort of clue that perhaps there's a little bit of tension there.
One other detail that can be easely seen, although it is really saddle,
look at the === of both figures.
Achilles again is relaxed, his heel is on the ground line,
But Ajax, his heel is picked up ever so slightly, so you can see the lithe bit of light underneath it.
Which means that his calf is engaged, those muscles are tense, his body is tense.
He is also a little bit more hunched over, his head is a little bit lower that that of his friend Achilles.
That does seam to mean something wider than just this board game.
Anybody who's looking it this pod in the ancient world would have known the story of Ajax and Achilles that Hommers tells.
As you said, Achilles is a great hero.
In fact, as a child his mother dipped him in the river Styx, which had the magical quality of making him invincible.
It's just that she held him by his heel, so his heel was not protected.
And ultimately he will be killed by an arrow that hits him there.
Hence, the term that we use often of "someone's Achilles' heel", that is their vulnerable spot.
Nevertheless, Achilles would die a great hero.
Ajax has a more complicated fate.
He will outlive Achilles and carry his great friend off the battle field.
Then ultimately he'll be in a battle for Achilles' armor.
Achilles has a very special armor, which has been made by the god Hephaestus.
Two people would want that armor and they would both give speeches to convince judges as to who should get the armor.
But Ajax, though he was closer to Achilles, would lose the contenst, have a bad moment, where he slayd a bunch of Greeks
and ultimately would kill himself on his own sword - humiliation at the end of his life.
So it's really interesting to think about this as an ancient Greek viewer who knows the whole story
and what would unfold for both of those heroes.
But the story is one thing and the way that Exekias the potter has represented this moment,
and these two figures with so much nobility, with such fine detail in the shape of a vase,
which is so elegant, is something else.
Exekias really was the great master of attic black-figure vase painting.
These black figures, they are silhouettes, that if you look closely, the decorative forms is mostly put inside with needle.
And the black surface is like paint, but is not quite paint.
This is slip-wear. The Greeks didn't had the technology to get kilns ovens hot enough to vitrify that is to create true gleasers the way ceramics do now.
So what they would do instead is they would take very fine particles of clay, suspend them in water
and use those as a kind of paint and depending on amount of oxygen they allowed into a kiln
it would turn it black or red. They would paint the surface with the slip and then
they would burnish it, that is they would take a very smooth surface, imagine the back of a spoon,
and they would rub it back and fort so you get this surface that is really glossy and it almost looks like gliss.
When I look closely at the decorative borders on the handles or the decorative border just above the figures,
I can see beautiful detail and it's almost in three dimentional form.
The slip is almoust raised in areas, so it catches the light.
Well, the Greeks did often =========
And so, one could imagine almost decorating a cake.
You have a kind of ............ and it leaves a kind of bead that is raised against the surface.
And in a much finer level, that's what we're seeing here.
So, Exekias is a master, hes pots stand out in so many ways,
in their shape, and the painting, and the detail, in the drama,
that he was able to convey.
Well, certainly the Etruscans thought that was the case, because they must have spent a good deal of money
importing this pot from Greece across the Mediterranean all the way to the Italian peninsula, where they lived.
You know, so many of the great pots from ancient Greece were actually buried in Etruscan tombs.
They were imported, the Greeks did a tremendous business, exporting such pots.
Exekias was one of the great masters.