We're now starting test 7. And we're on section two.
Let's see, problem 1 is on page 774.
So they say set x-- x is equal to this-- 30, 31, 32, 33.
I haven't read the problem yet,
I'm just drawing what they drew.
This is 32, 33, 34, 35 and 36.
Sets x and y are shown above.
How many numbers in set x are also in set y?
Well hopefully it's fairly straightforward.
Is 30 in set y? No. Then is 31 in set y? No.
32 is, right? And so is 33. 1, 2, the answer is 2.
That's choice A. Not too tough, huh?
All right, problem number 2.
If Peg traveled 10 miles in 2 hours,
and Linda traveled twice as far in 1/2 the time--
So Linda traveled twice as far.
So twice as far is 10 miles.
So she traveled 20 miles, right? Times 2, that's all I did.
And they say, in 1/2 the time,
so she traveled 20 miles in 1 hour, right?
I just do the 1/2 here. 20 miles in 1 hour.
What was Linda's average speed in miles per hour?
She did 20 miles in 1 hour. Well that's 20 miles per hour.
And that's choice C.
Also not a difficult problem.
Not that you should feel bad if you had it wrong,
it's just all about practice.
It's all about actually reading the problem.
I know that might seem a bit obvious, but you'd be surprised.
You've even seen me make a couple of mistakes
by not reading the problem properly.
OK, problem 3.
They say, my cousin marked this up with a black marker,
so I only hope that what I see is what you see.
So let's see, x is equal to--
she did this when she was in sixth grade.
So I'm very proud of her that
she was taking the SAT in sixth grade.
But anyway, x is equal to k times k minus 2.
Then x plus 1 is equal to what? [COUGH]
Excuse me. x plus 1 is equal to what?
So let's just add 1 to both sides of this equation.
So x plus 1 is equal to k times k minus 2 plus 1, right?
I just added 1 to both sides of that equation,
and that equals k squared minus 2k plus 1.
And that is choice-- if I can read this properly--
that is choice C. k squared minus 2k plus 1.
Problem number 4.
I should have drank water before starting this video,
but I will move forward and complete what I have begun.
So they draw a graph that looks something like that.
And then there's a line that goes something like this.
And then they tell us-- what do they tell us?
They tell us, well it looks like,
it intersects at this point, at y equals 1.
So this is the point,0,1, right?
x is 0, so this is the x-axis. This is the y-axis.
The figure above shows the graph of a line of y
equals ax plus b where a and b are constants.
Which of the following
best represents the graph of the line 2a x plus b?
So let's draw it.
I'm not even going to look at all the choices.
What would this look like?
So it's going to have the same y intercept, right?
It's going to intersect at the same point.
That's the y intercept. Let me draw in this peach color.
So it's going to intersect right here.
And its slope is 2 times the slope of the previous one.
So it's going to be even a steeper slope.
So the line's going to look something like this.
It's going to be twice as steep,
so it's going to look like this. All right
And all I just have is that same y intercept, right?
Because the b is still , but they've doubled the slope,
so it's going to go up even faster.
And so, if you look at all the choices,
we can immediately rule out all of the choices
that don't have the same y intercept.
And the only choices that have the same y intercept
are choices B and C, right?
Only those that intersect at 0, 1.
And then between B and C,
B is steeper so B is going to be our answer, right?
C is actually less steep than this green line.
Choice C looks something like this.
So its slope is less than a.
So it's not going to be choice C, so it has to be choice B.
B goes through the same y intercept
and it is steeper than our original green line.
So that's the answer,choice B.
Next problem, problem 5. OK, they drew us a triangle.
That's one side. That's another side.
They have drawn this-- whoops. I can't-- OK, there you go.
That's not as nice looking as I would have liked,
but you get the point. That's a right triangle.
They say that this is x.
And the figure above the perimeter of the triangle
is 4 plus 2 root 2.
What is the value of x? So what is the value of this side?
Well Pythagorean theorem, the value of that side
is the square root of x squared plus x squared.
So that equals, what? The square root of 2x squared.
You can take the x out, right?
Square root of x squared is just x.
So that equals x square root of 2.
And they actually even tell you that on the first page of--
if you go back to page 774,they tell you,
you have a 45, 45, 90 triangle, it's x square roots of 2.
But I like to solve it every time.
So this is x, this is x, this is x square root of 2.
So what's the perimeter? It's x plus x plus x root 2.
So it's 2x plus x root 2. That's the perimeter, right?
And they also tell us that,
that equals 4 plus 2 root to 2, right?
That's for the perimeter.
So you could just do pattern matching.
You'd say well, this looks a lot like x is equal to 2.
And it is, because if x is equal to 2, this becomes a 2,
and then this becomes a 4, right?
So that's our answer,x is equal to 2. And that is choice A.
Next problem. Let me switch colors. OK.
There's always something for me to draw.
Well before I draw it, let me read the question.
The scores on Tuesday's history test
for 16 students are shown on the table above.
Sam was the only student absent on Tuesday.
He'll take the test next week.
If Sam receives a 95 on the test,
what will be the median score for the test? OK.
So they give us a score and number of students.
So I'm actually going to write all this,score
and then number.
And so 1 kid got 100; two kids got a 95;
90, four kids got it; 85, 1 kid; 80, 3 kids;
75,2 kids; 70, 2 kids; 65, no kids; and then 60, 1 kid.
And then Sam comes along and gets a 95 on the exam, right?
So before, there's only 2 kids who got a 95.
Now Sam comes along
and there's going to be 3 kids who got a 95 on the exam.
So to figure out the median,
all I do is I list out all the numbers,
and then I pick the middle number.
That's all the median is. So one kid got 100.
3 kids got a 95: 95, 95, 95. Four kids got a 90: 1, 2, 3, 4.
One kid got an 85. Three kids got an 80: 80, 80, 80.
Two kids got a 75. Two kids got a 70. And one kid got a 60.
So how many does that total? I could have just added this.
That's actually what I should have done.
But it's 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12,
13, 14, 15, 16, 17. So there's 17 kids.
So the median is going to be the number
that has eight above it and eight below it.
So 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, Bam!
That's the median, because there's 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6--
oh, no, no, that's not the median.
Sorry, sorry, sorry, this is the median: 85.
Because there's 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8 above it.
And there are 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8 below it.
So the answer is 85.
Before Sam came in there, then the median actually would be--
you'd have one number less here,so you'd have to move it up.
So it'd probably be 90,or it'd be an average. But anyway,
we know that the median is 85. And that is choice C.
See you in the next video.