Lets say you are trying to make some kind of product
And the Product is for the United States
So, ideally, you would like to know the 'Mean Height of Men' in the United States
Let me write this down...
"Mean Height of Men in the US"
So how would you do that?
When I talk about the mean, I am talking about the Arithmetic Mean
If I were to talk about some other types of means; and there are other types of means,like the Geometric Mean, I would specify
But when people just say mean, they are usually talking about the Arithmetic Mean.
So, how would you go about finding the mean height of men in the US?
Well, the obvious one is you go and ask or measure every man in the US
take their height, add them all together, and then divide by the number of men there are in the US.
But the question you would ask yourself is
Whether that is practical?
Because you have on the order, see over here about 300 million people in the US
roughly half of them will be men, or at least still be male