What I wanna do in this video is give an overview of quadrilaterals.
And you can imagine from this prefix, or I guess you could say from the beginning of this word - quad
This involves four of something.
And quadrilaterals, as you can imagine, are, are shapes.
And we're gonna be talking about two-dimensional shapes that have four sides, and four vertices, and four angles.
So, for example, one, two, three, four.
That is a quadrilateral.
Although that last side didn't look too straight.
One, two, three, four. That is a quadrilateral.
One, two, three, four. These are all quadrilaterals.
They all have four sides, four vertices, and clearly four angles.
One angle, two angles, three angles, and four angles.
Here you can measure. Here actually let me draw this one a little bit bigger 'cause it's interesting.
So in this one right over here you have one angle, two angles, three angles
and then you have this really big angle right over there.
If you look at the, if you look at the interior angles of this quadrilateral.
Now quadrilaterals, as you can imagine, can be subdivided into other groups
based on the properties of the quadrilaterals.
And the main subdivision of quadrilaterals is between concave and convex quadrilaterals
So you have concave, and you have convex.
And the way I remember concave quadrilaterals, or really concave polygons of any number of shapes
is that it looks like something has caved in.
So, for example, this is a concave quadrilateral
It looks like this side has been caved in.
And one way to define concave quadrilaterals,
so let me draw it a little bit bigger,
so this right over here is a concave quadrilateral,
is that it has an interior angle, it has an interior angle that is larger than 180 degrees.
So, for example, this interior angle right over here is larger, is larger than 180 degrees.
It's an interesting proof, maybe I'll do a video, it's actually a pretty simple proof,
to show that if you have a concave quadrilateral
if at least one of the interior angles has a measure larger than 180 degrees
that none of the sides can be parallel to each other.
The other type of quadrilateral, you can imagine,
is when all of the interior angles are less than 180 degrees.
And you might say, "Well, what happens at 180 degrees?"
Well, if this angle was 180 degrees then these wouldn't be two different sides
it would just be one side and that would look like a triangle.
But if all of the interior angles are less than 180 degrees,
then you are dealing with a convex quadrilateral.
So this convex quadrilateral would involve that one and that one over there.
So this right over here is what a convex quadrilateral,
this is what a convex quadrilateral could look like.
Four points. Four sides. Four angles.
Now within convex quadrilaterals there are some other interesting categorizations.
So now we're just gonna focus on convex quadrilaterals
so that's gonna be all of this space over here.
So one type of convex quadrilateral is a trapezoid.
A trapezoid. And a trapezoid is a convex quadrilateral
and sometimes the definition here is a little bit,
different people will use different definitions,
so some people will say a trapezoid is a quadrilateral that has exactly two sides that are parallel to each other
So, for example, they would say that this right over here
this right over here is a trapezoid, where this side is parallel to that side.
If I give it some letters here, if I call this trapezoid A, B, C, D,
we could say that segment AB is parallel to segment DC
and because of that we know that this is, that this is a trapezoid
Now I said that the definition is a little fuzzy because some people say
you can have exactly one pair of parallel sides
but some people say at least one pair of parallel sides.
So if you say, if you use the original definition,
and that's the kind of thing that most people are referring to when they say a trapezoid,
exactly one pair of parallel sides, it might be something like this,
but if you use a broader definition of at least one pair of parallel sides,
then maybe this could also be considered a trapezoid.
So you have one pair of parallel sides. Like that.
And then you have another pair of parallel sides. Like that.
So this is a question mark where it comes to a trapezoid.
A trapezoid is definitely this thing here, where you have one pair of parallel sides.
Depending on people's definition, this may or may not be a trapezoid.
If you say it's exactly one pair of parallel sides, this is not a trapezoid because it has two pairs.
If you say at least one pair of parallel sides, then this is a trapezoid.
So I'll put that as a little question mark there.
But there is a name for this regardless of your definition of what a trapezoid is.
If you have a quadrilateral with two pairs of parallel sides,
you are then dealing with a parallelogram.
So the one thing that you definitely can call this is a parallelogram.
Parallelo,
parallelo
parallelogram
Parallelogram.
And I'll just draw it a little bit bigger.
So it's a quadrilateral. If I have a quadrilateral, and if I have two pairs of parallel sides
So two of the opposite sides are parallel.
So that side is parallel to that side and then this side is parallel to that side there
You're dealing with a parallelogram.
And then parallelograms can be subdivided even further.
They can be subdivided even further if the four angles in a parallelogram are all right angles,
you're dealing with a rectangle. So let me draw one like that.
So if the four sides, so from parallelograms, these are, this is all in the parallelogram universe.
What I'm drawing right over here, that is all the parallelogram universe.
This parallelogram tells me that opposite sides are parallel.
And if we know that all four angles are 90 degrees
and we've proven in previous videos how to figure out the sum of the interior angles of any polygon
and using that same method, you could say that the sum of the interior angles of a rectangle,
or of any, of any quadril, of any quadrilateral, is actually a hund- is actually 360 degrees,
and you see that in this special case as well, but maybe we'll prove it in a separate video.
But this right over here we would call a rectangle
a parallelogram, opposite sides parallel,
and we have four right angles.
Now if we have a parallelogram, where we don't necessarily have four right angles,
but we do have, where we do have the length of all the sides be equal,
then we're dealing with a rhombus. So let me draw it like that.
So it's a parallelogram. This is a parallelogram.
So that side is parallel to that side. This side is parallel to that side.
And we also know that all four sides have equal lengths.
So this side's length is equal to that side's length.
Which is equal to that side's length, which is equal to that side's length.
Then we are dealing with a rhombus.
So one way to view it, all rhombi are parallelograms
All rectangles are parallelograms
All parallelograms you cannot assume to be rectangles.
All parallelograms you cannot assume to be rhombi.
Now, something can be both a rectangle and a rhombus.
So let's say this is the universe of rectangles
So the universe of rectangles. Drawing a little of a venn diagram here.
Is that set of shapes, and the universe of rhombi is this set of shapes right over here.
So what would it look like?
Well, you would have four right angles, and they would all have the same length.
So, it would look like this.
So it would definitely be a parallelogram.
It would be a parallelogram. Four right angles.
Four right angles, and all the sides would have the same length.
And you probably. This is probably the first of the shapes that you learned, or one of the first shapes.
This is clearly a square.
So all squares are both rhombi, are are members of the, they can also be considered a rhombus
and they can also be considered a rectangle,
and they could also be considered a parallelogram.
But clearly, not all rectangles are squares
and not all rhombi are squares
and definitely not all parallelograms are squares.
This one, clearly, right over here is neither a rectangle, nor a rhombi
nor a square.
So that's an overview, just gives you a little bit of taxonomy of quadrilaterals.
And then in the next few videos, we can start to explore them and find their interesting properties
Or just do interesting problems involving them.