[MUSIC PLAYING]
What I want to do in this video
is to give a not too
mathy explanation of why bond
prices move in the opposite
direction as interest rates.
So bond prices verses
interest rates.
So to start off, I'll just start
with a fairly simple
bond, one that does
pay a coupon.
And we'll just talk a little
bit about what you'd be
willing to pay for that
bond if interest
rates moved up or down.
So let's start with a bond
from some company.
So let me just write
this down.
This could be company A.
It doesn't just have to be from
a company, it could be
from a municipality or it
could be from the U.S.
government.
And let's say it's a bond for
$1,000, let's say it has a
two-year maturity, and let's say
that it has a 10% coupon
paid semi-annually.
So, if we just draw the diagram
for this-- obviously I
ran out of space on the actual
bond certificate-- let's draw
a diagram of the payments
for this bond.
So this is today-- let me do it
in a different color-- let
me draw a little timeline
right here.
This is two years in the future
when the bond matures,
so that is 24 months in the
future, halfway is 12 months,
then this is 18 months, and this
right here is 6 months.
And we went over a little bit of
this in the introduction to
bond video, but it's a 10%
coupon paid semi-annually, so
it'll pay us 10% of the par
value per year, but it's going
to break it up into two
six-month payments.
So 10% of $1,000 is $100, so
they're going to give us $50
every six months.
So they're going to give us of
half of our 10% coupon every
six months.
So we're going to get $50 here,
$50 here, these are
going to be are coupon payments,
$50 there, and then
finally at two years
will get $50.
And we'll also get the par
value of our bond.
We'll also got $1,000 plus
$50 24 months from today.
Now, let's say this is today
that we're talking about, the
bond is issued.
And you look at that and
you say, you know what?
For a company like Company A,
for this risk profile, given
where interest rates are right
now, I think a 10% coupon is
just about perfect.
So you say you know what,
I think I will
pay $1,000 for it.
So the price of the bond right
when it gets issued, or on day
0 if you will, you'd be willing
to pay $1,000 for it,
because you say, look you know
I'm getting roughly 10% a year
and then I get my money back.
10% is a good interest rate
for that level of risk.
Now, let's say that the moment
after you buy that bond-- just
to make things a little bit--
obviously interest rates don't
move this quickly-- but let's
say the moment after you buy
that bond, or maybe to be a
little bit more realistic,
let's say the very next day,
interest rates go up.
If interest rates go up-- let
me do this in a new color.
And let's say they go up in
such a way that now that
they've moved up for this type
of a company, for this type of
risk, you could go out in the
market and get 15% coupons.
So let's say for this type of
risk you would now expect a
15% interest rate.
Obviously for something less
risky, you'd expect less
interest. In fact, for a company
just like Company A,
you would now expect a 15%
interest rate, so interest
rates have gone up.
Now let's say you need cash.
And you come to me and you say,
hey Sal, are you willing
to buy this certificate
off of me?
I need some cash, I need
some liquidity.
I can't wait for the two years
for me to get my money back.
How much are you willing
to pay for this bond?
Well I'll say, you know what I'm
going to pay you less than
$1,000 because this bond
is only giving me 10%.
I'm expecting 15%, so I want
to pay something less than
$1,000 that after I do all
of the fancy math in my
spreadsheet, it'll come
out to be 15%.
So in this situation, the
price will go down.
And I'll actually do the math
with a simpler bond than one
that pays coupons right after
this, but I just want to give
you the intuitive sense.
If interest rates go up, someone
willing to buy that
bond, they'll say, gee this
only gives a 10% coupon,
that's not the 15% coupon I can
get on the open market.
I'm going to pay less than
$1,000 for this bond.
So the price will go down.
Or, you could essentially say
that the bond would be trading
at a discount to par.
Now let's say the opposite
happens, let's say that
interest rates go down.
Let's say that we're in
a situation where
interest rates go down.
So now, for this type of
risk like Company A,
people expect 5% rate.
So how much could you
sell this bond for?
Well, if you weren't there and
if I had to just to go to
companies issuing their bonds,
I would have to pay $1,000--
or roughly $1,000-- for a bond
that only gives me a 5%
coupon, roughly give or take,
I'm not being precise with the
math, I really just want to
give you the gist of it.
So I would pay $1,000 for
something giving a 5% coupon
now, this thing's giving
me a 10% coupon.
So it's clearly better, so now
the price would go up.
So now, I would pay
more than par.
Or you would say that this
bond is trading at
a premium to par.
So at least in the gut sense,
when interest rates went up,
people expect more
from the bond.
This bond isn't giving more,
so the price will go down.
Likewise, if interest rates go
down, this bond is giving more
than what people's expectations
are, so people
are willing to pay more
for that bond.
Now let's actually do the math
to figure out the actual price
that someone, a rational person,
would be willing to
pay for a bond, given what
happens to interest rates.
And to do this, I'm going
to do what's called
a zero-coupon bond.
And actually the math is much
simpler on this, because you
don't have to do it for all of
the different coupons, you
just have to look at
the final payment.
So a zero-coupon bond is
literally a bond that just
agrees to pay the holder of
the bond the face value.
So let's say the face value, the
par value, is $1,000 two
years from today.
There's no coupon.
So if I were to draw a payout
diagram, it would
just look like this.
This Is today, this is one year,
this is two years, you
just get $1,000.
Now let's say on day one, for
interest rates for a company
like Company A-- this is Company
A's bonds-- let's say
people's expectations for this
type of bond is they want 10%
per year interest. So given
that, how much would they be
willing to pay for something
that's going to pay them back
$1,000 in two years?
So the way to think about it
is, and I'm going to do a
little bit of math now but
hopefully it won't be too bad.
So let's say P is the price that
someone is willing to pay
for a bond.
So whatever price that is, if
you compound it by 10% for two
years, so I do 1.10,
that's 1 plus 10%.
So after one year, if I compound
it by 10% it'll be p
times this.
And then after another
year, I'll
multiply it by 1.10 again.
This essentially is how much I
should get after two years if
I'm getting 10% on my initial
payment, or the initial amount
that I'm paying for my bond.
So this should be equal
to the $1,000.
So let me just be
very clear here.
P is what someone who expects
10% per year for this type of
risk would be willing to
pay for this bond.
So when you compound their
payment by 10% for two years,
that should be equal
to $1,000.
So if you do the math here,
when you get P times 1.1
squared is equal to 1,000.
Or P is equal to 1,000 divided
by at 1.1 squared.
Another way to think about it
is the price that someone
would be willing to pay if they
expect a 10% return is
the present value of $1,000 in
two years discounted by 10%,
this is 1.10 or 1 plus 10%.
So what is this number
right here?
Let's get a calculator out.
And so if we have 1,000 divided
by 1.1 squared, that's
equal to $826 and well I'll
just round down, $826.
So if you were to pay $826 today
for this bond, and in
two years that company would
give you back $1,000, you will
have essentially have gotten a
10% annual compounded interest
rate on your money.
Now, what happens if the
interest rate goes up, let's
say the very next day?
And I'm not going to be very
specific, I'm going to assume
it's always two years out, you
know it's one day less, but
that's not going to change
the math dramatically.
Let's say the very next
second that interest
rates were to go up.
So second one.
So it doesn't affect our math
in any dramatic way.
So let's say interest
rates go up.
So now all of a sudden
people expect more.
The new expectation is to have
a 15% return on a loan to a
company like Company A, so now
what's the price we are
willing to pay?
We use the same formula.
The price is going to be equal
to $1,000 divided by-- instead
of discounting it by 10% we're
going to discount it by 15%
over two years.
So 1 plus 15% compounded
Bring out the calculator.
And I think you have a sense, we
have a larger number now in
the denominator, so the price
is going to go down.
So let's actually calculate the
math. $1,000 divided by
1.15 squared is equal to $756,
give or take a little bit.
So now the price
has gone down.
The price is now $756.
This is how much someone is
willing to pay in order for
them to get a 15% return and
get $1,000 in two years.
Or get $1,000 thousand dollars
in two years and essentially
for it to be a 15% return.
Now, just to finish up the
argument, what happens if
interest rates go down?
So if let's say the expected
interest rate on this type of
risk goes down.
Let's say it's now 5%.
What is someone willing to pay
for this zero-coupon bond?
Well the price, if you compound
it two years by 1.05,
that should be equal to 1,000.
Or the price is equal to 1,000
divided by two years of
compounding at 5%.
Get the calculator out again.
We get $1,000 divided by 1.05
squared is equal to $907.
So all of a sudden we're
willing to pay,
price is now $907.
So you see mathematically, when
interest rates went up,
the price of the bond went
from $826 to $756,
the price went down.
When interest rates went down,
the price went up.
And I think it makes sense.
The more you expect, the higher
return you expect, the
less you're willing to
pay for that bond.
Anyway, hopefully you
found that helpful.
[MUSIC PLAYING]