We were able to already answer some interesting questions
about the different plans at super yoga studio, using the equations we set up.
But I'm a very visual guy.
I wanna make sure I analyze the problem fully before I spend my hard earned dollars.
What I wanna do now,
is really see a visual representation for the relationsship between
how many session I attend and how much its gonna cost me.
I'm gonna do it for the trial plan and the basic plan.
And to do that down here on the horizontal axis, I'm going to plot the number of sessions I attend.
So S is equal to the number of session I attend.
And here on the vertical axis,
I'm gonna plot how much its gonna cost me depending on how how many session I attend.
So C is equal is equal to my monthly cost.
So let's think about these points right over here,
and how these equations relates to what we might end up drawing.
So the first point here, is that if I spend, if I go to no sessions,
it's gonna cost me zero dollars.
Where would I plot that?
Right over here.
If I attend no session, and I should have marked off zero here, its gonna cost me zero dollars.
That is this point. Just like that.
If I attend 1 session, it will be $12.
Where would I plot that?
Well, 1 session is gonna cost me $12.
This is $15 so $12 is right around there.
I'll put it there.
If I attend 2 sessions, where would I plot that?
Well, 2 session is going to cost me $24, so right about there.
What about 3 sessions?
I could keep going to 4, 5, 6 sessions,
but I'll try 3, and I think you get the general idea.
3 sessions cost $36.
You see that all of these points seem to sit on a line.
I will attempt my best to draw that line.
And this line, it essentially describes all the possible combination of cost for a given number of sessions.
So any point, specially if we allow fractional sessions.
That is not conventional practice for most yoga studios but this one is a Super Yoga studio.
and it allows you to attend 4 1/2 session or 1 1/2 sessions or exactly half a session.
So if you attend half a session, its going to cost you $6.
Another way to think about it is,
if you attend zero session it'll be zero dollars.
But then as you add a session, so you go one step right, it's going to cost you $12 more.
so then you are gonna go up $12,
so we went to right one, we went up $12. If we go to the right one more we go $12 up again.
Because every session we add is gonna cost us $12 extra $12.
We go from $0 to $12 to $24 to $36, if you add another session you add another $12.
If you take away a session you will go $12 down.
It is a kind of way of thinking about how steep this line is.
Every time you go one to the right you go $12 up.
Now, let's think about the same thing for the basic plan.
How we might plot that.
We will start with this point right over here.
And basic plan, when I go to zero session it costs me $20.
Where would I plot that on my graph?
So zero session is going to cost me $20. That is that point over there.
What about one session?
Well one session is going to cost me $28.
Another way of thinking about it: you pay $20 no matter what
and as you add one session your total cost went up $8.
This scale and this scale is not the same.
If I did it to scale you would see these lines would look a lot steeper,
and I would have to let this axis go a lot taller.
But hopefully you get the idea, you add one session, we went up by $8.
You add another session,
so that was 1 and $28. That is that point over there.
If you have 2 sessions, its gonna cost us $36.
Where would we plot that?
2 sessions are gonna cost $36 so, that is over there.
Or another way to think of it.
We were at $28 and we added a session, so we add another $8 to our cost.
So $28 plus $8 gets us to $36.
Now let's do this other point. And once again, we can keep going.
Where would we plot the 3 sessions?
So, if we attend 3 sessions, its gonna cost us $44.
That's right about there.
Once again we added a sessions and we added $8 to our cost.
And you see these two seem to..., although I did not draw it as well as I can, these two seem to sit on a line.
This by itself is interesting,
but what might be even more interesting, is where these two lines intersect.
We see that they have different steepnesses so at some point they should intersect
And what's exciting about...
Well, actually, I will let you think about it.
What is exciting about where these two lines intersect?
What does it tell us about the sessions and the cost at those points?
I'll leave you there, and we will explore this more in the next video.