In this video we will look at the classification
and nomenclature of alcohols.
So here we have generic alcohol up the top and have an alcule group on the left.
and have an OH on the right which is called a hydroxyl group.
Lets look at the classification of our alcohol so
If I have a carbon bonded to an OH and that carbon
is bonded to one other carbon in this alcule group here
that said to be primary alcohol.
This carbon over here is bonded to two carbons in those two alcule groups so
it is therefore secondary alcohol.and
then this carbon over here on the right is bonded to three other carbons
so it is said to be tertiary alcohol.
Lets take a look at the nomenclature of alcohols.lets start with a simple molecules here.
So if i had a molecule look like that i wanted to name it using iupac nomenclature
I want to number my carbon chain to give that a away a lowest number possible
so therefore this carbon we get number 1
this carbon we get number 2 and for this carbon number 3.
now that weren't there we would have 3 carbon alkane which we call propane.
but since we have our OH there this is actually an alcohol
and alcohol is gonna have the OL endin so this is called propanol.
so go ahead and write propanol here.
so OH group is coming off of carbon 1 so we are gonna say this is 1 propanol like that .
how we classify this alcohol.
well the carbon right here is bonded to the OH that carbon is bonded to one other carbon
so this would be a primary alcohol.
so one propanol is a primary alcohol in terms of its classification.
lets look at similar looking molecule
still 3 carbon but this time we put the OH on the carbon in the middle there.
so once again we are going to number it this is
carbon 1,this carbon 2,and this is carbon 3
3 carbon alcohol those also called propanol.
The difference is the hydroxy group is on different carbon.
right its now on carbon 2.so we are gonna go and write 2 propanol here .which is the iupack name
which is also called isopropanol,rubbing alcohol all the same stuff.
but 2 propanol would be iupack nomenclature.
how would you classify 2 propanol
so once again we find the carbon attached to OH this one how many carbons
attached to .attached to 1 and 2 other carbon.so therefore this is a secondary
alcohol.so we have an example of primary alcohol and secondary alcohol here.
lets do a little more complicated nomenclature question.
so lets go ahead and draw out larger molecule with more substituents.so
lets put an OH here and lets do something like that and lets go ahead and do that as well.
so give the full iupack name for this molecule.
so you want to find the largest carbon chain that includes the OH.
and you want to give the OH the lowest number possible.so that gonna mean you are gonna start here
and make this carbon number 1 .so thats carbon number 1
this must be carbon number 2,3,4.5,6 and 7.
So we have a 7 carbon alcohol so 7 carbon alcohol be heptanol so we can start naming this make sure to give us plenty of space here so heptanol
and we know that the OH is coming off of carbon 2 so we can go ahead and write 2-heptanol
like that.lets look at the other substituentes that we have.
well what do we have right here coming off of our ring thats a 3 carbon alcule group
so that would be propyl so we have 3 propyl.so go ahead and write 3-propyl here.
like that and what else do we have carbon 5
we have 2 substituents alright so we have chloro group right here
ans we have methalic group right here.
remember our alphabet so c comes before m
so we can go ahead and put our methyl right here coming off of carbon 5
so we write 5methyl like that and also coming of 5-chloro that should do it
everything follows to alphabet rules.
so we have 5-chloro 5 methyl 3 propyl 2 heptanol for this molecule.
what about a problem that includes stereochemistery.
so lets say they give us one where we have to worry about stereochemistery.
so we go ahead and draw another chain out here.
so lets make an OH group going away from us.
and then lets go ahead and make this one coming out at us like that.
so giving iupack name for this molecule we have to include stereochemistery.
once again find longer carbon chain that includes OH group.and we want to give
OH lowest number possible .so it takes precedence over things like alcule groups and
halogens and double bonds. so we are gonna start from left
so 1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9 like that so we have a 9 carbon
alcohol so that will be nonanol and the alcohol is coming off of carbon 3
and OH is coming off of carbon 3 so we have 3 nonanol .
and lets see other substituents at carbon 6 so at carbon 6 we have a 2
carbon substituent so that would be an ethylic group so lets go ahead and put in our 6
ethyl .so for we have 6-ethyl-3 nonanol and we have to worry about stereochemistery.
put in wedges and dashes on the problem you need to think about
stereochemistery.and you put those absolute configurations at the beginning
of the iupack name.so lets figure out the stereochemistery of carbon 3
so this is our chirality center right here
this carbon and again you go to the atoms that are directly connected to chirality center
so thats carbon carbon oxygen and then we also have right coming off our chirality center
we have hydrogen which is coming out at us like that so that would be the lowest priority
we get number 4 over here.so oxygen has the highest atomic number
so thats gonna get number 1 so we have longer chain over here for this carbon
thats gonna get number 2 then number 3 then the hydrogen will be number 4
there is little trick that I covered in eariler videos.
right so it looks if you ignore the hydrogen it looks like you are going around
counter clock wise so it looks like its s but you have this lowest priority group is coming out
at you so remember the trick was it would look like its s with those 3.just reverse it
so it must be R .and must have an absolute configuration of R at carbon 3.so
go ahead and put in here a 3R.then we will have to worry about absolute configuration at carbon 6
so carbon 6 here so this is another chirality center.right 4 different substituents attached to it
there is also a hydrogen attached to this carbon going away from us like that
and lets think about a highest priority while this chain over here in the left
this chain is gonna get highest priority
thats most carbon is definitely gonna get highest prority
there is more carbon over here in right so again you assign priority its gonna get highest 1
and then this is gonna get 3rd.
so this time we have going around 1,2,3.going around counter clock wise
lowest priority group which is this hydrogen back here is going away from you
so this actually is going to be S.its counter clock wise so its S.
so 3R,6S and i want you kind of fast so go back and watch eariler videos
on absolute configuration if that was little fast for you.
so lets look at cyclic alcohol so ring systems.
so lets take a look at alcohol with 6 carbons in a ring and
OH coming off like that.so 6 carbons without the OH we call that cyclohexane.
and since this is an alcohol we would just change that to cyclohexanol
so thats very simple nomenclature cyclohexanol.you dont really need a number
but if you could right one there its implied if we dont put it in.so thats cyclohexanol.
what about something that has ring system with 2 hydroxyl groups.
so lets go ahead and put in some stereochemistery 2.lets say we have an OH coming out at us
and lets say we have OH going away from us like that alright so when you have a situation
like this when you have 2 alcohols in the same molecule prefix would be diol.
and the nomenclature is based off the cyclohexane molecule so you will write
cyclohexane and then write off cyclohexane where you put the diol .diol meaning two alcohols.
we have to specify where these two alcohols are on the ring.
so we need to go ahead and number our ring lets say this is carbon 1 carbon 2 carbon 3 and then carbon 4
so we have alcohols at the 1 and 4position so go ahead and write 1 and 4 here
and those 2 alcohols are trans to each other.alright one is coming out at you and one is
going away from you so you could go ahead and write trans-1,4-cyclohexanediol
and thats a good iupack name.so there are other types of alcohol.
we could have instead of cyclohexane ring we can have alcohol based on benzene ring.
so put in our pi bonds and OH here this is special type of alcohol called phenol
molecule called phenol and also you will see this hydroxybenzene portion of the molecule
and lots of natural products.
this is actually very imporant molecule to recognize the phenols.
alright so lets go ahead and put something on that ring and we have our phenol is base here
so lets go ahead and put a bromene (Br) right here so how would we name that molecule.
the base part of the molecule is phenol molecule so go ahead put phenol like that
go ahead and number it alright so OH this must be carbon 1
and want to give substituents lowest number possible so we are gonna give this
carbon number 2 bromene(Br) coming out from carbon number 2 so its very simple
we have to write 2-bromophenol like that.
so thats nomenclature for alcohol and special type of alcohol called phenol