I want to do one more video on total revenue and price elasticity of demand,
Just to make sure that you-- the relationship between the two is an intuitive one.
So let's draw an arbitrary demand curve:
this is my price axis,
that is my quantity demanded axis,
and let me just draw an arbitrary demand curve right over here,
so let's say that is my demand curve,
and let's pick some price and quantity that is on this demand curve.
So let's say that the price is up here - let's call that P1,
and then the quantity demanded - let's call that Q1.
We already know that the total revenue is the area of this rectangle right over here -
this is the total revenue, it's just the price times the quantity.
If I'm selling two burgers an hour for nine dollars a burger,
I'm going to make $18 per hour - that's going to be this area right over here.
Now let's assume in this part of the curve,
that the price elasticity of demand is greater than one (&gt;1), so we are elastic.
So absolute value of the elasticity of demand is greater than one,
which means for a 1% drop in price,
you have greater than 1% increase in quantity.
And that comes straight out of the expression or formula for what elasticity is
Remember, elasticity is our % change in quantity over % change in price
So if the absolute value of this is greater than 1
that means this quantity is going to be larger than this quantity
So if we have a 1% drop in price, the change in our quantity is going to be greater than 1%
And so for this point right over here, if we lower this by 1%
we're going to increase this by more than 1%
So any reduction in our height will be more than made up for --
this is generally the case -- will be more than made up for by increase in our width
So total revenue will increase
So when price drops -- so 1% drop in price and a larger than 1% increase in quantity
means that total revenue will go up
Now if we go down to this part of the curve
Let's call this P2, and let's call that quantity 2
And this area here will be total revenue 2
Let's call that total revenue 1 here
Price times the quantity
We're going to assume that
the absolute value of our price elasticity of demand is less than 1 at this point in the curve
And all that is a fancy way of saying that for a 1% drop in price
we get a less than 1% increase in quantity
So if we have a 1% drop, we're lowering the height by 1%
but we're not getting a 1% increase in our width
So the width isn't going to be increasing that much
So in general this is going to result in a lowering of this area
The area will get smaller. We're reducing our height more than we're expanding our width
So in this situation, the total revenue will go down
Remember this is a elastic situation
So when it is elastic, a drop in price tends to make total revenue go up
And when it is inelastic, a drop in price tends to make total revenue go down
And then you could imagine, right when you're at unit elasticity, someplace around there
A 1% drop in price will result in exactly a 1% increase in quantity demanded
And so they'll kind of trade off; you won't get a noticeable change in revenue
The reason why I say that is that many econ textbooks will tell you that
you don't get a change in revenue, but if you look at the detailed math --
let me write it over here. So the
absolute value of the price elasticity of demand at that point is 1
which tells us that a 1% drop in price
goes along with a 1% increase in quantity
but if you look at the math, -- let's call this price 3, and call this quantity 3
right over here, so total revenue 3, which is this area right over there
is going to be equal to price 3 times quantity 3
Now if we decrease price by 1%
then this will become 0.99 times our price
And if we increase our quantity by 1%, this'll become 1.01 times our quantity
Now, let's think about what this number here is. This is what I'm saying
The total revenue isn't exactly unchanged
If you multiply 0.99 times 1.01, you don't get exactly 1
Another way to think about it, .99 times 1.01 is going to be 1% less than 1.01
and 1% of 1.01 is slightly larger than 1
Or another way to think about it, this value is going to be 1% larger than .99
and 1% of .99 is less than 1
So it's not gonna get you to 1. You can calculate it
.99 times 1.01 is very close to 1. This is going to be equal to 0.9999
times P3 Q3, which is 0.9999 times total revenue 3
But it is roughly unchanged. That's the general rule of thumb
So when you're at unit elasticity
then a decrease in price roughly says no change in total revenue
So I just want to make sure that this makes sense. It really just comes from these areas
If you're reducing the height less than you're increasing the width
obviously the area is going to increase
or most of the case, I should actually say. That depends on where you are
If you're compensating whatever you reduce the height perfectly with the width
then you're not going to have a change in revenue
And if you decrease the height by more
if you're taking more area from the top than you're adding on the width
then you're going to have a total decrease in total revenue