Sometimes in medicine, you'll see that words get used a lot
and sometimes the meaning is pretty simple or straightforward and you know can be understood,
but the words themselves can be kinda tricky and confusion. I think some of that has to do with the fact
that these words in medicine often come from latin and so we haven't really changed the word and so,
because latin is not a language that any of us are really familiar with and it ends up being that the term has become confusing.
So what I'm going to do is, I'm actually gonna lay out four words for you. Starting with Chronotropy.
And we're going to go through them one by one, basically describing what they mean.
Chronotropy refers to the heart rate. Now as you see I've put in parentheses, a simpler way to think about these terms.
So chronotropy has to do with heart rate. A second term is Dromotropy. And Dromotropy has to do with conduction velocity.
How fast a signal is going from one cell to the next. And then we have Ionotropy - and Ionotropy has to do with contractility.
How hard the muscle is contracting. The force of contraction, you can think of it as the force of contraction.
And Lusitropy. Lusitropy has to do with the relaxation - how fast its relaxing. So, lets go through these one at a time and
talk about the effects of the sympathetics and the parasympathetics on this. So, actually - the other thing I'm
going to do maybe even write out where these things are primarily being effected. Where and then we'll talk about
sympathetics and parasympathetics. Ok so where is the first one happening? So we talked about chronotropy. Of course
its not just one cell that's going to be affected, but in general what cluster of cells are we thinking of? You're right if you're
thinking about the SA node. Right, the SA node and this is where the heart rate is usually set. And sympathetics are
usually going to make the SA node go and fire faster because they're going to want to allow more sodium into
those cells, so its going to get up to the threshold for an action potential more quickly. And parasympathetics
basically do the opposite right, they're going to let less sodium flow in, and its going to take longer to get to the
threshold potential. So what about Dromotropy? This is a word that's maybe less commonly used, and that's why I
want to throw it up so that you're at least familiar with at least the fact that it exists. But dromotropy has to do with
conduction velocity so how fast is the signal being conducted through the heart. And remember for this
the major delay ends up being in the AV node right. The huge delay sometimes, we say its a tenth of a second is in
the AV node. So what happens in the AV node with sympathetic stimulation, well you remember when you're
sympathetics are around they allow the calcium to come into the cell more quickly, so you actually have a faster