Let's draw ourselves a triangle.
Let's say this (blue) side has lenght 6, this (pink) side has lenght 10 and this (green) side has lenght x
And what I'm going to think about is how large or how small x can be
How large or how small can this (green) side be.
The first question is "How small can it get?"
Well, if we want to make this small we would just have to look at this (green) angle here and make it smaller
So let's try to make this angle as small as possible.
So we have our side of lenght 10, and I'm going to make this angle really really small, approaching 0
If that angle becomes 0 we end up with a degenerate triangle
Essentially it becomes one-dimensional, we lose our 2-dimensionality
But as we approach 0 this side starts to coincide or get closer and closer to the 10 side.
And you could imagine the case where it actually coincides with it and you actually get the degenerate
So if we want this point here (on the 10 side) to get as close as possible to that point over there (on the 6 side)
-essentially minimizing your distance x-
the closest way is that you make the angle all the way equal to 0
Let me draw a progression. Now the angle is getting smaller, this (blue) side is lenght 6
x is getting smaller
so we keep making that angle smaller and smaller all the way until we get a degenerage triangle
So you have the (pink) side of lenght 10. Now the angle that we care about is essentially 0
This (blue) side is lenght 6
And so what is the distance between this point and this point? That distance is lenght x
So in the degenerate case, this (green) length right over here is x
and we know that 6 + x is going to equal 10
So in this degenerate case x will equal 4
So if you want this to be a real triangle, at x = 4 you've gotten these points as close as possible
It's degenerated into a line segment.
If you want this to be a triangle x has to be greater than 4
Now let's think about it the other way.
How large can x be?
To think about larger and larger x's we need to make this (green) angle bigger
So let's try to do that.
Let's draw the 10 side again. This is my 10 side
and we make that angle bigger and bigger.
So now let me take the 6 side and put it like that.
So now our angle is getting bigger and bigger. It's approaching 180 degrees.
At 180 degrees our triangle once again will be turned into a line segment, becoming a degenerate triangle.
Let me draw the side of lenght x.
So we are trying to maximize the distance between that point (on the 10 side) and that point (on the 6 side).
This is the side of lenght x
Let's go all the way to the degenerate case.
At the degerate case, at 180 degrees,
the side of lenght 6 forms a straight line with the side of lenght 10.
And this is how you can get this point and that point as far appart as possible.
In this situation, what is the distance between that point (on the 6 side) and that point (on the 10 side)?
which is the distance that's going to be our x
In this situation x is going to be 6 + 10 = 16
If x is 16 we have a degenerate triangle.
If we don't want a degenerate triangle, then x is going to have to be less than 16
Now the whole principle that we are working on right over here is called the Triangle Inequality Theorem.
It's a pretty basic idea.
Any one side of a triangle has to be less than the sum of the other two sides.
So the lenght of a side has to be less than the sum of the lenghts of the other two sides.
If you're willing to deal with degenerate triangles,
where you essentially form a line segment, lose all your dimensionality and turn to a 1-dimesional figure,
then you could say "less than or equal"
but we're just going to stick with non-degerate triangles.
So the lenght of a side has to be less than the sum of the lenghts of the other two sides
And just using this principle we could have come up with the same exact conclusion
You could say "Well, look: x is one of the sides and it has to be less than 6 + 10 or x has to be less than 16"
The exact same result we got by visualizing it like this
If you want to say how "How small can x be?" you could say:
"Well, 10 has to be less than 6 + x, the sum of the lenghts of the other two sides"
If you subtract 6 from both sides right over here, you get 4  4.
So this is, in some level, kind of a basic idea.
But it's something that you'll see definitely in geometry
and then you'll go far into other types of mathematics and you'll see other versions
of what's essentially this Triangle Inequality Theorem