Your observable traits
also known as your phenotypes
result from the interaction between your
genes and the environment.
This interaction begins in the womb
and continues throughout your life.
Differences in some phenotypes, like height,
are determined mostly by genes.
If you had short parents and grandparents
you probably don't tower over your peers.
Though environmental factors, like nutrition,
can have some effect on your height.
Genes also play a role in whether you have a healthy body weight.
But diet and exercise can profoundly affect how much you weigh.
How genes influence your personality is less understood.
You can now learn about over a million SNPs
in your genome all at once.
And every day, scientists are learning more and more
about how some of these SNPs affect your phenotype.
Getting to know your genome can help you understand
a little better why you are the way you are
and in what ways you are similar to, or different from, your family, friends, and neighbors.