After World War II with most of Europe in ruins,
tension grew between the Soviet Union and the United States.
It was clear that the next global superpower
required the ability to both launch and
successfully defend nuclear attacks
from intercontinental ballistic missiles.
In North America the most vulnerable point of attack
was over the north pole.
So in 1958, a joint effort between
United States and Canada was established,
known as NORAD, or
North American Aerospace Defense Command.
An important line of defense with
the semi-automatic ground environment.
It was an automated system of over
100 long-distance radars
scattered across North America.
They were connected to computerized radar stations
that transmitted tracking data
using telephone lines or radio waves.
All of this radar information was fed
into a primary warning center
buried a mile deep
inside Cheyenne Mountain in Colorado.
This application of machine-to-machine communication
allowed operators to make
split-second decisions using information
transmitted and processed automatically by computers.
This idea of being on-line was quickly adapted
and advanced by universities in the following
years as they understood
the potential of computer networking.
The thing that makes the computer
communication network special
is that it puts the workers that's
the key members that are geographically distributed
in touch not only with one another
but with the information base
with which they work all the time.
And this is obviously going to make
a tremendous difference in how we
plan, organize, and execute
almost everything of any intellectual consequence.
If we get into a mode in which
everything is handled electronically,
and your only identification
is some little plastic thing you stick into
the machinery, then I can image that
they want to get that settled up with
your bank account, just right now,
and put it through all the checks
and that would require a network.
Money transfers were just one of a growing number
of applications which required encryption
to remain secure, and as the Internet grew
to encompass millions around the world,
a new problem emerged.
At the time, encryption required
two parties to first share
a secret random number,
known as a key.
So how could two people
who have never met agree
on a secret shared key,
without letting Eve who was always listening
also obtain a copy?
In 1976 Whitfield Diffie and Martin Hellman
devised an amazing trick to do this.
First, let's explore how this trick
is done using colors.
How could Alice and Bob agree on a
secret color without Eve
finding it out?
The trick is based on two facts.
One, it's easy to mix two colors
together to make a third color.
And, two, given a mixed color,
it's hard to reverse it in order to find
the exact original color.
This is the basis for a lock:
easy in one direction, hard in the reverse direction.
This is known as a one-way function.
Now, the solution works as follows:
first, they agree publicly
on a starting color, say yellow.
Next, Alice and Bob both randomly select
private colors and mix them into
the public yellow in order to
disguise their private colors.
Now, Alice keeps her private color,
and sends her mixture to Bob.
And Bob keeps his private color
and sends his mixture to Alice.
Now the heart of the trick.
Alice and Bob add their
private colors to the other person's
mixture, and arrive at a
shared secret color.
Notice how Eve is
unable to determine this exact color
since she needs one of their
private colors to do so.
And that is the trick.
Now, to do this with numbers,
we need a numerical procedure,
which is easy in one direction,
and hard in the other.