As you might imagine
World war I was one of the bloodiest events
in frankly all of human history. I was thinking about putting pictures in here and I encourage you
to do a picture search of WWI, of mass graves
and people starving, soldiers dead,...
trenches. I will make you feel ill and..
it's probably a good thing to look for these images. Because it will remind you
how disgusting, gross and crazy wars can be.
Sometimes we abstract it. When we look at it in hindsight and we
just talk about the numbers. WWI was gruesome
especially because this was the first time industrialized weapons
were put to use in a war context. There was far more bloodshed than any
of the fighting powers actually believed there would be.
But, just to put things in numbers, and these are huge numbers,
numbers that are hard for us to comprehend.
And, we don't know the exact numbers.
As you can imagine, it is not easy to take a census
the militaries have a better count of who might have been kille
or who might be missing. Civilian casualties are almost impossible
to count. You have people who are invertantly killed by a bomb, or dying
of starvation or a famine. So, these are very hard numbers to count.
But there is some concensus on the rough estimates, on the total casualties in WWI.
In particular I want to focus on the deaths.
When people talk about casualties, then we often also talk about injured.
But just the deads alone, the estimates I see and I encourages you to look it
your own and trying to figure out what concensus you can get to.
But the estimates that I see
have on the order of 16 millions deaths
during or due to WWI
and if were to break down these deads we have 8 to 10 million
in the military. So directly, in the military, this is the death of soldiers
So this is the military. It is roughly based on the accounts of
On the accounts that I've seen, about 16 percent of these deaths
were amongst the Entente. And about 40 percent were amongst the central powers.
But in either case, we're talking about millions
on either side of WWI.
and the rest, if we are talking in the order of 6-7 million, were civilian
The estimates that I've seen were directly
due to military action. So this is military action
civilians. This was disproportionately felt on the side of the Entente, on the side of the allies
That's if you look at, especially, I suppose,
where the western front was fought, it becomes clear, also where the eastern front was fought
it was thought, the war was fought on Russian land,
or was controlled by the Russian Empire at the time
The western front much of the, or most of the battle was in France
and in Belgium. And also in Italy. That was also
where you have a significant amount of the battle actually going on. This is were the
allies, the Entente, felt a disproportionate number of the civilian deaths,
directly to due military casualties.
To put on top of that: the rest of the civilian casualties. This is what, frankly,
very hard to get an exact number on.
This could be due to famine,
starvation, disease,
we've talk before about the blockades,
the central powers and you have definitely
people not being able to eat properly
you had the Spanish Flu.
You had this all around ugly situations. To make matter worse, and this is
is what the history books often forget:
You often had an explicit extermination of people,
during WWI the most notable, but often forgotten was the Armenian genocide
There was this campaign on the part of the Ottomans. This started before
WWI, but it kind of hit full page during WWI
where, I have seen estimates, 1 million into 1,5 millions Armenians were systematically
I mean, I am talking about men, women,
children, systematically killed by the Ottoman
government. So, war is ugly and brings out the worst in people
and you see it just from these numbers.
Just to give you a context on all of this
it's very easy for us to abstract these things.
I just wanted to say how horrible
this was. Just to bring it all into focus
this right here is a
passage from the Atlantic Monthly, volume 129, published in
1922. It is a passage on Joseph Tumulty's book.
Joseph Tumulty was the private secretary of staff, of Woodrow Wilson.
This is about his account
of being with Woodrow Wilson, after the war
was declared in WWI
It is fascinating, it applies to frankly all wars
The war president in the war.
At the time of delivering his far echoed
war message in April, 1917, the president was cheered by dense multitudes
phronging (?) the streets
past from the White House, to the Capitol and back again.
This is from Tumulty own description of the return
own description of the return
for a while he, we're talking about Woodrow Wilson, he
sat silent and pale in the cabinet room.
At at last, he said,
think what it was they were applauding
my message today was a message of death for our young men.
How strange it seems to applaud that.