Before we get into the meat of algebra,
I want to give you a quote
from one of the greatest minds in human history,
Galileo Galilei, because I think this quote encapsulates
the true point of algebra and really mathematics in general.
He said : Philosophy is written in that great book
which ever lies before our eyes
-- I mean the universe --
but we cannot understand it
if we do not first learn the language
and grasp the symbols in which it is written.
This book is written in the mathematical language...
without which one wanders in vain through a dark labyrinth.
So very dramatic but very deep
and this really is the point of mathematics
and what we'll see as we start
getting deeper and deeper into algebra
is that we're gonna start abstracting things
and we're going to start getting to core ideas
that start explaining really how the universe is structured.
Sure these ideas can be applied to things
like economics and finance and physics and chemistry
but at their core they're the same idea.
And so they're more fundamental, more pure,
than any one of those applications.
And to see what I mean by getting down to the root idea.
Let's go with a...I guess we could,
we started with the very grand philosophy of the universe
as written in mathematics.
but let's start with a very concrete simple idea.
but we'll keep abstracting and see how the same idea connects
across many domains in our universe.
So lets just say we're at the store
and we're going to buy something and there is a sale.
The sale says that it is 30% off and I'm interested --
and I don't shop at too fancy stores --
so let's say I'm interested in a pair of pants
and the pair of pants before the sale event is about $20.
That is about how much I spend on my pants.
so I'm interested in a $20 pair of pants but it's even better.
there is a thirty percent off sale on these pants.
How would I think about how much I'm going to get off of that $20 ?
And this isn't algebra yet
this is something that you have probably had exposure to.
You would multiply thirty percent times the twenty dollars.
so you would say your discount --your discount-- is equal to,
you could write is as 30% times $20.
We'll write twenty dollars in purple.
Or you could write it --if you wanted to write-- this is a decimal
you could write it as 0.30*20 dollars
And if you were to do the maths
you would get 6 dollars.
So nothing, nothing new over there.
But what if I wanted to generalize a little bit ?
That's the discount on this particular pair of pants,
but what if I wanted to know the discount
on anything in the store ?
Well then I could say, let x be the price
-- let's do it in another color --
I'm just gonna make a symbol.
Let x be the price of the product I want to buy,
the nondiscount price of the product in the store.
So now all of a sudden, we can say our discount,
is equal to 30%, 30% times x,
or if we wanted to write it as a decimal,
we could write 30% as a decimal.
we could write 0.30 times x --times x--.
Now this is interesting.
Now you give me the price of any product in the store
and I can substitute it in for x,
and then I can essentially multiply it 0.3 times that
and I would get the discount.
Now we're starting to, very slowly,
starting to get into the abstraction of algebra.
We'll see that they would get much more nuanced and deep
and frankly more beautiful
as we start studying more and more algebraic ideas.
But we aren't done here.
We can abstract this even more.
Over here we've said
we've generalized this for any product,
we're not just saying for this 20 dollar product.
If there's a 10 dollar product,
we can put that 10 dollar product in here for x,
and then we would say 0.30 times 10.
The discount would be 3 dollars.
It might be a $100 product,
then the discount would be 30 dollars.
But let's generalize even more.
Let's say : "What is the discount for any given sale,
--when the sale has a certain percentage-- ?"
Now we can say that the discount
--let me define a variable--
Let's let m = ... I'll say p, just so it makes sense,
p is equal to the percentage off.
Now what can we do ?
Now we can say that the discount
is equal to the percentage off.
In these other examples we were picking 30 percent,
but now we can say it's p, it's the percentage off.
It's p.
That's the percentage off times the product in question,
times the price, the non discount price of the product in question.
Well, that was x.
The discount is equal to p times x.
Now this is really interesting,
now we have a general way of calculating a discount
for any given percentage off and any given product x.
And we didn't have to use these words and these letters.
We could have said "Let y equal the discount"
Let y is equal to the discount.
then we could have written the same underlying idea
instead of writing discount, we could have written
y is equal to the percentage off p
times the non discount price of the product
--times x.
And you could have defined these letters anyway you wanted.
Instead of writing y there,
you could have written a greek letter,
as long as you can keep track of the fact
that the symbol represents the actual dollar discount.
But now things get really interesting,
because we can use this type of a relationship...
which is an equation, you're equating
y to this thing right over here,
that's why we call it an equation.
This can be used for things
that are completely unrelated
to the discount price at the store over here.
You might have...
so in physics you will see
that force is equal to mass times acceleration.
The letters are different
but these are fundamentally the same idea.
We could have let y is equal to force
and m is equal to... or mass is equal to p.
So let me write p is equal to mass
-- and this wouldn't be an intuitive way to define it --
but I wanna show you that the same idea, the same relationship
that's being applied to 2 different things.
And we could say x is equal to acceleration.
We could say x is equal to acceleration.
Well then the famous "force is equal to mass times acceleration"
can be rewritten and it is really the same exact idea
as y -- which we've defined has force --
can be equal to mass
-- for which we are going to use the symbol p --
which is equal to p times acceleration.
We are just going to happen to use the letter x here
-- times x.
Well this is the exact same equation.
This is the exact same equation.
We can see that we can take this equation
and it can apply to things in economics,
or it can apply to things in finance
or it can apply to things in computer science
or logic or electrical engineering
or anything -- accounting --
There is an infinite number of applications
of this one equation.
And what's neat about mathematics,
and what's neat about algebra in particular is
we can focus on this abstraction.
we can focus on the abstract here,
we can manipulate the abstract here,
and what we discover from these ideas, from these manipulations
can then go and be reapplied
to all of these other applications, to all of them.
And even neater, it's kind of telling us
the true structure of the universe
if you were to strip away all of these human definitions
and all of those human applications.
So for example we can say :
"Look, if y is equal to p times x".
So litterally if someone said
"Hey, this is y."
and someone says on the other hand "I have p times x."
I can say "Well, you have the same thing in both of your hands."
And if your were to divide one of them by a number
and you wanted them to still be equal,
you'd divide the other one by that number.
So for example,
let's say -- we know that y is equal to p times x --
what if you want to have them both be equal.
What is y divided by x gonna be equal to ?
Well y was equal to p times x
so y divided by x
is gonna be the same as p times x divided by x
But now this is interesting,
because p times x divided by x
-- well if you multiply by something
and divide by that something
you're gonna get the original number.
If you multiply by 5 and divide by 5,
you're just gonna get p,
or whatever this number is.
So those would cancel out.
But we were able to manipulate the abstraction here,
and get y over x is equal to p
-- we make that x green --
y over x is equal to p
and now this has implications,
this has implications for every one of these ideas.
One is telling us a fundamental truth about the universe,
almost devoid of any of those applications,
but now we can go and take them back
to any place where we applied it.
The really interesting thing is we're gonna find new...
-- there are an infinite number of applications
and we don't even know, frankly, most of them.
We're gonna discover new ones for them
in a thousand years.
And so hopefully this gives you a sense
for why Galileo said what he said about
mathematics is really the language
with which we can understand the philosophy of the universe.
That's why people will tell us
that if a completely alien life form would contact humans,
mathematics would probably be our first common ground,
the place that we can start to form a basis
that we can start to communicate from.