In this video
we're going to talk a little bit about amines.
And these are just organic compounds
where you have a nitrogen
bonded to groups that contain carbon.
So if I were to just draw some amines right here
you could have something like this
where you have a nitrogen bonded to two hydrogens
and then maybe some type of carbon chain.
Maybe it's just one carbon right here.
So maybe you have a carbon
which is also bonded to three hydrogens like this.
In this case you would have a primary amine.
If you have the nitrogen bonded to two carbons.
So if you have something like this
a nitrogen bonded to two carbons.
So it has one carbon chain right there.
And I'm just drawing methyl groups here.
The chain could keep on going.
Maybe you have two like that.
And then you have a hydrogen right there.
This would be a secondary amine.
And then finally you could imagine
if you had it bonded to three
it would be a tertiary amine.
This is just to get you introduced to the terminology.
CH3, just like that.
Now like all of the other new groups
or new types of compounds that we've explored
what I want to do is just
introduce you to the naming of it.
Because one, that lets you recognize them
when you hear their names.
But it also, I think on some level
familiarizes you with their structure.
So let's do a couple of naming examples.
I drew these ahead of time.
And in general, just to remember
amines are a pretty high-priority group.
Out of all the things that we've learned so far
the only thing that is a higher priority
is actually the alcohols.
Or actually the thiols
which I don't even remember if I did a video on it.
But thiols are just like alcohols
but instead of an oxygen you have a sulfur.
So this comes right after those.
So let's think about this one right here.
So we always want to
look for our longest carbon chain.
And our longest carbon chain is right here.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7 carbons.
You want to start numbering it
closer to the functional group.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7
And then the functional group
is on the two carbon right there.
So first of all, seven carbons.
We would use the prefix hept.
So it would be heptan. Let me write that down.
And since our functional group is an amine
in this situation
it has a higher priority than the fact this is an alkane.
So this will actually define the suffix.
So we would then say
well then on the two carbon
-- let me do this in new color--
on the two carbon right over here
we have the amine group.
So it's heptan-2-amine.
And we're done.
We know that we have an amine group
on the twocarbon.
Now let's do this one.
This one's a little bit more hairy.
So first of all, we always want to figure out
the longest carbon chain.
And it looks like the ring
is going to be the longest carbon chain.
We have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 carbons.
So this thing right here is the longest chain.
We only have 1, 2 carbons right there.
One carbon and one carbon, right over there.
So our root is going to be cyclohexane.
I want to make sure I have enough space.
Cyclohexane.
And then once again it's an amine
so this is going to take higher priority.
So we're not just going to put an e at the end
and call this cyclohexane.
This takes higher priority.
So it will actually define the suffix.
And another thing to think about is
you could say, OK, this is going to be the one carbon
And so you could call this cyclohexan-1-amine.
But in general, if this is defining it
you always assume that
you're going to start numbering
right there at number one.
So you could just call this cyclohexanamine.
If it's written like this
you assume that the one carbon
is where the amine group is attached.
Now what else do we have on this thing?
We took care of the amine.
We took care of the cyclo.
Well we have this ether right here.
And this ether has 1, 2 carbons.
If it was just a two carbon chain, it would be ethane.
But since what we have it's an ether
it's bonded to this oxygen
we call this ethoxy.
So that right there is ethoxy.
And we're going to have to think about
how we're going to number this.
So I'll leave that alone.
And what are these over here?
Well this is a methyl group. That's a CH3 implicitly.
You don't see it drawn, but there's a carbon there.
And if carbon is neutral, it has to have four bonds.
And if you only draw one of them
the other three are assumed to be the hydrogen.
So this is a methyl group.
And then this is also a methyl group.
So we have dimethyl.
So this is also a methyl group right over there.
And when we think about numbering
we could number from 1, 2, 3.
Or we could start numbering 1, 2, 3.
And in general
you want to go numbering in the direction
where you hit the functional group first.
So we want to go 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
So this right here is 5-ethoxy.
And this is one, two dimethyl.
These two combined
you would call this one comma two dimethyl.
And then when you want to list them in order
the ethoxy would take precedence in alphabetical
because the di you shouldn't count
in the alphabetical order.
This is just saying two methyls.
So you really just want to look at the two
of whatever you're talking about.
M comes after e in alphabetical order.
So this is going to be 5-ethoxy.
Actually let me just rewrite the whole thing.
So this is going to be 5-ethoxy
1,2-dimethylcyclohexanamine.
And we're done.
This was probably one of the longest words
we've used in naming.
But hopefully you see
when you break down the different pieces
it actually makes sense
that it represents this molecule.