A functional group is a group of atoms and bonds that possess a predictable chemical behaviour.
We're gonna cover the most common functional groups that you will see in a college organic chemistry class
And you can group them into 3 categories. The first category will have carbon with multiple bonds
So lets look at an example where carbon has more than 1 bond.
Well if carbon is bonded to one other carbon atom, we've already referred to this as an alkene.
If i were to complete my dot structure over here, I would know that i need two more bonds on my carbons like that
And those could be connected to just not anything, so we're gonna put an R group here to represent the fact that there could be just anything attached to the carbons
And R stands for the rest of the molecule, or the remainder of the molecules.
Usually we are talking about carbons and hydrogens here but could be 1 carbon, 2 carbons or 5 carbons
It doesnt really matter. It just allows us to focus on the alkene functional group
So if I were to draw an example of an alkene I could put my double bond in here.
And then on either side of double bond I could put just about anything, right?