Consider the numbers 1/3 , 7 , -15
To which of these sets of numbers
these numbers belong to. Lets review each of these
Natural numbers are counting numbers
not equal 0. it is 1,2,3,... so on and so forth
The whole numbers are natural numbers plus 0
Whole numbers are 0,1,2,3,4
The integers is the whole numbers plus opposite of it
It is whole numbers plus negative of natural numbers
like -4,-3,-2,-1
0, 1, 2, 3,4, ... so on and so forth
rational numbers are numbers that can be expressed
as a ratio of two integers.Rational number can be
expressed as m/n where m and n are integers
and n cannot be 0 as anything divided by 0
is not defined. But m could be 0
as 0 can be expressed as 0/1 or 0/2 or 0/3
or 0/-537 these are all representations of 0
Irrational numbers are numbers that cannot
be expressed as ratios of integers
examples of irrational numbers are numbers that
keeps repeating on and on and on
π, √2 are examples of irrational numbers
and then real numbers are really all of these combined
if you are combining the rational numbers
and irrational numbers you are talking
about real numbers.every real number
is either rational or irrational.
lets classify what we have
1/3 is not a natural number as it is not
a counting number. It is not a whole number
it is not an integer.is it a rational number
sure it is as 1 and 3 are integers. so 1/3
is a rational number.if something is rational
it cannot be irrational and it is also a real number
lets try 7
number 7 is a natural number, whole number
any natural is a whole number
any natural and whole number si an integer
so 7 is also a integer.
any number that is natural, whole and integer
is a rational number. we can write 7 as 7/1
we can write any integer as that number / 1
if it is rational it cannot be irrational.
it is also going to be real
we have -15.
it is not a natural number
natural number are positive integers only
it is not a whole number
it is an integer, it is the opposite of +15
it is rational as it can be written as -15/1
and because it is rational it cannot be irrational
it is also real.