What I want to do in this video is review all the neat and bizarre things
that we have learned about triangles
so first we learned
So let me just draw a bunch of triangles for ourselves
so let's have a triangle right over there
the first thing that we talked about is
the perpendicular bisectors
of the sides of the triangles,
so if we take, so let's take
let's bisect this side over here,
and let's draw a perpendicular line to it,
so this line right over here would be
the perpendicular bisector of this side
right over here,
so it's bisecting and it's perpendicular, let's draw another
perpendicular bisector right over here,
so we're learning that this is the midpoint
of that side, let's draw a perpendicular bisector
and this length is equal to this length,
and then let's do one, let's do one
over here, this is the midpoint of that side
right over there, and then we will draw
a perpendicular - we know that this length
is equal to this length right over here,
and what we learned is where all these
perpendicular bisectors intersect,
what's neat about this and frankly,
all the things we're going to talk about
in this videos is
they do intersect in one unique point
that one unique point is equidistant from
the vertices of this triangle,
so this distance is going to be equal to
this distance, which is going to be
equal to that distance,
and because it's equidistant to the vertices,
you could draw a circle of that radius
that goes through the vertices, so
that goes through, that goes through
the vertices, and that's why we call this
right over here, that point,
that intersection of the perpendicular bisectors
let me write this down so we can keep track
of things, perpendicular bisectors,
perpendicular bisectors,
we call this point right over here our
circumcenter, because it is the center
of our circumcircle, a circle that can be
circumscribed about this triangle, so
this is our circumcircle.
And the radius of the circumcircle,
the distance between the circumcenter
and the vertices is the circumradius,
so that was the perpendicular bisectors.
Now the next thing we learn is
the whole point of this video is to
make sure we differentiate between these things
and not get too confused
let me draw another arbitrary triangle
right over here, the next thing we thought about
is, well, what about if we were to
bisect the angles?
Now, we're not talking about perpendicular bisecting
the sides, we're talking about
bisecting the angles themselves, so
we can bisect this angle right over here,
my best attempt to draw it-
so this angle is going to be equal to that angle,
we could bisect this angle right over here,
we could bisect- oh, that's - I could do a better version of that
so that looks- well, one more try.
So I could bisect it like that,
and then if I'm bisecting it,
this angle is going to be equal to that angle
and then if I bisect
this one, we know that this angle is going
to be equal to that angle over there,
and once again, we have proven to ourselves
that they all intersect in a
unique point, and this point,
instead of being equidistant from the vertices,
this point is equidistant from
the sides of the triangle,
so if you drop a perpendicular to
each of the sides, this distance is
going to be equal to that distance,
which is going to be equal to that distance,
and because of that, we can draw
a circle that is tangent to the side
that has this radius, we can draw a circle,
we can draw a circle
that looks like this,
and we call this circle, because
it's kind of inside the triangle
we call it an incircle, incircle,
and this point, we can call,
which is the intersection of
these angle bisectors, we can call this,
we can call this the in-radius,
now the other thing we learned about angle bisectors
and this was - we just have to draw one-
so let me just draw another triangle right over here,
and let me draw an angle bisector,
so I'm going to bisect this angle,
so this angle is equal to that angle,
and let me label some points here, so let's say that this is-
change the colors, let's say that is A,
this is B,this is C, and this is D,
we learned that if AC is really
the angle bisector of angle BAD,
that the ratio between AB over BC,
is going to be equal to the ratio
AD to DC, sometimes this is called
the angle bisector here, so that- that's neat
so the next thing we learned is - let's draw
another triangle here, this is to be a full review of everything
we've been covering in the last few videos-
so let me draw another triangle here-
so now, instead of drawing the perpendicular bisectors
let me label everything, this is angle bisectors,
this is angle bisectors,
and now what I'm going to think about are
the medians, the medians.
So the perpendicular bisectors were lines
that bisect the sides, and they are
perpendicular, but don't necessarily go through
the vertices. When we talk about medians,
we are talking about- we are talking about
points that bisect the sides, but
they go to the vertices, and they are not
necessarily perpendicular.
So let's draw some medians here. So let's say
this is the midpoint of that side right over there,
so we can draw the median like that,
notice it's going through the vertices,
these did not necessarily go through the vertices
this right over here is not necessarily perpendicular
but we do know that
this length is equal to that length right over there
and we draw a couple of more medians,
right over here, so this, the midpoint looks like
it's right about here, the midpoint looks
like it's right about there, so this length
is equal to that length, and notice it goes
through the vertex, but it's not necessarily perpendicular
and then this one,is a midpoint
looks like it's right about, well,
right about there,
and once again, all of these are concurrent,
they all intersect at one point right over here,
so this length right over here is equal to
this length right over here.
There is a bunch of neat things about medians-
when you draw the three medians
like this, that unique point where they intersect
we call this a centroid, centroid,
and as I mentioned, and you might learn this
later on in physics, is
if this was a uniform triangle, and it had
a uniform density, and if were to throw it
or rotate it in the air, it would
rotate around it's centroid,which is essentially-
it would essentially be its center of mass,
it would rotate around that as it's flying
through the air, if it had some type of
rotational or I guess you'd say
angular momentum, but the neat thing about this is
it also divides this triangle into
six triangles of equal area, so
this, this triangle has the same area as
that triangle, we proved this in several
videos ago, each of these 6 triangles all
have all have the same area.
The other thing that we learned about medians is that
where the centroid sits on each
of the medians is two thirds along the median,
so the ratio of this side of this length
to this length is two to one, or this is
two thirds along the way of the median-
this is two thirds of the median, this is
one third of the median, so the ratio is
two to one.
Another related thing we learned,
this wasn't necessarily about medians,
but a related concept, was the idea of
medial triangle, a medial triangle like this,
where you take the midpoint of each side
the midpoint of each side, and you draw
a triangle that connects the midpoints of each side,
we call this triangle a medial triangle,
a medial triangle, and we've proved to ourselves
that this- when you draw a medial triangle,
it separates this triangle into four triangles
that not only have equal area, but
the four triangles here are actually, they are actually
congruent triangles, and not only are they
congruent, but we've shown that this side
is parallel to this side,that's what we do,
use some more colors here,
this side is parallel - actually, I should
draw two arrows like that, that side is
parallel to that side,this side is
parallel to this side, and then you have
this side is parallel to this side right here,
and this length is half that length,
this length is half of that length, and
it really just comes out of the fact that
these are four congruent triangles.
There's a last thing that we touched on is
drawing altitudes of a triangle, so
there's medians, medial triangles,and
I'll draw one last triangle over here, and here
I'm going to go from each of the vertex,
and I'm not going to go to the midpoint
I'm going to drop a perpendicular to the
other side. So here I will drop a perpendicular
but this isn't necessarily bisecting the other side,
once again, we're going to drop a perpendicular
but not necessarily bisecting the other side,
and then drop a perpendicular but not necessarily bisecting the other side
and we have also proven to ourselves that
these are the altitudes of the triangle,
altitudes of the triangle, and
these also intersect in a unique- these also
intersect in a unique point.
And I want to be clear, this unique point
does not necessarily have to be inside
of the triangle. The same thing was true of
the perpendicular bisectors, it actually could
be outside of the triangle, and this
unique point we call an ortho, orthocenter.
So I'll leave you there, and hopefully this is
useful, cause I know it can get confusing,
you know, how's a median different than a
circumcenter, which is different than an
orthocenter, or inrays, or any of these type
of things, so hopefully, this clarifies things a little bit.