Now you got your chance to
use this scale
to figure out how much something weighs.
So we're asked "how much Old Spice Man weigh?"
We have Old Spice Man, this little guy here
plus you have three blocks
so on the left hand side you have
Old Spice Man plus three blocks.
And you see that the scale is balanced
so on the right hand side you have eight blocks.
So Old Spice Man plus three is equal to eight blocks.
And you can see what happens when we do something
to one side of the scale or another.
If we were to take a block from the right hand side
all of the sudden the right hand side
becomes lighter and it tilts up
And our scale is no longer balanced
so we can no longer say that the left and the right
side is equal and there is an explanation of it below here.
So what we wanna do is add or remove blocks
So essentially we're left with Old Spice Man but the
scale is balanced so whatever is on the right hand side
is how much he weighs in blocks.
So let's see if we can do that.
So let me add that block back that's were we started
from. So let's see, I wanna get rid of these three.
So if I take one away from the left hand side
Well I can't just do it there because
all of the sudden the left hand side is too light
so I am going to have to take one away from the
right hand side as well.
And let me do it again!
Take one away from the left hand side
and take one from the right hand side as well.
And I'm getting close,
one from the left hand side
now one from the right hand side
and it is balanced.
Old Spice Man is equal to five blocks