Part c: Find the value of the sixth derivative of f evaluated at zero.
You can imagine if you just tried to find the sixth derivative of f - that would take you forever.
And then to evaluate it at zero because it is x squared here
and you'd have keep doing the product rule over and over, the chain rule and all the rest.
It would become very, very, very messy.
But we have a big clue here!
The fact that they made us find the first four terms of the Taylor series of f about x equals zero
tells us that there might be a simpler way to do this as opposed to just taking the sixth derivative
of this and evaluating it at zero.
And the simplest way to do this is to just go back - in the last problem we were able to come up with the
first 4 non-zero terms of the Taylor series of f,
and if you look at your definition of the Taylor series right here,
(and we go in depth of this in another Khan Academy video where we talk about why this makes sense),
you see that each degree term of the Taylor series, its coefficient is that derivative,
(and this Taylor series is centered around zero and that's what we care about in terms of this problem),
we see the coefficient is that derivative evaluated at zero divided by that degree's factorial.
So the second degree term is the second derivative of f evaluated at zero divided by 2 factorial.
The fourth degree term is the fourth derivative of f evaluated at zero divided by 4 factorial.
So the sixth degree term...
Let's remind ourselves what we're even trying to figure out.
So they want us to figure out the sixth derivative of f evaluated at zero,
that's what they want us to figure out.
Well, if you think about the Taylor series centered at zero, or at zero, or approximated around zero,
the sixth degree term in the Taylor series approximation of f
is going to be the sixth derivative of f evaluated at zero times x to the sixth over 6 factorial.
This is going to be the sixth degree term in Taylor approximation...
in Taylor series.
And we have that term sitting right over here!
This is the sixth degree term. We figured it out in the last problem!
This right here is the sixth degree term.
So we have x to the sixth over here
x to the sixth over here.
You have 6 factorial over here
6 factorial over here.
So this -121 must be the sixth derivative of f evaluated at zero.
So that's our answer.
This is equal to -121 and we're done.