I love Greek sculpture, I love the archaic
I love the classical and all it's restraint and harmony, but I have
to tell you I really love the Helenistic -- and the reason I do is because
two fragments from a great freeze from Pergamon.
One has Athena at it's center and one has Zeus.
And I can see why you love these sculptures. They combine
what is most wonderful about ancient Greek scupture in the love of the body, but also
the sense of expressiveness and drama which we associate so much with the Helenistic.
The Helenistic refers to the last period of Greek art, the last phase of Greek art.
After the death of Alexandra the Great;
now Alexandra whose father had been a king in Northern Greece
in Masadonia had been able to conquer all of Greece,
and ultimately conquer an enormous territory
well beyond Greece's original borders.
And in so doing, he expanded
the influence the Greek culture across a much wider area.
That's right, he in a sense helped Helenize this area, or made it Greek. His expanded territory reached from
the ancient civilization of Egypt all the way to the border
between Persia and India to the Indus Valley itself. It was an enormous territory
but after he died his empire was divided among his four generals,
and one of those generals saw
a hilltop near the coast of Turkey which he believe was an important
defensive position and there founded the garrison of Pergamon that became
ultimately the kingdom of Pergamon.
And those are the people who built this fabulous alter and sculpted
this fabulous freeze. So what's going on here is a battle
between the giants and the gods and godesses
of mount Olympus. We're witnessing a celestial battle
of enormous porportions.
This is the great mythic battle where the giants battled the olympian
gods for supremecy of the earth and universe. So lets take a close look
at it. Let's start with the fragment that has Athena at it's center
She is graceful and beautiful even as she battles
a ferocious giant, a Titan.
It's clear who's gonna win. Athena looks totally in control.
She's grabbed Alcyoneus by the hair
pulling him out of the earth
disempowering him. His mother on the other side,
completely unable to help him, although she's wild with fear over
about what's about to happen to her son.
Look at the way the artist, whoever it is, has actually constructed this image.
My eye starts with Athena herself, where her head would have been.
My eye rides down that beautiful arm until it's grasped
almost tenderly by Alcyoneus. It continues around his elbow
and then across his face and down his chest. I notice that one of
Athena's snakes is biting him on his right side.
My eye then sweeps down that gorgeous curve that is his body,
his torso that leads into his leg, but is slowed down by almost
the staccato of the intersection of the deeply carved drape
that belongs to Athena. And of course,
that leads us right back to Alcyoneus' mother.
So it's as though Athena, this powerful, in control goddess, is bracketed on either side by these passionate, wild figures that are being defeated
and at the same time Athena is being crowned
by a winged nike who comes from behind with a crown for her head.
So there's really a sense hear of figures coming from behind,
of figures coming from below, of something that's completely influx, of something that's
completely in motion with an incredible sense of drama.
It's as if the entire surface of this marble is swirling in a kind of
counter clockwise motion around Athena's shield which is at it's very center.
It is full of diagonals which activates the surface.
It is full of the deepest carving that creates this
brilliant contrast between the highlights of the exposed bodies
and the dark shadows behind them.
But, what's also amazing to me is
the complexity of the compositions of their bodies. Athena who
moves toward the left, keeps her arm to the right
and then Alcyoneous lifts his head up, twists his shoulders
his legs still back behind him,
and we're really talking about virtuoso sculpting here of the human body.
Imagine what this would have looked like when it was painted.
You know, we think so often about Greek sculpture as being just this
brilliant white marble. But we have to remember
that all of this was brilliantly painted. Let's take a look at
the fragment with Zeus at its center.
Like Athena, he seems composed and totally in
control, even as he rushes forward. We have no doubt
that he's the victor here.
So Zeus is an enormously powerful figure.
We have this beautifully exposed chest and abdomen
and this wild, almost living drapery that seems to whip around
his legs, and he is taking on not one, but three giants at the same moment.
But luckily he's the king of the gods and he's got things like
eagles and thunderbolts to help him out.
That's right, if you look at the upper right
you can see that an eagle, Zeus' emblem, is taking on
the elder titan. As the eagle is preoccupying that giant,
Zeus is able to turn his attention to the giant at his feet
who's on his knees and is shortly going to be vanquished. You can see
that on Zeus' other side he has just finished putting a way a giant
who almost seems to be sitting on a rock. He's gotten stuck
in his theigh, what looks like a torch but is actually the way
the Greeks represented Zeus' thunderbolts.
Ouch, that has to hurt...
(laughter) It does, there's a sense of heroism, a sense of balance, even as there
is the sense of the momentary and a kind of excitement
that really pulls us in. You know, the story of the gods and the giants
is a story that was really important to the Greeks.
It was really a set of symbols that spoke of the Greek's fear
but also optimism that they could overcome chaos.
So this battle, it's really a metaphore for the victory of Greek culture
over the unknown, over the chaotic forces of nature.
Right, and also represents the military victories over other
cultures that they didn't understand and also feared.
So let's walk up the stairs of the great alter, into the most sacred part
of the great alter where the fire, presumeably to Zeus, would have been lit
and the sacrifices might have been offered.
You had mentioned earlier that the figures seemed to almost spill out
away from the wall, and I think that's most clearly seen as we walk up the stairs.
There are moments when the figures that are carved in this high relief
actually rest their knee on the stairs,
actually literally enter our space. For instance, one of the sea nymphs
whose legs actually end in the tail of a great serpant, coils her tail
on one of the stairs. There is this wonderful way in which they
literally pour out into our world.
And so this whole drama is unfolding
around us, moving into our space, and it, it must have been an amazing fitting to have seen --
One of the questions that comes to mind is why are these sculptures here
in Berlin, and the answer can be found in
the political ambitions of Prussia at the time.
They were very much wanting to be rhe equal of the French and the British, and that meant in part to have great
museums that express the civilizations of the past
so they could be in a sense the inheriters of the great classical tradition
which was so revered in the 19th century.
You know, Berlin in someways wanted to be the new Rome.
And so one of the great thing about being in the Pergamon Museum in Berlin
is that instead of just putting what remains of the freezes on the wall
they've reconstructed the alter and as much of the freeze as possible
and so we really get a sense of what this was like
in the city of Pergamon in the 3rd century B.C.
Right, and so this was the 3rd century.
We would be on the Acropolis, this hilltop, in the city of Pergamon
about 20 miles from the coast in what is now Turkey.
We would walk up this hill, and we would find the alter of Zeus
surrounded by a great library that is reported to have had 200,000
scrolls. A garrison for soldiers, a royal palace for the king.
And so this whole drama is unfolding around us, moving into our space
and it must have been an amazing thing to have seen in the 2nd century B.C.