When you get into higher mathmatics you might see a professor write something like
this on a board like this R with this extra backbone right over here
and maybe they write R2
or if you're looking at it in a book, it might just be a bolded capital R
with a 2 superscript like this
and if you see this they are referring to the 2-dimensional real coordinate space..
real coordinate space..
which sounds very fancy.. real coordinate space
but one way to think about it, its really just a 2-dimensional space
that you're used to dealing with in your coordinate plane.
To go a little more abstract, this isn't necessarily, this visual representation
this visual representation is one way to think about this real coordinate space
if we were to think about it a little more abstractly, the real R two
the 2-dimensional real coordinate space.. let me write this down..
the 2-dimensional real coordinate space, and just to break down the notation
the 2 tells us how many dimensions we're dealing with, and the R tells us
this is a real coordinate space. The 2-dimensional real coordinate space is all
the possible real valued 2-tuples.
let me write that down.. this is all possible
all possible real valued 2-tuples
so what is a 2-tuple? Well, a tuple is an ordered list of numbers
and since we are talking about real values it's going to be an ordered list of real numbers
and a 2-tuple just says it's an ordered list of two numbers.
So this is an ordered list of two real valued numbers. Well, that's exactly what we did here
when we thought about a 2-dimensional vector. This right over here is a 2-tuple.
And this is a real valued 2-tuple. Neither of these have any
imaginary parts, so you have a 3 and a 4.. order matters!
We view this as a different 2-tuple than say
than say, 4, 3.
Even if we would try to represent them in our
axis right over here, this vector 4, 3 would be four along the horizontal axis
and then 3 along the vertical axis.
And so it would look something like this. And remember
we don't have to draw it just over there, we just care about it's magnitude and direction.
We could draw it right over here.
This would also be 4, 3.
The column vector 4, 3. So when we're talking about R2, we're talking about
all of the possible real valued 2-tuples. So all of the
possible vectors that you can have where each
of it's components, and the components are these numbers right over here,
where each of it's components are a real number.
So you might have 3, 4. You could have -3, -4.
So that would be one, two, three, one, two, three, four.
It might look something like.. Actually I should make this scale a little bit bigger
so it looks the same, one, two three, four,
So it might look something like
that, so that would be the vector -3
Let me write it a little better than that, -3
and -4, so if you were to take all of the possible 2-tuples
including the vector zero, zero, so it has no magnitude
you could debate what it's direction is right over there, you take all of those
combined and then you have created your 2-dimensional
real coordinate space, and that is referred to as R2.
Now as you could imagine, the fact that we wrote this two here, we had to specify it
like hey, could I put a 3 there? And I would say absolutely
you could put a 3 there, so R3 would be the
3-dimensional real coordinate real space. So 3D real
coordinate space.
And so you would view this as all the possible real
valued 3-tuples
real valued 3-tuples.
So for example, that would be
a member of R3, let me actually label
these vectors so we get in the habit of it, so lets say this vector
we call this vector x, lets say we have a vector b,
that looks like this, -1, 5, 3.
Both of these would be members of R3. And if you want to see some fancy notation
a member of a set, so this is a member
this is a member of R3
It is a real valued 3-tuple. Now you say
well what would be not a member of R3? Well this right over here isn't a 3-tuple.
This right over here is a member of R2, now you might be able to extend it in some way
add a zero or something, but formally this is not a 3-tuple.
Another thing that would not be a member of R3, lets say someone wanted
to make some type of vector that had
some imaginary parts in it, so lets say it had i, 0, 1.
This is no longer real valued, we have put
we have put an imaginary, this number up here has an imaginary
part, so this is no longer a real valued 3-tuple.
And what's neat about linear algebra is that we don't have to stop
there, R3 we can visualize. We can plot these things.
We've already, probably in your previous mathematical career, especially if you have some type
of a hologram or something, it's not hard to visualize things in three dimensions.
But what's neat is that we can keep extending this. We can go to 4, 5, 6, 7
20, a 100 dimensions, and obviously there it becomes much harder
if not impossible to visualize it, but then we could at least
represent it mathematically with a n-tuple vectors,
so if we were to talk about a real coordinate space generally,
we'll often see the notation Rn, with n as a superscript.
So this right over here is a n-dimensional
n-dimensional real coordinate space.
Real coordinate space.