I've drawn a crazy looking function here in yellow
and what I want to think about is
when this function takes on maximum values
and minimum values.
And for the sake of this video,
we can assume that the graph of this function
just keeps getting lower and lower and lower
as x becomes more and more negative,
and lower and lower and lower as x goes beyond
the interval that I've depicted right over here.
So what is the maximum value that this function takes on?
Well, we can eyeball that. It looks like it's at this point,
it looks like it's at that point right over there.
So we would call this a global maximum.
The function never takes on a value larger than this
So we can say that we have a global maximum at the
point x-nought. Because f(x)-nought is greater than
equal to f(x) for any other x
in the domain.
And that's pretty obvious when you look at it like this.
Now do we have a global minimum point
the way that I've drawn it? Well no,
this function can take on arbitrarily negative values
it approaches negative infinity as x approaches
negative infinity. It approaches negative infinity as
x approaches positive infinity.
So we have, let me write this down, we have
no global minimum. Now let me ask you a question.
Do we have local minima, or local maxima?
When I say minima, it's just the plural of minimum.
And maxima is just the plural of maximum.
So do we have a local minima here, or a local minimum here?
Well, a local minimum you can imagine means that
the value of that funtion is lower than the points around it
SO right over here it looks like we have a local minimum.
We have a local minimum.
And I'm not giving you a very rigorous definition here,
but one way to think about it is, we can say that
we have a local minimum point at x-one, is if we have
a region around x-one where f(x)-one is less than f(x)
for any x in this region right over here. And it's pretty
easy to eyeball too. This is a low point for any
values of f around it.
Right over there.
Now do we have any other local minima?
Well it doesn't like we do.
Now what about local maxima?
Well, this one right over here, let me do it in purple.
I don't want to get people confused, actually,
let me do it in this color.
This point right over here looks like a local
maximum. Not lox, that would have to deal with salmon.
Local maximum, right over there.
So we can say at the point x-one, sorry, at the
point x-two, we have a local maximum point at x-two,
because f(x)-two is larger than f(x) for any x around
a neighborhood around x-two.
I"m not being very rigorous,
but you can see it just by looking at it.
So that's fair enough. We've identified all of the
maxima and minima, often called the extrema,
for this function.
Now how can we identify those if we knew something
about the derivative of the function?
Well, let's look at the derivative at each of these points.
So at this first point right over here, if I were to try
to visualize the tangent line,
let me do that in a better color than brown.
If I were to try to visualize the tangent line, it
would look something like that. So the slope here is a zero.
So we would say that f-prime of x-nought is equal
to zero.
The slope of the tangent line at this point is zero.
What about over here? Well, once again, the tangent line
would look something like that.
So once again we would say f-prime at x-one is equal
to zero.
What about over here? Well, here, the tangent line
is actually not well-defined. We have a positive slope
going into it and it immediately jumps into being
a negative slope.
So over here, f-prime of x-two is not defined.
Let me just write "undefined."
So we have an interesting, and once again, I'm not
rigorously proving it to you. I just want you to get the
intutiion here. We see that if we have some type of extrema,
And we're not talking about when x is at an endpoint of
an interval, just to be claerwhat I"m talking about.
when I'm talking about x as an endpoint of an interval.
We're saying that, let's say that the function is,
let's say we have an interval from there,
so let's say that a function starts right over there and then keeps going.
This would be a maximum point, but it would be an endpoint.
We're not talking about endpoints right now.
We're talking about when we have points in between,
or when our interval is infinite.
So we're not talking about points like that, or points like
this.
We're talking about points in between.
So if you have a point inside of an interval.
It's going to be a mimum or maximum, and we see the
intuition here.
So, non-endpoint min or max at x is equal to a,
so you know if you have a minimum or maximum point,
at some point x is equal to a, and x is at the endpoint