In the following table, is y a function of x?
In order for y to be a function of x
for any x that we input into our little function box,
let's say this is y as a function of x,
it needs to spit out only one value of y.
If it spit out multiple values of y, then it might be a relationship
but it's not going to be a function.
So this is a function.
If we have a situation where we input x into a box,
and it could be multiple possible y's,
then this is not a function.
So let's think about this table right over here.
When x is equal to 1, we get y is equal to 1.
but when x is equal to 1 again
all of a sudden y is equal to 2.
So here we have a situation where we input 1
into our little relationship box,
and when we input 1 into our relationship box
we could get a 1 or we could get a 2 for y.
So this is definitely not a function.
For any input into a function it has to map
to exactly one output.
Here it is mapping to two outputs,
so this is not a function.