Drawing or color, which is most important?
This was a burning question for artists and art critics in the 16th century.
And helped to divine the styles of entire city-states.
Well we're here in the Academia, in Venice.
Looking at Bellini's Madonna and Child with St. John the Baptist and Saint.
And Looking at this painting, I would say that Bellini would have said that color was more important.
The reds, and the blues, and the greens, just glow.
They're spectacular. And that's of course because Bellini is using a new technique.
Which has been perfected in the North, known as 'glazing.'
That's right. Taking their clue from the artists of the Northern Renaissance.