If you start with the plain piece of wood,
how do you go about making this in different shapes.
It depends on what kind of tools you wanna use.
Any time you take a raw product,
and you use tools and machinery to turn it into something useful,
what you're doing is manufacturing.
Manufacturing has changed over time
and we use different tools now, than we used to long ago.
But all of those tools can accomplish the same functions.
So, what happens if you want to make a flower that looks like this?
There is various ways that you can do that and various levels of automation.
Automation is using computers and technology to help us
instead of just using our own hands.
Carpenters used to do everything by hand.
So, say we wanna drill that hole in the middle of the flower.
How would you drill a hole by hand?
This is the tool called the brace and bit.
The drill bit is here that has sharp edges that allow to drill into the wood.
So, the way you would use this,
is you position the drill bit where you'd like to make the hole,
you apply pressure, and then by hand, you rotate the drill bit
and have a drill into the wood.
It is effective but it takes a very long time and quite a bit of elbow-grease
to get the hole to the through.
We have a hole, ladies and gentlemen.
We can drill a hole by hand, but we can also use technology
to help us do it faster and with less work.
This is called the power drill.
It uses the same drill that the hand drill did,
except now, we have a motor attached with the battery
that helps us do some of the work.
So, with this
we can drill right through.
This is a piece of equipment called a CNC mill,
which is a computer controlled piece of equipment that we can program
to cut whatever shape we want.
In this case we're going to be using this for drilling a hole,
just like we used the power drill and just like we used the hand drill.
Because this equipment is automated, instead of cranking on hand drill by hand,
all we have to do is hit a button.
So, now we figured out how to drill the hole
so that we have a nice centre for a flower,
but what happens when we wanna make the petals?
Now, instead of drilling, we're gonna have to use the technique called cutting.
One of the earliest methods was just with the saw.
These are two examples of hand saws. There are two different kinds of hand saws.
One is called a pull saw and one is called a push saw.
This is an example of a Japanese pull saw
and what you can see is that the teeth here face a little bit backwards.
That means that when you cut,
you'll be pulling in this direction in order to make the cut.
This is an example of a push saw
and you can see that the teeth face slightly forward
and that means that you're cutting while you're pushing the saw through the material.
Just like our hand saw had a blade middle metal with teeth on it to cut your material,
this is a machine called a band saw
that has the same blade right down here, also made on the metal with teeth to cut your material
but instead of pulling the blade by hand,
you have a motor up here which turns the blade for us.
So using this machine we can cut right to our material.
Just like using a band saw was a more automated way than using a hand saw
in order to cut material a water jet is even more automated.
A water jet is controlled by a computer that we can program to cut any shape we want.
It takes an abrasive grit and it mixes it with a high pressure high velocity stream of water
that goes through a tiny nozzle to blast through almost any material.
The nozzle traces out the contours of whatever shape that was wanted.
So, today we've looked at using manufacturing processes to make a flower
in order of increasing automation we've looked at drilling
from a hand drill to a power drill on the way to a computer controlled mill
and then for cutting, we've looked at starting with the hand saw,
moving to a band saw, on the way up to automated water jet.
All of these tools do essentially the same things
and at the end of the day, you' ve turned your plain piece of wood into a beautiful flower.
Thank goodness manufacturing has become automated
and it's moved from hands on to hands off or I might still be here
drilling a hole with the hand drill.