Let's try to come up with a mathematically rigorous definition for what this statement means.
The statement that f(x) as x approaches c is equal to L
So let's say that this means that you can get
you can get f(x)
as close to L as you want
I'll put that in quotes right over here...
but as close as you want
by getting x sufficiently close
to c, so another way of saying this is if you tell me
"hey I want to get my f(x) to be within 0.5 of this limit", then you're telling me if this
limit is actually true, then you should be able to hand me a value around
c that if x is within that range, that f(x) is definitely going to be as close to L as I desire.
So let me draw that out to make it a little bit clearer and I'm gonna zoom in
and I'll draw another diagram. So let's say that...
that is my y-axis and I'm gonna zoom in
and I'll draw a slightly different function just so that we can
focus on what's going on around here, the range
is around c and the range is around L
so that's x
right over here is y
this is c, and let's just say
our function is doing something like
doing something like --let's see I don't want it to be defined
at c, at least just for the--. It could be, you could always find the limit even
when it's undefined. But let's just say our function looks something like that.