Let's say the United States economy is going into a recession,
or maybe even worse than a recession,
and you are the chairman of the Federal Reserve
and you need to do something about it.
Well the first thing that you would do is that you would lower the
Federal Funds Rate, and that's the rate that banks lend to each other overnight
and the way that you lower it, if the banks don't do it on their own after you say you want to lower it
is that you print money, as the Federal Reserve
and you use it to buy, usually short-term treasury securities
and that money gets deposited in banks,
so the demand for reserves, because that's what these things are
the demand for reserves goes down, and the supply goes up
and the federal funds rate should go down.
But what happens if you keep doing this,
and you keep lowering the federal funds rate
all the way down so that the overnight borrowing rate is
approximately 0%, what do you do then?
If the economy still looks like it's in a bit of a tail spin?
well you could still print, you could still print money
but using that money to buy short-term debt
won't help any, because you're not going to lower
the short-term overnight inter-bank interest rate anymore,
so you can go out and buy other things
and those other things can be longer-term treasuries
or, they could be other types of securities
they could be, you could buy mortgage backed securities
you could buy commercial debt
and this idea of printing money,
not just for a target interest rate,
but essentially to get that money into circulation
and maybe to effect other parts of the market
this is called quantitative easing.
And in Bernanke's mind, although that's exactly what he's doing
he's printing money to buy other things
than what the Fed traditionally does,
when it cares about the overnight borrowing rate,
he calls it, not necessarily quantitative easing,
but credit easing, and in his mind,
even though mechanically they're the same thing,
in his mind, he's saying, "Look, I'm printing this money
"...not just for the sake of printing the money,
"...and putting it into circulation,
"...I'm printing the money so that I can buy particular assets,
"...where it seems like there might be a log jam in the credit market"
because with just printing money and buying government securities
maybe the interest rates on government debt goes down
but maybe because of panic or crisis, interest or the prices on these things
don't behave properly. So in order to fix that
credit easing, in Bernanke's sense, would be to
go out and buy this type of asset.