This video is on Perimeter and Area
Perimeter on the left and Area on the right.
Perimeter is the distance to go around something.
If you were to put a fence around or measure something
If you were to put a tape around a figure,
if i have a rectangle, and the rectangle is a figure
that has 4 sides and four right angles,
This has 4 right angles and 4 sides and the
opposite sides are equal in length.
I will label the points ABCD, let us say we
know the following AB = 7, and BC = 5
We want to know what is the perimeter of ABCD
Perimeter of rectangle ABCD = the sum of the lengths of the sides
If I were to build a fence on the plot of this land
I need to measure the length of the sides,
we know this length AB is 7, this length isBC 5,
DC is going to be same as Ab = 7 and DA is going
to be the same length as BC = 5.
So we have 7+5+7+5 = 24, perimeter is 24
We can go the other way around, lets say we have a square
A square has 4 sides and 4 right angles and
all sides are equal. let me draw a square, this is ABCD
and this square has a perimeter of 36
Given that what is the length of each side.
All sides are of equal length, let us call x as the length of a side
AB = x, BC=x, CD = x, DA = x
If we want to figure the perimeter it will be x+x+x+x
x+x+x+x = 4x = 36
To solve this 4 times something = 36
divide both sides by 4, we get x = 9
This is a 9 by 9 square.That is perimeter
Area is a measure of how much space this thing take
One way to think is if I have a 1 by 1 square,
for a rectangle you need to specify 2 dimensions as
the other sides will be the same, for rectangle we
say it is a 5 by 7 rectangle.
If one side is 1 in a square, all sides are 1
Area of any figure is how many 1by 1 square can you fit on that figure
If we go back to that rectangle and I want to find the area
of this rectangle and the notation to be used is
put it in brackets area of rectangle ABCD =
it is the number of 1 by 1 squares we can fit in this rectangle
Lets try doing it , we have 5 - 1by 1 squares this way
and 7 - 1by 1 squares this way,
Going along one of the sides we can put 7 , over here
we can put 5 rows, this is 1 each and adds upto 5
and this is 1 each adds upto 7
We can actually count the number of 1 by 1 squares
we have 5 rows and 7 columns, we have 35 squares
So the area of this figure is 35 .
So the general method is take one dimension and
multiply by the other dimension
If i have a rectangle of dimension 1/2 by 2,
we can just multiply these two 1/2 * 2 = 1
In this dimension i can only fit half a square
When we add 2 halves, we get 1
Now what about area of the square.
Square is a special case where length and width are the same
So if have a square and lets call it XYZS,
i want to find the area and i know XS = 2, i want to
find the area of XYZS =
We know all the sides are equal,
It is a special case of a rectangle, we know if this is 2
this also is 2 So we just multiple 2 by 2 = 2 * 2 = 4
And you can see you can fit 4 - 1 by 1 squares in this