What I want to do in this video is dig a little bit deeper into the deficit
And just so you can get the data yourself
they are all available in this document
which is hosted by the Department of Treasury
so you know that I am not making up these numbers
but just of you, the deficit is really a measure of how much
you are overspending in any given year
if you look at the deficit
i am gonna focus on 2010 in this video
In 2010, the government spent
so the spending for the government in 2010
was about 3.5 to 3.6 trillion dollars
and it brought in, in mainly tax revenues
but it has a few other sources
mainly tax revenues, it brought in about
2.2 trillion dollars
so based on this, the overspending
or the amount of money which beyond the revenues
or the deficit, the deficit in 2010 was 1.3 trillion dollars
What I want to be clear on it
this is only one way to account for spending
verses revenues, and this is not the way most companies
would primarily report their own income over the course of the year
or their own cost, or their own lost
over the course of the year
most companies would not just have to account for their
cash outlets, that's all we are considering in this
3.5 to 3.6 trillion dollars
a traditional company would also has to include
any other liabilities, any other obligations
that they are taking on
for example, if I hire you and I promise to pay you
$50,000 over the course of next year
and I am gonna pay them to you in cash
But I also promised that when you retire,
I am gonna pay you $10,000
I am gonna give you a $10,000 per year pension
In a traditional income statement
I would not just expense the $50,000
I would definitely put that in my expenses
and government would put that in their expenses
but I would also have to account for this liability
that I am taking on
I would also love to say, look, in order for me to be able to
afford the $10,000 pension in some future day
I have to make some estimates about when you would retire
and how long you would live, and what interest
I can get on money, and all of the rest
But I have to set aside some of the amounts of money
so that in the future I can meet that obligation
so maybe I have to set aside $2,000 this year
and hope it grows properly
over the course of the next 20 30 years
until you retire, so that I can afford to pay you that much
who knows, but I would also have to account for, right here
the extra liability, the government, in the calculation of the deficit
is not account for that extra liability
And it is taking on other liabilities
It is making these pension promises to government employees
It has obligations to the veterans, and veterans' affairs
and all of that
and that is not taking account, or that is not accounted for the deficit
It is accounted for in the gross cost
And you see here, we said, when we look at just the budget
we were talking 3.5 to 3.6 trillion dollars
that's direct cash outlets, mostly direct cash outlets
if you include all of this other stuff
then it ballons to 4.5 trillion dollars
4.5 trillion dollars, so in previous video that I mentioned,
that the government right now, for every dollar it has spending
it has to borrow 40 cents of that dollar
but if you really think about the total obligations that it has
the total obligations has to be 4.5 trillion took on
view that way, it only has it about half of that
it only has it about half of that coming in revenue
so every dollar the government is taking on
the equal obligations that year
some of that is going to express itself in terms of increased debt
and some of that is going to show up as increased obligations
and you can see both of those things are increasing
year after year after year
And depending on who you talk to
inside the political spectrum, some people would blame it
on Bush, they will say, look at this, you know
the spending increase under Obama
or some of the right would say
some of the left would say, yes, but
the spending increase, because we have to do all these bailouts
the economy went into the, start to tank
at the end of the 2008
we have to do all of these emergency things
as soon as the economy tanks, you automatically
the deficit position gets worse
because you bring in less revenue
And you not only bring in less revenue
because corporate profits are down
fewer people are employed, few people start earning less
but you also have higher expenses
because all of these automatic obligations came to effect
unemployment benefits, social security benefits
medicare benefits, those increase
so deficit is not actually get worse
but the whole point here is say regardless of
what party you are on
things are getting worse and
they don't seem to be getting better
And generally, you always see this net operating cost
sometimes the net operating cost would look lower than
the actual deficit like in 2008
And that's because there will be some type of
actual area of accounting
re-estimate of the future obligations
maybe the pension obligations, whatever
But in most years, we are taking on more obligations
than just our cash outlets
That's why you see the operating cost
so much higher than just the pure deficit right over here
And this chart, right over here, actually goes into
what some of those, what the difference is
the actual difference and you see
that is mainly things like liabilities for veterans'
compensation, military and civilian employee benefits
government sponsored enterprises
there's some down division of the tarp, i don't think you can see that
So all of a sudden, you realize that tarps gonna cost us
more in the future than you thought it's going to be
even though you don't spend that 86 billion this year
you realize that you have an 86 billion higher obligation
and so if you add all of these, or i can say,
if you track all of these from the budget deficit
then you are going to get the net operating cost
and that you might already find that depressing
But the point of this video is actually
"that's just the beginning"
because if you look at where we were going
that you actually get even more depressing
because not only do we have this huge budget deficit
or this huge operating cost, this loss, I guess you can say
on an annual basis, but it's gonna get worse
it's gonna get worse not just the overspending
not just the overspending on the government's programs
of the defense, and all of that
but because our debt is increasing so much
that the interest, the amount we spend on interest
is only going to incease
and that just make matters worse
the more you spend on interests, the larger deficits
the larger deficits, the more you have to borrow
the more you have to spend on interest
and this is a long time line right here
goes out to 2080, but it's pretty clear that something
something is going to give
so the percentage of the GDP
the government, the size of the government has historically
be around this, you know,depending on different periods of
the history, but in the recent past,
it's been the 20 percent range
but if you just let things go the way they are gonna go
and a lot of these kind of mandatory spending
things we've already obligating ourselves
to what we think we obligate ourselves to
it looks like the size of the government is going to take over
the economy and it's gonna grow over the next 20 30 years
30% 35% 40% of the entire economy
now if that by itself is not scary or depressing enough for you
then we just have to look at this chart right over here
And we've already gone over some of this chart
this is the gross cost, this is the total amount of spending
outlets, cash outlets and other obligations
that we are taking on and accounting for someway
the present, and then you have the taxes
you are bringing in, and you see this is your
net operating cost that we calculated already
and then chose your assets, your assets of the government
mainly buildings and lands that the government has
a lot of nice land and buildings
and you also see a properly plan to the equipment to all
that air-craft carriers whatever you want to throw
into the mix right over here
but then you see the debt
and we've done a lot of talk about the debt
you might be saying, wait, even in 2010, they don't
you know, right now, we hit debt ceiling
we have like 14.3 trillion, but didn't we have like
13 point something trillion debt in 2010
why this only say 9 trillion
that's because we have another 4 trillion in debt
that is not held by the public
this is just debt held by the public
we have a public clews, things like foreign government
but there's another 4 trillion that is held by the government itself
so that is not accounted for
and that 4 trillion is mainly excess funds for
the social security trust that all invested in treasuries
but the government at the end of the day is responsible for
the social security trust, and so is not accounted for right over here
so you have 9 trillion there
you have another 6 trillion that is seldom talked about
which is benefits for federal employees and veterans
that's right over here, so huge obligation
so a total of 16 trillion in liabilities
now that by itself doesn't scare you enough or
doesn't depress you enough
we just have to go down a few lines on the statement
and you will see something that does
and this right here is the expected or present value of
the obligations for social insurance
and the way they talk about social insurance is supposed
social security and things like medicare
so these things we've promised we would pay the people
in the future that we told people that we will pay them
in the future. And the present value, the easiest way
to think about present value, I've done videos,
I am going to do more depth on that
how much money given some assumptions
if I assume that if I put money aside, that money grows
at some rate, how much money would I have to put aside
and in order to fund those obligations
and this values over the next 75 years
And I want to make it clear
75 years is of course gonna be huge number
but remember, we are assuming that we can grow money
we are assuming that obligations that are 75 years from now
that if I have to pay someone 10 dollars 75 years from now
I don't have to put 10 dollars aside
I might only have to put 50 cents or dollar aside
and assume that 50 cents or dollar will grow
by some percentage, so that by the time 75 years go by
I will actually have the 10 dollars
this is actually a discounted value
this is assuming that money you can set aside today
the obligation today that it would grow to actual fulfill
the actual amount you have to pay
and this should scare you
these are huge numbers
this close group are what they call the current participants
and we could read the footnotes
includes current participants receiving an all
edible benefits for the social security and medicare program
ages 50 and over at the start of a 75 year of projection period
so that's 43 trillion than open group
they have current and future participants
this is slightly lower because including people
who are going to be paying into the program
and not necessarily taking out of the program
but is still a huge huge liability
it's twice as big as the official liabilities
that the government takes on