We're on part B. The region R is rotated about the x-axis to form a solid. Find the volume V of the solid in terms of k.
So this is our region R, and it's going to be rotated around the x-axis... it's going to be rotated around the x-axis to form a solid.
So that solid's going to look something like this: It's going to look like this- this is going to be this end of the solid when it's rotated around,
and it's going to look something like this. My best attempt to draw our solid.
It's going to be... and then that side's going to look something like that; it'll look a little bit like a loudspeaker. Let me shade it in a little bit.
So that's going to be our solid and you can imagine... you can imagine that maybe this is... this right over here is our y-axis.
That is our y-axis, and then going straight through the centre of the solid... straight through the centre of the solid you have your x-axis.
and let me just... even... if the solid was slightly transparent you would see the other side of this
opening right over here. The x-axis goes straight through the centre.
So how do we find the volume of the solid? Well we can think about each of the individual discs of this
solid right over here. So think about it this way: let's take a disc right over here.
Take this disc right over here.
So that you can imagine this little bit of a cross-section, it's a little bit of a cross-section of
this solid so this disc right over here is going to have some area.
It's going to have some surface and then it's going to have some depth.
You can imagine the depth is the edge of the quarter while the surface area is kind of the face of the quarter;
the area of the face of a quarter. So what's going to be the volume of this white disc right over here?
Well it's going to be the surface area of the disc times the depth. So what is the surface area?
Well surface area of a circle is pi times the radius squared. It's pi times the radius squared so it's going
to be pi times... what's this radius? What's this radius?
Well the radius is the height between the x-axis and the function, so this radius is e to the 2x power.
So the area of each of these discs at this value of x is going to be pi times (e to the 2x) squared,
and then if we want the volume of this entire disc we then multiply the area times the depth,
so times dx.
So this would be the volume of this little disc over here, that has a very small, infinitessimally wide
depth, but what we want to do is sum all of these discs. We want to do... we want to have a bunch of
these discs. And we want to sum up all of them so we want to take the infinite sum of these infinitely
thin discs. So essentially we're just going to take the sum of all of these from x is equal to zero,
all the way to x is equal to k. Right, because this right over here, this is x = k, this is x = 0,
we take the sum of all the discs, we will get our actual volume.
So we can actually evaluate this integral analytically, it's not too bad. Because e to the ... let me rewrite it...
pi times... (e to the 2x) squared is e to the (4x) - just 2x times 2. And then if we want to take the
integral - you might be able to do this just by inspection - but if you want to say, "Hey look, I have a little function here
I want it's derivative sitting here", what we can do - we can multiply this expression by four;
we can also divide it by four. If you multiply something by four and divide it by four you haven't changed its value -
you've multiplied it by one. But what this does is it givs us, if you let me rewrite it a little bit, so this is
we can rewrite this as (pi over 4) times four times e to the 4x. I just rewrote this - I multiplied and divided by four.
And the reason why I did that is so that we have the derivative of 4x is sitting right over here, we
have this four. Pi over 4 is constant so we can actually take it out of the integral, and so we can say
this expression right over here is the same as... is the same thing as this expression right over here.
(pi/4) times the integral from zero to k of (4 e to the 4x) dx.
And so... the whole reason I multiplied and divided by four is: I have something here; I have its derivative.
So I can really just pretend like this is e to the x: I take its... I guess you could say you take the
[derivative with respect to] - or you could take the integral or the antiderivative with respect to 4x.
So this - the inside is e to the 4x. And you can verify: if you take the derivative of e to the 4x,
it is the derivative of 4x, which is 4, times (e to the 4x).
So this right here is the antiderivative of that, and we're going to evaluate it...
we're going to evaluate it from zero to k. And all of this times pi over four.
So when you evaluate it at k, it's e to the 4k.
So that's pi/4 times: e to the 4k minus e to the (four times zero), which is e to the zero, which is [minus] 1.
So this is our volume: (pi/4) times [e^(4k) -1]. And so that is part B. We did that.
Now part C - I think we have time for this. The volume, V, found in part B changes as k changes.
If dk... if the derivative of k with respect to t is one third, determine the derivative of V with respect to t
when k is one-half. So this is straight up from the chain rule
So the chain rule will tell us... and if you view differentials as just very very small numbers it actually
just seems like a little bit of common sense...
The rate of change of V, so this very small change in V with respect to a very small change in t
is equal to a very small change in V with respect to a very small change in k, times
times a very small change in k divided by a very small change in t.
Or: the derivative of v with respect to t is equal to the derivative of V with respect to k
times the derivative of k with respect to t.
And the reason why I said this made sense if you view a differential as a small number is:
You would... and that's not a very rigorous way of doing it but it's a good kind of common sense way
of just thinking about things... is that these guys would cancel out if these were numbers, and then
you would have dV/dt on both sides. So that's why I said this is a slightly common sense -
you can kind of view it that way.
But this essentially gives us everything we need to know:
We need to solve for dV/dt. They already gave us dk/dt = 1/3 when k = 1/2,
So they're already telling us the rate of change of k with respect to t, we already know that this thing
right over here is going to be 1/3, and we can figure out the derivative of V with respect to k very easily:
We have V as a function of k right over here, so let's figure that out.
So the derivative of V with respect to k is equal to pi/4 times the derivative in here.
The derivative of this is just 4(e^4k), derivative of -1 is just zero.
So e... this is times four... e to the 4k is the derivative. These guys cancel out,
so this is equal to pi * e to the 4k, that's the derivative of V with respect to k,
we want to find it when k = 1/2, so we could write V' at 1/2,
or when k=1/2, dV/dk is going to be equal to pi times e to the (4 times 1/2),
which is pi * (e squared). So this part right over here is pi*e^2.
And so the derivative of V with respect to t when k is equal to 1/2, and
and the derivative of k with respect to t is 1/3, is going to be just pi*e^2 times 1/3.
So let me just rewrite it over here. So dV/dt is going to be equal to 1/3 * this.
Or we could write pi e^2 over three.
And we're done! :-)