This triangle that we have right over here
is a right triangle and it's a right triangle because
it has a 90 degree angle or it has a right angle in it.
Now we call the longest side of a right triangle
we call that side, and you can either view it
as the longest side of a right triangle or the side
opposite the 90 degree angle, it is called
the hypotenuse. It's a very fancy word for a
fairly simple idea, just the longest side of a right
triangle or the side opposite the 90 degree angle.
It's just good to know that because someone might
say hypotenuse, and you'll know that they're talking about
the side opposite the 90 degree angle. Now, what I
want to do in this video is prove a relationship, a very famous relationship
and you might see where this is going, a very famous relationship
between the lengths of the sides of a right triangle. So let's say
that the length of AC, so uppercase A uppercase C, lets call
that length lowercase a, let's call the length of BC lowercase b