We're told that A B C D E F is a regular hexagon
And this regular part hexagon obviously tells us
That we're dealing with six sides and you could just count that
You didn't have to be told it's a hexagon
But the regular part lets us know all of the sides
All six sides have the same length
and all of the interior angles have the same measure
Fair enough
And then they give us the length of one of the sides
And since this is a regular hexagon
They're actually giving us the length of all of the sides
They say its two square roots of three
So this side right over here is two square roots of three
This side right over here is two square roots of three
And I could just go around hexagon,
every one of their sides is two square roots of three
They want us to find the area of this hexagon
Find the area of A B C D E F
And the best way to find the area especially of regular polygons,
Is to try to spilt up into triangles
And hexagons are a bit of special case
Maybe in the future videos,
we'll think about the more general case of any polygon
With the hexagon, what you can think about is if we
If we take this point right over here and let's call this point G
Now let's say it's the center of the hexagon
And when I'm talking about a center of a hexagon
I'm talking about a point it can't be equidistant
From everything over here coz this isn't a circle [1:08 7]
But we could say it's equidistant from all of the vertices
So GD is the same thing as GC is the same thing as GB,
Which is the same thing as GA, which is the same thing as GF,
which is the same thing as GE
So I'm gonna draw some of those that I just talked about
So that is GE
There's GD
There's GC
All of these lines are going to be the same
So there's a point G which we can call the center
The center of this polygon
And we know that this length is equal to that length,
which is equal to that length,
Which is equal to that length,
Which is equal to that length
We also know that if we add
if we go all the way around the circle;
If we go all the way around the circle like that,
We've gone 360 degrees
And we know that these triangles,
these triangles are all going to be congruent to each other
and there's multiple ways if we could show it;
But the easiest way is look they have two sides
All of them have this side and this side be congruent to each other
Coz G is in the center and they all have this third common side
Of two square roots of three
So all them by side-side-side they are all
They're all congruent
What that tells us is if they're all congruent
Then this angle, this interior angle right over here
Is going to be the same;
is going to be the same for all six of these
all six of these triangles over here
And maybe we'll call that X
That's angle X, that's X, that's X, that's x, that's x;
And if you'd add them all up we've gone around the circle
We've gone 360 degrees and we have six of these Xs
So you get six X is equal to 360 degrees
you divide both sides by six, you get X is equal to
X is equal to 60 degrees
All of these are equal to 60 degrees
Now there's something interesting
We know that these triangles-
for example triangle GBC
And we could do that for any of these six triangles
It looks kind of a trivial pursuit piece
But we know that they're definitely isosceles triangle
That this distance is equal to this distance
So we can use that information to figure out,
To figure out what the other angles are
Because these two base angles-
it's an isosceles triangle; the two legs are the same
so are two base angles
This angle is going to be congruent to that angle
And we could call that Y right over there
So you have Y+Y which is 2Y+60 degrees, plus 60 degrees
is going to be equal to 180
because the interior angles of any triangle,
They add up to 180
And so subtract 60 from both sides,
You get 2Y is equal to 120;
divide both sides by 2, you get Y is equal to 60 degrees
Now this is interesting
I could've done this with any of these triangles
All of these triangles are 60-60-60 triangles,
which tells us and we've proven this earlier on
When we first started studying equilateral triangles
We know that all of the angles of a triangle are 60 degrees
And we're dealing with an equilateral triangle！
Which means that all the sides have the same length
So this is two square roots of three
then so is This is also two square roots of three
And this is also two square roots of three
So pretty much all of these green lines are two square roots of three
And we already knew because it's a regular hexagon
That the every out
each side of the hexagon itself is also two square roots of three
So now we can essentially use that information
We can use that information to figure out;
Actually we don't really have to figure this part out
I'll show you in a second
To figure out the area of any one of these triangles
And then we can just multiply it by six
So let's focus on let me focus on this triangle right over here
Think about how we can find its area
We know that length of DC is two square roots of three
We can drop an altitude over here
We can drop an altitude just like that
And then we if we drop an altitude,
we know that this is
we know that this is an equilateral triangle
And we can show very easily
That these two triangles are symmetric
These are both 90 degree angles
We know that these two are 60 degree angles already
And then you just
if you look at each of these two independent triangles
You'd have to just say well they have to add up to 180
So this has to be 30 degrees; this have to be 30 degrees
All the angles are the same
They also share a side in common
So these two are congruent triangles
So if we wanna find the area of this broader
Of this little slice of the pie right over here,
We can just find the area of this slice or this sub slice
And then multiply it by two
Or we could just find this area and multiply by 12
For the entire hexagon
So how do we figure out the area of this thing?
Well this is going to be half of this base length
So this length right over here-- let me call this point H
DH is going to be the square root of three
And we are or hopefully we already recognized
this is a 30-60-90 triangle
Let me draw it over here
So this is a 30-60-90 triangle
We know that this length over here is square root of three
We know and we already actually did calculate it
This is two square root of three or we don't really need it
What we really need to figure out is this altitude height
And from 30-60 degree 90 30-60-90 triangles
we know that side opposite the 60 degree side is square root of three
Is a square root of three
Times the side opposite the 30 degree side
So this is going to be square root of three
Times the square root of three,
times the square root of three
Square root of three times square root of three
Is obviously just 3
So this altitude right over here is just going to be three
So if we want the area of this triangle right over here,
Which is this triangle right over here
Is just one half base times height
So the area of this little sub slice
is just one half times our base;
Just the base over here
Actually let's take a step back
We don't even have to worry about this thing
Let's just go straight to the larger triangle GDC
So let me let me rewind this a little bit
Coz now we have the base and the height of the whole thing
If we care about, if we care about the area triangle GDC
So now I'm looking at
Now I'm looking at this entire triangle right over here
This is equal to one half times base times height
Which is equal to one half
What's our base?
Our base we already know
It's one of the sides of our hexagon！
it's two square roots of three
So it's this whole thing right over here
So times two square roots of three
And then we wanna multiply that times our height
And that's what we just figure out using 30-60-90 triangles
Our height is three
So times three One half and two cancel out
We're left with three square roots of three
That's just the area of one of these little wedges right over here
If we wanna find the area of the entire hexagon
We just have to multiply that by six
Coz there are six of these triangles there
So this is going to be equal to six times three square roots of three
Which is 18 square roots of three and we're done