What I want to do in this video
is give you a bunch of properties of limits
and we're not going to prove it rigorously here -
- in order to have the rigorous proof of these properties
we need a rigorous definition of what a limit is
and we're not doing that in this tutorial -
- we'll do that in the tutorial on the epsilon-delta definition of limit -
- but most of these should be fairly intuitive
and they're very helpful for simplifying limit problems
in the future
So let's say we know that the limit of some function
f(x) as x approaches c is equal to L
and let's say that we also know that the limit of some
other function, let's say g(x), as x approaches c
is equal to M
Now, given that, what would be the limit
of f(x) plus g(x) as x approaches c?
Well, and you could look at this visually
- if you look at the graphs of two arbitrary functions
you essentially just add those two functions -
it'll be pretty clear that this is going to be equal to -
- and once again, I'm not doing a rigorous proof;
I'm just really giving you the properties here -
- this is going to be the limit of f(x) as x approaches c
plus the limit of g(x) as x approaches c
which is equal to - well, this right over here is -
(we'll do that in that same color)
- this right here is just equal to L: it's going to be equal
to L plus M - this right over here is equal to M
Not too difficult
This is often called the Sum Rule
or the Sum Property of Limits
and we could come up with a very similar one
with differences - the limit as x approaches c of f(x) minus g(x)
is just going to be L minus M
It's just the limit of f(x) as x approaches c
minus the limit of g(x) as x approaches c
So it's just going to be L minus...
L minus M
It's often called the Difference Rule
or the Difference Property of Limits
and these once again are very, very (hopefully)
reasonably intuitive
Now what happens if you take the product of the functions?
The limit of f(x) times g(x) as x approaches c?
Well, lucky for us this is going to be equal to
the limit of f(x) as x approaches c times the limit of g(x) as x approaches c
Lucky for us, this is kind of a fairly intuitive property of limits
So in this case this is just going to be equal to -
- this is L times M
L times...
...this is just going to L times M
Same thing, if instead of having a function here we had a constant
So if we just had the limit -
(I'll do that in the same color)
- the limit of k times f(x) as x approaches c
where k is just some constant
This is going to be the same thing as k times the limit
of f(x) as x approaches c and that is just equal to...
...this is just equal to L...
This is equal to L, so this whole thing
simplifies to k times...
...k times L
And we can do the same thing with the differences -
- this is often called the Constant Multiple Property -
- we can do the same thing with the differences
So if we have the limit as x approaches c
of f(x) divided by g(x), this is the exact
same thing as the limit of f(x) as x approaches c
divided by the limit of g(x) as x approaches c
which is going to be equal to -
- I think you get it now -
- this is going to be equal to L over M
And finally - this is sometimes called the Quotient Property -
- finally, we'll look at the Exponent Property
So if I have...
...if I have the limit of -
- let me write it this way -
- of f(x) to some power
- and actually let me even
write it as a fractional power -
to the r over s power,
where both r and s are integers -
then the limit of f(x) to the r over s power
as x approaches c is going to be the exact same
thing as the limit of f(x) as x approaches c
raised to the r over s power
once again, when r and s are both integers
and s is not equal to zero, otherwise this exponent
would not make much sense
and this is the same thing...
...this is the same thing as L...
...this is the same thing as L to the r over s power
This is equal to L to the...
...L to the r over s power
So, using these we can actually find the limit
of many, many, many things and what's neat about it
is the properties of limits kind of are the things that
you would naturally want to do and if you
graph some of these functions actually it
turns out to be quite intuitive