What I wanna do in this video is
See if we can identify similar triangles here
And prove to ourselves that they really are similar
Using some of the postulates that we've set up
So over here I have triangle B, D, C it's inside of triangle A, E, C
They both share this angle right over there
So that gives us one angle
We need two to angle -angle which gives us similarity
And we know that these two lines are parallel
And we know if two lines are parallel we have transversal
That corresponding angles are gonna be congruent
So that angle is gonna correspond to that angle right over there
And we're done
We have one angle and triangle A, E, C that is congruent
to another angle in B, D, C
and then we have this angle that is obviously congruent to itself,
That's in both triangles
So both triangles have a pair of corresponding angles
that are congruent, So they must be similar
So we can write triangle A, C, E
A, C, E is gonna be similar triangle
We wanna get the letters in the right order
So where the blue angle is here, the blue angle there is vertex B
We're gonna go to the white angles C
and then we go to the unlabeled angle right over there B, C, D
B, C, D
So we did that first one
Now let's do this one right over here
This is kinda similar
but at least it looks just superficial looking at it
YZ is definitely not parallel to ST
So we won't be able to do this corresponding angle argument
Alright, especially cuz I didn't even labelled this parallel
And so you wanna, you don't wanna look at things
just by the way they look
You definitely want to say what am I given and what am I not given
These weren't labelled parallel,
we wouldn't be able to make this statement
Even though if they look parallel
One thing we do have is that we have this angle right here,
This common to the inner triangle and to the outer triangle
And then given us a bunch of sides
So maybe we could use SAS for similarity
Meaning if we can show the ratio of the sides
on either sides of this angle,
And they have the same ratio from the smaller triangle
to the larger triangle
Then we can show similarity
So let's go, we have to go on either side of this angle
right over here
Let's look at shorter side on on either side of this angle
So the shorter is 2, and let's look at the shorter side
on other side of the angle for the larger triangle
Well then the shorter side is on the right hand side
And that's gonna have, that's gonna be xt
So we wanna compare is the ratio between, right this way,
We wanna see is xy/ xt, over xt is that equal to the ratio
of the longer side Or if we're looking relative to this angle,
the longer of the two
I'm sorry the longest of the triangle,
though it looks like that as well
Is that equal to the ratio of xz,
xz over the longer of the two sides,
When you're looking at this angle right here
on either side of that angle
for the larger triangle over xs, over xs
And it's a little confusing cuz we've kinda flip with side
But I'm just thinking about the shorter side
on either side of this angle and between,
and then the longer side of either side of this angle
So these are the shorter side for the smaller triangle
and the larger triangle
These are the longer sides for the smaller triangle
And we see xy this is 2
Xt is 3 +1 is 4, xz is 3, xz is 3 and xs is 6
So you have 2/4 which is ? which is the same thing as 3/6
So the ration between the shorter sides on either side of the angle
And the longer side on either sides of the angle for both triangles
The ratio is the same, so by SAS we know,
so by SAS we know that the 2 triangles are congruent
But we have to be careful on how we state the triangles
We wanna make sure we get the corresponding sides
So we could say that triangle, and I'm running out of space here
Let me write it write above here
We can write the triangle xyz, xyz is similar, is similar to triangle
So we started up at x which is the vertex of the angle
And we went to the shorter side first
So now we want to start at x and go to shorter side of large triangle
So x, so you go to xts, xts
Xyz is similar to xts
Now let's look at this over here,
so in our larger triangle we have a right angle here
But we really know nothing, we really know nothing about
What's going on with any of these smaller triangles
in terms of their actual angles
You know this looks like a right angle
We cannot assume it
And it shares, if we look at this smaller triangle right over here
It shares one side with the larger triangle,
Well that's not enough to do anything
And then this triangle over here also shares another side,
But that also doesn't do anything
So we really can't make any statement here
About any kind of similarities
So there's no similarity going on here
If they, if they gave us, if they gave us,
And well there are some, there are some shared angles
This guy they both share that angle
the larger triangles, small triangle
So there could be a statement of similarity we can make
If we knew that this definitely was a right angle
Then we can make some interesting statement about similarity
But right now we can't really do, we can't do anything as is
Let's try this one out or this pair right over here
So this the first ones that we've actually separated out the triangles
So they've given us the 3 sides of both triangles,
So let's just figure out the ratios
between corresponding sides are a constant
So let's start with the short side
So the short side here is 3, shorter side is here is 9,
So we have, wanna see whether this the ratio of 3 to 9 is equal to
The next longest side over here is 3, is equal to 3 over
the next longest side over here which is 27, which is 27
And then if that's gonna be equal to,
if that's gonna be equal to the ratio of the longest side
So the longest side here is 6, 6
and then the longest side over here is 18, 18
So this is going to give us, let's see this is 3
This is 8, let me do this in a neutral color
So 3, we could this becomes 1/3
This becomes which seems like a different number
But we wanna be careful here
And this right over here this becomes,
this is a if you divide the numerator and denominator by 6
this becomes a 1 and this becomes 3
So you get 1 , 1/3 is to be equal to 1, needs to be equal of /9
which needs to be equal to 1/3
At first they don't look equal
But we can actually rationalize this denominator right over here
We show that 1/ 3 if you multiply it by a /,
This actually gives you a numerator of / 9
is 3 times 3 is 9
So these actually are all the same
This is actually saying this is 1/ 3 root 3
which is the same thing as
Which is this right over here which is the same thing as 1 /
So actually these are similar triangles
So we actually say it and I'll make sure I get the order right
So let's start with E which is between
the blue and the magenta side
So that's between the blue and the magenta side that is H,
right over here
So triangle E, I'll do it like this,
triangle E and then I'll go along the blue side F
Then I go over along, along the blue side over here side
Let me do it this way
Actually let me just write it this way
E triangle E, F, G we know is similar to triangle
So E is between the blue and magenta side,
blue and magenta side that is H
And then we go along the blue side to F
Go along the blue side to I
And then we're go along the orange side to G
Then you go along the orange to J
So triangle E,F,J is, E,F,G is similar to triangle H,I,J
by side, side, side similarity
They're not congruent sides
They all have just the same ratio or the same scaling factor
Now let's do this last one right over here
So we have, let's see, we have an angle
that's congruent to another angle right over here
And we have 2 sides,
and so it might be attempting to use side angle side
Because we have side angle side here
And even the ratio's looks kind of tempting
Because 4 times 2 is 8, 5 times 2 is 10,
But it's tricky here because they aren't the same
corresponding sides
In order to use side angle side,
the 2 sides that have the same corresponding ratios
That could be on either side of the angle
So in this case they are aren't on either of the angle
In this case the 4's on one side of the angle
but the 5 is not, the 5 is not
So because if this 5 was over here,
if it was over here then we could make it an argument for similarity
But this 5 not being on the other side of the angle
is not sandwiching the angle with the 4
We can't use side angle side
and frankly there's nothing that we can do over here
So we can't make some strong statement
about similarity for this last one