There is a classic story out there
that has a character named Jack.
You may have heard this story,
but I'm sure that there's a part of that story
that you have not heard.
And so I'm actually gonna try to fill in those parts so that
you get a complete a idea of what happened.
Now, Jack came across, a long time ago,
a famous, now famous, beanstalk.
So this beanstalk has been growing and growing
and have these huge leaves.
And actually Jack used these leaves
to make his way up this beanstalk.
So, this is how this beanstalk became very famous
because it basically allowed Jack to use it like a ladder.
Now, the part that we don't hear about is,
what was going on between Jack and the beanstalk?
He was exercising, right?
He was actually making a lot of carbon dioxide.
He is making a lot of this gas, this carbon dioxide gas,
as kind of a waste product, as he was running,
scampering up the beanstalk.
And the beanstalk was helping him physically,
but also actually providing him with a very precious oxygen.
In fact, if the beanstalk didn't do that,
he may not have even made it.
And we also... We don't know for sure but we think that perhaps
some of the story may have taken place during the day.
And in fact, we know that sunlight is quite important
for this process and we think that
this process... the name that we give it,
for the beanstalk anyway, is photosynthesis.
And so, what is really happening?
I'm actually kind of gonna write it out here,
between Jack and the bean stock? And really,
between all plants and animals?
What is this process between them?
We know that on the one hand,
you have beanstalk doing photosynthesis,
and on the other hand, you have folks like Jack
doing cellular respiration, right?
This is really kind of interesting simbiosis.
And by that, I just mean that the two
are kind of relying on each other
to really work, right? So you kind of need
both of them to work well.
And so, let's actually take a moment to write out
these processes that are happening
between Jack and the beanstalk.
So let's start with the process of photosynthesis, the beanstalk.
So on the one hand, you've got water,
'cause of course the beanstalk needs water.
And you've got carbon dioxide.
I'm gonna do carbon dioxide in orange.
So it's taking in water and carbon dioxide.
And it's going to put out, it's going to take these ingredients,
if you want to think of it as it's kind of cooking,
it's gonna take these ingredients and
it's gonna put out oxygen and glucose.
I'll put glucose at top and oxygen down below.
So these are the inputs and outputs of photosynthesis, right?
And on the other side, you've got something very similar.
You've got inputs, you've got glucose and oxygen going in.
You're gonna see some serious similarities here.
You've got glucose and oxygen going in.
So, Jack is taking in those two things.
And he's again, of course, processing them.
And he's putting out water and carbon dioxide.
So, this looks really really nice, it looks perfect actually because
everything is nice and balance, and you can see
how it makes perfect sense that
not only did Jack need the beanstalk,
but actually it sounds like the beanstalk
needed Jack, based on how I've drawn it.
Now remember, none of this would even happen
if there was no sunlight. So we actually need light energy.
In fact, that's the whole purpose of this, right? Getting energy.
So you have to have some light energy.
I'm gonna put a big plus sign, I might even circle it because
it's so important, I don't you lose track of it.
And on the other side, of course,
Jack is getting something as well.
He's getting chemical energy.
In fact, he's using the chemical energy
to help him climb the beanstalk.
And so the chemical energy comes in
the form of what we call ATP,
which is just a molecule of high energy.
And so, Jack is basically,
or Jack is actually going from light energy to chemical energy,
using these two equations. Now here's the part that
people don't always appreciate.
And I'm actually gonna take just a moment to show you
that this isn't the full story, there's actually
something else going on as well.
And that is that, there is actually
some cellular respiration happening
on the plant side. So remember,
not only does the human or Jack need energy,
but so does the plant, right, the plant
needs energy as well, and in fact,
if it takes in light energy right here,
it needs to find a way to
eventually get some chemical energy itself
so that it can do all the things it needs to do.
You know, it doesn't need to run because
plants don't move in that sense,
but it might need to make new roots, it might need to
make a flower and all these things take energy.
So actually, photosynthesis is happening during the day,
but at all times, plants are also capable of doing cellular respiration,
just like humans are, so humans and plants have actually
more in common than you might think.
So, this brings up an obvious question:
Why in the world would a plant sends
its glucose and oxygen this way where it needs it itself?
You know, why would it actually get rid of it?
Well the truth is that, the glucose ends up often times in
fruits and vegetables that we can eat,
but as far as the oxygen goes,
it makes an excess of oxygen,
so there is actually enough oxygen
to go both to us or to Jack,
and to be used by itself, so it actually has
an excess of oxygen that it's making.
So that's actually kind of interesting, good to know.
Now if you think about it, if I was to...
Let's say sketch out a planet.
Let's draw a little, a planet over here.
And ask you the question, you know,
if this was your planet Earth,
and you've got thousands, instead of just one Jack.
Let's say now you have thousands of Jacks
and thousands of beanstalks.
In fact, not even thousands, let's say, billions,
because really, that's what we have, right?
We have a planet full of humans,
and full of other animals and full of plants.
What would the atmosphere look like? This is the atmosphere.
What would the atmosphere look like? Well, you guess,
that the atmosphere is, you know, gas.
What would those gases be?
???
It looks like I've got lots of oxygen and lots of carbon dioxide. So well,
I guess there must be, I don't know,
maybe 50-50 carbon dioxide and oxygen,
based on what we know so far.
And the truth is, that's actually not true.
If you actually look at air,
you actually kind of break down the atmosphere or air.
I'm gonna write "air" here, you actually break it down.
It turns out that the ratio is actually
a little different, so for example,
oxygen makes up about 21% of our air.
This is our air breakdown. Air.
And carbon dioxide makes up about less than 1%.
So, that leaves you wondering
what the heck is making up all that other
parts of the air? What does it made of?
And it turns out about 78% is nitrogen.
Now you know, you've got nitrogen in your protein,
we've got nitrogen in our DNA; so nitrogen is part of us,
part of, you know, many many living things.
But nitrogen gas specifically is actually N2.
And N2, this nitrogen gas, really, it's not too reactive.
It kinds of just hangs out by itself.
It does not like to react with things.
So, looking at our little atmosphere graph,
you'll now think about it,
knowing that we've got very little carbon dioxide and
you know, about 21% oxygen. You could think of
oxgyen kind of being, let's say something like that,
well then, relative to that, nitrogen would be
you know, much more, right? You have
much more nitrogen hanging out.
And so, this is really what our atmosphere looks like.
It looks more filled with nitrogen than anything else.
And, it turns out that carbon dioxide, it's just got a little ???
maybe right there, that could be carbon dioxide,
maybe even less than that.
So, this is really what our atmosphere looks like visually.
And the nitrogen again, it's making up the majority.
And if you actually kind of wonder
where all that nitrogen is coming from.
'Cause it's not mentioned in any of the equations, right?
Most of the nitrogen has been around...
Scientists think since the beginning of...
When Earth even had an atmosphere.
And that nitrogen was just kind of
carrying with us at all times and
that's why it just kind of remains at 78%.
It will probably remain there for many many years to come.