If we want to get the upside of owning a stock
while still mitigating the downside in case the stock price goes down
We saw that we could buy a stock and an appropriate put option
so that when the stock goes below some price
the put option starts to have value and so it mitigates our downside
And just as a review, these payoff diagrams are the values of, or at least the one on the left,
is the value of holdings at some future date
and we are defining that date to be the maturity date of the options under question
Now, and this one over here is the profit at that maturity date
and that's why we are subtracting the actual costs to enter the position on this one on the right
Now the question I want to answer in this video is, "How can we get the same payoff diagram without buying either stocks or puts?"
and as a bit of a clue, think about what happens if we were to just buy a call option
actually let me do it in that same color
So if you were to just have a call option, the payoff diagram would look like this.
You would never exercise the call option at expiration
unless, and we're assuming this is at expiration or at maturity,
but if the stock price goes above $50, you would then exercise your option to buy it at $50
So then it starts to have value as the stock price goes above $50
If the stock price goes to $60, you would exercise your option to buy at $50 and then you could sell at $60
and you would make $10
So you start to get some of the upside
So how can we shift this graph up to get exactly the same payoff diagram?
Well, we could have a call option and we could own something that would essentially shift this entire graph up by $50
So we could have, essentially, a $50 bond, or a bond that is worth, let me write it this way, a bond that is worth $50 at option expiration
So if there's some interest we're getting, we might be able to buy it for a little bit less
If there's zero interest, then it's pretty much like cash and we would pay $50 for it
But the payoff diagram for a bond that will be worth $50 at this date, at maturity, or at expiration
The payoff diagram for just the bond would look like this. It would just a straight line.
It's guaranteed to pay you $50
So if you own the bond and the call option, below $50 the call option is worthless, so you're just going to have the bond over here
And then, above $50, you still have the bond, but now the call option is worth something
So you have the value of the bond plus the call option
So at $60, the call option is worth $10. The bond is worth $50. The combination is worth $60
And so the combination of the call option plus the bond, you see it here on the left,
it's actually going to have the same payoff diagram as the stock plus the put
So you have the situation here that the stock plus an appropriately priced put
or a put with the appropriate strike price is going to be the same thing
when it comes to payoff at a future date, at expiration, as a bond plus a call option
And this right here is called "Put-Call Parity"
and it shows the relationship between all of these different securities
and if any of these prices start to, kind of, not make this thing hold true, there might be an arbitrage opportunity, but we'll cover that in future videos.