Part D. Let p4(x) be the fourth-degree Taylor polynomial for f about x=0. Using information from the
graph of y= (f^(5) (x)) shown above,and that's the graph right over here. I put it on the side to save space. Show that the absolute value of (p^4(1/4)- f(1/4)) < 1/3000.
So this seems like quite an interesting problem here. So first let's just think about what they asking.
They are asking for the difference between the polynomial and the function evaluated 1/4. In other words,
they are asking us to, they are asking us to bound the error, the error of the function approximation
at, at, at x=1/4. So let me draw a little graph here, just so we can visualize it a little better. So
that's our y- axis, and let me draw it like this. So this is our y- axis, and this is our x-axis. And
our function, lets say our function looks something like this. Our polynomial is centered at zero, our
fourth- degree polynomial is centered at zero and so it will be equal to the function at zero. And then
it will become probably a worse approximation as we get furthur and furthur away from zero. And what
they're saying is bound how bad of an approximation that is when x is equal to 1/4. So, if we say, that
this is, x is equal to 1/4, right over here. They're saying, "Look take the value of the polynomial at
1/4, subtract from that the value of the function at 1/4 and then take the absolute value and that will
essentially give us the absolute value of the error, or give us absolute value of the remainder, or the
distance between the two functions there," and they want us to bound. They want us to bound that distance.
Now to do this problem there is the something that you just kind of have to know, and I prove it another
series of videos two videos, I think.