This is Steven Zucker and Juliana Kreinik.
And we are talking about the "twittering machine" by Paul Klee.
- Or "Zwitschermaschine". - So this is one of my favourite works by Klee and I think
many peoples. Perhaps for me the most fancible ,most playful works of art
I can think of. These little figures which
to me they look like half bird-like creature, half puppet,
half doll, even though you can't have three halfs.
You have these different faces where you can see details if you look really closely
each of them has a sense of individuality. They all seem
a little bit mischievous.
This is the perfect word. They seem mischievous and about to do something.
And you know it is funny because I look at the characters and
then I am thinking what is the "twittering machine"?
Well, he has exposed for us this wonderful kind of mechanical object.
It is drawn in this simplist pen and ink on a kind of watercolor wash
really subtle and lovely but not too finished and still quite
sort of open. But
this fabulous kind of invitation for the viewer
to somehow reach in and turn that handle and to
bring this to life. - You know what I am just thinking of? And I am thinking of
this because Klee is swiss, and I am thinking of this because
it is turning and there is birds, so I am thinking of a cuckoo clock
- You are absolutely right. - Do you think he was maybe creating this sort of inner workings of
of the cuckoo clock deconstructed and sort of turned in on its head? - I think so absolutely.
- Like the birds have been freed. - But here they are freed because this is not about
the mechanics of time, it's not about the structure of time at all, this is
a kind of human-powered machine. We have to reach in to bring this thing to life.
and if it was brought to life, you would get a sense of this chaos
which is completely at odds with the notion of the precision of the Swiss
clock. - Absolutely. It does not have this kind of precision at all.
It is not that kind of machine. It's a machine of frivolity. - Look at the way he has done it.
Because if you look at for instace the shapes that come out of the mouths
or the beaks of these bird. - Yes, they definetly have a beak-like quality. - They do.
Those are different shapes and they almost become
visual signs,they become notations of the sounds that you can imagine
they would be making. It would be a fracas, it would be a kind of
cacophony. But each with a distinct kind of tone.
- So this second figure from right
with this spiral. I feel like
he would make sort of a "boing boing boing" like up and down, and up and down.
- A spring-like sound, yes absolutely.
- Yeh, and you know some of the others
would be like "qwah qwah qwah" and you
know you could sort of imagine
all of this happening
all at once.
- I think that's right.
And you could also imagine sort of
the chaos visually
of how this would look
if you'd pull the handle
because each bird is perched
on sort of a wire that sort of archs
in space. You can get this sense of them
sort of balancing up and down, and sort of
gyringing and maybe that almost bowtie-like
double triangle.
- They must rotate around that.
- Exactly.
- So you'd turn it up and this whole thing spins
around that axis.
- So it's just incredible, it's brilliant.
In an extatic frozen drawing
He has been able to evoke sound
and energy
and motion.
And also an invitation for us to somehow power
the entire image.
As a viewer so often really does.
- It really calls for us to interact with it
and it calls for us to play with it
and it really seems just like an invitation to have fun.
- That is so interesting because Klee
is at the Bauhaus for a year now.
And often when we think of the Bauhaus
we think of something that is slightly dower
something a little serious.
- I think it is very serious.
I think they certainly had a lot of fun.
But even their fun was serious.
Like we must make new things.
And we must have new parties.
And we must find new ways to make trouble.
- And yes, Klee seems to be making trouble
in a just simple and wonderful playful way here.