Part C.
Find all values of "x" on the interval negative 4 is less than "x" is less than 3 for which the graph
of "g" has a point of inflection.
give a reason for your answer.
So, an inflection point is a point where the sign
of the 2nd derivative changes.
So, take the second derivative at that point or as we
go close to that point, or as we cross that point it goes
from positive to negative or negative to positive.
And to think about that visually, you can think of some
examples, so if you have a curve that
looks something like this, you'll notice that over here
the slope is negative, but it's increasing.
It's getting less negative, less negative, then it goes to zero,
then it keeps increasing.
Slope is increasing all the way to there, then it starts
getting less positive.
So it starts decreasing.
So it's increasing, the slope is increasing over this point
right over here, so even though the slope is negative,
it's getting less negative over here. So it's increasing,
and then the slope keeps increasing because it's getting more
and more positive up to about this point, but then the slope
is positive, but then it becomes less positive, so the slope
begins decreasing after that.
So then the slope begins decreasing after that.
So, this right over here is a point of inflection.
The slope has gone from increasing to decreasing, and the
other thing happened- if the slope went from decreasing
to increasing, that would also be a point of inflection.
So if this was maybe some time of a trigometric curve, then
you might see something like this.
And so this also would be a point of inflection.
But for this, g of x is kind of hard to visualize the way
they have defined it right over here.
So, the best way to think about it is just figure out where
it's second derivative has a sign change.
And to think about that, we have to find it's second derivative.
So let's write g of x over here. We know g of x is equal to