So let's say you were walking down the street
and you see this person, this green sickly person
and this person is coughing and sneezing
and you feel really bad for them, they look awful and they must feel awful as well
and the thought that goes through your mind is
How do you avoid getting sick as well?
Because you don't want to feel this way either right?
so you want to think about all the things you can do to make sure that you don't
get sick from this person
So what are some of those things that you might
be able to do to avoid getting sick?
Well let's think through it.
How are you interacting with your environment?
What is the only real way in which you interact?
It's when you touch things right?
You usually have your feet and your body covered up
But your hands are always exposed and always kinda touching things
and then you usually turn around and touch your mouth, your eyes, your face.
So two real quick things you can do to try to prevent getting sick
are simply making sure that you wash your hands
and that's why you always hear that message
Wash your hands after you go to the bathroom
before you eat, and that's the reason why
And the other key message is don't touch your face
You want to make sure you avoid your mouth your eyes your nose
because that's where the viruses get into your body
So don't touch your face.
So these are two really good ideas, right?
But are some others? What else can you do?
Well you can try
But this isn't always possible. Well you can try to avoid the person altogether
You can try and just kind of move away.
You can make some distance over here so you are further away from this person
And that's another possible strategy
And like I said it doesn't always work but
when you can avoid someone that's always a good idea
So avoid sick people
And finally, and this one is going to be the main point of this video
Is you can actually get vaccinated.
You can get a vaccine that will actually prevent you from getting ill
So, flu vaccine is something that a lot of people
have strong feelings about
and the first thing I want to point out
is on this list of prevention, it is probably the most important
It is the most effective way of preventing, of getting sick from the flu
So certainly think about it
But if you're gonna think about it
You want to think critically about doing something like this
you want to make sure that it is a good idea
Do we really have any evidence that it really does help?
Or is it the opposite?
Does flu vaccine actually make you more sick? Does it give you the flu?
So let's talk about that
Think through how the vaccine works and what we know about it?
There is some research that has been done on flu vaccine
I'm going to present you with what we've learned so far.
A group out of the University of Michigan came along
and they said "Let's figure out the answer to whether vaccine is a good idea"
Let's actually take, start over here on the left side
Let's take an injection and fill it with salt water
So this is regular old salt water
or something very similar to it and it has no real effect at all
In fact sometimes people call this a placebo, I'll write that over here
So that's one side
On the other side let's actually come up with a vaccine
and this vaccine that I'm going to draw out looks basically the same
It's also an injection
And this injection is full of DEAD virus.
They literally take live virus, remember live virus has an envelope
and it has RNA on the inside, I'm going to sketch that out
And what they do is they actually have different ways of killing it.
They literally just destroy this thing
And just like human beings, if you're killed you cannot come back to life
And a virus is the same way
Once a virus is dead it is dead forever.
So this dead virus is lying here on its side
Completely and utterly dead , right?
And this dead virus, they take it and they put it into the vaccine
So this is what is in the vaccine, this is our flu vaccine
Let me label it over here, Flu vaccine
So two groups of people then are going to get two different types of injections
And they also had 100's and 100's of people involved in this study
But I'm only going to show you a representative slice.
So let's say this is 100 people over here and that's a grid
So each square represents one person
And there is 100 people over here.
They don't know which vaccine they're going to get
They don't know if they're getting the salt water
or the flu vaccine
They're what we call "blinded" in this study
And I should also tell you that these people are very healthy
and they're young adults so they're between 18 and 49 years old
They're healthy and the two groups are fairly similar
in terms of the amount of the number of men and women in each group
their age breakdowns and the two side are fairly similar
So these two groups get the salt water or the flu and they don't know which is which
and they're told over the course of 6 months over the course of the flu season
to keep track of illnesses and if they get flu I'm going to sketch them out in red
What they actually did is they said if you get the flu let us know and we will confirm it
Actually do a lab test to make sure it really is the flu and not just some other illness
that you think you have. So they actually took all these people that said they have the flu
and I'm only going to draw them in red if they were confirmed by PCR
that was the lab technique they used
So these are PCR confirmed so that's laboratory confirmed
illness with flu
So this is people with PCR confirmed illness
And you can count them out. Out of 100 people in the first group, in the salt water group
we had a total of 10 individuals. So that 10% percent of these folks were ill with the flu
over the flu season
And on the flu vaccine side we also had some people sick with the flu
So that is the first thing you should know is that the flu vaccine does not prevent you 100% from getting the flu
But look at how many people I shaded in.
In the placebo side I said there were 10 out of 100 people that got sick
and on the flu vaccine side only about 3 out of 100 people got sick.
And both, I should put arrows on both sides, were PCR confirmed.
So what does this mean? How do you take this and make some sense out of it?
There is a term called Vaccine Efficacy
And what it refers to is how good is the vaccine at preventing you from getting sick
So this is the term vaccine efficacy and sometimes you might even see the term VE
Sometimes people use VE for vaccine efficacy
And the way you calculate it, you say
VE equals the proportion of people that got sick
with the salt water, that was 10 out of 100
minus the proportion that got sick with the flu vaccine, so minus 3 out of a hundred
and you divide by the group that did not get vaccine
and so you can take this and you can simplify it
you say this is basically 7 over 100
divided by 10 over 100. And you can make it even simpler by cancelling the 100's out
And this is seven tenths (7/10)
And to make a percent out of it you multiply 7/10ths by 100 %
So if I were to describe the VE or the vaccine efficacy based on this study
I would say well flu has a 70% vaccine efficacy
So you see how we got that number. It's fairly simple
Just comparing the two groups to each other. And there have been many studies on the flu
And the CDC took all this data and they said well in general the VE
or the vaccine efficacy for the flu vaccine is usually between 60 and 70 %
That's kind of the number they usually quote for this vaccine
So take that number, 60 to 70 % VE
I'm going to write that down here
so we don't lose track of what that is
And lets take it back up here to our little example
We said that there are a few ways to try to prevent the flu
And if I imagine now that there is a force field around me
Let's say there is a little purple force field around me
And this force field protects me from germs.
I'm going to show germs kind of coming in and bouncing off my force field.
Well this would be really accurate if I was describing 100% vaccine efficacy
meaning if I get the vaccine I am completely unable to get sick.
But we know that is not true. That it is actually closer to 60 to 70 %
So for 60 to 70%
Let me show you what you can kind of change this picture to look like.
Instead of making it completely impenetrable you can just draw a few holes in it.
So a few holes there, maybe a hole there, and maybe a hole down here.
So now you can show a few of the germs kind of breaking through and getting in.
Maybe getting in over here. But many of them actually still kind of bounce off
And so you are still protected by a lot of the germs but some of them can still get you sick.
Probably the best way to avoid getting sick is to get your vaccine
but still make sure you wash your hands
Don't touch your face and avoid sick people