Let's imagine that this is you,
and you are headed home for the holidays.
So you board a plane.
And you notice, while you're on this plane,
that the people around you are pretty sick.
The guy next to looks like he has a fever –
maybe the flight attendant is coughing.
So you head on home.
Although you're excited to see
everybody in your family,
you are feeling completely run down.
So, you decide to head to bed,
hoping you'll feel better tomorrow.
Unfortunately, you don't feel better the next day.
You have a very high fever.
You don't even have the strength
to get out of bed for a few days.
And when you finally start to feel better,
you notice that you're not the only person
in your house who is sick.
Your dad is sick.
Your mom is sick, as well –
maybe some of your siblings.
You call your best friend.
They are sick, and their entire family is sick.
Maybe you talk to a neighbor,
and someone on your street, you learn,
has died from this illness.
And news reports say that this is not
unique to your town – but it's happening
all over the state, and all over the country.
Now, this is a really scary situation.
But, unfortunately, it's not one that is
out of the realm of possibility.
In 1918 and 1919,
this was a particularly bad influenza season.
In fact, it was so bad that it led to approximately
50 to 100 million deaths worldwide.
And this is a pretty famous picture
from that era of a makeshift hospital.
There were so many sick people
during this flu season, that hospitals
couldn't provide enough beds and resources
for the patients who needed them.
Even during a so-called regular flu season,
every year, the influenza virus causes a lot of damage.
Flu is a top-10 killer in the United States.
And it leads to approximately
200,000 hospitalizations every year,
due to complications of influenza infections.
In addition to the 200,000 hospitalizations
that we have every year in this country,
approximately 20 to 40 thousand people
die every single year.
20,000 to 40,000 deaths on an annual basis.
So you can see that influenza
is not something to be taken lightly –
that it can lead to very serious consequences.
But luckily, there is something that can be done.
In fact, there's something that you can do about this.
As someone who's taking this training,
you're learning how to vaccinate
people in your community.
The modern influenza vaccine
is approximately 70% effective
in preventing influenza infection.
And so this is a great way to help prevent illness and death.