Let's divide 3771 by 8.
So I'm going to do a little bit of long division so the way we set it up.
So the first we want to do and to think about: Well, does 8 go into 3?
Well, no, 8 does not go into 3 so we'll keep moving.
Does 8 go into 37?
Sure, 8 times 4 is 32. (8 times 5 is 40 so that's too big)
So 8 goes into 37 four times.
4 times 8 is 32 and we subtract and we get 37 minus 32 is 5.
And just so you have a little glimpse of what's actually going on here:
We're really saying, how many times this 8 go into 3700.
And we're saying that it goes into the 3700 four hundred times as 4 is sitting in the hundreds place.
And that 400 times 8 is 3200 and then we subtract 3200 from 3700, we're getting 500.
But we'll revert back just to traditional long division mechanisc.
But that's what's really going on here:
When we say: "8 goes into 37 four times.", we're really saying: "8 goes into 3700 four hundred times."
But let's keep going.
So now we have this 5 to deal with (which is as we already talked about it, it's in the hundreds place so it's really a 500.)
But now let's bring down another place value.
So let's bring down the 7 and let's think about how many times does 8 go into 57.
(And we're really thinking about how much the 8 goes into 570.)
But 8 goes into 57... let's see. 8 times 5 is 40, 8 times 6 is 48, 8 times 7 is 54.
So let's go 7 times.
7 times 8, we've already (Oh, actually I did that wrong)...
8 times 7 (my multiplication tables are weak!) it is... so does go into seven times,
but 7 times 8 isn't 54, it's 56.
(I always have trouble with that one.)
It is 56.
And so now we subtract again.
And 57 minus 56 is 1. And now we have one more place value to bring down.
We have (let me do that in a color I haven't used yet... I'll do blue.) a 1 to bring down.
And now we're literally saying: "How many times does 8 go into 11?"
Well, 8 goes into 11 one time, 1 times 8 is 8
and we are left with (because we have no more places to bring down): 11 minus 8 is 3.
So 8 goes into 3771 four hundred seventy one times and the remainder here is 3.