Write the following numbers as complex numbers.
And just as a little review.
A complex number is a number that has a real part or an imaginary part.
Actually, let me make that clear--
has a real part and an imaginary part.
So if I have a plus bi, where a is real and b is real, this is a complex number.
This part right here is the real part.
And this part right here is imaginary.
And why is it imaginary? Because it is a scaled up version of this special number.
The imaginary unit. This special number "i." Scaled up by b, in this case.
And you may or may not already be familiar with it--I know it's kind of whacky.
But, the definition of i says that i squared is equal to negative one.
Hey, we didn't have any numbers before where if we took the square, we get negative one.
Now, if you take i squared, you get negative one.
So what's neat about imaginary numbers is that their squares are negative.
And what's useful about them is that it allows us to solve a bunch of equations
that we couldn't have solved if you're only looking for real solutions.
It has all sorts of implications. In Engineering, especially.
And other things, like physics, and all the rest.
So right now, you really just have to go with this definition.
And as we do more numbers, and especially as you start to see some more engineering applications,
hopefully you'll realize the value of imaginary numbers.
So going back to the problem, write the following numbers as complex numbers.
So this number is just a plain vanilla negative 21.
Well how do I write it as a complex number?
I write it as a combination of a real and an imaginary number.
So I could just write this as negative twenty-one plus zero times i.
Zero times i is zero, so it's still just going to be negative twenty-one.
We have no imaginary part, really. So this is just a complex version of it.
Very straightforward.
Same thing down here.
Seven times i is in imaginary number, so there's no real part to this.
The real part is just zero.
This is zero plus seven i.