[MUSIC]
What I want to do in this
video is explain what a
mortgage is.
I think most of us have at least
a general sense of it,
but even better than that,
actually go into to the
numbers and understand a little
bit of what you are
actually doing when you're
paying a mortgage, what it's
made up of, and how much of it
is interest verses how much of
it is actually paying
down the loan.
So let's just start with
a little example.
Let's say that there is a house
that I like that I would
like to purchase.
It has a price tag of--
I need to pay
$500,000 to buy that house.
This is the seller of the house
right here, and they
have a moustache.
I would like to buy it.
This is me right here, and
I've been able to save up
$125,000 but I would really like
to live in that house.
So I go to a bank, and I say,
Mr. Bank, can you lend me the
rest of the amount I need
for that house, which is
essentially $375,000?
I'm putting 25% down, this
number right here that is 25%
of $500,000.
So I ask the bank, can I have
a loan for the balance?
Can I have a $375,000 loan?
And the bank says, sure, you
seem like a nice guy with a
good job who has good credit
rating, I will give you the
loan but while you're paying
off the loan you can't have
the title of that house.
We have to have that title of
the house and once you pay off
the loan, we're going to give
you the title of the house.
So what's going to happen here
is we're going to have-- the
loan is going to go to
me, so it's $375,000.
Then I can go and
by the house.
So I'm going to give the total
$500,000 to the seller of the
house and I'll actually move
into the house myself,
assuming I'm using it for
my own residence.
But the title of the house,
the document that says who
actually owns the house-- so
this is the home title-- it
will not go to me, it
will go to the bank.
The home title will go from the
seller, or maybe even the
seller's bank, because maybe
they haven't paid off their
mortgage, to the banking that
I'm borrowing from.
And this transferring of the
title to secure a loan, when I
say secure a loan, I'm saying,
look, I need to give something
to the lender in case I don't
pay back the loan
or if I just disappear.
So this is the security
right here.
That is technically what
a mortgage is.
This pledging of the title as
the security for the loan,
that's what a mortgage is.
And actually it comes from Old
French mort means dead and to
gage means pledge.
I'm 100% sure I'm mispronouncing
it, but it
comes from dead pledge because
I'm pledging it now, but that
pledge will eventually die
once I pay off the loan.
Once I pay off this loan, this
pledge of the title to the
bank will die and it'll
come back to me.
And that's why it's called a
dead pledge or mortgage.
And probably because it comes
from Old French is the reason
why we don't say more mort
gage, we say mortgage.
But anyway, this is a little
bit technical, but normally
when people refer to a mortgage,
they're really
referring to the loan itself.
They're really referring
to the mortgage loan.
And what I want to do in the
rest of this video is use a
little screen shot from a
spreadsheet I made to actually
show you the math or actually
show you what your mortgage
payment is going to.
And you can download this
spreadsheet sheet at
khanacademy.org/
downloads/mortgagecalculator.
Actually, even better, just go
the downloads folder and on
your web browser you'll see a
bunch of files and it'll be
the file called
mortgagecalculator.xls, so
it's a Microsoft 2007 format.
So just go to this URL and then
you'll see all the files
there and you can just download
this file if you want
to play with it.
But what it does here, in this
kind of dark brown color,
these are the assumptions that
you can input and you can
change these cells in your
spreadsheet without breaking
the whole spreadsheet.
So here I assumed the
5.5% interest rate.
I'm buying a $500,000 home.
It's a 25% down payment, so
that's the $125,000 that I had
saved up that I talked about
right over there.
And then the loan amount, well,
I have $125,000, I'm
going to have to borrow
$375,000.
It calculates it for us and then
I'm going to get a pretty
plain vanilla loan, this is
going to be a 30-year, so when
I say term in years this
is how long the loan
is for, so 30 years.
It's going to be a 30-year
fixed rate
mortgage fixed rate.
Which means the interest
rate won't change.
We'll talk about that
in a little bit.
This 5.5% that I'm paying on the
money that I borrow will
not change over the course
of the 30 years.
We will see the amount I've
borrowed changes as I pay down
some of the loan.
And this little tax rate that
I have here, this is to
actually figure out what is
the tax savings of the
interest deduction on my
loan, and we'll talk
about that in a second.
You can ignore it for now.
And these other things that
aren't in brown, you shouldn't
mess with these, if you actually
do open up the
spreadsheet yourself.
These are automatically
calculated.
And this right here is the
monthly interest rate.
So it's literally the annual
interest rate,
5.5% divided by 12.
And most mortgage loans are
compounded on a monthly basis.
So at the end of every month,
they see how much money you
owe and then they will charge
you this much interest on that
for the month.
Now given all these assumptions,
there's a little
bit of behind-the-scenes math,
and in a future video I might
actually show you how to
calculate what the actual
mortgage payment is.
It's actually a pretty
interesting problem.
But for a $500,000 house, a
$375,000 loan, over 30 years
at a 5.5% interest rate, my
mortgage payment is going to
be roughly $2,100.
Now, right when I bought the
house-- I want to introduce a
little bit of vocabulary, and
we've talked about this in
some of the other videos.
There's an asset in question
right here,
it's called a house.
And we're assuming that
it's worth $500,000.
We're assuming it's worth
$500,000, that is an asset.
It's an asset because it gives
you future benefit, the future
benefit of being able
to live in it.
Now there's a liability against
that asset, that's the
mortgage loan.
That's a $375,000 liability.
A $375,000 loan or debt.
So if this was your balance
sheet, if this was all of your
assets and this is all of your
debt, and if you were
essentially to sell the assets
and pay off the debt-- if you
sell the house you get the
title, you can get the money
then you pay it back
to the bank.
Well, actually it doesn't
necessarily go into that
order, but I won't
get to technical.
But if you were to unwind this
transaction immediately after
doing it, then you would have
a $500,000 house, you'd pay
off your $375,000 in debt, and
you would get in your pocket
$125,000, which is exactly
what your original down
payment was.
But this is your equity, and the
reason why I'm pointing it
out now is-- in this video,
I'm not going to assume
anything about the house price
whether it goes up or down.
We're assuming it's constant.
But you could not assume it's
constant and play with the
spreadsheet a little bit.
But I'm introducing this
because, as we pay down the
debt, this number is going
to get smaller.
So this number is
getting smaller.
Let's say at some point
this is only $300,000.
Then my equity is going
to get bigger.
So you can kind view equity as
how much value do you have
after you pay off the
debt for your house.
If you were to sell the house,
pay off the debt, what do you
have leftover for yourself?
So this is the real wealth
in the house.
This is what do you own, wealth
in house or the actual
what the owner has.
Now, what I've done here is--
well, actually before I get to
the chart, let me actually
show you how I
calculate the chart.
And I do this over the course
of 30 years and it goes by
month, so you can imagine that
there's actually 360 rows here
on the actual spreadsheet,
you'll see that if you go in
and open it up.
But I just want to show
you what I did.
So on month zero, which
I don't show here,
you borrowed $375,000.
Now, over the course of that
month, they're going to charge
you 0.46% interest. Remember,
that was 5.5% divided by 12.
0.46% interest on $375,000
is $1,718.75.
So I haven't made any mortgage
payments yet.
So I borrowed $375,000, this
much interest essentially got
built up on top of that,
it got accrued.
So now before I pay any of my
payments, instead of owing
$375,000 at the end of the first
month, I owe $376,718.
Now, I'm a good guy, I'm not
going to default on my
mortgage, so I make that first
mortgage payment that we
calculated right over here.
So after I make that payment,
then what's my loan balance
after making that payment?
Well, this was before making the
payment, so you subtract
the payment from it,
this is my loan
balance after the payment.
Now this right here with a
little asterisk here, this is
my equity now.
So remember, I started with
a $125,000 of equity.
After paying one loan balance,
after my first payment, I now
have a $125,410 in equity.
So my equity has gone
up by exactly $410.
Now you're probably saying,
hey, gee, I made a $2,000
payment and my equity only
went up by $410.
Shouldn't this debt have gone
down by $2,000 and my equity
have gone up by $2,000?
And the answer is no, because
you have to pay all of this
interest. So in the beginning,
your payment, your $2,000
payment is mostly interest. Only
$410 of it is principal.
But as your loan balance goes
down, you're going to pay less
interest here, and so each of
your payments are going to be
more weighted towards principal
and less weighted
towards interest. And then to
figure out the next line, this
interest accrued right here, I
took my loan balance exiting
the last month, multiply that
times 0.46%, you get this new
interest accued.
This is your new pre-payment
balance.
I pay my mortgage again, this
is my new loan balance.
And notice, already by month
two, $2 more went to
principal, and $2 dollars less
went to interest. And over the
course of 360 months, you're
going to see that it's an
actual sizable difference.
And that's what this chart
shows us right here.
This is the interest and
principal portions of our
mortgage payment.
So this entire height right
here-- let me scroll down a
little bit-- this is by month,
so this entire height, you
notice, this is exactly our
mortgage payment, this $2,129.
Now, on that very first month
you saw that of my $2,100,
only $400 of it went to
actually pay down the
principal, the actual
loan amount.
The rest of it went to pay down
interest, the interest
for that month.
Most of it went for the
interest of the month.
But as I start paying down the
loan, as the loan balance gets
smaller and smaller, each of
my payments, there's less
interest to pay-- let me do it
the better color than that.
Let's say we go out here,
this is month 198.
Over there, that last month,
there was less interest. So
more of my $2,100 actually goes
to pay off the loan until
we get all the way to month 360,
and you could see this in
the actual spreadhseet, at month
360 my final payment is
all going to pay off
the principal.
Very little, if anything,
of that is interest.
Now, the last thing I want to
talk about in this video,
without making it too long,
is this idea of a
interest tax deduction.
So a lot of times, you'll hear
financial planners and
Realtors tell you, hey, the
benefit of buying your house
is that it has tax advantages,
and it does.
Your interest is
tax-deductible.
Your interest, not your
whole payment.
And I want to be very clear
what deductible means.
So first let's talk about
what interest means.
So this whole time over 30
years, I am paying $2,100 a
month or $2,129.29.
Now in the beginning, a lot of
that is interest. So on month
one, $1,700 of that was
interest. That $1,700 is
tax-deductible.
Now, as we go further and
further each month, I get a
smaller and smaller
tax-deductible portion of my
actual mortgage payment.
Out here, the tax deduction is
actually very small as I'm
getting ready to pay off my
entire mortgage and get the
title of my house.
Now I want to be very clear
on this notion of what
tax-deductible even means,
because I think it is
misunderstood very often.
Let's say in one year, I paid,
I don't know-- I'm going to
make up a number, I didn't
calculate it on the
spreadsheet.
Let's say in year one, I pay
$10,000 in interest. Remember,
my actual payments will be
higher than that, because some
of my payments went to actually
paying down the loan,
but let's say $10,000 went to
interest. And let's say before
this, I was making a $100,000
a year-- and let's put the
loan aside-- let's say I was
making $100,000 a year and
let's say I was paying roughly
35% on that $100,000.
I won't go into the whole tax
structure and the different
brackets and all of that.
Let's say, you know, if I didn't
have this mortgage, I
would pay 35% taxes, which
would be about $35,000 in
taxes for that year.
This is just a rough estimate.
Now, when you say that $10,000
is tax-deductible, the
interest is tax-deductible, that
does not mean that I can
just take it from the $35,000
that I would have normally
owed and only pay $25,000.
What it means is I can deduct
this amount from my income.
So when I tell the IRS how much
did I make this year,
instead of saying $100,000,
I say that I made $90,000
because I was able to deduct
this, not directly from my
taxes, I was able to deduct
it from my income.
So now if I only made $90,000
and-- I'm doing a gross
over-simplification of how
taxes actually get
calculated-- and I pay 35%
of that, let's get
the calculator out.
So 90 times 0.35 is
equal to 31,500.
So this will be equal
to $31,500.
So off of a $10,000 deduction,
a deductible interest, I
essentially saved $3,500.
I did not save $10,000.
So another way to think about it
is, I pay $10,000 interest
and my tax rate is 35%, I'm
going to save 35% percent of
this in actual taxes.
This is what people mean when
they say deductible, you're
deducting it from the income
that you report to the IRS.
If there's something that you
actually could take straight
from your taxes, that's
called a tax credit.
So if there was some special
thing that you could actually
deduct it straight from your
taxes, that's a tax credit.
But a deduction just takes
it from your income.
And so on this spreadsheet, I
just want to show you that I
actually calculated in that
month how much of a tax
deduction do you get.
So, for example, just off of
the first month, you paid
$1,700 in interest of your
$2,100 mortgage payment.
So 35% of that, and I got
the 35% as one of your
assumptions, 35% of $1,700, I
will save $600 in taxes on
that month.
So roughly over the course of
the first year, I'm going to
save about $7,000 in taxes.
So that's nothing
to sneeze at.
Anyway, hopefully you found this
helpful, and I encourage
you to go to that spreadsheet
and play with the assumptions,
only the assumptions in this
brown color unless you really
know what you're doing with the
spreadsheet, and you can
see how this actually changes
based on different interest
rates, different loan amounts,
different down payments,
different terms, different
tax rates.
That'll actually change the tax
savings and you can play
around with the different types
of fixed mortgages on
this spreadsheet.
[MUSIC]