We're asked to graph the function f(x)
is equal to the principle square route of .5x-1
And to graph it we're going to just sample some points
some x values that are within the domain of this function,
this function definition, and see what the function is equal to
for those x values, and then we can connect those dots
and see what the curve will look like
So, let me do a little table here, and so I'm going
to pick some x-values, and I'm going to figure out what
the f(x) values are given those x values
And actually, I'm going to do something in between
because I want to have nice, clean numbers
I want to pick x-values that are nice clean integers
and I want to get f(x) values that are nice clean integers
So I'm going to be a little bit more careful
in what x values I pick.
I wanna pick x values so that this part of the expression
this part of the function definition
ends up being an integer
and if this needs to be an integer, then what's underneath
the radical, that .5x
that needs to be a perfect square
So, let me make another column over here
just to make our math a little bit cleaner
You could pick just arbitrary x-points
you could pick x to be 1, 2, 3, just go like that
but on some of those you might get strange radicals
over here, which might be hard to graph without a calculator
So let's try so let me write over here what 0.5x is
And I'm doing this just so that I can pick this
we want this thing over here
to be perfect squares
because if 0.5x is a perfect square, than the square root
of that is going to be an integer
So let's say that 0.5, let's think about all
of the perfect squares, you can start at 0, then you
could go to 1, then we could go to: 2 isn't a perfect
square, 3 isn't a perfect square,
I'm just thinking of all the values where if I took the
square root, I'd get an integer
And then I go to 4, then I go to 9, then I go to 16
and then I go to 25.
These are the first five perfect squares, obviously
with 0, if you take the principle square root of that you get
zero. So these would be good values for
.5x. But if those are what .5x is equal to, what is
x going to be? So, if 0.5x is 0, then x
is also going to be 0. You could solve that
separately over in an equation right over here
you could say 0.5x is equal to 0,
x is equal to 0 divided by .5, just divide both sides
by .5, and you get that equal to 0.
So in general, to get what the x-value is, we
jsut have to take this number and divide it by .5
or another way of thinking of that is just taking
this number and multiplying it by two.