In the last video, using the accrual basis for accounting
we had $200 of income in month 2,
but over that same month, we saw that we went
from having $100 in cash, to having negative $100
in cash, so we actually lost $200 in cash.
So how can we reconcile the fact that
it looks like we made $200 in income,
but we lost $200 in cash?
And that reconciliation is going to be done
with the cash flow statement.
So most cash flow statements, they'll start
so I'm going to do a cash flow statement right over here
So they'll start with your net income
or actually they'll start with the cash that you started out with
so they take you from
this cash balance to that cash balance.
So they'll say something like
Starting cash, we know is $100
And then they'll say well in the most naive
interpretation of things, you net income
in theory should be the cash you're getting
or at least it's some type of profit
you're getting assets in the door
or at least you're counting as if you're
getting some assets in the door.
So then you're having, you have your
net income, your net income during the period.
And here we'll literally just take whatever is
reported from the income statement.
So over there we get $200 net income,
and now we have to do the reconciliation part
because if this was all that you were getting,
then you should have $300 cash at the end of the period
which we clearly don't have,
so we have to reconcile by looking at the changes
in different things on the balance sheet.
So over here we have a net change
in accounts receivable. So we have an increase
in accounts receivable.
So I'll call it AR increase
AR is short for accounts receivable, just to save some space
So let's just think about it,
when you have an increase in account receivable,
you're kind of letting people owe you money
you're letting people owe you $400
if you didn't let them owe you,
that would have been cash,
so you're kind of pushing back the time
that you're getting cash.
This is $400 that you didn't get
that you could have gotten
if you didn't allow, I guess, this person to delay
when they paid you.
So an increase in accounts receivables is
actually less cash than you would have otherwise gotten
so this is negative $400 for your cash flow.
And we had no other changes, we haven't even addressed
accounts payable, that's essentially pushing back,
owing people, paying other people, paying your vendors money,
but I don't even address that in the previous example.
No other changes in our liabilities, so this is
the only adjustment we make. And so if we do this,
and sometimes this will be called a use of cash,
or a subtraction from, there's different ways
it can be phrased in different contexts,
but over here you'll have your net cash
from operations. Cash from operations, I'll say ops,
and over here you can see, when you add it all
just the cash from operations
$200 minus $400, so I'm just adding this part right over here,
you have negative $200
and so your starting cash is $100,
you have negative $200 cash from operations,
and this is what you would have also gotten
if you had done cash accounting,
you would have negative $200 cash from operations,
and then, if you start with $100, you use $200
in cash, your ending cash will be negative $100.
So this little thing that I just created here,
this little reconciliation between the positive $200 in income
and the negative $200 of cash,
it's showing how we got
from this starting point in cash to this ending point.
This is a cash flow statement, so you now know the 3 major financial statements.