Solve for x and y and we have the system of equations right here we have 2x-5 is equal to 14
and negative 6x + 3y is equal to negative 42.
so we could try to solve this by elimination and maybe we want to
let's see if we can eliminate our y variables first. We have a 3y here and a negative y up here
and we could it won't eliminate if you just add 3y plus negative y
that won't eliminate but if we could turn this negative y into a -3y then it would cancel out
with the 3y and the best way to turn a negative y into a -3y is to multiply this entire top equation
by 3
so lets do that, let's multiply then we can get some space over on the left
let's multiply this entire top equation
by 3 so we're going to multiply by three. So when I multiply 2x by three I get 6x
when I multiply -y by three I get -3y and then i multiply 14 by three
3 times 14 is 42 right? 3 times 10 is thirty plus 12 is 42
and then we can add both of these equations something interesting should already maybe be showing up on
your radar but let's add both of these equations. I have the left hand side
-6x+6x well those cancel out we get 0
we have 3y minus 3y those cancel out so you get another 0
and then finally we get -42 plus 42 well that's 0 so we end up with just 0=0
which is clearly true which is clearly true, but it's not putting any constraints on the x or y
and that's because whenever you have a situation like this where you just get something that's obviously
true 0=0, 1=1 or 5=5 what we're dealing with in this situation is where both of our constraints,
both of our equations are actually the same equation and this right here is a dependent system
this is a dependent system
when you see it right over here and you multiply it by 3 you got 6x-3y is equal to 42
if we then multiply it by -1 you would get the exact same equation as the second equation
you would get -6x plus 3y is equal to -42.
Another way to think about it if you want to go from the first equation to the second equation
you just multiply both sides of the equation by -3
so both of these constraints are the same constraints. they're just kind of a scaled up multiple of eachother
so if you were to graph them and I might as well just graph them for you
right here, this first equation right here is 2x-y is equal to 14.
so you subtract 2x from both sides, and you would get on the left hand side:
you're left with just -y on the right hand side you have negative 2x + 14
now multiply both sides by negative one and you get y=2x-14