What we're going to go over
in this video is
one of the core principles
in Calculus,
and you're going to use it anytime
you take the derivative
of anything even reasonably complex.
And it's called the chain rule.
And when you're first exposed to it
it can seem a little daunting
and a little bit convoluted,
but as you see more and more examples
it will start to make sense
and hopefully it will even start to seem
a little bit simple and intuitive over time.
So let's say that I had a function.
Let's say I have a function, h of x.
And it is equal to,
just for example,
let's say it's equal to
sine of x -
let's say it's equal to sine of x,
squared.
Now I could have written that,
I could have written it like this:
sine squared of x,
but it will be a little bit clearer using,
using that type of notation.
So let me make it so I have h of x.
And what I'm curious about is,
what is h prime of x?
So I want to know h prime of x,
which another way of writing it is
the derivative of h
with respect to x -
these are just different notations -
and to do this I am going to use the chain rule.
I am going to use the chain rule.
The chain rule comes into play any time
your function can be viewed as a composition
of more than one function,
and that might not seem obvious right now
but it will hopefully maybe by the end of this video
or the next one.
Now what I want to do is
a little bit of a thought experiment.
If I were to ask you what is the derivative,
with respect to x,
if I were just to apply the derivative operator
to x squared with respect to x,
what do I get?
Well this gives me two x.
We've seen that many, many, many, many times.
Now what if I were to take the derivative
with respect to a of a squared?
Well it's the exact same thing.
I just swapped an a for the x's.
This is still going to be equal to two a.
Now I will do something
that might be a little bit more bizarre -
What if I were to take the derivative
with respect to sine of x
with respect to sine of x,
of sine of x,
sine of x, squared?
Well, wherever I have the x's up here
or the a's over here
I just replace it with the sine of x.
So this is just going to be two times the thing that I had.
So whatever I'm taking the derivative with respect to -
here it was with respect to x,
here is was with respect to a
here's with respect to sine of x.
So it's going to be two times sine of x.
So the chain rule tells us
that this derivative is going to be
the derivative of our whole function with respect,
or the derivative of this outer function,
x squared, the derivative of x squared,
the derivative of this outer function
with respect to sine of x,
so that is going to be two sine of x -
two sine of x -
so we can view it as the derivative of
the outer function with respect to the inner,
two sine of x,
we can just treat sine of x like it's kind of an "x"
and it would have been two x,
but instead it's a sine of x.
And we say, two sine of x
times, times the derivative of sine of x
with respect to x -
times the derivative of sine of x with respect to x.
Well that's more straight forward
and a little bit more intuitive.
The derivative of sine of x with respect to x,
we've seen multiple times,
is cosine of x.
So times cosine of x.
And so there we've applied the chain rule
There's the derivative of the outer function
with respect to the inner,
so derivative of sine of x, squared
with respect to sine of x
is two sine of x,
and then we multiply that times the derivative
of sine of x with respect to x.
So let me make it clear -
this right over here
is the derivative -
we're taking the derivative of
sine of x, squared.
So let me make it clear -
that's what we're taking the derivative of
with respect to sine of x
and then we're multiplying that
times the derivative of sine of x
the derivative of sine of x
with respect to x.
And this is where it might start making
a little bit of intuition.
You can't really treat these differentials,
this d whatever, this d x, this d sin of x,
as a number.
And you really can't -
the notation makes it look like a fraction
because intuitively that's what we're doing.
But if you were to treat them like fractions,
then you could think about canceling that and that.
And once again, this isn't a rigorous thing to do,
but it can help with the intuition -
and then what you're left with is the derivative
of this whole sine of x squared with respect to x.
So you're left with,
you're left with
the derivative of essentially our original function
sine of x, squared, with respect to x.
Which is exactly what dh/dx is.
This right over here is
our original function, h.
That's our original function, h.
So it might seem a little bit daunting now.
What I'll do in the next video
is another several examples
and then we'll try to abstract this a little bit.