Let's think a little bit about why credit default swaps are
famously referred to by Warren Buffet as FInancial Weapons of mass destruction
At the center of it, and there is not one Credit Default Swap writer
but I will put one in the middle because each of them are writing many many
Credit default swaps, AIG is the most famous, but you have some writer here
they are given some good credit rating.
May be in the past the credit rating was actually earned in the past by a credit rating agency.
And then frankly the credit rating agency got a litlte sloppy and really didn't
wasn't willing to downgrade them given all of them Credit default swaps all of the obligations they are taking on.
Credit Rating Agencies, as you could tell, I kind of view these guys and these guys as a main culprits
and may be a little bit of the regulatory agencies saying, Hey look these guys are writing insurance, may be we should actually regulate them.
But with that said, you have companies over here, I will do the companies in this pink color,
and they want to borrow money from the other parties.
Lets say investors, I will do the investors in this orange color, so the investors are lending them money
The companies gives them interest.
So investors lending money, giving interest.
lending money, giving interest, lending money, giving interest.
And then these investors, and seems pretty reasonable, says hey look, there's this guy over here with a
double AA rating, the people we're lending to don't have a AA rating.
This guy has a B, may be this guy has a BB, may be this guy only has a singe A,
and so he says hey look, I want to be completely safe here so I am gonna pay a little bit of premium
to AIG, or to the writer, whoever the writer is
and in exchange I will get insurance. I will get insurance on, on this debt
I will get insurance
insurance. And it seems pretty reasonable
except for the fact that this player right over here
did not put out any money aside or did not put an appropriate amount of money aside
to properly account for all of these liabilities, all of these risks that is taking on
and also all of these risks are correlated.
You can imagine a situation where the economy goes bad. Now all of a sudden
this company defaults on its debt and this company defaults on its debt
In fact when the economy is good is likely that very few of these companies is going to default and when the economy goes bad
is likely that many of them will default.
But the real problem is that as soon as these defaults start happening then the credit default swap writer
is going to have to actually start paying for the defaults.
They will get the bad debt and in exchange they will make
the other side of the Credit default swap that the holder of it they will pay to make them hold.
And so this could take them out of business. And all of a sudden the people are over here
who are, who thought they had insurance no longer do and they might
actually say wait I can only hold AA debt and they might actually have to dump this debt on to the market.
Even worst you have all of the people, all of the people over here
who didn't lend any money over to any body but they really just wanted to make side bets
either the side bets might have been pure directional bets
on the state of the economy saying hey i think a bunch of companies or I think this company in particular
is going to default on its debt and they too could get credit default swaps really as just side bets.
So just for may be may be this right here is 1 billion dollars is in debt, may be
these all of these parties took side bets on this guy
So even though there is only a billion dollars of debt here, there might be
four or five or ten billion dollars worth of insurance on that 1 billion dollar bet.
So if all of a sudden this one company, can't pay it's 1 billion dollars, now AIG is on the line not for 1 billion
but for 4 or 5 or 6 billion, how ever much it insureded for
So it allows people to insure for things that they dont have the offsetting liability for.
And so you can imagine these guys, some of these people if these guy fails will just kind of take a loss
and that's bad and all of the rest they were expecting that they wouldn't. But some of these players might have had
offsetting hedges. The only reason that they might have felt comfortable
taking on some other liabilities is they said look If the economy goes really bad I have, I have this insurance over here
and they did that transaction with another third party.
Now all of a sudden if the economy goes bad and these guys said,
Hey look I am in a lot of trouble good thing I have this Credit default swap but then it
turns out that they don't because the counterparty here fails, the credit default swap writer and now all of sudden this guys becomes insolvent
but this guy was dependent on this guy paying and he thought
he was good because he was even looked into his books and thought that this guy had offsetting hedges
and now this guy might fail and so you can have this entire cascade through the entire financial system.