Let's say I'm an economist
and I'm curious about whether in general
things are getting more expensive or not
and if they are getting expensive, by how much?
So the way I'd approach that is I would think of
well what are just a bunch of goods and services
that the average person would buy
So I would think up some type of basket of goods
goods and services
And I would try to weight that basket based on
how people actually spend their money.
So I'd say, okay, 40% of peoples' money on average
is spent on housing.
Maybe another 10% is spent on transportation,
maybe another 10% is spent on food
and I would go out into the market
and I would see, I would try to take an average
of what these things cost. And I would sample
a bunch of products, a bunch of services,
so that I get a decent average of that
So this is not a simple thing to do,
but I'm an economist and I'm serious about trying to calculate that
And let's say that when I take that weighted average
of all of this stuff, I just come up with a number.
And this is, I'm not giving you the details
of how it's actually calculated,
but to give you the idea of what they are doing.
So I get a number, so I just, you know...
to rent, to buy or lease your average automobile
to lease your average apartment
to buy your average servings of food
for a given family, all the rest...
let's say I come up with that costs
and I'm making up a number here,
let's say that it costs $20,000
my basket of services,
just based on the way that I've weighted it.
And this is all happening in year 1.
So this is in year 1.
Now I'm curious whether between year 1
and let's say year 5,
whether things got more expensive
So I'll take that same basket of goods and services
So basket of goods and services
and I'll try to figure out what is their weighted average cost in year 5
and this is a lot harder than it sounds right now
because the basket of goods and services change
If computers get faster, do you use the same computer?
Or do you think about what the average computer is
which would now be a better computer.
If most people's TVs got bigger, do you use the same TV
in year 1 and year 5? Or do you adjust now the average TV
which has now gotten bigger.
If houses have gotten bigger on average, do you use the same house?
Or do you use the average house?
So there's a whole bunch of areas here
that you could really tweak (change),
and these are actually huge subjects of debate
on what is the actual increase in cost.
But let's say that you're able to do this
in what you think is a pretty reasonable way
and you find that the same basket of goods
adjusted for things like technology and all of the rest,
Now costs $22,000. So your takeaway
from here is the same things that cost $20,000
the things that give you the same standard of living in year 1
to get that same standard of living in year 5
you now need to spend 10% more
it's gotten $2,000 more expensive off of $20,000
so it's gotten 10% more expensive
So you as the economist
what you would say is, as the way you've defined it
your consumer price index, and this is abbreviated with CPI
Your consumer price index is up by 10%
Another way, based on the way you measured it
and it change from country to country
even within countries, they change the way
that they do these baskets of goods,
but by the way you've measured it,
you would say that the price inflation has been
10% between year 1 and year 5
or in general, everything got 10% more expensive
or you would 10% more money to have the same standard of living
and in general, when people are just refering to
inflation, so if you just see the word inflation being referred to
they are referring to price inflation,
this general increase in the price of goods and services
measured by some type of basket of goods.
There is another type of inflation, and that is
monetary inflation
and they are related,
monetary inflation is inflation due to purely the increase of the money supply
So this is increase in money supply.
And in general, if this increase in the money supply
does outstrip kind of the productive capacity of the country
it could very well lead to price inflation
but in general, what people measure,
when they talk about inflation from one year to the next
they're talking about this basket of goods
they're talking about price inflation.
The other thing that you'll sometimes see
maybe in year 5, someone says, "hey!"
"I could sell you this house"
this house is in year 5
"I could sell you a house"
and this house in year 5 is $660,000
and someone might ask, well
"What would be that price if we adjusted it for inflation in year 1 dollars?"
So what they're saying is, you adjust for how much value
your money has lost.
Because if things are getting more expensive that means
each dollar is being worth less.
You can buy less with each dollar.
So when people say, "How much is that adjusted to inflation in year 1 money?"
You're essentially saying,
What amount of money would that house have had to have cost in year 1,
that when you adjust it for inflation
you increase it by 10%, so that's the same thing
increasing by 10% is the same thing as multiplying by 110%
or multiplying by 1.1
So what amount of money would that house have had to have cost in year 1
that if I multiply it by 1.1, I get $660,000?
Now we can do a little quick math here to figure that out
So if we say, let's say that, I don't know
that P, P is the price of the house in year 1
I'll call it P1, that times 1.1
is going to be equal to $660,000
When you factor in the 10% inflation over these years
Now this is simple algebra right here
You could divide both sides by 1.1
and we get, these cancel out
you get the price of that house in year 1
66 divided by 11 would be 6
now you can work it out with a calculator if you don't feel comfortable enough
with what I'm about to do.
This would give you $600,000, if you work this math right out here
And you could figure out the decimals,
what we could do, well, I think you get the general idea here
you can use your calculator. I kind of did this in my head
But the general idea is a house in year 1 that is $600,000
if you factor in the devaluing of the current year
or how much more expensive everything got in year 5
will cost you $660,000.
So you might hear someone say
when they're talking about inflation or they're talking about price increases
This house in year 5 is $660,000
which is equal to $600,000 in year 1 money.
And as an example of that,
you know I live in neighborhood where
the houses have gotten all of a sudden
because I live in the heart of Silicon Valley
it's not a fancy neighborhood by any stretch of the imagination
but the house are now quite expensive
and we have neighbors now that moved in in the 1950s,
and they say, "My god, I bought my house for $10,000 and now people are selling these houses for
so much more!"
And the reality is is that it is true,
the house has appreciated,
but $10,000 in 1950 was actually a lot
a lot of money.
Doctors and engineers did not make that much more
than that much per year.
I don't know the exact amount.
So the reality is, is that you actually have to
adjust money for the year you are talking about
and you have to adjust it for inflation
So if you believe this 10% inflation number
Hopefully people's incomes also increased by the same amount
So the same person, maybe with the same skills
and the same job, who could afford
the house for $600,000 in year 1,
could now pay $660,000 for it, and it won't take
an unusually large chunk of their expenditures
it would take the same chunk that it did in year 1.
So hopefully that clarifies things a little bit,
and I'll in the future do more videos
going into the details of inflation