[Intro Music]
We're in the Louvre and we're looking at a large alter panel by Giotto of St Francis.
It's really spectacular painting.
It is. It shows St Francis receiving the stigmata from Christ who appear to him in the form of seraphim.
And what's striking is that this is not St Francis in a very iconic frontal way.
As we might've expected in the more medieval tradition.
Exactly. Instead, St Francis is kneeling;
He's in a naturalistic landscape, or a beginnings, we could say, of a naturalistic landscape
and as he receives the stigmata, he looks up in wonder, in awe, and in confusion, and even some anxiety.
A little fear there, right?
Yeah.
But they're very human emotions. It's really an expression of, you're right, not an eternal iconic image
but rather of a moment of a man responding.
And his body is rendered naturalistically, too.
We have modelling.
We see the folds in the drapery.
We see his left knee, his right knee folded under him.
The modelling in his hands where we see the stigmata.
Modelling in his face.
So he really seems like this bulky three-dimensional presence.
Really different from the flat transcendent figures of only a little bit earlier.
And actually other artists that are still painting.
I want to go back to the point that you made a moment ago,
of the naturalistic landscape.
This is certainly not naturalism as we would expect now in the 21st century.
But it is at the very beginning of the 14th or the very end of the 13th century
quite extraordinary innovation to place this really physical figures you had described him, in an environment
with trees with mountain.
Clearly his scale doesn't match the buildings and the trees
but there's an effort here by Giotto to place him on Earth not just in a heavenly space.
So we see this extraordinary gold filled background the light of heaven pours down
and we see that literally in the divine rays that go from the seraphim-from Christ, down to Francis, down to his feet to his hands and to the wound in his side.
This gift from heaven for his faithfulness.
Now it's important to remember that Francis was a mendicant.
Was a beggar.
That he'd given up his worldly possessions and like the Dominicans,
Franciscans would renounce worldly possessions in honour of Christ
and initially there are some reports that the church was not sure that it wanted to accept St Francis'
ideas