solve the systems of linear equations by graphing.
and they give us two equations here.
5x + 3y is equal to seven and 3x - 2y is equal to eight.
when they say solve the systems of linear equations
they are really just saying to find an x and a y that
satisfies both these equations.
when they say to do it by graphing we are
esentally going to graph this first equation.
remember the graph is really just depicting
all of the x and y that satisfy this first equation
and then we graph the second equations thats
depicting all the x and y that satisfy that one.
so if we are looking for an x and a y that
satisfies both that point needs to be on both equations
and so or it has to be on both graphs
so it will be the inter section of the two graphs
so lets try to see if we can do that.