First, let's build up the conceptual mechanics
for these new types of random algorithms
which accept some input 'n'
and if 'n' is prime
our algorithm will ouput
'prime' with 100% certainty
and it will never label it as composite.
Or if 'n' is composite, there will be
some tiny chance of error 'e'
that we'll label it prime.
Otherwise, there is a 1 minus
this tiny error probability
that correctly identify it as composite.
So we'll start simple. Out of some
universe of integers up to some limit.
We grab a number
and call this integer 'n'.
And we input 'n' into our machine.
And previously with
our trial division methods,
We basically iterated through
all values from 1 to the square root of 'n'
and tested if that number divides 'n'.
And ideally we only wanted
to check primes to save time.
And if yes 'a' divides 'n',
then we know that 'n' is a composite number,
because we found a composite witness.
If not then we're not sure,
so we go back
and we increment 'a' and we test again.
And once we exhausted all posible tests,
we can then say yes 'n' is prime,
if we found no divisors.
But now let's be lazy.
What if we just pick a few random ntegers
and do a few divisibility tests,
which you can think of as random questions.
Since we know that some number 'n',
if it's composite, it must have
some divisors scattered around.
and at minimum it has a single divisor.
And some composite numbers
have many divisors.
So anyway, we pick a random integer 'a'
between 1 and square
root of 'n' and that's it.
Then we just check if 'a' divides 'n'.
And as before, if 'a' divides 'n',
then we know for sure that 'n'
is composite, we found a wittness.
If not, then we haven't learned
too much except that 'n' could be prime.
So to be save, we can generate
a few more random 'a's and keep testing.
And perhaps after 100 or 1000 interations,
we can stop and say it's
probably prime with some certainty
say for example 99.9%.
And this is similar to the example
game on conditional probability.
In a simplest version, we were trying
to guess if a coin was fair,
or if it was a two-headed coin.
In this case, tails is like
finding a divisor.
It's a witness of a fair coin.
Heads is the case where we might want
the person to flip again and iterate.
In this case, after around 5 heads,
we are more than 90% sure,
so we could stop and say
that we think the coin is two-headed.
So here's a program I set up which compares
our old trial division methods
with this new random division test.
And I'm specifically using
the current trial division speed leader,
which is the program by Dino and I posted
the link in the header of the program.
So to begin, notice
the variable number of trials.
This is the number of random guesses,
so we'll start at something small such as 3.
And notice even with small input
If the input is prime, the random division
algorithm will always output prime.
But when the input is composite,
we see the random division can make mistakes
and identify incorrectly as prime.
However, we can fix thi
by increasing the number of trials
and then the probability
of an error goes down
and we see now that
the outputs more or less match.
And as I test larger inputs,
the error grows again
so I need to increase the number
of random tests accordingly.
And when I do, the outputs
match very nicely. They seem identical.
But with huge input size, I need
thousands of tests for this to be accurate.
So we haven't actually improved
the number of steps needed.
Our trial division method
still seems better.
This is because the error rate
of the division test is so high.
We are close,
we have the right idea.
So we need to use another test.
We need an equation
which is fast to calculate
that can be used to prove
whether a number is composite.
And it must accept
not only the input integer 'n',
but also random integer 'a'
and do a random test
in the same sort of way.