I just realized that I didn't answer a question that might be burning in your brain after watching the
video on life insurance where we talk about term life and whole life because in whole life we talk about
the scenario where you can pay this premium your whole entire life and in the event and you can just
all the way until the day you die so that when you die your family will definitely get the payoff. They
will get the $500k upon your death. And we also talked about the scenario where any time before that
you decide that I don't need life insurance anymore, you can stop paying your premium. Your family won't get
the death benefit in the event that you die but you would get the cash payout or whatever is left
after the insurance company has taken their fees and and set aside some for the insurance component of
what they are selling you but the question you might ask is what happens to the cash amount? Because
before you die you can cash it out; if you die, you definitely get the payoff. But what happens to the
cash amount? And the answer there is that you don't get it. It's kind of viewed as what is backing up
your death benefit. And what's kind of unfortunate if for whatever reason the cash amount is even larger
than the death benefit. Maybe you lived an unusually long amount of time maybe you lived 50 years and
you're paying... or you live to 90 so you live 50 years from the start of the policy. So you pay $250k
but you have to remember compound interest, you're getting returns on that year after year. Maybe this
cash payout becomes $600k when you accrue all the interest and everything else in it. Regardless of that
fact, although, this would be a silly thing for you to do, if you were to die your family would only
get the $500k dollars. Which really makes you ask the question if you know your cash payout is larger
than the amount that is going to be paid off when you die, then the best thing to do is just to stop
paying the premium and get the cash payout and give that to your family rather than waiting around to
die. This is worse in 2 ways, first you die, and in the 2nd way, you're getting less money. Just to answer y
our question, in the event of your death, your family does not see the savings portion, they only get this payout right over here.