We're once again at the Museum of Modern art in the room of devoted to pop art
and we're standing in front of -- sort of walking around -- the Oldenburg's Floor Cake from 1962.
And both of us are smiling because it's just a hilarious work of art.
What's funny to me is that when we get up close it really doesn't look like cake at all.
It looks like, actually, the giant cherry on top looks like a piece of poop.
Yeah. In fact, the closer you get to it the less appetizing it becomes. It's this piece of
canvas, it's sort of disgusting and filthy and it's wonderfully not edible.
We should just describe it first. It's gigantic.
Eight feet long?
A young woman who was just in the gallery a moment ago was walking in the gallery
said that 'I just want to lay down and sleep on it'
because it actually kinda looks like a gigantic bed.
It's preposterous to have food this large but it's not just that it's large because in no way is it
an accurate representation of a piece of cake. In fact, it's sort of wonderfully floppy and
the thing that I find incredibly endearing about it is listing to the right. It's this gigantic soft
series of pillows.
But you know, cake is a floppy thing because the messy, gooey, sensual experience and the squishiness
of this reminds me of digging into the frosting and having it smush down--
Right, right, but it's not sensual. It is from a distance and from association it is, definitely, but
as you get close to it it looks dry and it's fabric and it's sort of badly painted fabric
and it's got all these competing associations that're completely at odds with each other.
To me it has associations with oversweetness, saccharine and American culture burying itself
and sweetness and massproduced food.
It's looking at what we as a culture fetishize, right?
I mean, this is 1962, it's incredibly early. If you think about where pop is at this moment it's just
being born in the US. Warhol is just creating his first soupcans, Lichtenstein is just at the
early stages of his cartoon--
So the pleasures of American consumer culture--
Absolutely.
But it's sort of undermined, really undermined.
Yeah, I think there's a tremendous sense of humor as well. But you're right, the kind of critical aspect
here but not only critical towards American culture but about what our canon should be.
There was that great quote. Lichtenstein said that 'by the early 60s, after I've studied expresionism,
you could take a rag that had been soaked in paint and hang it up on the wall and that would be considered
art.' So we've definied something that was still difficult. It also raises questions about what representation
is supposed to be and what representation is.
If you think about representation as something that traditionally, maybe something out of the
nineteenth century, is meant to refer to in some very direct ways, this is sort of against
I mean, it identifies what it is but in so many ways it's at odds with what it's meant to represent.
It is still maintianing essential identity as a slice of cake but when you look at it in any way, other
than that broad identiy, it refuses to be that.
But it also remindes me of is the heroic tradition of scultpture. It's not a hard bronze or marble
thing, it's smushy, say.
But not only that, it's not this idealized human body, it's not this body of a god--
Yeah, it's not a heroic, it's the exact opposite, it's the everyday, it's the mundane, it's the lowest.
So it's the lowest brought up to this absurd height.