We are in San Francisco and we are looking at Frida Khalo's portrait
Frieda and Diego Rivera from 1931
So it's an early Frida Khalo
and they were both in San Francisco so it's kind of a wonderful place to see this painting
and they were here because Rivera was commisioned to paint the murals here
He was already an established painter who was famous in Mexico and was invited to the united states
He was on the verge of a major one person exhibition at the Museum of Modern Art in New York
And I think that was only the second solo exhibiton that the museum had held.
That's right the first was of Matisse
And so that's quite extraordinary company
Andy Rockefeller was involved with the founding of the museum of modern art
he wanted Picasso and Matisse to create a large mural in the lobby
They both declined but Rivera was the third choice which is pretty extraordinary company
This is not Rivera this is Frida
She looks so small and diminutive next to him and so delicate
I'm so struck by the way she tilts her head and looks at us
Where he looks so stocky and looks at us straight on
The way she's really depicted him, seeing in him
Offering him to us as think incredibly solid figure
And she floats in a way that he doesn't, right.
He's so rooted those boots are so strong
and there is something in the way that her dress is off the floor that gives her a lightness
and also the tilt of her head
Yes and there's curving forms in that shawl that she wears and in the necklace and headband and the frills
of the skirt. So she's got this feminine curviness to her that seems really different
than his blockiness
and there is a lot of symbolism in what you are talking about, in their clothing
So she's referencing her Mexican heritage, the folkloricness
it's really trying to ressurect and give a sense of her pride and of the importance of that heritage
Within this portrait. The way that they are against this very spare background
is coming right out of the colonial Mexican artistic tradition as well
Diego is represented with this work shirt under a suit.
Which is an interesting parallel because it really shows the sense of the working class
but also a kind of seriousness
His tradition that he is coming from of the Mexican mural painters from the 1920's
who were trying to build and artistic tradition on the Mexican revolution
of creating art for the people
He's depicted as a worker
I'm also struck by their hands
Her hand is sort of light over his
It obviously looks to me like she's letting go, it's interesting to me that he has
got paint brushes and the palatte and this is her painting
She almost lets got and looks at us. It feels to me like she is establishing her independance
Diego is sturdy and not moving, he has got his hand there and open for her
Bu when she tilts her head she has got a little movement
She's the one who lifts her hand and cocks her head and looks out at us
And if you look at the bird on top, the bird is flying with a banner
As the museum translates that to english it reads
Here you see me; Frida Khalo with my beloved husband Diego Rivera
I painted portrait in this beautiful city, San Francisco for our friend
Mr. Aver Bender who was a trustee of the museum that we stand in
It was the month of April in the year 1931