f(x) = 9 - x squared
and g(x) = 5 times x squared
plus 2x plus 1
and then they say find (f + g)(x)
and this looks a little bit bizzare
what kind of notation is this
and that's really the core of this problem
is just to realize that when someone writes
(f +g) in parentheses of x
is just notation for, this is the same thing as
f(x) + g(x)
you can view (f + g) as a new function
that's created by adding the other twp function
when you view it like this
then you really just have to add these two functions
so f(x) given the definition
is 9 - x squared
and g(x) given the defintition
right over here
'is 5 times x squared plus 2x plus 1
so when you add f(x) to g(x)
this is going to be equal to
and I'm just re-writing this over here
the f(x) part is 9 - x squared
and then you have the plus
in yellow
plus the g(x) part
which is 5 times x squared
plus 2x plus 1
and now we can simplify this a little bit
let me just get rid of the parentheses
so this is equal to
9 minus x squared plus
since this is positive we don't have to worry about the parenthese
so plus 5 x squared plus 2x plus 1
and then we have two x squared terms
we have 5 x squared and then we have negative x squared
so 5 x squared minus x sqaured is 4 x squared
so you get 4 x squared when you combine these two terms
and you only have one 1st degree term
2x there
so plus 2x
and then you have two constant terms
or zero degree terms
you have the 9 and youhave the 1
so 9 plus 1 gets us to ten
so we're done
(f + g)(x)
is equal to
4 x sqaured plus 2x plus 10
notice this is a new function
that is created by summing the function definitons