What I want to do in this video is compare investment to consumption
and we're going to think about it in two contexts.
One I would call the everyday conventional context
and the other one would be how we think about in an economics context
because these words mean something very particular to an economist
and it's important that it means something particular
because we're going to start using these words or this terminology or this classification
to understand where GDP is coming from.
So every day, so let me draw a line over here, this is going to be, this is kind of every day
or conversational versions of this term, and down here we'll put the economics
the economic versions of these terms, especially when we think of it in the context of accounting for GDP
and there not necessarily all different, but they are different in important ways
so an investment, really in both cases, you can generally view it as something that you do to get some future gain
so for example, if I today, build a house, so I build a house
So that is the house I build today and that will be the time line
the house will keep lasting and it's an investment because it's going to be giving me future gain
a year from now, I'll still be able to live in this house, so I will be able to have the same rent, which is a future gain
Future gain two years from now -- it'll keep giving some kind of gain.
You could have a financial instrument, maybe some kind of debt instrument
you're lending money to someone else, so maybe, maybe you buy a bond,
which is essentially you lending money to someone else.
That is an investment, because in the everyday sense of it,
because when you make, when you have that asset, it's going to pay off something in the future
it's going to pay off some interest or some profit
and in the everyday sense, I would consider something like, hopefully it would be
going to college, would be an investment.
so education, so I'll say education. So if you invest time and money into education,
it's going to keep paying off.
hopefully by doing that, you're going to get better employment and higher wages.
the rest of your life. It will keep paying off.
So this is the everyday notion of investment.
The everyday notion of consumption, the way I think about it is,
you are buying something or you are doing something that you're just going to use
up in the short term, and just by using it up, whatever that object is, if you just use it up,
and it's just going to hopefully benefit you in some way, but it's more of a short term thing,
I would consider that consumption in the everyday sense.
So if you go buy a candy bar and eat it, you have consumed the candy bar.
You have not made an investment. If you go to a movie, that is consumption.
And I'm not making any value judgment that one is better than the other.
Investment, at the end of the day, you are investing so that you can get future benefit
that could lead to consumption, because at the end of the day, consumption is one of the things
that might make your life a little bit better off. So I'm not saying that one is better than the other.
But watching a movie, that would also be consumption. Spending time buying a book, well you could debate
if that's education or not, but let's say you buy a book that is not educational
that is consumption. but it is making you happier. Hopefully it's making your life better in some way
Now, the economic definitions are related to these everyday definitions
but they're a little bit more precise. And they make the definitions in a way
that they're easier to account for if you are a nation. They're easier to keep track of
So the way an economist would define it,
they would define economic investment as spending on capital equiment,
capital equipment are things like if you are a factory,
you will buy the equipment to run your factory, you buy the robots, and you buy the assembly line
and you buy the wheel barrow and whatever else.
the things that have to cart things around. It would be things like inventory
so for example, the inventory -- and this is still not so different --
both are being used to produce things in the future
to produce future benefit. You're buying inventory, sometimes raw material,
you're going to add value to it, and then they're going to be used to produce something
in the future. It includes things like the structures, the buildings
and, and so for all of this, in the economic sense, and this is why it's easier to count for
this, for the most part, is done by the firms, and it also includes the one thing that
households do, which is build -- construction of new homes.
New homes.
This is from the household. Households. Actually, the buying of a house
does not show up in consumption or investment because nothing new is produced
Something just changed hands. So anytime we talk about any of these things, especially
when we're talking about specific economic terms, is the production of new capital equiment,
new inventory, new structures, new homes,
if I just buy a factory from someone else, that does not add to GDP
it would not be considered investment or consumption because I'm just transferring
an asset from one person to another.
It would only be added to GDP when it is first created. And on the consumption side,
from an economic point of view -- so let me draw a little bit of a line right over here --
consumption is considered to be any spending, any spending on final goods
by households except for new homes.
So let me make this even clearer
because remember if we're just transferring goods that shouldn't count
so let me put new, newly produced goods
now what's unintuitive over here, according to the way we account for GDP
the tuition that you spend on a college education, that is new spending
on final goods, let me write final goods or services, that would be consumption
so education would fall here in the economic sense,
while in the everyday sense, I would consider education right over here.
Maybe you're buying a car, you're not buying a car for leisure purposes,
you're buying a car because you need your car to go to work.
There's an argument that that could be an investment in the everyday sense
by buying, by having that car, you have something that can take you to work every day
so you're getting future benefit, so there's an argument that maybe that's an investment
in the everyday sense. But in the accounting sense,
that car, the car would sit right here.
You bought a new car, but that is considered consumption.
You did not buy a new house. And the whole reason or at least as far as I understand,
this is easier to account for. You look at all the spending by firms,
that's easy to account for. You essentially call that investment
because at the end of the day, all the spending that the firms are making
is they're doing to produce some good or service.
So, we call this investment any spending that the firms do and on top of that,
when households purchase new homes, we also call that investment
and that's just easier for the accounting offices of governments to keep track of
and everything else that households do, we consider consumption
and we'll see in the next few videos, there are few other categories of things
that the governments do, and then we'll have to think about imports and exports.