We're at the Musee d'Orsay,
in front of Manet's famous painting,
"Le dejeuner sur l'herbe,"
or "Luncheon on the Grass,"
which was exhibited
at the Salon des Refuses in 1863.
It was exhibited there
because the painting was rejected
when the artist submitted it
to the traditional salon.
In fact, that year there were so many artists
who were rejected
that Napoleon III opened something called
the "Salon des Refuses,"
or the salon of refused or rejected works.
And this work was the focal point
of the Salon des Refuses for the critics.
This is a painting that is very much
a kind of taunt.
And very much, I think, an attempt to
break as many rules as the artist can.
It breaks formal rules.
It breaks compositional rules.
It breaks rules of subject.
The composition was borrowed
from a print after Raphael.
There was a tapestry by Raphael
that was lost.
So the composition is borrowed
from a traditional source.
And the subject matter, nude women
with clothed men, in an idyllic landscape,
is borrowed from a painting
by Giorgione in the Louvre.
The problem is that this
is not a Venus.
The problem is this is not
a classical context.
The problem is this
is modern France,
perhaps a park,
perhaps the Bois de Boulogne.
Not only is she not a goddess,
but she is a specific person.
Manet's model, Victorine Meurent,
and she looks very much like a real person
that you would see walking down
the streets of Paris fully clothed.
And worse, she's looking at us.
That is to say, that she is not even in a sense
giving us the sort of opportunity to gaze on her
with a kind of coyness.
But she is actually confronting
us directly.
The men who she sits with who are fully clothed
don't look at her and don't look at us at all.
So there is this assumption of sexuality,
but in a non-classicizing manner,
and yet at the same time
it's so matter of fact
that it feels totally desexualized.
On the other hand there are all these clues
about sensuality and sexuality.
We have in the lower left a very
sensual still life of fruit and bread
and a flask with some alcoholic beverage in it.
And that lies on top of the clothing
that she's discarded.
The original title of this painting was
"The Bath."
So she's not a nymph that lives in
a mythological forest who's always naked.
But she's a modern woman who's
taken off her dress.
She's not nude.
She's naked.
This painting is breaking lots of rules
when it comes to subject.
But it is also breaking lots of rules when it comes
to the way in which the painting was actually made.
If you look at the very bright flesh of the female figure,
she is so bright and so heavily outlined,
and I shouldn't say outlined.
But she is surrounded by darker tones.
So that she actually seems
somewhat flattened, doesn't she?
And the internal modulation of tone that you
would expect to see in a 19th century painting
of this sort is absent.
So that some might have looked at this and seen her
almost as a kind of two-dimensional cutout.
And worse than that, there are other ways in which Manet is in a sense breaking the rules
that one followed at that point
to create naturalism.
For instance, look at the way the ribbon in her hair
which is so dark, and the darkness of the hair itself,
mesh with the darkness of the bush that is
many feet in back of her
and kind of collapse that space.
We really have no sense of the distance
between the figure we see in the background
who is emerging from the water.
The other female figure.
She almost seems too large.
Well, especially since her hands,
which are so small,
because of the distance, seems to
actually be reaching down to the man's thumb.
And there is this terrible kind of disjunction.
Right, a kind of collapsing of space.
Yeah, and scale, and in a sense,
of the rules of illusionism
that Manet seems to be inviting
the destruction of.
He seems to be sort of willfully and playfully
undermining the very rules of the academy.
And at the same time, there is all
of this pleasure that one senses in paint,
in applying paint in this kind
of very loose brushwork
that is very sensual,
especially the blue of her clothing
and the still life or the gray
pants and white pants
worn by the male figures.
Manet had been looking at people
like Velazquez and others
where the brush becomes critically important
and he's very interested clearly in us
not only seeing what is being depicted,
but seeing the means by which it was depicted.
Seeing the paint itself refusing to give us
that perfect illusion that had been really
the foundation of western painting
since the time of the Renaissance.
The other thing that is so odd about it, right,
is you have all of this loose Velazquez
handling of paint,
but then you move into the background
and you get paint that seems like
it's been very diluted and applied in a way
that's very much like a wash or a stain,
especially where the trees and field
behind that female figure.
And then on the other hand there is clumps
of paint in the trees.
So there is all these kinds of different
handling of the paint itself.
It is, in a sense, a dismantling of the
expectations of art at this moment.
And it's reminding me of Baudelaire's
talking about the painting of modern life
and the painting of the modern nude.
Let's forget about Venuses.
We don't live in Ancient Greece.
Let's paint life today.
Where does one find the female nude?
Well, sort of Manet made up a theme
for modern female nudes.
But in a sense it sort of underscores the absurdity
of the classical tradition,
of the way in which we have clothed the nude
in those traditions to make it acceptable.
Manet is saying, does this make sense?
The illogic of this painting, and the way
in which it sort of pushes at social norms
is also underscoring the way in which the art
that we so readily accept from this period
makes no sense.
Exactly.