- ♪ music ♪ -
You view the real Florence when you can see the bell tower
The Campanile, and in the centre on the lower left
the just low cornered baptistry and on the back the cathedral
of Florence which Brunelleschi's dome at the top. - Well, the baptistry
is a medieval building and from the tenth century probably
and the cathedral that we all know they began
building in the strand 1300 and the bell tower starts going up a little bit perhaps after that
and then the dome is built from the early 1400 and finished
in the 1470's. - So, what are we looking at with the bell tower?
the bell tower now we are going to concentrate on is the lower part of it
around 1340 even when the tower was not complete yet, they decided
that the town and the guild of Florence, specifically the world guild
that was in charge of decorating the cathedral
decided that they want to decorate the bottom of the tower
because even though it was completely embarassing, having business there
on decorated surface where one is walking around as you can see, all the time
and so the two very bottom layers are decorated
with many reliefs designed in stone marble
rather than the bronze that is on the bapistry.
the reliefs cover a lot of subjects. there are typical scenes
there are signs of the zodiac and there are also scenes of
local art and industry. Some of these things may sound unusual
of course the biblical scenes make sense on such buildings
well those might have been a little bit unusual
we'll see why they might want to include those
we should also say that the zodiac signs are
not unusual because the medieval christians
were very able, and very comfortably blended
their belief in christianity and christian devotion in
with interest in horse gathering, we see that a lot in medieval trasures
thats right.lets look at some of these relics
her is one of these religious scenes.this is
the creation of adam.the artist is andrew epizano
who at rather the same time is working on
the bronze relics just across the street
on the side towards the bapistry. those secenes are about
john the bapist and here is one of the typical scenes on the bell tower
and again this is typical of the zious belif
belief described at. it is very very simplified
with mostly a blank background, just a few things to
give you a sense of the setting.there are a few stylysed trees
and we have god leaning over and creating adam
verily out of the dust of the earth he takes form. exactly.
this is another good exampleo fhow at aura combines
a graphic stylistion with a sort of naturalist classicism.
where do you see the graphic stylistion?
well the figure of god the father some ways the robes
went about with a sense of the body underneath
with a kind of ritual folds. all this is pretty
traditional so you ense of the body with not yet so
attire sensive and atomically correct and real physical
instead the figure adam is a nude athletic male
you know it is calassicising as well as naturalistic
he is in a contapastic stance even though
he is lying down. this does not make any sense
for contra posture is usually for standing up.
but the fact that he has done that anyway shows that
how interested he was in giving alassical piecec
thats true of his ribs muscles riht thro.
this is quite typical of his style. you are now looking
at one of the scenes of local industry. it
is lot like one of the god fearing adam. it
is interesting that you say that because the
industry that is represented here is sculpture and this is
an interesting way for an artist tosuggest that the work of the sculpture
is in some ways like the work of god. thos who are
creative in fact we see here that the creator here the artist
leaning over with stylised robes leaning over a nude
more naturalistic more classicising figure
well, of course, he is not going to get on trouble because of modesty here
because look again and compare this to the way God creates Adan
God is innature and he uses a gesture of his hand
and Adan is clearly sopposed to be a real living person
When we look at the sculptor in the studio, he is in the studio,
he is using tools. The use of the tool is a really conspicuous.