In the last video we saw ways to determine the
acidity of molecules look at the stability of the conjugate base.
The more stable the conjugate base the more acidic the molecule.
In the last video we talked about electronegativity stabilizing
the conjugate base in this video we are also going to look at electronegativity
but we are going to focus on resonance structures.
and resonance structures will allow the stabilization of conjugate base.
So we start with propane here and we think PKA of this proton is approximately
50.So propane is not very acidic at all.
but if I think about propane donating a proton
then these electrons will left behind in that carbon.So I can go ahead and draw
these conjugate base to propane .So i go ahead and put in my hydrogens
so this carbon on the left hand has 3 hydrogens this carbon has 2
the carbon on right has donated one of the proton so there is lone pair of electrons
left behind on that carbon.Which gives that carbon -1 formal charge.so we have a carb anion.
So in this carb anion charge is localized to this carbon atom
and since carbon is not very electronegative it doesn't stabilize the negative charge very well.
so that's t one reason why this is an unstable conjugate base.
Another reason is you cant draw a resonance structures for this conjugate base.
you cant spread out that negative charge throughout the molecule to delocalized those electrons
and stabilize the conjugate base.ans so for both those reasons we have
unstable conjugate base and since we have an unstable conjugat ebase
that's the reason why propane is not very acidic and has such a extremely high value for its PKA.
lets compare propane with this next molecule here is propene.so we are looking at
this proton has PKA approximately 43.so this propeneis more acidic than propane.and we can explain by looking at conjugate base.
so if I think about propene donating that proton these two electrons will remain behind on the carbon.
so I can go ahead and draw the conjugate base so the carbon on left still has two hydrogen.
top carbon has one and carbon on right now has 2 hydrogens.
Lone pair of electrons on this carbon so that's our carb anion.So once again we
have a negative charge on an atom that isn't very electronegative and so that's a fact that
will lead you to believe this is not a very stable conjugate base.
however there you can draw a resonance structure for this conjugate base.
So we go ahead and put this resonance arrow here and I can think about these
electrons moving in here to form a pi bond between these two carbons
which will kick these electrons of onto this carbon so lets go ahead and draw the
resonance structure that will results .So now we have a double bond between those two
carbons and carbon left still has two hydrogens.
Carbon in the center has 1 and the carbon on the right still has 2 like that.
Now you would have lone pair of electron on this carbon which will give it a -1 formal charge.
and so this would be the resonance structure that you can draw.
So lets go ahead and follow these electrons so the electrons in the those are the once that moved in here
to form a pi bond and then we can look at these pi electrons like these blue
these came of onto this carbon like that.
So we have delocalized electrons and remember the actual conjugate base would be
hybrid of these resonance structure.
but your negative charge is spread out.
its not localized to one carbon its spread out and delocalized throughout your molecule
and that will stabilize the negative charge and that will make the conjugate base
more stable.since the conjugate base is more stable thats the reason why propene is more acidic that propane.
lets go ahead and compare propene to ethanol.here we have ethanol and we have
seen this in two videos and this is the acidic proton on ethanol tha PKA value is approximatel 16
for that proton and so we think about ethanol donating a proton so these electrons will left behind
on the oxygen so we can go ahead and draw in the conjugate base.
so this carbon still has three hydrogens ,this carbon has 2 hydrogens
and for the oxygen on the right its goona have three lone pair of electrons.
which gives it a -1 formal charge.and now we can actually draw a resonance structure
for this conjugate base.so that negative charge is localized to the oxygen atom.
but we know that oxygen is relatively electronegative atom so that oxygen is better
able to pair that negative charge than the carbon was in the previous example.
so that makes a conjugate base stable and so by comparing these PKA values we can see
that ethanol is more acidic than propene.so even though propene we can draw resonance structures for it
and for ethanol you can't it turns out that the charge that has negative
atom is more important factor than resonance.so the fact that this negative charge
on this oxygen is which is an electronegative atom that turns out to be more important
than the idea of resonance.so electronegativity is more important than resonance.
so lets compare ethanol to acetic acid.so here we have acetic acid.the acidic proton on the acetic acid is 1.PKA value is approximately 4.75.
and lets think about the conjugate base .so acedic acid donates that proton right and these electrons left on that oxygen so we can draw the conjugate base to acidic
acid so this carbon would still have 3 hydrogens ,
right this top oxygen has 2 lone pair of electrons and oxygen here in right would have 3 lone pair of
electrons which gives it a -1 formal charge
and so this is the acetate anion the conjugate base to acedic acid
and so once again we have a negative charge on electronegative atom which stabilize this conjugate base.
but this acidic acid is more acidic than ethanol so there must be something else stabilize
the conjugate base .and that something else is of course resonance structure.
so we can go ahead and put in resonance pair here and we could show these electrons moving
in here to form a pi bond .which kick these electrons of onto the oxygen.
so we can go ahead and draw the resonance structures.
so the carbon in left still has 3 hydrogens.
carbon in the middle here used to have two bonds of oxygen now it has only one
so this top oxygen picked up another lone pair of electrons like that. so
this double bond between this carbon and this oxygen now like that.
so this is your structure the -1 formal charge is now on this
oxygen and once again the actual structure of the conjugate base is a hybrid of
these resonance structures.but this time you have the
negative charge delocalized which spread out stabilizes the conjugate base.
but delocalized over two oxygens in this case and so that makes the conjugate base
even more stable than the ethaxoide.
so if i think about the hybrid for this conjugate base having the negative charge
delocalized and over 2 oxygen. this example we have negative charge on one oxygen
so the fact that we can delocalized that negative charge on to negative atms make the acetate ion more stable
than tha ethoxide anion.
and since the acetate anion is more stable than the ethoxide anion that makes the acidic acidmore acidic than
ethanol.
so when you are
trying to think about acidity of molecule
not only you have to think about the electronegativity of atom
you have to think about possible responance structures.
more resonance structures you can draw the more stable the conjugate base.