Let's say I have some object that's traveling in a circular path just like this.
And what I've drawn here is its velocity vector at different points along that path.
So this right over here is going to be v one, velocity vector one,
and this is going to be velocity vector two,
and this right over here is going to be velocity vector three.
and we're going to assume in this video is the magnitude
of the velocity vectors is constant or another way to think about this
is that the speed is constant.
So I'll just say, lower case V without the arrow on
top so this is going to be a scaler quantity, I'll call this the speed
or you could call this the magnitude of these vectors, and
this is going to be constant, so this is going to be
equal to the magnitude of vector one, which is equal to the magnitude of vector two.
The direction is clearly changing but the magnitude is going to be the same, which is
equal to the magnitude the magnitude of vector three
We're going to assume that it is traveling in a path, a circle with radius r.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to draw a position vector at each point
Let's call r one, over there; that's position vector one, r one.
That is position vector r two.
So the position is clearly changing, that's position vector r two,
and that is position vector r three
but the magnitude of our position vectors are clearly the same,
and I'm going to call the magnitude of out position vectors, r.
That's just the radius of the circle; it's this distance right over here.
So R is equal to the magnitude of R one, which is equal to the magnitude of R two,
which is equal to the magnitude of R three.
Now what I what to do in this video is to prove to you visually that
given this radius and given this speed that the magnitude of the centripetal acceleration,
and I'll just write that as A, sub C.
I don't have an arrow on top, so this is an scalar quantity.
So the magnitude of the centripetal acceleration, is going to be
equal to our speed squared, our constant speed squared, divided by,
divided by the radius of the circle this is what I want you
I want you to feel good that this is indeed the case by the end of this video.
And to understand that, what I want to do, is I want to re-plot these
these velocity vectors on another circle,
and just think about how the vectors themselves are changing.
So let's copy and paste this, so let me copy and paste V one, so copy and paste so that is V
actually and want to do it from the center, so that is V one,
the same thing for V two. So, let me copy and paste it. That is V two
and then let me do it also for V three.
So, V three I'll just get the vector part of the label. So, copy and paste it.
That right over there is vector, V three and let me clean this up a little bit.
just do that we don't, so that's clearly Vtwo, I don't think we have to label anymore
we know that Vtwo is in orange, we know that Vtwo is in orange.
And what is the radius of this circle going to be right over here?
Well, the radius of this circle is going to be the magnitude of the velocity vectors,
and we already know the magnitude of the velocity vectors is this quantity V. The scaler quantity.
So the radius of this circle is V,
the radius of this circle we already know is equal to R.
And just as the velocity vectors, what's giving us the change in position vector over time.
What's the vector that's going to give us the change in our velocity vector over time?
Well that's going to be our acceleration vectors.
So you will have some acceleration we will call this A1, we will call this A2
And I'll call this A3
and I want to make sure you get the analogy that's going on here.
As we go around the circle the position vector, first they point out to the left,
then the upper, up, kind of the 11:00 position or I guess the top, the top left, then to the top
So it's pointing to these different positions like a hand in a clock.
And what's moving it along there, is
the change in the position vector over time which are these velocity vectors.
Over here the velocity vectors are moving around like the hands of a clock.
And what is doing the moving around, are these acceleration vectors
and over here the velocity vectors,
they are tangential to the radius, or sorry, they are tangential to
the path which is a circle, they are perpendicular to the radius.
you learn that in geometry,
that a line that is tangent to a circle is perpendicular to a radius
and it is also going to be the same thing right over here.
And just going back to what we learned,
when we learned about the intuition of centripetal acceleration
if you look at A1 right over here and you translate
this vector it will be going just like that, it will be going towards the center.
A2, once again is going towards the center.
A3, if you translate that, that is going towards the center.
So all of these are actually center seeking vectors, you see that right over here.
So all of these are actually centripetal acceleration vectors right over here.
Here we're talking about just the magnitude of it.
And we are going to assume that these all have the same
magnitude, so we are going to assume that our centripetal,
they all have a magnitude of what we call A sub C. So that's the magnitude,
it's equal to the magnitude of A1, that vector it's equal to the magnitude of A2,
and it's equal to the magnitude of A3.
Now, what I want to think about is how long is it going to take to get to
this point on this circle to the point on that circle right over there.
So, the way to think about it is, what is the length of the arc that it traveled.
The length of this arc that it traveled right over there that's 1/4 around the circle
it's going to be 1/4 of the circumference.
The circumference is 2pi(r) it is going to be 1/4 of that.
So, that is the length of the arc, that is the length of the arc.
and then how long will it take to go that?
Well you would divide the length of your path divided by the actual speed,
the actual thing that's nudging it along that path so you want to divide
that by your actual, the magnitude of your velocity or your speed.
This is the magnitude of velocity, not velocity.
This is not a vector right over here, this is a scaler.
So this is going to be the time, the time to travel along that path.
Now, the time to travel along this path is going to be
exact the same amount of time it takes to travel along this path.
For the velocity vector,
so this is for the position vector to travel like that,
this is for the velocity vector to travel like that.
so we can set these two things equally to each other, so we get on this side we get
1/4 2(pi)r over V is equal to 1/4 2(pi)V over the magnitude of our acceleration vector
and now we can simplify it a little bit. We can divide both sides by 1/4 get rid of that.
We can divide both sides by 2pi, get rid of that.
Let me re-write it, so then we get r/V is equal to V over the centripetal acceleration.
And now you can cross-multiply,
and so you get v times v so I'm just multiplying, cross multiplying over here
V times V you get Vsquared is equal to AC times R.
Cross-multiplying remember is just the same thing
as multiplying both sides by both denominators.
By multiplying both sides times V and AC
times V and AC, so it's not some magical thing,
if you multiply both sides times V and AC these V'a cancel
out, these AC's cancel out, you get V times V is Vsquared is equal to A sub C times R.
And now to solve for the magnitude of our centripetal acceleration,
you just divide both sides by r.
And I guess we've earned the drumroll now
We're left with the magnitude of our centripetal acceleration.
It's equal to the constant magnitude of our velocity, i.e. our speed
divided by the radius of the circle and we're done