In the last video we saw that
if Ben's shoe company's stock prices
are trading at $21.50 per share
and if Ben's shoe company has 10,000 shares,
and we saw that over here on the left....
If it had 10,000 shares,
and actually both of the shoe companies had 10,000 shares,
then the market is essentially
valuing the equity of Ben's shoe company
at $215,000,
even though the book value of the equity
was $135,000.
What I want to do in this video is think about
what does that mean,
or how should we perceive
the market's value of the assets of Ben's shoe company,
and then we can also think about Jason's shoe company.
So, remember,
assets are equal to liabilites plus shareholder's equity,
so if all of a sudden
the market value of the equity,
the market capitalization,
for Ben's shoe company is $215,000...
(That is the equity part right over here)
This is the equity...
And the only liability that Ben's shoe company had
was this $5,000 in accounts payable...
So let me show you that right over here...
He had this $5,000 dollars in accounts payable,
also depicted over there.
So the only liability is this $5,000.
So the liabilities plus the equity
in the case of Ben's company
is $215,000 plus $5,000,
so this piece right over here is $220,000.
Now, you might remember from previous videos
that the book value of the assets in Ben's company
are only $140,000!
$20,000 of cash, $100,000 of inventory,
$20,000 of... this is not equity,
this is equipment I should call it.
This is equipment, $20,000 of equipment.
So the question is what makes up the gap here?
when we think about the market value of the equity.
Because remember,
this piece right here only adds up to $140,000!
But our total assets,
or the market's perception of the total assets of the company,
are essentially what it's willing to pay
for the equity plus the liabilities,
so the market is saying that Ben's assets,
the assets in that company are worth $220,000.
So what makes the difference?
And even better, let's assume that
Ben has actually done a good job
of saying the market value of his inventory,
the market value of his equipment.
Well, what the market is saying in this situation,
and this is actually what tends to happen
where the market value
or in general the market value of a company
tends to be higher than the book value,
is that the company is saying that
this company has some type of intangibles,
things that you really can't put a finger on,
or touch or feel or hold.
But it makes this company's assets,
or this company has more than just the sum of its parts.
There's more to this company
than just the equipments, the inventory and the cash.
It might be Ben's management expertise.
It might be a certain way they have of doing business.
It might be a certain location they have.
It might be their assortment.
Who knows what it has!
But the market is saying that the combination of this
plus all of the expertise
and how the business is organised
means that it actually has more assets
than are on the books.
And the same thing is true of Jason's company.
When they assign a $120,000 market cap there...
This is $120,000 in equity, market value of equity,
he has another $105,000 in liabilites.
So the market is valuing their equity plus liabilities
at 100 and... or $225,000.
Is that right?
120 + 100 + 5
So 225,000
So once again they're valuing all of the assets
at 225,000.
Because assets are equal to liabilites,
(these are the liabilities right here)
plus equity.
So once again they're saying there's something above and beyond
the $140,000 that makes this company special
And an interesting thing to think about,
and we'll address it in the next video is:
Which one is a better deal?
Considering that these companies are pretty, pretty similar.