In the last video we finished up asking ourselves
how much do we produce
if the market price is at 45 cents
and just going with the logic
that we introduced in the last video
you want to produce as much as possible
to spread out the fixed costs
but you don't want to produce so much
that the marginal cost is higher
than your marginal revenue
and your marginal revenue is your market price
every unit, every incremental unit
you're going to get 45 cents
So you wanna look at the quantity
where your marginal revenue, the 45 cents
is equal to your marginal cost
and you can look at it over here
so, if you look at our marginal revenue
so, let's say 45 cents is right over there
you wanna look
where the 45 cents is equal to your marginal costs
It looks like it is right over there.
You can even see it in our table
When does our marginal cost equal 45 cents?
It equals that
when we produce 8,000 gallons of our juice
Now, the reason why this is somewhat interesting
is that at that point
the amount of revenue that we're getting per unit
our marginal revenue
is less than our total cost per unit
We're selling each unit at 45 cents
but our total cost for each of those units
is 48 cents, on average
So this right over here is our total cost
So you might say
look! I'm making a loss on every unit!
The total amount of revenue I'm getting
is a smaller rectangle over here
It's the quantity times the marginal revenue per unit
so, this is the amount of revenue that I'm getting
let me colour it in carefully
That is the amount of revenue that I'm getting
while my costs are this larger rectangle
My quantity times my average total cost per unit.
and so, what I end up with
is if you take that revenue
and you subtract that quantity
you end up with a loss of exactly this much
you're operating in this situation at a loss
when you are producing 8,000 units
and you're getting 45 cents per unit
So, does it make sense for you to do this?
And we can even figure out the loss
You're producing 8,000 units
and you're selling them for 45 cents a unit
and it costs you 48 cents per unit to produce them
on average
when you put all the costs in
48 cents per unit
So you're losing 3 cents per unit
per, I guess, gallon
we're talking about orange juice here
times 8,000 gallons
means that we are losing 240 dollars
8,000 times 3 cents is 24,000 cents
which is the same thing as 240 dollars
so, does it make sense for us to do this?
Well, one way to think about it
let's say we didn't do it
Let's say we're just like
hey, I'm not going to produce any gallons
well, then what's going to be our loss?
Well, we're assuming that this is our fixed cost
we've already committed ourselves
to this expenditure right over here
Whether we produce no drops of orange juice
we are still going to be spending 1,000 dollars
So we if produce nothing
we are garuanteeing ourselves
a weekly loss of 1,000 dollars
And this is at least better than that
So by starting to produce some units
we are at least able to offset some of that loss
and we're spreading out that fixed cost
over more and more and more gallons
And you might say
hey! Why don't I just produce more and more units?
Why don't I go here, maybe I'll produce 9,000 units
where the marginal cost, all of a sudden
is higher than our marginal revenue
and the reason why that won't make any sense to do
is because if you produce that many units
then all of a sudden
each of the incremental units
that you're producing beyond the 8,000
you're losing money on those
That 8,000 and first unit
the marginal cost is going to be higher
than the marginal revenue
that you're bringing in on that unit
so you're going to be losing money
You're going to start having a lower profit
than even the negative 240 dollar loss
so we'll start going into negative 240 something
negative 250 and so forth and so on
so you still don't wanna produce beyond that point
and we'll touch more deeply on that in future videos
but this is essentially what differentiates
the short term supply curve
from the long run supply curve
In the short term
we're going to assume that we have these fixed costs
and so, it's just going to make sense
to produce equivelent to our marginal costs
But over the long run
maybe our fixed items
our capital
our machinery wears off
or maybe the contract for my emplyees wears off
and then we have a different cost structure
over the long term
and we'll think about that in another video
But the simple answer is
assuming these really are your fixed costs
you still want to produce as many units as possible
so that your marginal cost
is equal to your marginal revenue
which in this case, is the market price
We are price takers
so it actually is a rational thing
to produce 8,000 units and take a loss on that
and take 240 dollar per week loss
as opposed to producing nothing
and taking a thousand dollar per week loss
now, it might not be rational
once these things have been worn out
like your robots and your employee's contracts
it might not be rational
to continue them past their term
and we'll think about that more in another video
because, obviously, we are running at a loss
and this is not necessarily a good business to be in
but now that we've gotten int the business
we might as well stay in it
in order to recoup some of our costs here
or at least spread them out
or at least not have a thousand dollar per week loss
Anyways. See you in the next video