[piano music]
We're on the second floor of the Metropolitan Museum of Art
and we're looking at a painting by Degas: "The Dance Class".
This is a painting that was, according to the wall text, originally intended
for the first Impressionist Exhibition in 1874
but not actually shown until two years later.
Thinking about that very first Impressionist Exhibition,
the first moment when this scoop of artists decided
"we're not going to show at the Salon,
we're going to create our own exhibition space",
and how incredibly normal that seems to us today.
But it was radical...
Completely radical... to not show in the official exhibition.
Didn't they actually borrow the photographer's studio, Nadar,
on the Boulevard des Capucines?
They did, but there was real concern that not enough people would come to see it,
they wouldn't become known, they wouldn't become famous,
no one would buy their work, how would they eat...
Because if they showed their work at the official exhibition at the Salon...
Everybody would.
But I think we know who the Impressionists are.
They were fairly successful.
They did the right thing in the end.
There were some really hilarious... some positive reviews and some really
scathingly sarcastic reviews of that first Impressionist exhibition.
This is a pretty outrageous painting.
It doesn't look so outrageous to us now, does it?
No, it looks beautiful to us.
It's like a snapshot.
This woman in the center whose body comes out of the two heads
of these other two standing women.
She seems to have her fingers in her mouth.
It's interesting that despite the fact that we assume right off
that the ballerinas are beautiful and graceful,
many of the ballerinas, if not all of them,
with the exception of the one who's performing,
are really rendered in a very ungainly way.
Actually she looks pretty ungainly herself.
You can see what's happening. This is a little narrative here.
You have the dancers waiting their turn,
the dance master, the male with the staff,
and the one dancer who's moving across the floor
and the young women who have finished.
And the mirror they're practising in front of,
that gives us a sense of the window that must be outside of the painting
on the right side...
It's illuminating. You can see the city through it...
And this is really all about this new urban world, this culture of pleasure.
The city of performance and leisure.
These women who are in the back, just hanging out
and sitting around, with their hands on their hips...
Those might actually be the escorts, right?
Because older ones not in tutus are their mothers.
The ballerinas were the movie stars of today.
Even if with that little bit of that risqué element involved.
The notion of the ungainliness is so clear when you look for it.
Look at the dancer who is in the very foreground, just at the back of the music stand.
She looks as if she's hiking her tutu.
And the woman behind her, fixing something about her tutu...
You're right. And the other one has her fingers in her mouth,
she's biting her nails.
And we can't see the bottom of her body at all.
Her torso seems to grow out of these three heads,
of these three figures in the front.
Another figure on the left looks out at something
outside of the picture.
This is not a self-contained, clear narrative,
which is exactly what would have been presented at the Salon.
It completely breaks all the compositional rules...
And narrative...
There's something intensely modern about this notion of an image that
seems so momentary and so unchoreographed.
But, of course, we know that it was graphed by Degas
and carefully planned in structure...
A perfect metaphor for the subject.
The way that the perspective of the room is exaggerated,
this very asymmetrical thing that Degas does very often. The whole bottom right at the corner is empty.
And look at what that does.
You have this incredible velocity of the perspective,
especially in terms of the ceiling line.
But then you're right, the bottom right is completely empty
and it's doing a kind of East-Asian or Japanese... asymmetry.
Not only asymmetry but also creating a kind of flat plain.
Absolutely.
In a sense very much at odds with the velocity of this tension that develops
between the two-dimensionality of the bottom right
and the hyper three-dimensionality of the upper left.
There's this other issue. We are here viewing something
that is very intimate and very spontaneous.
That people wouldn't be allowed to see...
Or we do have the privilege of the dance master.
We're really about at his eye level and we are another sort of viewer... we have that...
Insiders... It's like having backstage tickets.
Except that they don't notice us.
No, they don't notice us at all.