We're on Part B.
Write the first four nonzero terms of the Taylor series for cosine of x about x equals 0.
Use this series and the series for sin of x squared
found in Part A to write the first four nonzero terms
of the Taylor series for f
(so for this f right over here)
about x = 0.
So let's just do the first part
let's first find the first four nonzero terms
of the Taylor series for cosine of x
about x equals 0.
So let's just say—we'll put our kind of
formula for the Taylor series up here
around x is equal to 0.
So we're centering it around x equals 0 right over here.
And so if we say h of x is equal to
cosine of x, then h of 0 is going to be
equal to cosine of 0, which is equal to 1.
And then if you have h prime of x,
that's going to be equal to negative sine of x.
And you could look of here:
this is essentially h of x and this is going
to be h prime of x.
So it's essentially just one step ahead
of where we were with g of x.
We'll just redo it over here
just so it's clear.
So the first derivative at 0 is
negative sine of 0, which is just 0.
And then you have the second derivative—
second derivative of h of x.
So derivative of sine of x is cosine of x,
but we have that negative out front
so it's negative cosine of x.
So h prime prime of 0 is going to be
equal to—cosine of 0 is 1. You have that
negative out front so it's -1.
And then you have the third derivative
of h is equal to derivative of negative cosine of x
is positive sine of x.
So the third derivative at 0 is going to be
equal to 0. And then, this is also,
and then you take the derivative of this,
you're going to get cosine of x again.
So then the cycle starts again.
So I could write, this is also equal to
the fourth derivative at 0.
Right, let me just make it clear what I'm saying.
If I take the derivative of this, I get cosine of x.
The fourth derivative of h is cosine of x again.
So the fourth derivative at 0 is going to be
the same thing as the function evaluated
at 0 which is 1.
And so the fifth derivative at 0
is going to be 0.
The sixth derivative at 0 is going to be -1.
And then the seventh derivative at 0
is going to be 0.
So that's enough now. I think we have—
we definitely have four nonzero terms.
We have this term—let me pick a nice color here.
We have this term, because we have a 1 coefficient.
This is going to be a 0 because we have a 0 coefficient.
This is a nonzero term. Then this is a nonzero term,
because we have the 1 again.
And then this is a nonzero term, because
we have the -1. So we could say,
cosine of x is approximately equal to—
because we're just approximating it
with the first four nonzero terms.
So, f of 0 is 1.
So that's this term right over here.
Instead of f of x we're calling it h of x right here
so that we don't get confused with
the original f defined in the problem
that we're going to work on in the second part of—
this section of the problem.
So cosine of x is equal to 1,
f prime of 0, or h prime of 0 is 0, so there's no term there.
Then f prime prime of 0—second derivative—it's -1.
So it's negative x squared over two factorial.
And then you get another 0 for the third degree term.
Then you get a 1 for the fourth degree term.
So plus 1—and we don't have to write the 1,
it's implicitly there. Plus 1 times x to the fourth
over four factorial. And then, the next
nonzero term is this -1 over here.
So -1, we can just write minus,
and that's a sixth degree term.
So x to the sixth over six factorial.
And we're done. Those are the first four
nonzero terms of cosine of x.
Now let's do the second part of the problem.