Welcome back.
We're now going to be in the next section,
section four in our fourth test.
And that's problem one, 594.
Problem one.
x minus y is equal to 8. y is equal to 3z.
And z is equal to 2. What is x?
z is equal to 2, y is equal to 3z, so y is equal to 6.
So x minus 6 is equal to 8, or x is equal to 14.
E.
I already said z is equal to 2.
I sometimes forget when I just said.
Maybe I'm aging.
Problem number two.
Todd is older than Marta,but younger than Susan.
Let's say their first letter is their age.
Say Todd is older than Marta,
so his age is greater than Marta.
But he's also younger than Susan,
so his age is less than Susan's age.
Oh I think I did this problem inadvertantly.
If t, m, and s represent the ages in years of Todd, Marta,
and Susan respectively, which of the following is true?
And exactly what I drew is choice A.
And this comes straight from their statements.
I literally was just writing this
because I thought they were going to ask something harder.
But this they're saying Todd is older than Marta,
so t is greater than m.
And Todd is younger than Susan,so t is less than s,
so that's just choice A.
Problem number three.
If the areas of two regions are equal,
and the sum of the areas of the regions is 5,
what is the average of the areas of the two regions?
So area 1 equals area 2. We know that.
And we also know that the sum of the areas is 5.
So area 1 plus area 2 is equal to 5.
But then, of course,
we know that area 2 is the same thing as area 1.
So we also know that area 1 times 2 is equal to 5,
or that each of the areas is 2.5.
And area 2 would also be 2.5.
We know that because they're equal to each other,
and when you add them up it's 5.
So they're each going to be half of that,
so they're each 2 and 1/2.
And they want to know,
what is the average of the areas in the two regions?
Well they're the same number, right?
So if you average two of the same number,
the average is going to be that number.
You could add them and divide by 2,
but you're going to get 2.5.
And if you look at the choices, where's 2.5?
2.5 is the same thing as 2 and 1/2,
which is the same thing as 5/2, so it's choice B.
Next problem. I'll switch colors. Problem number four.
Let s be the set of all integers
that can be written as n squared plus 1,
where n is a non zero integer.
N is greater than zero,
and it soon. is an integer, it is a non zero integer.
Which of the following integers is an s?
So n squared plus 1.
So let's get a feel for what it is.
When n is 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
When n is 1, n squared,plus 1 is 2.
2 squared plus 1 is 5. 3 squared plus 1 is 10.
4 squared plus 1 is 17.
It's always going to be one more than a perfect square.
25 plus 1 is 26. There's 37, right?
So the choice is,it has to be one more than a perfect square.
So which of the following integers is an s?
So choice A is 16.
16 is a perfect square,
but it's not one more than a perfect square.
Similarly, choice B, 28.
28 minus 1 is 27, that's not a perfect square.
35 minus 1 isn't a perfect square.
39 minus 1 isn't a perfect square.
And if you look at choice E, 50.
50 minus 1 is 49, which is,of course, 7 squared.
Actually we would have gotten there
if we had just done one more.
7 squared plus 1, 49 plus 1, is equal to 50.
The important thing to realize is that,
the integers in s are integers
that are one more than a perfect square.
So you just have to look at the choices and say,
which of these is one more than a perfect square?
Let's do problem number five.
So I have a circle here,that's my circle.
And it has a triangle inside the circle.
It looks something--
I try to draw these as close to what
they drew in the book as possible.
There's point like that, there's point like that,
and then there's a triangle that looks like that.
And they write this is the center, of course, is o.
They're saying that this right here is x.
They say that this right here is y.
And then the question reads, in the figure above,
point o is the center of the circle.
If x is equal to 40 degrees,what is the value of y?
And you'll be like, how do I figure this out?
I know the angles of a triangle add up to 180,
and all that, but they've only given me one angle.
And I don't know the angle.
Or so you think you don't know this angle.
One of the things that should immediately enter your mind
when you see this in the SAT is,
the sides of this triangle are the radius of the circle.
It's the radius of the circle.
Because every time it gets to the end point,
and they actually it draw like that.
So if this is the radius,
we know that this side is going to be equal to this side.
Because both of these sides
are the length of the radius of the circle.
And they do this a lot in the SAT.
If something is a radius of a circle, it never changes.
Anywhere you draw it.
The radius is constant as you go around the circle.
So if this side is equal to this side,
what do we know happens?
It's an isosceles triangle, and the base angles are equal.
So this is y, we also know that this is y.
Because they're the base angles.
You know they're corresponding angles to these two sides.
They're the base angles for this triangle.
Now we can solve it.
We could say, x, which is 40 degrees,
plus y plus y is equal to 180.
Or we could say 40 plus 2y is equal to 180.
2y is equal to 140. Y is equal to 70 degrees.
And that is choice D.
Next problem. Problem number 6.
A simple square is any integer greater than 1
that has only three positive integer factors.
Itself, its square root, and 1.
Which of the following is a simple square?
It can only have three factors, it can't anything else.
So, for example,
if we wrote all of the perfect squares. 1, 4, 9, 16, 25, 36.
If we write the factors, this factor only has 1.
This factor has 1, 2 and 4. This has 1, 3 and 9.
I'm just writing out all the factors.
1, 2, and 4.
So it would be 1, 2, 4, 8, 16.
I'm just doing this as an example.
You shouldn't do this on the SAT.
But I want to explain what they're saying.
All of these numbers are perfect squares,right?
But notice 16 has itself, 1,and it has some extra factors.
While these numbers only have its square root,
and themselves, and 1 as factors.
So these are simple squares.
So if we look at the choices,choice A, 121.
121, I know 1 is a factor,I know that's 11 squared.
I know it's 121.
And I think, other than that,there's not any other factors.
It's not divisible by 3. B is 100.
100's got a ton of factors.
I mean it's got 1,10, and 100. It also has 2 and 50.
It has 4 and 25,
it has a ton of factors other than its square root,
so it's not choice B.
Choice C, 81, same thing.
It could be 1, 1 times 81,it could be 9 times 9.
Or it could be 27 times 3,and so forth and so on.
So it's not choice C. I think A is our prime contender.
Choice D, 64.
Once again, tons of factors outside of its square root.
It has 1, 64, and 8. But it also has 2 times 32.
It has 4 times 16, and you could go on.
64 has a ton of factors. And, finally, choice E.
33.
E doesn't work, because that's not even a perfect sqaure.
What squared equals 33? I don't know.
So that doesn't even work.
So it's definitely choice A.
Next problem. Actually I only have 40 seconds left,
so I'll do it in the next video.
See you soon.