Let's say I've got some type of book over here. There is my book
I'll write it down, book
Draw the entire book
So this is my entire book just like that
and then I have a mirror over here
This is our mirror. We're looking at from the side
So that is a mirror
I'm really picking an arbitrary point of this book
We know that there's light that is coming on this book
We're assuming that the book will reflect the light diffusely
like most books do. It's not a shiny book
And so any point on this book--we can pick any arbitrary point on this book
It's going to be emitting light at a whole bunch of directions
I'm going to pick 2 light rays that's being emitted from this point on the book
It'll be more than 2, but this will help us understand what's going on here
So let me pick one light rays that goes like this and hits the mirror
Incident angle is equal to reflected angles
So it'll reflect off at the same angle just like that
Let me pick another ray that is coming out radially from that same point like that
It has a larger incident angle, so it'll have a larger reflected angle, just like that
And now let's think about what an observer--someone who has their eyeball right over here
So let's think about what this person right over here will actually see
Now their eye--all reality is really just a big simulation just going on in our brains
Now this person's eye is going to see these 2 light rays diverging from some common point
If you were to look straight at the book--
let me just do another examples
Someone's looking any arbitrary object
Let's say, that's some orange right over there
Just ignore all the stuff on the left
Look at the orange. No mirror, nothing, no reflection or anything
If I look at a certain point on the orange
light from that point would be diverging out radially
and if my eyes were right over there
my brain says, okay, I have these light rays diverging from a single point
It will show me that point, that orange in my brain
Now the same thing is going to happen here
even though these 2 rays actually aren't diverging a point out here
Your brain will say, okay, I've got
2 rays that are coming out from what looks like a point over here
It'll really just extrapolate these lines backwards
It'll take that green ray and say, it must be coming from a point out there
and it'll take that magenta ray and say, it must be coming from a point out there
Even here, your eye is just seeing these two light rays
It doesn't know what's going on over here. It just says
okay, they're converging from a point
And so in this person's reality or my rally, I think that there is an orange there
Likewise, I see these two light rays diverging from some common point
I will extrapolate to figure out or my brain will try to think about where that
point is in a three-dimensional space. It says, look
these two rays look like are coming from a point back over here
Now the reality is, they're not back over here
There it nothing behind the mirror
but to this observer, it looks like the light is being emitted behind the mirror
So what the person would actually see is something like this
and this is probably not too foreign to anyone's experiences
We've all looked in mirrors
Remember, this is the right side of this book
This is the side that has the curvy part of the B
So this side has the curvy part of the B. So it looks like this
So what this observer sees is an image that looks like this
This is what people call the mirror image
It flipped the left and the right and you can think about why that is
I could draw another ray here to make it clear
This ray is coming like this. Now it will reflect and come out back like this
To this observer it came from that point right over there
So he sees a flipped version of the book
There's a whole reason why I did this
One's to make you feel a little comfortable with these reflecting lines and all of that
but I guess more importantly, to make you more comfortable with the idea of a virtual image
This right here is a a virtual image
We are going to compare it with a real image in the next video
To some degree, a virtual image is more intuitive
because we have so much experience with it when we think about mirrors or reflective surfaces
So it's a virtual image
We call it a virtual image because we can't--the book really isn't there
It's virtually there. There is no actual physical space for that image
Our brain just uses this diverging light
and creates a model inside of our brain to say, okay, that book exists there
even though the source of the light is over here
Now I'm going to draw another diagram. This is more--
you normally won't have the diagrams that have this type of perspective
but just to give you a sense of the same thing, of some of these diagrams we're gonna do
when we study mirrors and lenses
As we can imagine, let's say that this is the ground
This is our mirror
And let's say that this is--this actually could be somebody standing in front of a mirror
Usually people will draw an arrow here, just saying an arbitrary object
Let's just say we have an arrow in front of the mirror, just so you get used to this notation
This is just a physical arrow; this is not a light ray
Now let's think about what the image of this arrow
Let's say this arrow had eye. So it's actually a person
This arrow had eyes. What would this arrow see?
Let's just pick an arbitrary point of this arrow; you can do with any point
of this object, because every point will be reflecting light diffusely
So I'm gonna take one point that's coming straight out of the mirror
One light ray that goes straight to the mirror. Parallel to the ground
It's going to reflect straight off and then come back to the source of that light
may be that arrow's eye if you view it as a person
Let's just do another ray coming from that point. It might come out like that
Incident angle is equal to reflected angle. So it would come back like that
Now maybe this whole thing is an eye. Maybe that will simplify things
Let's say it's really close to the mirror. This whole thing is an eye
Now what would the eye see?
Well, this ray looks like it's coming from back over here
And this ray looks like it's coming from back over here
This is where they converge
So the eye would see this point of the eye over there
So it will actually see itself
And in general, this type of diagrams are used to think about
what would the real or virtual image be of an object
once the light from that object either is reflected off a mirror
or goes through some type of lens
We'll be doing this a lot more in future videos
but anyway, hopefully that gets you a little bit familiar with the things we'll be dealing with