So what are looking at here?
This is a Jackson Pollock,
in The Museum of Modern Art, number 1A, 1948
and it's one of his signature drip paintings
It's called 1A, is it his first?
It seems like it is based on how it was named.
Pollock was a little bit tricky with his naming conventions,
especially when he moved to numbering
and so he's not all that consistent..
Yeah..he didn't necessarily start with 1
and then sort of move up to 2,
in fact, I think he added the A at a later date.
He didn't want to confuse it with another painting that was called 1.
Haha, I see, we do that ourselves
with Khan Academy videos, we change the naming..
You know, when you look at this
and I've actually seen some of,
I don't know if I saw this exact piece,
they sometimes blend together a little bit,
but I've seen some of his paintings in real life
and, you know when you look at it, from afar,
they do look like, kind of just a mess, a craziness,
but up close, they just seem to be..you know I couldn't just
paint this exactly the way he did it, it seems like there is some technicality to it,
but it does, I guess a more general question of, I mean, it just looks like a random..
..mess or he just looks like he's throwing up paint there
and I think for a lot of people, they feel,
"So what's the big deal here?", you know I feel like a lot of people could have done something like this.
You know, I think Pollock actually would have liked the idea
that we looked at it and saw a bit of a mess,
in fact, one of the issues that he was interested in, I think,
certainly the abstract expressionists were interested in, is this idea that
somehow the internal self was being brought out and that might be, in fact, a mess.
You know, in a lot of our conversations, we've been talking about the importance of context,
not just looking at that piece by itself.
To get some context, and this was done in 1948, was there other stuff like this
that was done before or was he really the first to put up stuff like this?
He was really the first, in fact, one of his from patriots of another abstract expresions said: "Jackson really broke the ice."
This was the first painting. Not that was absolutely abstract
but there was what we called action painting
it's a kind of almost performative action in arena of the