Let's say I've been researching some
stocks to potentially invest in, and I feel pretty good
at my ability to predict how good a company's
going to do, relative to peoples' expectations
or the market's expectations. In particular I focus
on companies A and B. In the case of company A
I think it's going to do a lot worse than the market expects it to do
So, I'm tempted to short it. And in the case of company B
I think it's going to do much better than the market expects
So, I'm tempted to buy it, or go long.
But, there's one thing about this process that gets
me a little bit uncomfortable. I have confidence
in my ability to pick out companies that are
going to out-perform the market, or are going to under-perform the market
But, I have no confidence in my ability to predict the market.
In general... let me draw a little chart of the market
this is the market price, maybe this is the S&P 500 or the NASDAQ...
And I've just found that it's pretty as good as random
as opposed to me trying to pick out bottoms of the markets
or tops of the markets, and all of the rest
So, my fear is what happens if I buy company B,
based on my sound research, and then the market
goes down? Then company B will probably still go down.
Maybe it won't go down as much as the market
but it will still go down, and I will lose money.
Or what if I short company A and the market
goes up. Maybe company A won't go up as much
as the market, but I will still lose money on my
short position, which is essentially a bet
that the stock is going to go down.
Is there some arrangement I could do, some
combination of buying company B and selling (or shorting) company A
that will essentially hedge out a lot of this market risk?
and as you can imagine, there is! And I won't go into
all the statistics of it, and beta, and how you can
really try to statistically hedge-out the market risk
But the general idea is, if you really think this is
going to out-perform the market, or definitely
out-perform company A, and if you think A is
going to under-perform the market, or definitely
under-perform relative to company B, you can
buy a similar amount of B as you will short company A
So in this case, let's just do one share
you can obviously do multiples of this
you buy one share of company B, and you sell
or you short one share of company A
you borrow the share, you sell it, and you'll have to
buy it at a future date. So you short
two shares of company A, and the reason why I'm saying
two shares of company A instead of one share
is because A is only $5 per share and
B is $10 dollars per share. So I want to do
roughly the same amount, and once again, you can
do fancier statistics on it to tweak it, so you can
see how much they actually move in the market
but we're not going to worry about that right here.
So for simplicity, what we've done here is we've taken
a long position in B... and we have a $10 dollar long position
and we've taken a short position in A
and it is also a $10 short position. Once again
because A is $5 per share, so we've taken two shares of A
which makes the same dollar amount.
Now let's think about, and maybe I'll save this for the
next video, I want you to think about what happens
if the market moves up or down, but B out-performs A
or, A out-performs B?