Simplify the cube root of
125, x to the sixth, y to the third power.
So, taking the cube root of something
is the same as raising that something
to the one third power.
So, this is equal to
125, x to the sixth, y to the third power,
raised to the one third power.
And, if we take the product of a bunch of stuff
and raise that to the one third power
that's the same thing as individually raising
each of the things to the one third power,
and then taking the product.
So this is going to be equal to
125 to the one third power,
times x to the sixth to the one third power,
times y to the third to the one third power.
And then, we can think about how we can simplify each of these.
What is 125 to the one third?
Well, let's just factor and see if we can have
at least three prime factors of something,
and maybe more than one prime factor
that shows up three times.
So, 125 is 5 times 25.
25 is 5 times 5.
So, 125 really is 5 times 5 times 5.
So, if you multiply 5 times itself 3 times you get 125,
or 125 to the 1/3 power is going to be 5.
So, this is going to simplify to 5, times...
And then, x to the sixth to the one third power...
we saw this in a previous example.
If you raise a base to an exponent,
and then raise that whole thing to another exponent,
you can take the product of the two exponents.
So 6 times 1/3 is 6/3 or 2.
So this part, right over here simplifies to
x to the 6 divided by 3 power,
or x squared.
x squared.
And then, finally over here, same principle:
raising y to the third power
and then that to the one third power.
So, that's going to be y to the 3 to the 1/3 power,
or y to the first power.
And then times y.
And we are done.
And if you don't want to write this little multiplication here,
you can just write this as 5, x squared, y.
And we have simplified.