We're on problem 226
In the figure above-- let me draw the figure above
So I have a line there
then I have another line that's like that
and then this is a triangle like that, and then
they draw another line that goes straight down like that
And they call this right here z degrees, this is y degrees
this is x degrees
They tell us that these are right angles
Fair enough
In the figure above, if z is equal to 50
so that is equal to 50 degreeS
then x plus y is equal to what?
Well if z is 50-- well, first of all
we know since these are both right angles
both of these lines are going to be parallel, right?
Both of those lines are parallel
And so you can view this green line as a
transversal of the parallel
And so, z and y are corresponding angles
so y is also going to be 50
That should make a little intuitive sense
but you could watch the Khan Academy geometry videos
if that doesn't make sense
But just eyeballing it looks right, too
but that's a property of transversals and parallel lines
And if that's true, then what is this angle right here?
Well, 50 plus 90 plus this angle is equal to 180, right?
So we could say 50 plus 90 plus theta is equal to 180
So you get 140 plus theta is equal to 180
Subtract 140 from both sides
so theta is equal to 40 degrees
So this angle right here is 40 degrees
What's x?
Well, they're supplementary
They have to add up
They have to add up to be 180, right?
This whole angle's 180
So that whole angle is 180, this is 40
then x has to be 140 degrees
So they wanted to know what x plus y is?
Well x is 140, y is 50, so 140 plus 50 is 190 degrees
And that is not one of the choices
So I must have -- oh, I see my mistake
This angle right here
actually, we're still completely fine
This angle right here isn't y
This angle right here is y
But everything we did so far still holds
If this angle is 50, this angle is still 50
since it's a corresponding angle, right?
And if that's 50, this is 90, then this is 40, x is 140
Now we just have to figure out what y is
Well, y is supplementary with this angle right here, right?
So y plus this angle that I used to think was y
until I looked closely at the drawing
y plus 50 has to be equal to 180 degrees, right?
Because it's complementary with this 50 degree angle
So y is equal to 130
So x plus y is equal to 140 plus 130
which is equal to 270 degrees, and that's choice D
Problem 227
Looks like they've drawn another coordinate axis
which I'll draw
Nope, that's not what I want to draw with
I'll draw with that
OK, and then they have a line that comes down
something like that
And they mark it off
They say that this is-- let me see how they mark it off
They say that this is the point 1, this is the point 2
They don't write the 2 there
They call this line l
This is the origin
This is the x-axis and that is the y-axis
And they say in the coordinate system above
which of the following is the equation of line l?
Well, if we just eyeball it--
I mean, they don't say it explicitly
but it looks like this is intersecting at y is equal to 2
and this is intersecting at y is equal to 3
I guess that's a safe assumption
So how do we set up this equation?
Well, you just have to figure out the slope of the
y-intercept
We already know the y-intercept, right?
It intersects-- when x is 0-- so y of 0
When x is 0, y is equal to 2, so that's the y-intercept
and now we just have to figure out the slope
Well, let's think about the slope
If we take this point--
well, I'll do it the formal way, right?
The slope is equal to change in y over change in x
So let's take this as the end point
This is 3 comma 0, [PHONE RINGS]
and let's see who's on the phone
If it's someone-- oh, I'll take that call
I'll continue this in the next video