I have two identical rectangles here,
and I want to measure how much each of them,
or how much space each of them takes up on the plane of my screen; The screen you are looking at right now.
And I want to do it using two different units.
It is clear since they are two identical rectangles that they take up the exact, same amount of space.
They will have the same area.
But what we can see is that we can measure that area using different units.
So, first over here. Let's say, this figure is one foot in width.
So, let's say that, it is one foot in width. So that is, one foot in width.
And, it is also one foot in height. One foot in height.
So, this right over here is equal to one square foot. It is clearly a square, it has the same width and the same height.
And each of these dimensions are one foot. So, we can call it 'one square foot'.
So, let's see how many square feet we can get on to one of these rectangles.
Essentially, what we will be measuring its area in terms of square feet.
And, so we want to cover the entire space without overlapping, and without going over the boundaries.
So, that is: One...Two...Three...Four...Five...and Six.
Six in that first row. And then I have: Seven...Eight...Nine...Ten...Eleven...and Twelve.
So that looks like this area, which is the same as this area down here, if I were to measure in square feet it is equal to...
The area is equal to (let me write this down)...The area is equal to, we have (let me write it down): One...Two...Three...Four...Five...Six...Seven...Eight...Nine...Ten...Eleven...Twelve
square feet.
12 square feet.
Now, I am going to try to measure that same area in a different unit.
And I am going to make-up this unit.
I am going to call it a: "Furgle."
And a "Furgle" in one-dimension is twice a foot. And this (that) distance over here I am going to call a: "Furgle."
That is one "furgle." This is something that I made up just for the purposes of this video.
Most people will not recognize what a furgle is.
So, its height is one "furgle" and its width is one "furgle."
And so we can say that this is, one square "furgle."
One square "furgle." So, let's see how many square "furgles" is this area. That same area that is 12 square feet.
So, let me copy and paste this. So, let me, copy...and then paste.
So let's see, we can get one square"furgle" on there,
another square furgle on there
and we can get a third square "furgle" on there!
So, we get one...two...three square furgles.
The area of this figure in "furgles," square "furgles" I should say: The area is three square "furgles."
So it's the same exact area. Three square "furgles" is equal to twelve square feet.
Covering the exact same area.
And, what I encourage you to think about is:
How many square feet make a square "furgle"?