when we learned about social security
we saw that people who are currently working are paying their faco taxes
those...essentially those revenues are being used directly
to provide the social security benefits for
existing retirees and other beneficiaries
and any surplus courses Social security trust
and when you have this baby boomer generation
on the left hand side of this...
of the system right here so the baby boomer generation is this
huge population boom that happened after world war 2
after...after you know the country was happy
and all the soldiers had come back, they produced a lot of babies
and it was ...this population boom when the population boom
was on the left hand side of this system
they were able to generate a lot of revenue
to supply for the benefit for essentially
their parents' generation and so that did help build the surplus
the problem is that they didn't produce
uh...the population did not grow as much
as next generation and you can do that as a problem or a good thing
but it's a problem in the context of social security
because starting recently in over the next 2 decades
this baby boom generation is going to move on to the right
hand side of this equation
and we saw that they will start to
drawdown even this surplus fairly soon and that
because of this demographic change the social security surplus
will be completely depleted between 2030 and 2040
medicare is very similar
you have some portion of the faco taxes is for medicare
and that revenue is used to paid for the health benefits of the retirees
any surplus goes into a medicare trust and
that medicare trust of the formal name is the hospital insurance trust fund
the problem with medicare is that the situation is even worse
the medicare trust the medicare or i guess you could
see the medicare system is already running at a deficit meaning
they're spending more money on the right
they're spending more money on the right and they're getting it on the left
so there are already starting to drawdown
already starting to draw down their trust
so social security at least the trust is continuing to grow to 2023
and that's our best estimate right now
that it'll start drawing down and we get the puted between 2030 and 2040
in medicare
situations is a lot worse
so in medicare we are already starting to draw down the trust we are already
spending more beneficiaries and we're taking down
it that we were taking in fico revenues
and the entire trust based on uh...
our current assumptions will probably be depleted
in the next ten years
depleted
in next
ten years
and what makes medicare especially troubling despite the fact
it is a kind of a worst financial position
is that these costs are growing even faster
and i want to be clear a lot of people think that
the so for social security the main problem with this system over here
is a demographic changes you have this huge population
that's retiring the baby boomers
which makes this not sustainable
but with medicare that's also going on but what makes medicare even
uh...a bigger problems until security is above and beyond
those demographic changes above and beyond these
this baby boomer generation retiring
instead of paying into medicare takings benefits from medicare
the big problem is that you actually have medical
health care costs going up
well above the cost inflation personal security
these people's benefits to just go up with
inflation for medicare the benefits go up with
the cost of medical care and that's going well above
the cost of inflation and so you have the situation
where based on current benefits and our best assumptions
about the economy in the faco taxes coming in
you kind of have a reality where
if you have to give the cart benefits
and if you expect medical costs health care cost to
continue to increase at the rate they're doing
and there's no sign frankly that it is stopping
then you have this reality medicare
left on checked could at a rate right now
it's roughly about 23 percent of our budget 23,24 percent of our budget
Three twenty four percent of our budget,or about four percent of our GDP.
so here we are
twenty eleven it’s about four percent of our GDP,
we are spending on medicare and medicaid
and medicaid is essentially health benefits for mainly the poor
it’s run by the states but it’s gets federal funding
so right now that’s four perent of GDP,
but because of the cost growth in at health care costs,
if we need a completely inch unchecked over the next fifty sixty years.
it could go to fifteen sixteen seventeen percent of GDP in just to be clear.
that’s the ,that’s the percentage of GDP.
that’s roughly our entire federal budget.
So this has a potential if we do not grow our bugdet
any to actually crowd out a lot of other things and just understand this graph a little bit.
They show they said they show the part of that part of the cost of medicare
the part of the growth to do two defferent things
This is the effect of aging population.
This is the affect of access cost growth
and and this is the interaction of the two
and understand why that make sense,
you just have to think about the total costs being the product of the number
and maybe to see the net number of recipient for some people are paying as well.
But this will hopefully hope you understand what I’m talking about number of recipients,
number of recipients times.
Times the cost per recepient,solicited this is ht cost per recipient
cost per recipient.Cost per recipient
so if you take the numbers have been some times the cost per recipient
you are gonna get the total cost.
Let’s say that the total cost today.
So that’s that would be the area of that square just multipllying the base times high.
So card costs,
card cost and anunal cost,card costs.
Now because of demographic changes
you are going to have some increase in the net number of recipients.
so you were to have some increase there
but because of medical costs growth
you are going to have old big increase in the cost per recipient.
So this thing is going to increase much more
and so if you go to some future point when you can pice your future point.
But future point
i am really just try to make you understand why we have three categoriest.
the total cost is going not be that total cost for the total cost
is going to be that total cost for sippin that has grown dramatically
times the total number of recipients number of sippin
and so now you are talking about this area. this area.
this area is going to be the total cost
and if you think about how much of the stole
causes do purely to the increased cost growth
well it would be this part right over here.
would be this part over here
this part would be the amount the cost the increase in the area ture
ture purely due to the increased cost growth.
So that would be this part of the graph right over here.
What part of this increased area is due purely to the increased number of recipients.
Well,that would be best part of the graph right over here.
Purely due to the increased numbers recipients and that is right of your affect of aging population
And then, you have some part of this error
that’s created by both of you not increasing the number severty
and the increase in costs and thats going to be
That’s going to be this area right over here.
Which is this part of the graph.
So when people talk about the unsustainable.
Well one we have an unsustainable that to begin with
the second thing.The second thing is that the liabilities the obligations
that we have aren’t even on
these are not even counted in the govemment deficit
and these are the things that are really really scary.
Because something has to give
Some thing all of these that the single factor this t
this kind of driving most of the scariness is medicare in particular.
And not just medicare
but it’s not just the demographic change but specific to medical.
It’s the increased costs of healthccare
So if somehow that not can be cracked
if health care can also be grow maybe just with inflation or maybe even slightly fashion inflation
but not the right now
then you could to alarge degree mitigate kind of the scariest of
of what’s going on with our with our obligations.