We're asked to convert 150 degrees and -45 degrees to radians
So lets think about the relationship between degrees and radians
and to do that, let me just draw a little circle here so that's the center of the circle and then
do my best shot to
best attempt to draw a reasonable looking circle
eh, thats not, i've done worse...i've done worse than that
alright. Now if we were to go in degrees
if we were to go one time around the circle like that. How many degrees is that?
Well we know that, that would be 360 degrees.
Well if we did the same thing, how many radians is that?
If we were to go all the way around the circle. Well we just have to remember
when we're measuring in terms of radians we're really talking about the arc that subtends that angle
so if we go all the way around, you really talking about the arc length of the entire circle or essentially the