So if you're like me you probably don't carry around a protractor everywhere you go
and even if you do, you sometimes you want to have only the angles you want, because you needed a whole bunch
without all those other degrees getting in the way. This is the need that the Angle-A-Tron fufills.
A protractor is kinda like a 180 degree Angle-A-Tron. It's great at 180 degrees.
You can make your own 180 degree Angle-A-Tron super easily from any piece of paper.
Even if your paper doesn't have an edge, you can just fold it and ta-da Angle-A-Tron!
One extremely useful Angle-A-Tron is the 90 degree Angle-A-Tron.
Many pieces of paper come pre-equipped with one of these,
but, if they dont, you can get one by folding a 180 degree Angle-A-Tron in half.
Now, you can draw all sorts of "rectangley things" and "perpendicularites".
Following the "fold stuff in half" method you can get a 45 degree Angle-A-Tron pretty easily,
or a 22.5 degrees, or a 11.25, and so on.
And you get these weird looking numbers, but that's only because we started with something
arbitrary, like 360 degrees, when, really the numbers we are looking at
are a half, a fourth, an eighth, a sixteenth,
you know, one over two to the n. It's not hard to fold paper into thirds, either.
Might take a litte evening out, then BAM!
180 degrees turns into 60 degrees, good for making equilateral triangles.
Or put two together and get 120 degrees, a very common and useful angle.
For when, say, bubbles meet, If you're drawing bubbles. Or honeycombs, or something.
Then you can start adding them together, 135 degrees is easy, 90 degrees plus 45 degrees.
Now you can make puzzles for yourself. Say you make a 60 degree Angle-A-Tron, and a 135 degree Angle-A-Tron,
How do you make an Angle-A-Tron that completes the circle?
Or, if a friend gives you an Angle-A-Tron, can you make a Complementary, or supplementary, I forget which is which,
Angle-A-Tron? And then, let me know if this is going a little bit too far, maybe you can put an Angle-A-Tron on
your Angle-A-Tron. And now, I have a 60 degrees, and another 60 degrees, which comes over here,
to make another 60 degrees, and now I have an equilateral Triangle Polygon-A-Tron!
And just in case you thought that wasn't going to far, Why not make that a Polyhedron-A-Tron?