What I wanna do in this video is introduce you
to what I think is one of the neatest ideas in computer science
and that is recursion.
So the way we define this factorial function
in the last two videos is actually an iterative definition.
We're iterating through different values
for this variable "i", and then we're essentially
taking those value adding one then
multipling those times over our original "product".
And when we keep iterating through all of that,
our eventual product has all the values from one
through the number multiplied by each other
and they're all sitting in this variable "product".
What I'm gonna do here is rewrite this program.
What's cool about functions, I'm gonna rewrite this function,
what's cool about functions are...
This function, we just say: "Look, it returns a factorial of a number".
We don't care how this is actually written.
And so, anything that's using this function,
no matter how I implemented it,
as long as I implemented it correctly,
it shouldn't worry about it.
So as long as I implemented this, the inside,
the guts of this function right,
even if I do it in a very different way,
it shouldn't affect the behaviour
of any of the functions that called it.
So, let's go ahead and try to define this
function recursively.
And I think you're gonna find this
slightly fascinating.
So, I'm gonna do it a little bit different.
We're gonna get some conditionals in here as well,
so I'm gonna say...
Some way recursion is really deep and complicated
and in some levels, it's way simpler than anything else.
So let me put all of this stuff down there...
So, I'm gonna say: "Look, if the number..."
You always wanna think about a base case.
What's the situation where the smallest values
we can put into for number, that will give us
a decent response?
So, we'll say: "Look.
If number is less than or equal to 1.
So, if it is less than or equal to 1,
let's just return, then it's factorial is...
let's just return one.
As if you wanna have the same behaviour
as the old function.
The old function, regardless of wether we put
a one there, a zero there, actually you can put
a -1 or -2 there, it always gave us the factorial
being equal to 1.
So, that's exactly what we're doing over here.
We're returning 1 if the number is less than one.
And this also defines our base case.
I can even label it here.
This is our base case.
And you will see what I mean for a second
by a base case.
And this is, what I'm about to do now,
this is the really exciting part about recursion.
If the number is not less than or equal to one,
so I can write elif,
let me write else actually.
So if the number is not less than or equal to one,
I'm gonna return something different.
And what I'm gonna return is
that number times the factorial of one less than that number.
Now, the reason why this is fascinating and cool,
and all the rest, is that I've just defined something
using that something.
So I've just defined a function called "factorial"
and I've defineded it using the definition of
the function factorial.
It is referring to itself.
This is what recursive functions do.
But if you think about it, and I'll diagram it out
in more detail in the next video
so it makes a little bit more sense,
it should kind of work.
'cause if you put a 1 or a 0 in for number
it'll just return 1.
What happens if number is 2?
Well, if number is 2, it'll say:
"Look, number is less than one, so I'll go over here."
So it says:
"It'll return 2 times factorial of 2-1."
Or factorial of 1.
Then it'll call factorial again,
and factorial of 1 is just 1.
So it'll return 2 times 1.
So, that'll work out for 2.
Try it for 3.
If you do factorial of 3,
it'll go down to this clause over here,
'casue 3 is nos less than or equal than 1,
and it'll return 3 times the factorial of 3-1,
which is 2. The factorial of 2.
And we now that it'll return the right answer
for factorial of 2, so it'll return
3 times 2, which is 6, which is the factorial of 3.
So hopefully you're getting the gist of it.
Factorial of 4 is going to work for the exact same reason.
It's gonna boil down to to 4 times the factorial of 3.
We know that it works for the factorial of 3.
And just to prove to you that I'm not doing
some type of crazy voodoo, and that
this will actually work,
let's try to run the program.
Let's try to run the program right here.
So, this is some stuff I was doing before hand,
let's get rid of that.
So, let's just run the program.
So, all I've done is I've redefined
the factorial function, but
I've redefined it recursively.
I don't wanna have to change the comments, so
let me save it and
let's run, let's interpretate this program,
let's execute it and see if it does
what we need it to do.
All right!
So they're prompting us for something,
let's say the factorial of 5.
120.
So, once again, our factorial program
no matter what we put in there,
it gives us the right answer.
But what's really cool is that it's now
doing it recursevly.
When I do factorial of 6,
say: "Ok, factorial of 6.
Is 6 less than or equal than 1?"
No, it's not.
So it goes to this else clause right over here.
So, then it says:
"Return 6 times the factorial of 5."
Ok, let me remember, 6 times
the factorial of 5 was...
I forgot what the factorial of 5 is!
Well, the factorial of 5 is going to be
5 times the factorial of 4.
And so, then that factorial of 4 is
4 times the factorial of 3,
all the way down to the factorial of 1, which is 1.
And so, it'll actually return 6 times
5 times 4 times 3 times 2 times 1.