We're on 121.
It says, if x/2 is equal to 3/y, is x less than y?
So this is essentially saying that x times y is equal to 6.
I just cross multiplied. Or you could do that step by step.
Multiply both sides by 2. Then, multiply both sides by y.
And you get xy is equal to 6.
And they want to know whether x is less than y.
Statement 1 says, y is greater than or equal to 3.
If y is greater than or equal to 3, what does that mean?
So let's think about this. x is equal to 6 divided by y.
If y is greater than or equal to 3-- so if it's 3,
that's the largest that x can be if y is 3.
If y is any larger number, then x will only be smaller.
So x will be less than or equal to 6/3.
Or x will be less than or equal to 2.
And just, I want you to understand why I said that.
Think about this. It says, y is greater than or equal to 3.
If y is 3, x is going to be 2.
If y is 4, x is going to be 1 and 1/2.
If y is 6, x is going to be 1.
So the highest value for x happens when y is equal to 3.
And then, as y gets larger and larger, x just gets smaller.
So y being greater than or equal to 3 says that x is less
than or equal to 2. So statement 1, alone,
is sufficient to say that x is less than y.
If x is less than 2 and y is greater than 3,
then x is definitely less than y.
Statement 2 tells us, y is less than or equal to 4.
So this is interesting.
It's really just the inverse of this statement right here.
Now, you're saying, instead of y being greater than a certain
number, y is less than a certain number.
So if you think about it this way-- so let's go
back to this equation.
If y is 4, x is going to be-- let's do a little table. y, x.
If y is equal to 4, x is equal to 1.5.
If y is equal to 3, x is equal to 2.
If y is equal to 2, then x is equal to 3.
So actually, this constraint, I can pick a bunch of
different y's that meet this constraint.
But it still doesn't tell me about anything whether x is
greater than or less than y. Here, x is less than y.
And here, x is greater than y. So this statement is useless.
So statement 1, alone, is sufficient to answer this question.
Statement 2 doesn't help us much. 122.
If v and w are different integers, does v equal 0?
Different integers. Remember, it says, different.
They say that vw is equal to v squared.
Now, let's think about this.
This doesn't tell me for sure that v is equal to 0.
And, in fact, as long as-- well, let's think about this.
The only way that this could be true is if v is equal to 0,
that's one case. Now, if v does not equal to 0--
So if v does not equal to 0, then this case implies what?
That soon. w equals v. Think about it.
If v doesn't equal 0, we can divide both sides by v.
Because we know we're not dividing by 0.
You divide both sides by v,you get, on the left-hand side, w.
Because this v cancels out.
And then v squared divided by v, you get v.
And so you are left with--
Well, I want to be careful here, though.
Because w would have to equal v. And
they already told us that w and v are two different numbers.
So we know that this situation-- if w equals v,
then v does not equal 0.
But they tell us in the problem statement that w and v
are two different integers.
They tell us that w does not equal v.
So we know that the only way that this could be satisfied,
if w does not equal v, is if v is equal to 0.
So statement 1, alone, is sufficient to answer this question.
Statement 2. w is equal to 2.
Well, that doesn't do anything for me.
I mean w could be 2 and v could be 0. Or v could be 3.
All they told us was that v and w are different integers
and that they don't equal each other.
So this doesn't help me at all in determining whether
v is equal to 0. So statement 1, alone, is sufficient.
I just want to make sure I got that first part right.
I mean the only way that this is true,
this is true if v is equal to 0.
Or it's true if w is equal to v.
Either of those cases are true. That's the only way it works.
And we know w does not equal v. So v has to be equal to 0.
What are we on? 123.
What is the value of 36,500 times 1.05 to the nth power?
All right, statement number 1 tells us,
n squared minus 5n plus 6 is equal to 0.
So we could solve for n. There will be two solutions.
So this is n minus 2 times n minus 3. I just factored it.
I said, what two numbers, when I multiply them,
equal positive 6? So I said, minus 2, minus 3.
And when you add them become minus 5.
That's why I picked the minuses, as opposed to plus 2
and plus 3 or some other combination. Equals 0.
So statement 1 tells us that n is equal to 2 or
n is equal to 3. So statement 1, by itself, isn't enough.
Because I don't know whether
I should put a 2 here or a 3 here.
So I can't determine this value just yet.
Statement 2 tells us, n minus 2 does not equal 0.
This statement, by itself, is fairly useless.
Because it just tells me that n does not equal 2.
So n could be any other number.
So I don't know what number to put here.
But used in conjunction, these two statements--
statement 1 says that n is either 2 or 3.
Statement 2 says, well, it's not 2.
So if you use both of these together,
we know that n is equal to 3.
And then we can, obviously, solve this problem.
Taking 1.05 to the third power and multiplying by 36,500,
which I won't do because it would be a waste of time. 124.
In the rectangular coordinate system above--let me draw that.
They have the y-axis. They have the x-axis.
Then, they draw on a triangle.
I'll do that in a different color. That and like that.
And the letters are O, P, you and Q.
In the rectangular coordinate system above, if OP is less
than PQ-- so OP is less than PQ. Let me write that down.
OP is less than PQ. Is the area of OPQ greater than 48?
So we want to know, is area greater than 48?
OP is less than PQ.
So the way I drew this actually isn't right.
It's probably a little bit shifted to the left a little bit.
But fair enough. We can visualize. We can imagine that.
So let's see. Statement number 1.
The coordinates of point P are 6 comma 8.
So this is 6 comma 8. Let's see. That tells us the height.
When we figure out the area of a triangle,
we need to know the base times the height.
And then multiply that times 1/2.
The height of this triangle is the y-coordinate,
which is 8. So the altitude of this triangle is 8.
So we have the height, but we still don't know the distance
from O to Q.
So statement 1, by itself, isn't much information.
So that tells that the point was 6, 8. That P was 6, 8.
Statement 2 says, the coordinates of point Q are 13 comma 0.
Well, this is helpful. 13 comma 0.
So this distance right here is 13.
So by itself, that's useless.
Because if I didn't have the height, I still wouldn't be
able to figure out the area of this triangle.
But now, if I use both statements,
I know the base times the height.
So the area is going to be the base times the height times1/2
So 8 times 1/2 is 4. Times 13 is 52.
And so 52 is clearly greater than 48. Let me make sure.
Because I didn't use this information.
I didn't use that information at all.
Let's see. Let me think about it. Actually, no.
I think I'm wrong.I think statement 1,alone, might be enough.
Let's assume that we don't have-- these are tricky.
Let's assume that we don't have statement 2 there.
Let me see if I can figure out whether the area is greater
than 48 without it.
Let me see. Yeah, I think I'm wrong. I caught myself.
OK, so if this is 6 comma 8,
the area of this triangle right here,
well, this distance right here is going to be 6.
This distance right here is 6. 6 comma 8. Right.
OK, so the area of this triangle is 6 times 8. 48 times 1/2.
So the area of this triangle is 24.
But they told us that OP is less than PQ.
That this distance is less than this distance.
Maybe I should draw it like that, so you can kind of see it.
And the only way that this distance is less than this
distance is if this distance is less than this distance.
This is a tricky problem. This has to be less than this.
Q has to be further away.
Because that's the only way you're going to get this
altitude to be longer than this altitude.
Because you're assuming that Q is along the axes.
So that's the only thing that you can shift back and forth.
So if this distance is larger than this distance,
then the area of this triangle is going to be at least 24.
So the area is going to be greater than 48.
So actually, all you needed was statement 1
to solve this problem. That's all you needed.
Statement 1 gave you enough information.
Statement 2 does not, by itself, give you enough
information because you don't know how high P is.
It could be really low down here, in which case the area
is going to be less than 48.
It could be really high, in which case the area would be
greater than 48.
But anyway, see, I almost got that one wrong.
But I'll leave you there. I'll see you in the next video.
Statement 1, alone, was sufficient for this one.
See soon.