of my name is james white and today it
will be investigating he transferred
heat transfer affects our everyday life
for example it allows our computers
around without burning up it helps us to
design houses they use less energy
it makes cooking food possible
and very importantly it helps keep us
warm or cool like this radiator
we'll look at three different types of
he transferred
conduction convection and radiation and
fine examples where they occur roundups
to do this will use a thermal camera at
thermal camera can see the radiation
given off by all objects and use it to
measure their temperatures
for example called objects normally give
off less radiation
then hot objects which give off more
aviation
the camera records this radiation and
creates a picture
the colors in the picture represent
temperatures
hotter temperatures are lighter colors
and colder temperatures are darker
colors
in this picture my hand is warm but the
copper wire below it
is cold
however at the camera is and always
correct let's look at a video of the
lighter fluid
although the flame appears to be the
same time because my hand
it's actually about two thousand degrees
celsius
this is too hot for the video to show us
the real temperature
using the lighter in copper wire we will
observe the first type of heat renter
conduction
i'll show you our simple experiment
conductive heat transfer occurs when
there's a temperature difference between
two materials in contact with each other
in this case the right side of the wires
heated by the lighter
at this point temperature in the
material is very high and one area and
cold in other areas
he transfers from the high temperatures
sided to the low temperatures sat
wet swatches this happens
overtime the temperature of the material
becomes more more uniform
as he transfer moves energy from hot to
cold areas of the wire
when including a building we often care
about keeping warm or cold air inside
how long can retain heat of building
depends on two things its thickness and
its thermal conductivity
materials that are thicker
will at last he through
materials with higher thermal
conductivity
will add more heat through
how do you think this metal door
compares to this poem panel which lets
the more heat
what about traditional materials like
these adobe blocks
when the temperature of a waller door is
different than the surrounding area
a different type of heat transfer begin
to kerr
named convection
a lighter a copper wire in a cardboard
backdrop makeup are simple experiment
with emmitt till is hotter a colour than
a fluid surrounding it
it causes the fluid to rise rsync
in the case of aha wire heated air rises
as cold air fills its place
this cools down the wire faster than
conduction
if we push the wire towards the
cardboard
we see that the hot air rising off the
wire heats the cardboard this hot stream
of air is call the convection correct
and is part of natural convection
sometimes natural convection is
ambassador so engineers will use force
convection your computer uses force
convection to keep itself from
overheating
that's why you're fans too
using the thermal camera of we can see
that this laptop as several hot
components
here here
here and here
when these components get too hot
fans in the laptop will start to pull
cool air across the parts
this results imports connection
the hot air is them blown out the side
or back of the computer
her dad mentioned that all objects give
off radiation
when radiation from a hot object
it's another object it warms it up
this process is called thermal radiation
too bright lights a piece of aluminum
foil and a cardboard backdrop make our
simple experiment
when the lights are turned on let's see
what happens
we can see the radiation from the lights
is absorbed by the cardboard
however the radiation is reflected by
the aluminum foil
when the lights are turned off
we can see that the cardboard under the
aluminum foil was not heated because
radiation never reach it
the sun is an extremely hot object and
it's there more radiation warms our
entire planet
this means that when designing a
building
window placement is a very important
part of the thermal engineering
when the sun's radiation comes through
windows
it will heat up the exposed cooler
indoor materials
conducting convection then transfer this
heat around the building
by considering thermal radiation
indesign a building will be warmer
during the winter and cooler during the
summer
radiators are common way to keep
buildings in cold environments
although named irradiated this device
actually uses radiation and convection
transfer it to you to the room
thermal radiation is sent out in all
directions from the radiator and makes
you very warm when you stand next to it
natural convection then circulates the
hot air from the radiator around the
building
there are so many examples of heat
transfer or owners every day
and as engineers we have to think about
using them to make the world a better
place