Let's do a little bit of probability with playing cards
For the sake of this video we're going to assume
that our deck has no jokers in it.
You could do the same problems with the joker,
you'll just get slightly different numbers.
So with that out of the way
Let's first just think about
how many cards we have in a standard playing deck?
so you have four suits
and the suits are: the spades, the diamonds, the clubs
and the hearts.
You have four suits
and then in each of those suits you have thirteen different
types of cards or sometimes it's called the rank.
So each suit has thirteen types of cards
You have the ace, then you have the two, the three,
the four, the five, the six, seven, eight, nine, ten
and then you have the jack, the king and the queen.
And that is thirteen cards
So you can have for each suit you can have
any of these, for any of these you can have any of the suits
So you can a jack of diamonds, a jack of clubs
a jack of spades or a jack of hearts.
So if you just multiply these two things
you could take a deck of playing cards and actually
count them, take up the jokers and count them.
But if you just multiply this, you have four suits
each of those suits has thirteen types
so you're gonna have 4 times 13 cards
or you gonna have 52 cards in a standard playing deck.
Another way you can say it is like: look, there is thirteen
of these ranks or types
and each of those come in four different suits,
13 times 4 once again you'd have gotten 52 cards.
Now that out of the way, let's think about the probabilities
of different events.
So let's say I shuffled that deck,
I shuffled it really, really well.
And then I randomly picked a card from that deck.
And I want to think about what is the probability that I pick
what is the probability that I pick a jack?
Well, how many equally likely events are there?
Well, I can pick anyone of those 52 cards, so there's
52 possibilities for when I pick that card.
And how many of those 52 possibilities are jacks?
Well, you have the jack of spades, the jack of diamonds
the jack of clubs and the jack of hearts.
There's four jacks
There's four jacks in that deck.
So it is 4 over 52, these are both divisible by four
Four divided by four is one
52 divided by 4 is 13.
Now let's think about
the probability, so I will, you know, we're gonna start over
I'm gonna put that jack back in, I'm gonna reshuffle the deck
So once again I still have 52 cards.
So what's the probability that I get a hearts?
What's the probability that I randomly picked a card from
a shuffled deck and it is a hearts? Its suit is a heart.
Well once again, there's 52 possible cards I could pick from
52 possible, equally likely events that we're dealing with
And how many of those have our hearts?
Well, essentially thirteen of them are hearts. For each
of those suits you have thirteen types so there's thirteen
hearts in that deck, there thirteen diamonds in that deck
there thirteen spades in that deck, there thirteen clubs in that deck.
So the 13 of the 52 would result in hearts.
And both of those are divisible by 13, this is the same
thing as one forth. One in four times I'll pick it out
or I'll have one forth probability of getting a hearts
when I go to that, when I randomly pick a card
from that shuffled deck.
Now let's do some things a little bit more interesting
or maybe it's a little obvious: what's the probability
that I pick something that is a jack and it is a hearts?
Well, if you're reasonably familiar with cards, you'll know
that there's actually one card that is both jack and a heart
It is literally jack of hearts.
So we're saying what is the probability we picked exactly the card
jack of hearts?
Well, there's only one event, one card that meets these criteria
right over here and there's 52 possible cards.
So there's a 1 in 52 chance that I pick the jack of hearts
something that is both a jack and it's a heart.
Now let's do something a little more interesting.
What is the probability, you may want to pause this and think
about this a little bit before I give you the answer, what is the
probability of, so I once again have a deck of 52 cards, I shuffle it
randomly pick a card from that deck, what is the probability that
that card I picked from that deck is jack or a heart?
So it could be the jack of hearts or it could be the jack of diamonds
or could be the jack of spades or it could be the queen of hearts
or it could be two of hearts. So what is the probability of this?
And this is a little bit more of an interesting thing, because it's
we know first of all that there are 52 possibilities
but how many of those possibilities meet the criteria
meet these conditions, that it is a jack or a heart.
And to understand that I'll draw a Venn diagram.
Sounds kind of fancy, but nothing fancy here.
So imagine that this rectangle I'm drawing here represents
all of the outcomes. So if you want you can imagine it has
area of 52. So this is 52 possible outcomes, now how many of
those outcomes result in a jack?
So we already learned this, one out of thirteen of those outcomes
result in a jack. So I can draw a little circle here with that area
and I'm approximating
that represents the probability of a jack.
So that should be roughly 1/13 or 4/52 of this area
right over here. So I'll just draw it like this. So this right over here
is probability of a jack. It is four, there's four possible
cards out of the fifty two. So that's 4/52 or 1/13.
Now what's the probability of getting a hearts?
Well, I'll draw another circle here, that represents that.
13 out of 52, 13 out of these 52 cards represent a heart.
And actually one of them represents both a heart and a jack.
So I'll actually overlap them and hopefully this will make sense
in a second.
So there's actually thirteen cards that are heart.
So this is the number of hearts.
And actually let me right that top thing that way as well.
It makes it a little bit clear, we were actually looking at -- clear that
-- so the number of jacks. And of course this overlap
right here is the number of jacks and hearts. The number
of items out of this 52 that are both a jack and a heart.
It is in both sets here it is in this green circle and it is in
this orange circle. So this right over here I'm going to do that in yellow
since I did that problem in yellow.
This right over here is a number of jack and hearts
so let me draw a little arrow there. It's getting a little cluttered
I've actually should've drawn it little bit bigger.
The number of jacks and hearts.
And that's an overlap over there, so what's the probability
of getting a jack or a heart?
So if you think about it the probability is going to be the number of
events that meet this conditions over the total number of events.
Yeah, we already know the total number of events are 52.
But how many meet this conditions?
So it's going to be the number, it's going to be
you could say: well look, the green circle right there says the number
that gives us the jack and the orange circle tells us the number
that gives us a heart. So you might wanna say
well, why don't we add up the green and the orange,
but if you did that you'd be double-counting.
Cause if you add it up, if just did four plus thirteen
what are we saying?
We're saying that there are four jacks and we're saying
that there thirteen hearts.
But in both of these we're, in both when we're doing it this way
in both cases we're counting the jack of hearts.
We're putting jack of hearts here and we're putting a jack of hearts here
So we're counting jack of hearts twice, even though there's only
one card there. So you'd have to subtract out where they're common.
You'd have to subtract out the item that is both the jack
and a heart.
So you'd subtract out a one.
Another way to think about it is
You really want to figure out the total area here.
Let me zoom in. I'll generalize it a little bit.
So if you have one circle like that and then you have another
overlapping circle like that. And you want to figure the total area
of both of the circles combined. You'll look at the area
of this circle and then you could add it to the area of this circle.
But when you do that, you'll see that when you add the two areas
you're counting this area twice.
So in order to only count that area once, you have to subtract
that area from the sum.
So if this area, if this is, if this area has A, this area is B
And the intersection, where they overlap is C
the combined area is going to be A plus B minus where they overlap
minus C.
So that's the same thing over here.
We're counting all the jacks and that includes the jack of hearts
we're counting all the hearts and that includes the jack of hearts.
So we counted the jack of hearts twice, so we have to subtract one out of that.
So it's going to be four plus thirteen minus one.
Or this is going to be 16/52. And both of those things are divisible
by four.
So this is going to be the same thing as
if I divided sixteen by four you get four, fifty two divided by four
is thirteen.
So this is, there's 4/13 chance that you get a jack or a hearts.