I wasn't serious when I came up with this idea,
but you know how these things get out of... hand.
All right, listen up-each of my fingers is a digit,
but instead of a ones, tens, hundreds, thousands place
which are the power of ten, try it again
with ones, twos, fours, eights, sixteens and remember count it one to eight.
Now instead of ones and zeros, let's use your fingers: one, two, three.
This is how you count with your hands in binary
i'm gonna make it easy and write the place values on my fingertips
count the ones you see.
Four plus two, that's six.
Sixteen plus two is eighteen, and you can do it up.
Or dance it down put those digits on the ground.
Now do it with me.
One... two... three... four... five... six... seven... eight.
Hands at one... two... three... four... five... six... seven...eight.
Now, pi in binary looks something like this.
One, one, point zero zero one, zero zero one, dot dot dot.
It's not what we're doing.
We're taking the decimal version and putting each digit in binary.
Now let's dance us some pi.
We got three, one, four.
I've got my bro doing three, one, four.
Got my mama doing three, one, four.
Even my grandma's doing three, one, four.
All right, one,
two,
three,
four,
five,
six,
seven,
eight,
nine,
ten,
eleven,
twelve,
thirteen,
fourteen,
fifteen,
sixteen,
seventeen,
eighteen,
nineteen,
twenty,
twenty-one,
twenty-two,
twenty-three,
twenty-four,
twenty-five,
twenty-six,
twenty-seven,
twenty-eight,
twenty-nine,
thirty,
thirty-one, oh!