We're in the church of Santa Maria del Carmine
in a chapel within the church
which is called the Brancacci chapel.
it is completely filled with fresco and also tempa painting
and on the left in the upper register,
is a painting by Masaccio
It's actually two paintings.
One is the "Expulsion from Eden"
and to its right, is a much larger painting,
"The Tribute Money"
And the chapel is filled with people here
to see Masaccio's great masterpeice.
Masaccio painted a few of the scenes here
of the life of Saint Peter,
but the rest of the chapel was largely
painted by one of his contemporaries, Masculino.
But it's Masaccio that we are here to see.
So let's talk about the "Tribute Money" first
It's a pretty complicated scene. It's a story from the
New Testament that tells of Christ
being confronted by a tax collector who works for Rome.
The problem is Christ has renounced
all worldly possessions;
he doesn't have any money to pay.
Right, Christ and the apostles have no money to pay the tax collector who we see here in the center
in orange with his back to us.
And with a short skirt, unlike the
other figures which are more fully clothed.
And Christ and the apostles have helos,
and we can identify the tax collector
because he doesn't have a halo.
And he's making gestures demanding money.
The tax collector is standing in the lovely contrapposto.
And some art historians have suggested that they may have been painted from a Roman sculpture.
The contrapposto could have also
have come from Donatello.
Absolutely.
Christ directs Saint Peter to go get money
to pay the tax collector from the Sea of Galilee,
from the mouth of a fish. So Christ performs a miracle, the apostles will indeed be able to pay
the tax collector because the money
will appear in the mouth of a fish,
that we see Saint Peter getting on the far left,
and then on the far right,
we see Saint Peter paying the tax collector.
So we have three difference moments of time.
In the New Testament, Christ says:
"Render unto Caesar what is Caesar's,
render unto God what is God's."
In a sense saying, Caesar minted this money -
we can give it back to him -
it's not important. What's important is the soul.
There's a really specific Florentine context for this.
The Florentine government had just initiated a new tax
called the 'Catasto' which was an income tax.
I think this was seen by the Florentines as an idea
that Christ was condoning that kind if civic responsibility.
I'm really interested in how complicated that story is,
and yet how clearly Masaccio was able to convey it.
Our eye goes not to the left of the scene first,
which presumably would be where we would start -
we read from left to right.
But instead goes to Christ in the center.
All of the apostles attention and the tax collector's attention
is on Christ. And so our eyes go to Christ as well.
Christ points to Peter who in turn points, almost incredulously, to the Sea of Galilee
Right, you want me to go to get the money from where?
And that of course moves our eye left,
over to where we see Peter again.
We can recognize it's Peter,
even though his face is so foreshortened.
He has taken off the red garb, presumably
not to get it dirty or wet as he kneels.
You can see him just opening up the
mouth of the fish.
I love it. It's so literal.
It's very sweet.
Masaccio is also separating
that scene on the left,
so we read it as a separate scene.
Because he has put Saint Peter
way into the background.
And there really is a background.
And it's been accomplished in a
number of different ways.
This is lovely atmospheric perspective that allows
us to move back from mountain to mountain
as the sky gets lighter.
Masaccio has created a deep illusion of space here.
So the figures are really in a very believable landscape.
Not only the atmospheric perspective,
but linear perspective is employed on the right.
We can see the orthogonals in the rather
classical looking building on the right.
In fact, sometimes I've suspected the only reason
that there's a building in this painting at all,
is because Masaccio is so interested in linear perspective.
This is one of the first surviving examples of employment of linear perspective in a painting.
And we have the "Holy Trinity" just a year or so earlier.
Christ's head is the vanishing point
in his use of linear perspective
so not only is all of the attention
paid to Christ by his apostles,
but the very structure of the painting brings our eye there.
So you look as Christ - he looks very calm.
You follow his gesture over to Saint Peter
and Saint Peter looking agitated and annoyed.
He does look grumpy, doesn't he?
And in disbelief.
And then you see this circular gathering
of the apostels around them and
you start to register their reactions.
Some of them looking
"Oh, what's going to happen next?"
Apprehensive.
Some of them looking a little bit more calm.
But in all of that, Christ remains central
and calm in this moment
when he performs a miracle.
It really is a kind of conversation.
It's all this gesturing to tell the story.
Really activating the story. Absolutely.
I really love also, the contrast between certain apostles.
For instance, you're absolutely right.
Peter looks like he's angry.
And is not sure if he is not sure if he should actually
be protecting Christ from the tax collector or not.
Whereas John, next to him with blonde hair,
is such a passive face.
Very calm.
So calm. I can't help but think Masaccio put
those faces together in order to achieve
the greatest contrast.
I think there is no question.
I mean Masaccio is thinking about every possible way
he can make this image seem real.
And I think that the space, to a 15th century viewer,
looked incredibly realistic.
The use of light and shadow really
picking up on Giotto's achievement
of the previous century.
And pushing it forward dramatically.
To me, the element that adds the
greatest realism are those cast shadows on the ground.
Yes, they're amazing.
They're so believable. I mean you really get a sense of
of these figures standing in a landscape.
The light hitting them from the right,
which is by the way, the same direction
as the real light in the chapel.
There's a window over to the right.
Just over the alter.
If you follow those shadows back,
if you look down at the ground,
they give you an alternation of light and dark
that helps establish a foreground and background.
I have to say I'm really taken with
the representation of the feet.
We talked about the sense of mass
and volume in the figures.
All of these figures seem so planted.
Oh, I love their feet.
There're so grounded. If you, look for example
at the left of the tax collector, you'll see
that the left side of his ankle is in shadow, but the front
part of his left foot is in the sunlight.
So, Masaccio is paying such careful
attention to light and shadow.
And look at those foreshortened halos
that Masaccio puts in place
so that they're not those flat gold circles that...
Well, they're foreshortened, just like
Peter's face on the left of the painting.
Right, except a halo isn't a real thing.
So in a sense, taking this symbol of spirituality and
treating it as if it were a solid in the world.
It is this funny moment in the 15th century when the symbolic traditions of representation
that have been handed down from the Medieval,
are coming into contact
with a kind of naturalistic facility,
and an interest in naturalism.
And so you get these very funny relationships.
So Masaccio really is giving us a masterpiece of
illusionism, of the illusion of space,
of the illusion of volume.
To me, the figures are just fully
human in the way
I think about Donatello's figures or,
and San Michele.
They have psychological depth.
What is it about Florentine culture that is allowing
for this kind of fully human expression?
And this is one of the great centers of humanism,
that's looking back to classicism
and certainly we see that in a number of direct ways.
But more than that,
it's this ennobling of the human experience
that I think is so central to the
license that Masaccio was taking here.