Add: 5x squared plus 8x minus 3
Plus 2x squared minus 7x plus 13x
So we can really view this as just adding two polynomials.
The second polynomial can be simplified right off of the bat.
We have two like terms here. It's not the 2x squared. There's no other 2x squared term here in this
polynomial.
but you have a -7x term and then you have a +13x.
So we can actually add these two terms.
What is -7 of something plus 13 of that something?
Or another way to view it. What is 13x minus 7x? 13 of that something minus 6 of that something?
It's just going to be 6x. And then you have your 2x squared right over here.
So this polynomial here simplifies to 2x squared plus 6x.
And then we want to add it to this polynomial right over here.
And what we can do is rewrite this polynomial under this polynomial.
And I'm going to align the similar terms or the like terms.
The terms that have the same variable raised to the same power.
So we have x raised to the 2nd power, x raised to the 2nd power. So let's put the 5x squared over
here
We have an x raised to the 1st power, an x raised to the 1st power. So let's put the 8x over here.
And then we don't have a constant term in the first, this yellow, polynomial.
We don't have anything raised to the 0th power.
Or an constant terms but we do here. So let's just put a minus 3.
And then we can add these two things up. We have 2x squared plus 5x squared.
That is 2 of something plus 5 of something is 7 of that something.
So it's going to be 7x squared.
And then to that if I have 6 of something and I add 8 of that something to it.
I'm gonna have 14 of that something.
If I have 6 x's and I give you 8 more x's, you're gonna have 14 x's.
And then we have nothing here. So if we add nothing to -3, you're just going to have a -3.
So this simplifies to 7x squared plus 14 x minus 3.