Ancient Greek's sculptures, bronze or marble, are frozen
but that doesn't mean that the the Ancient Greeks did not want to convey
movement. In this
case movement that couldn't even see with the naked eye
What we are looking at is a sculpture by a artist whose name is Myron.
We've lost his original, but we have a later marble
of the discuss thrower.
The original was in bronze from the 5th century BCE.
About 450 to 460 and what we are looking at is one of many
Roman copies, in fact, there is one next to the other in this museum
Testimate to how popular these were among the Romans.
This sculpture shows a man who is at that moment
where his body is fully wound.
Look at the way that his right leg is
baring the weight of his body. His left leg, the toes
are bent under, dragging slightly, he is about to throw that discus.
There is this moment of tremendous attention
but it is also this moment of stasis, stillness, right
before action. Athletes and our historians have
debated whether this is even an actual pose that
the discus thrower would actually takes in the process.
It's so interesting because when we look back to the history
of the Greek figure we think, first, of the archaic
who is so stiff and so stylized and then we just break
throughs of people like Polyclitus who develop an understanding
of the body and show it in (...) but here we
have something so dynamic and so complex and just look at
the arc of the shoulders and the arms and the way that they reverse
the arc of the twist of the hips.
That is the overriding concern of Myron the sculpture to capture
the aesthetic qualities here, the sense of balance
and harmony, and the beauty and the proportions of the body
There is a kind of anti realism here for all of its
careful naturalism. There is no real strain
within the body. It is absolutely at rest and ideal
even in this extreme pose. If your think of a figure
from much later, but in a similar pose of movement and athletic
energy like Bernini's David. Well that has got
portion, absolutely. That figure expresses all of the
physical power of the face. He is clinching his teeth
That's true and his brow is really nit forward, but
here the face is absolutely serene and it reminds me
of the consistence that the Greeks always contained
their nobility, even in battle, even in terrible situation with monsters
and here even at this moment when he is about to release
the discus. That nobility, calmness in the face
is a sign of a nobility of the human being.
Well, this is a sport, and the the man is naked, which
was what the Greeks did, but there was a real logic there.
Why would you cover up the beauty of the body
in sport, which is a celebration of what the
human body can achieve. This is really
a way to remind ourselves of the potential of humanity
the potential of the mind and the potential of the body.
Taken that extra step to become even more ideal, more heroic,
more noble than even the finest athlete.
It is a perfect form.
Music...