What I wanna do this video is prove that the opposite angles
of a parallelogram are congruent
So, for example, we wanna prove that CAB is congruent to BDC
So, that angle is equal to that angle and that ABD,
which is this angle is congruent to DCA which
is that angle over here
And to do that we just have to realize that we have some parallel
lines, we have some transversals and the parallel lines
and the transversals actually switch roles
So, let's just continue these so it looks a little bit more like
transversals intersecting parallel lines
And really you could just post it for yourself and try to prove it
'cause it really just comes out of alternate interior angles and
corresponding angles of transversals intersecting parallel lines
So, let's say the angle right over here, let's make this,
let me do the new color since I've already used that yellow
So, let's say, let's start right here at angle BDC
Well angle BDC and I'm just gonna mark this up here
Angle BDC over here, it is an alternate interior angle with this
angle right over here with that angle right over there
And actually we can extend this point over here
I could call that point E if I want
So, I could say angle CDB is congruent to angle EBD
by alternate interior angles
This is a transversal, these two lines are parallel
AB or AE is parallel to CD
Fair enough
Now, if we kinda change our thinking a little bit
and instead we now view BD and AC as the parallel line
and now view AB as the transversal, then we see that angle EBD
is going to be congruent to angle BAC because they're
corresponding angles
So, angle EBD is going to be congruent to angle BAC
or I could say CAB they are corresponding angles
And so, if this angle is congruent to that angle,
that angle is congruent to that angle,
then they're congruent to each other
So, angle, let me make sure I get this right, CDB
or we could say BDC is congruent to angle CAB
So, we've proven this first part right over here
And then to prove that these two are congruent,
use the exact same logic
So, first of all we view this as a transversal
We view AC as a transversal of AB and CD
And let me go here and let me create another point here,
let me call this point, point F right over here
So, we know that angle ACD is going to be congruent
to angle FAC because they are alternate interior angles
And then we change our thinking a little bit and we view AC
and BD as the parallel line and AB as the transversal
And then, angle FAC is going to be congruent to angle ABD
because they're corresponding angles
Angle FAC is congruent to angle ABD and
they are corresponding angles
So, in the first time we view this as the transversal AC
is a transversal of AB and CD which are parallel lines
Now AB is a transversal and BD and AC are the parallel lines
And obviously if this is congruent to that and that is congruent
to that then these two would have to be congruent to each other
So, we see that if we have opposite angles that are congruent
then or if we have a parallelogram then the opposite angles
are going to be congruent