We've got 9601 - 8023.
And immediately when we try to start subtracting
in our 1s place, we have a problem.
This 3 is larger than this 1.
And we also have this
problem in the 10s place.
This 2 is larger than this 0.
So we're going to have to do some
type of borrowing – or regrouping.
And so, the way I like to think about it –
I like to go to the first place value
that has something to give.
Obviously, the 10s place is in no position
to give anything to the 1s place.
It needs things itself.
And so we're going to go
to the 100s place –
because the 100s place has
an abundance of value
that can be regrouped into
the 10s and 1s places.
This 6 right over here
represents 6 hundreds.
So why don't we take 1 hundred
from that 6 hundred –
(So then this will become 5 hundred.)
– and then give that 100 over to the 10s place.
Now, if we give 1 hundred to the 10s place,
how would I represent that in the 10s place?
Well I have 0 10s.
And now I'm going to give 100
100is the same thing as 10 10s.
It's going to be 0 + 100.
100 in the 10s place is just 10.
So let me write it this way.
So this right over here
is now going to be rewritten as 10.
Now you might be saying, "Wait, wait, wait.
"What's going on here Sal?
"You took 100 from the 100s place.
That's why it became 500.
Now why did this become 10 and not 100?"
Now remember, this is 10 10s.
So this is still representing 100.
You have not changed the value of this top number.
Before, the value was 9000 + 600 + 1
Now it's 9000 + 500 + 100 ...
(10 × 10 is 100.) ... + 1.
I have not changed the value here.
Now, we're still not done yet.
We don't want to just subtract, because
we still have the problem with the 1s place.
The 1s place still doesn't have enough value.
Now, the good thing is we've given
some value to the 10s place.
So why don't we take 10s from the 10s place?
So if you have 10 10s, and you take
1 10 away, you're going to be left
with 9 10s, or 90.
And then we can take that 10
and give it to the 1s place
So let's do that.
You take that 10 we just took
from there, and you give it to the 1s place.
You now have 11 here.
And now we are ready to subtract.
11 - 3 is 8.
9 - 2, (this is really 90 - 20) is 70.
Then in the 10s place, we represent that as a 7.
5 hundreds - 0 hundred is 5 hundreds (500),
represented as a 5 in the 100s place.
9000 - 8000 is 1000.
And we're done.
And just to make things really clear,
I'm going to redo this problem now 
but with things expanded out.
So, this first number is 9000.
9 thousands + 6 hundreds + 0 tens + 1 one.
(9000 + 600 + 00 + 1.)
And this number right here,
we are subtracting 8 thousands 
we are subtracting 0 hundreds.
We are subtracting 2 tens, which is 20.
Subtracting 20.
And subtracting 3 ones.
So I have just rewritten
this exact same statement
but the regrouping, and the borrowing
is going to become
a little bit clearer now.
So, the same exact thing 
We say "Hey, we can't subtract this 3
from this 1 or the 20 from the 0."
But we have a lot of value
over here in the 600.
So why don't we take 100
from that, (So it becomes 500.)
 and we give that 100
to the 10s place.
So this becomes 100.
Notice, the value has not changed,
this is 9000 + 500 + 100 + 1
That's the same thing as
9000 + 600 + 1.
We have just put the value
in different places.
And here we have explicitly written 100.
But when represented in the 10s place,
10 10s is the same thing as 100.
Now, we aren't done
regrouping just yet.
We want to give some
value to the 1s place.
So, we can take 10 from the 10s place
(And this becomes a 90.)
 and give that 10 to the 1s place.
10 + 1 is 11.
So notice, I did the exact borrowing 
the exact regrouping  that I did here.
I just represented it
a little bit differently.
This 500 was represented
by a 5 in the 100s place.
This 90 was represented
by 9 in the 10s place.
But either way, we are
ready to subtract now.
11 - 3 is 8.
90 - 20 is 70...
Let's write a plus (+) there.
500 - 0 is 500.
And then 9000 - 8000 is 1000.
And we got the same result 
because 1000 + 500 + 70 + 8 is 1578.