Use the change of base formula to find log base 5 of 100,
to the nearest thousandth.
So the change of the base formula is a useful formula,
especially when you're going to use a calculator,
because most calculators don't allow you to arbitrarily change
the base of your logarithm.
They have functions for log base e,
which is a natural logarithm.
And log base 10.
So you generally need to change your base.
And that's what change of base formula is.
And if we have time, I'll tell you why it makes a lot of sense
or how we can derive it.
So the change of the base formula just tells us that
-- and let me do some colors here --
log of base a of b is the same thing as log base x,
where x is arbitrary base of b over log base x over a.
The reason why this is useful is that we can change our base.
Here our base is a and we can change it to base x.
So if our calculator has a certain base x function
we can convert to that base, it's usually e or base 10.
Base 10 is an easy way to go.
And in general if you just see someone write a logarithm like this.
If they just write log of x -- they're implying, this implies
log base 10 of x.
If someone writes natural log of x,
they're implying log base e of x.
And e is obviously the number 2.71...keeps going on and on forever.
Now, let's apply it to this problem.
We have logarithm -- I'll use colors -- base 5 of 100.
So this property, this change of base formula tells us that
this is exact same thing as log -- I'll make x = 10 --
log base 10 of 100 divided by log base 10 of 5.
And actually we don't even need a calculator to evaluate this top part.
log base 10 of 100 -- what power I have to rise 10 to get to 100?
The second power.
So this enumerator is just equal to 2.
So this simplifies to 2 over log base 10 of 5.
We can now use our calculator, because log function
on the calculator is log base 10.
So let's get our calculator out. And we're going to get,
we want -- let me clear this -- 2 divided by,
when someone just writes log, they mean base 10.
They press ln, they mean base e. So log without any other information
is log base 10.
So it is log base 10 of 5 is equal to,
and they want us to round to the nearest thousandth,
so 2.861.
So this is approximately equal to 2.861.
And we can verify it, because in theory if I raise 5
to this power I should get 100. And it kinda makes sense,
cause 5 to the 2nd power is 25, 5 to the 3rd power is 125.
And this is in between the two and it's closer to the third power
than it is to the second power and this number is closer to three
than it is to 2.
But let's verify it, so if I take 5 to that power.
And let me type in what we did, to the nearest thousadth.
5 to the 2.861, so I'm not putting in all of the digits.
What do I get?
I get 99.94. if I'd put all of those digits in, it should get pretty close
to 100.
So that's what make you feel good that this is the power
you have to raise 5 to get to 100.
Now that out of the way, let's actually think about
why this property, why this thing right over here makes sense?
So if I write log base a, I'm trying to be fair to the colors,
log base a of b, let's say I said that to be equal to
some number, let's call that's equal to c.
So that means a to c-th power is equal to b.
This is an exponential way of writing this truth.
This is a logarithmic way of writing this truth.
... is equal to b.
Now we can take the logarithm of any base of both sides of this.
Anything you do... if you say 10 to the what power is equal this.
10 to the same power will be equal to this,
cause those two things are equal to each other.
So let's take the same logarithm of both sides of this.
So logarithm with the same base.
And I actually will do log base x, to prove the general case here.
So I'm going to take log base x of both sides of this.
So this is log base x of a to the c-th power.
I'm trying to be faithful to the colors.
Is equal to log base x of b.
Let me close it of with orange as well.
And we know from out logarithm properties:
log of a to the c is the same thing as c times the logarithm
of whatever base we are of a.
And of course this going to be equal to log base x of b.
Let me put b right over there.
and if we want to solve for the c,
you just divide both sides by log base x of a.
So you get c is equal to and I'll stick to the color --
so it's log base x of b over log base x of a.
And this is what c was, c was logarithm base a of b.
... is equal to log base a of b.
Let me write it... let me do it in the original colors,
just so it becomes very clear what I'm doing.
I think you know where this is going.
But I want to be fair to the colors.
So c is equal to log base x of b over --
let me scroll down a little bit --
over log base x -- dividing both sides by that -- of a.
And we know from here, I can just copy and paste it.
This is also equal to c.
This is how we defined it.
So let me copy it and then we paste it.
This is also equal to c.
And we're done.
We've proven the change of the base formula.
Log of base a of b is equal to log base x of b divided by log base x of a.
And in this example: a was 5, b is 100
and base we switched to is 10 -- x is 10.