Let's see if we can add 9.087 to 15.31.
And I encourage you to pause the video and try to do it on your own.
So I'm assuming you have tried to do it on your own.
And now let's see how we could actually tackle this.
Now one thing I want to point out.
Some of you all might see these numbers all lined up, and immediately want to say,
"Hey. 7 + 1 is 8.
And 8 + 3 is 11.
Carry the 1, etc., etc."
And if you did that, you would be making a mistake.
Because, you see, right over here, these decimals aren't lined up.
Here, if you did that, you'd be adding the 7 thousandths to 1hundredths.
You'd be adding 0 tenths to 5 ones.
You'd be adding 9 to 1 tens, because essentially, this is a 10 right over here.
So the places would be all mixed up.
So what you need to do is to actually align the decimals so that your place values are aligned.
So what you want to do is you want to align things up.
So we could write 9.087.
And then we want to align the decimals.
So let's align the decimals.
This is what has to match up.
And this is going to be 15.31.
And this should hopefully make sense to you, as well.
This is 9. + 15..
So is going to be – if you add 9.. to 15.., you get will be 24., give or take a little bit.
So now you see that here.Here you have a 9 plus 15.
You have lined up the appropriate place values.
And now we are ready to add.
It's a good idea to start with the smallest place value, so if you have any extra at a certain place, you can bring into some you can bring something into the next place value.
So here you say 7 –
This is 7 thousandths.
This is in the thousandths place.
And you might say, "What do I add it to?
There are no thousandths right over here."
And you're right.
There are no thousandths.
So we could rewrite that as 0 thousandths.
So 7 thousandths + 0 thousandths is 7 thousandths.
8 hundredths + 1 hundredth is 9 hundredths.
0 + 0 tenths + 3 tenths is 3 tenths.
We got our decimal.
Then you have 9 ones + 5 ones is 14 ones.
Well 14 ones is the same thing as 4 ones and 1 tens.
So we'll carry that 1 right over there.
This is just 1 ten + 4 ones which is 14.
And so finally we have 1 ten plus another ten is 2 .
So we get 24.397.