I thought I would do another example of partial quotient method
for long division
So there actually has some positives to do
It's actually kind of fun to do
So let's say I want to do something really hairy
like 291 divided into-- let me just throw some digits over here-
actually let's stole another digit right over here-
So this is- how many times does 291 go into- what is this-
9,873,952
And to just kind of get our bearings
we know what 291 times 1 is. That's pretty easy
291 times 1 is clearly just 291
We know what 291 times 10 is. That's clearly 2,910
Let's get some stuff in between here
that will help us to try to approximate
how many times 291 goes into this crazy thing over here
So let's just pick- in the last example I picked 2 and 5-
you could just pick 3 and 6 if you want
You could pick 2 and 7. You could pick whatever you want
You could even just do 1
one of them, one of the above
Let's just say 291 times- let's try 3 out. 291 times 3
So I could do this in my head
or I could just make sure I don't make a mistake
Let me do it right over here
So 291 times 3 is- 1 times 3 is 3. 9 times 3 is 27
2 times 3 is 6. 6 plus 2 is 8
So this is equal to 873
It's actually strange that 873 showed up over there
My brain is doing strange things in the back ground
But anyway
that has actually no relevance to the actual solution of this problem
And let's also try 291 times 6. Let's figure out what that is
So 291 times 6
It's actually going to be this thing times 2
But I'll just calculate it. 291 times 6-
1 times 6 is 6. 9 times 6 is 54. 2 times 6 is 12, plus 5 is 17
So it's 1746
And you might say, Sal
why did you go through the trouble of figuring out this and this?
And I'm just using these as some of the approximation tools
when we try to figure out
how many times 291 goes through this whole crazy mess
So first of all, let's just look at this whole thing
This is 9873952
So let's just say, how many times does 291 go into 9,000,000?
So 291 times 3 would be 873
We want to have a bunch of zeros after the 873
So think of it this way- I'm picking 873
because its leading digit is as closer than 9 as possible
But it's definitely lower than the 9
So you say, okay, 873- and I'm going to have 1,2,3,4 zeros behind it
So 291 times 3 would give me 873
But I have to multiply- times 3 with 1,2,3,4 zeros to get this number
8.73 million
I have to multiply by 30,000
But I got this straight from this idea, that 291 times 3 is 873
So let's subtract this right over here. Let's subtract this
2 minus 0 is 2. 5, 9, 3, 7 minus 3 is 4, 8 minus 7 is 1
9 minus 8 is 1
So now we are left with 1,143,952
So which of these just gets us right under that?
So let's see, if we want to go to-
we can't go straight to 1746
That would be too big over here
We might want to do 873 again
But this time we are going to do 873,000
That is equal to 3- and then you have 1,2,3 zeros. So 1,2,3
3 times 291 is 873. 3000, is 873000
Let me write this a little bit neater
My handwriting is- so this is going to be 3000
3000 times 291
Let me make sure. This is a 2 right over here. 2 minus 0 is 2
And then you subtract again
2 minus 0 is 2. 5 minus 0 is 5. 9 minus 0 is 9. 3 minus 3 is 0
And then you have 4 minus 7
The way I like to do it when I have to start regrouping and borrowing
is making sure I go from the left
So this 1, I could borrow from there. So this becomes 11
And then the 4, I can borrow 1 from here
So that becomes a 10, and this becomes a 14
So 14 minus 7 is 7. 10 minus 8 is 2
Now 270,952. What's right below that?
So it seems we can get pretty close if we do 291 times 6
If we do a 1746, and then add two zeros to it
This is going to be times 6 with two zeros
So this is times 600
Once again, you subtract
We see I'm only using the 6 and 3
because I figured those out ahead of time
so I didn't have to do any extra math
2 minus 0 is 2. 5 minus 0 is 5. 9 minus 6 is 3. 0 minus 4--
Well, there are a couple of ways you can think about doing this
You could borrow from here. That will become a 6
This becomes a 10. 10 minus 4 is 6
Now this one is lower, so it has to borrow as well
Make this into a 16. 16 minus 7-
I have multiple of videos on how to borrow
if I'm doing that part too fast
But the idea here is to show you a different way of long division
So 16 minus 7 is 9
So now, 96,352
And once again
it looks like the 873 is about the closest we can get
So let me put a 873 over here with 2 zeros
So that would literally be 291 times 3 with 2 zeros
Times 300. And so once again, we want to subtract here
2 minus 0- you get a 2. 5. 0. Make this a 16. Make this an 8
16 minus 7 is 9
And then we have to get close to 9,052
Once again, that 873- those digits look pretty good
873- we still want to multiply 3, and then 10
So this is going to be times 30 right over here
We subtract again. 2 minus 0 is 2. 5 minus 3 is 2
And then you have 90 minus 87 is 3
I'm doing the subtraction a little fast
just so we can get the general idea
Then we have to go into 322. How can we get close to that?
Well, actually 291 is pretty darn close to that
So it's 291. You go into it one time
1 times 291 is 291. 2 minus 1 is 1. 32 minus 29 is 3
So you have a remainder of 31
291 cannot go into 31 any more. So that's our remainder
But how many times does it actually go into this big beastly number?
This 9,873,952
Well, there, we just have to add up all of these right over here
30000 plus 3000- we could even do it in our head
30000 plus 3000 is 33,000. 33600. 33900. 33931
33,931
And we're done, assuming I haven't made some silly mistake
291 goes into this thing 33,931 times with a remainder of 31