So let's start with 3 points: point A, point B, and point C
and if we connect these 3 points,
and they are not co-linear, they are not on the same line,
if I connect them with line segments, I will get a triangle
I think you're familiar with the idea of a triangle
now what I wanna do in this video is prove
that the angles inside a triangle sum up to 180 degrees
if the measure of this angle is a, the measure of this angle is b, the measure of this angle is c,
and I use lower case a, b, and c
actually, let me not use those, as I've already used A, B, and C
This is x, y and z, I am going to prove that
x+y+z = 180 degrees
Now let me clear up some space
What I am going to do is I am going to start off
by constructing a line that is parallel to
line segment BC, but it goes through Point A.
That line might look something like this
I can call that line L, & let me continue
this line segment BC into a line
They really are parallel lines, so Line L is parallel to BC
and the reason why i do that is then all of a sudden
the two other sides of the triangle become transversals
Line AB & AC intersect these two paralell lines
If you think how could you construct a parallel line
all of a sudden, you could always given one line
find a point off that line where a unique parallel line
goes through that.
So what I want to do is to think of line segment
AB & AC as transversals of those two parallel lines
That is line AB and then i have line AC
Now let us think about the sum of the angles
inside the triangle. Let us say the measure of this angle
over here is x, well we know from parallel lines
that this is one angle between the transversals
and one of the parallel lines then there is a
corresponding angle between the same transversal and the
other parallel line . We know that the corresponding angle
is equal to x. If this 30 degrees, that is also 30 degrees
We also know that if that is x, the vertical angle
is also going to be x. So this is also going to be x
Now let us think about another angle in the triangle
The measure of this angle over here is y
So if this angle is y what is this entire angle
That is going to be x + y. If this entire angle is x+y,
then does x=Y have any corresponding angles
It has a corresponding angle right over here
This angle is also x+y.
Now, if this angle is x+y, what is this
angle over here. This angle is supplementary to
this magenta angle.So x+y + ? = 180 degrees
So, ? angle is 180-x-y .
So given how we have set up the three angles, let us add
it up . We have x+y+180-x-y= 180 degrees
So we proved ourselves that sum of angles of
of any triangle add upto 180 degrees