We are asked to solve log of x plus log of 3 is equal to
2 log of 4 minus log of 2.
So let's just rewrite it.
So we have the log of x plus the log of 3
is equal to 2 times the log of 4 minus the log of 2.
And this is reminder: whenever you see logarithm
written without a base, the implicit base is 10.
So we could write 10 here, here, here and here.
But for the rest of this example,
I'll just skip writing 10 just cause it'll save a little bit time.
But remember it only means log base 10.
So this expression right over here
is the power I have to raise 10 to get x.
Power I have to raise 10 to get 3.
Now that out of the way,
let's see what logarithm properties we can use.
So we know -- and these are all the same base --
we know that if we have log base a of b plus log base a of c
that this is the same thing as log base a of bc.
And we also know --
so let me write all of the logarithm properties that we know,
over here.
We also know that if we have a logarithm --
let me write it this way actually times log base a of c
this is equal to log base a of c to the b-th power.
And we also know --
and this is derived really straight from both of these, is:
that log base a of b minus log base a of c
that this is equal to log base a of b over c.
And this is really straight derived from these two right over here.
Now with that out of the way let's see what we can apply.
So right over here we have -- all of the logs are the same base --
we have logarithm of x plus logarithm of 3,
so by this property right over here --
the sum of the logarithms of the same base
this is going to be equal to log base 10 of 3 times x of 3x.
Then based on this property right over here
this thing can be rewritten, this is going to be equal to
this can be written as log base 10 of 4 to the second power,
which is really just 16.
and then we still have minus logarithm base 10 of 2.
And now using this last property --
we know we have one logarithm minus another logarithm.
This is going to be equal to log base 10 of 16 over 2,
16 divided by 2, which is the same thing as 8.
So right-hand side simplifies to log base 10 of 8
the left-hand side is log base 10 of 3x.
So if 10 to some power is going to be equal 3x,
10 to the same power is going to be equal to 8.
So 3x must be equal to 8.
3x is equal to 8.
And then we can divide both sides by 3.
You get x is equal to 8 over 3.
One way this little step here I said: look this is an exponent.
If I raise 10 to this exponent I get 3x,
10 to this exponent I get 8.
So 8 and 3x must be the same thing.
One other way you could've thought about is:
let's take 10 to this power on both sides.
So you could say 10 to this power and then 10 to this power over here.
If I raise 10 to the power that I need to raise 10 to get 3x
well I'm just going to get 3x!
If I raise 10 to the power that I need to raise 10 to get 8
I'm just going to get 8.
So once again you get 3x is equal to 8.
And you can simplify,you get x is equal to 8/3.