It's very complicated with this body thing, you know, how--
I was painting as a young artist, and mostly I was painting these clouds.
And one day, sitting and painting and looking at the sky,
I saw 12 military planes passing by,
and they made these incredible drawings in the sky,
and I looked at them and I said God it's ridiculous
I'm painting these paitings that are so two-dimensional.
Maybe I could go to the military base and ask for
the twelve planes to make drawings in the sky.
I went to the military base and my father was a general in the army
so they called him and said "Your daughter is in our base. Can you take her home
because she's out of her mind. She wants to use the planes to paint the sky.
Do you know how much this could cost?"
So after that I stopped painting
and I started realizing I could use any material I want.
Fire, water, and the body.
And the moment when I started using the body i felt enormous satisfaction.
That I could communicate with the public that I never could do anything else.
I could never go back to the seclusion of the studio and be protected by the space there.
The only way of expression is to perform.
And if I put art into a heirarychy I would always put music on the top
because it is so immaterial enough to (
incoherent) performance
and then any other art, from a subjective point of view.