What is the slope of the line that contains the points (7/2, -19/4) and (-2/3, 57/8) ?
So I will do this problem because those people who wrote this problem want us to do it this way,
by using the formula.
But you know I'm not a fan of blindly using formulas.
So maybe after we do this, we will work it out, or we will visualise it a little bit
to show us the formula really is just measuring the inclination of the line.
So if I have two points,
So let's say one point is (x1,y1)
The other point is (X2,Y2). The slope of a line; and they use the letter "m" for the slope of the line.
Is going to be the difference between the "y"s, and you want to make sure
you get the order right. So if we start with "Y2"