In the first video in future's fair value
we learned that it was the price
at which an investor would be neutral
between buying the stock
on the actual stock market
or buying the front month future's contract
What I want to to in this video
is talk about how does one interpret the fair value
especially relative to the future's price
So lets say you wake up one morning
the market hasn't opened yet
the stock market hasn't opened
and you see a quote like this for stock ABCD
The fair value according to
the closing of yesterday's trading
the fair value is $102
but the future's market which trades
usually as the trading hours
beyond the regular market
and often times 24 hours
So the future's market trading price
for the front month future
even though the fair value
based on yesterday's closing is $102
The future's market is trading at $101
So how would you use that information
or how would one interpret that information
So the future's market
people are trading the futures contract
They are buying and selling
at price below the fair value
based on yesterday's close price
So what that means is
that the market thinks that
this is actually no longer
the correct price of the stock
They think that the correct price of the stock
is the stock at which they would be neutral
between that price and this future's contract
So I don't know what it is
you'd have to discount it back
by the risk-free rate
but maybe its something like
So this is implicitly saying
that the correct price of the stock isn't $100
if the future's price was $102
it would say that the stock should be $100
If the future's price is $101
then it means that maybe
the stock is something less than that
Maybe if we do our math
maybe it implies a stock price of $99.
So the way you would potentially act on it.
although it's easlier said than done
is say well look that means that
at least in the very early stages once the market opens
the stock is going to go down
Now you initial reaction might be saying
Wow, this is really amazing
this is some type of future indicator
and it is pretty strong future indicator
when you see this
when you see the actual price of the future
being below the fair value
It is very likely that the stock will open down
Unfortunately, you have many many
very sophisticated high frequency traders
who already have their computers set up
to look at this type of discrepency
and they are going to be ultra fast
and they are optimizing
how fast their bandwidth is
so they can do these
in a matter of split seconds
So it is very, very unlikely
that a average investor
or even a reasonably sophisticated investor
will be able to take advantage
of this type of arbitrage
or this type of an expected arbitrage
to know this price is likely to go down
Now, if the opposite happened
let's say that the fair value is $102
which implies that the fair value
of the front month future's contract is $102
which implies $100 stock price
Let's say that the future's
is actually trading
even though the fair value is $102
Let's say it's trading at $105
So, this is a situation that
since the market closed
the future's market for some reason thinks
that the stock is going to be worth more
This would imply a stock price
of, maybe, I don't know what it might be
I'm not going to do the math exactly
but maybe a price of $103 or $104
And so if you saw this
where the future's price is above the fair value
in the pre-market
that means that the stock is likely to go up
But once again, its very hard
to take advantage of
because you're going to see that movement
very, very, very quickly.