[intro music]
We're in Louvre and
we're looking at the Victory Stele of Naram-Sin.
This a really old stele.
It's a really old relief sculpture.
It is 4200 years old.
It was made, we think, in approximately 2200 BCE.
Now, Naram-Sin was the great-great grandson
of the founding king of Akkadia, Sargon.
And this stele
commemorates a really important victory of his.
It commemorates a victory over the Lullubi people
who were mountain people
living in the Eastern region of Mesopotamia.
Now, normally victory scenes like this from Ancient Mesopotamia
are shown in registers.
In other words,
the scene is divided into horizontal bands.
Here, the artist has created a new kind of composition
where we see Naram-Sin at the top.
And diagonally on the left,
underneath Naram-Sin,
we see his soldiers climbing the mountain.
And then on the right, the vanquished,
falling and defeated and wounded.
What I find so interesting is that
Naram-Sin's army is so disciplined.
They don't break ranks,
they're marching in line.
There're standard bearers
followed by those with weapons
whereas on the right there's all kinds of chaos.
And Naram-Sin is so erect and noble-looking,
and clearly associated with the gods,
compared to the mortals that surround him.
One of the things I have noticed immediately is
how everyone's gaze, or nearly everyone's gaze,
is directed at Naram-Sin himself.
So his soldiers look up at him,
the vanquished turn towards him.
He's clearly the focal point of this composition.
One of aspects that I love most about this
are the vanquished, I have to say.
You have one of the vanquished mountain people
who were actually literally thrown off the mountain.
You can see him upside down, falling,
as if he's falling into water.
You see somebody else literally under Naram-Sin's foot,
somebody with a spear in his neck.
And then, most interestingly, I think,
to the extreme right,
profiled against the mountain,
is a man who is fleeing.
Because you can see that
his feet are facing away from Naram-Sin,
but he's also turned around,
turned back and pleading as he flees.
Clearly, what we're seeing
is using a symbolic language.
This isn't supposed to be a naturalistic representation
of an army climbing a mountain,
but a symbolic image that
tells the story through symbols of this event.
And so we see Naram-Sin,
much larger than everyone else,
with his shoulders frontal, his head in profile,
and close to the deities of the top
who are represented by... well, they're look like suns.
Right, the suns or the stars above are the forces
that have helped guide him to victory.
But also, and this is important,
he's wearing a horned helmet
which is for the Akkadians a symbol of divinity.
So through this victory,
he's actually assuming the importance and status of the gods.
Right.
And in fact, the whole ascension to the mountain top
certainly supports this idea
he's rising into the realm of the heavenly.
[outro music]