A ball is shot into the air from the edge of a building
50 feet above the ground
It s initial velocity is 20 feet per second
The equation h (height) = -(negative)16t squared+20t+50 can be used to model the height of the ball
after t second
And I think in this problem they just want us to accept this formula
Although we do derive formulas like this
we show why it works for this type of problem in the Khan academy Physics playlist
But for here we will just go with the flow in this example
So they give us the equation that we use to model the height of the ball after t seconds
and then say about how long does it take the ball to hit the ground
So if this is the height, the groudn is when the height is equal to zero
So hitting the ground literally means that h (height) is equal to zero
So we need to figure out at which times does h (height) equal zero
So we are really solving the equation
0 = -16tsquared + 20t + 50
And if you want to simplify this a little bit
Let's see everything here is divisible at least by 2
so let's divide everything by negative 2 just so that we can be rid of this negative coefficient
So you divide the left hand side by negative 2, you still get a zero
Negative 16 divided by negative 2 is eight so 8t squared
20 divided by negative two is negative 10
Minus 10t
50 divided by negative 2 is minus 25
is equal to zero. If you okay with this on the left hand side you can put it on the left hand side
We can say this is equal to 0
And now we solve
And we can complete the square here or apply the quadratic formula which is derived from
completing the square
and we have this in standard form, we know that this is our a
this our b and this over here is our c
And the quadratic formula tells us that the roots
In this case in terms of the variable t are going to be equal to
negative b plus or minus the square root of b squared minus four a c.
All of that over 2 a
So if we apply it we get t is equal to negative b
b is negative 10
so negative negative 10 is going to be postitive 10
plus or minus the square root of negative ten squared
well thats just positive 100 - 4*a which is 8
times c which is negative 25
and all of that over 2 a
a is 8 so 2a is 16
and this over here we have a negative sign
negative times a negative... so this is a positive
4 times 25 is 100
100 times 8 is 800
so all that simplifies to 800
and we have 100 + 800 under the radical sign
so 10 plus or minus the square root of 900 all of that over 16
is equal to 10 + or - 30 over 16
so we get time is equal to 10+30/16
40-16 which is the same thing if we divide the numerator
and denominator by 4
which is 10 over... or even better divide by 8
5 over 2
so thats one solution.
Thats if we add the 30
if we subtract the 30
so or t = 10 -30 which is -20 over 16
divide the numerator and the denominator by 4
and you get -5 over 4
Now we have to remember
were trying to find a time
and so a time at least in this problem
is positve
we want to figure out how long it takes for the ball
to hit the ground
we dont want to go back in time, we dont want negative time
we only want to think about our positive answer
and so this tells us that the only root that should work
is, we have to assume that this is in seconds
so 5/2 seconds
i woudnt worry to much about the phisics here
i think they just want us to apply the quadratic formula
into this modeling situation
the physics, we go into a lot more depth in the physics playlist
so lets verify that we definitley
are at a height of 0 at 5/2 seconds
so if t=5/2 then this expression is equal to 0
so we have, lets try it out, so we have
-16*5/2^2
+20*5/2
+50
this needs to be equal to 0
so this is -16*25/4 + 50+50=0
-16/4 is -4
4/4 is 1
so -4/25 which is 100, +50
sorry, -4/25 is NEGATIVE 100
100+50+50
so we have -100 plus 100
so thats definatly going to be 0
we get 0 = 0
and it all checks out
we hit the ground after 5/2 seconds
or another way to think about it is 2.5 seconds