Usually the most quoted number
people give you when they're
publicizing information about
their credit cards is the APR.
And I think you might guess,
or you might already know,
that it stands for annual
percentage rate.
What I want to do in this
video is to understand a
little bit more detail on what
they actually mean by the
annual percentage rate, and do
a little bit of math to get
the real, or the
mathematically-- or the
effective annual percentage
rate.
I was actually just browsing the
web, and I saw some credit
card that had an annual
percentage rate of 22.9%
annual percentage rate.
But then right next to it they
say that we have a 0.06274
percent daily periodic rate.
Which to me, this piece tells
me that they compound the
interest on your credit card
balance on a daily basis.
And this is the amount
that they compound.
So where do they get
these numbers from?
Well if you just take 0.06274
and multiply by 365 days in a
year, you should
get this 22.9.
And let's see if we get that.
And of course this
is percentage.
So this is a percentage here.
And this is a percent here.
Let me get out my trusty
calculator, and see if that is
what they get.
So if I take 0.06274-- and
remember this is a percent,
but I'll just ignore the percent
sign, so as a decimal
I would actually add
2 more 0's here.
But 0.06274 times 365
is equal to 22.9%.
And you say, hey Sal, what's
wrong with that?
They're charging me
0.06274% per day.
They're going to do that
for 365 days a year, so
that gives me 22.9%.
And my reply to you
is that they're
compounding on a daily basis.
So if you were to give them $100
and if you didn't have to
pay some type of a minimum
balance, and you just let that
$100 ride for a year, you
wouldn't just owe them $122.9.
They're compounding this
much every day.
So if I were to write
this is a decimal.
So let me just write
that as a decimal.
So 0.06274% as a decimal this
is the same thing as 5 These
are the same thing.
1% is 0.01.
So 0.06% is 0.0006
as a decimal.
Now this is how much they're
charging every day.
And if you watch the compounding
interest video,
you know that if you want to
figure out how much total
interest you would be paying
over a total year, you would
take this number, add it to 1.
So we have 1.0006274.
So instead of just taking this
and multiplying it by 365, you
take this number and you take
it to the 365th power.
You multiply it by
itself 365 times.
That's because, if I have $1 in
my balance, on day 2, I'm
going to have to pay this much
times one dollar $1.
1.0006274 times $1.
On day 2, I'm going to have to
pay this much, times this
number again, times the $1.
So let me write that down.
On day 1 maybe I have
$1 that I owe them.
On day 2, it'll be $1 times
this thing, 1.006274.
On day 3, I'm going that have
to pay 1.0006274 times this
whole thing.
So on day 3 it'll be
$1 times 1.0006274.
Then I'm going to have to pay
that much interest on this
whole thing again.
I'm compounding, 1.0006274.
So you can see we've kind of
kept the balance for 2 days,
and I'm raising this to the
second power, if I'm
multiplying it by itself,
I'm squaring it.
So if I keep that balance for
365 days, I have to raise it
to the 365th power.
And this isn't counting
any kind of extra
penalties or fees.
This number, whatever it is,
once I get this and I subtract
1 from it, that is the
mathematically true-- that is
the effective annual
percentage rate.
So let's figure out
what that is.
So if I take 1.0006274 and
I raise it to the 365
power, I get 1.257.
So if I were to compound this
much interest, 0.06% for 365
days, at the end of a year I
would owe 1.257 times my
original principal balance.
So this right here is
equal to 1.257.
So I would owe 1.257 times my
original principal amount.
Or the effective interest rate,
APR, annual percent
rate, or the mathematically
correct annual percentage rate
here, is 25.7%.
And you might say, hey Sal,
that's still not too far off
from the reported APR, where
they just take this number and
multiply by 365 instead of
taking this number and taking
it to the 365 power.
You're saying, hey this
is roughly 23%
this is roughly 26%.
It's only a 3% difference.
But if you look at that
compounding interest video,
even the most basic one that I
put out there, you'll see that
every percentage point really,
really, really, really
matters, especially if you're
going to carry these balances
for a long period of time.
So be very careful.
In general, you shouldn't carry
any balances on your
credit cards, because these are
very high interest rates.
And you'll end up just paying
interest on purchases you made
many, many years ago.
And you a long ago lost all of
the joy of that purchase.
So I encourage you to not
even keep balances.
But if you do keep any balances,
pay very close
attention to this.
A 22.9% APR is still probably
not the full effective
interest rate, which might be
closer to 26% in this example.
That's before they even count
the penalties and the other
types of fees that they might
throw on top of everything.