Solve this system. And here we have three equations with three unknowns.
And just so you have a way to visualize this,
each of these equations would actually be a plane in three dimensions.
And so you're actually trying to figure out where three planes in three dimensions intersect.
I won't go into the details here, I'll focus more on the mechanics,
but you can imagine if I were to draw a three dimensional space over here.
Now all of a sudden we'll have an x, y, and z axes.
So you can imagine that maybe this first plane
and I'm not drawing it the may it might actually look.
It might look something like that. (I'm just drawing part of the plane.)
And maybe this plane over here.
It intersects right over there and it comes popping out like this and then it goes behind it like that.
It keeps going in every direction, I'm just drawing part of the plane.
And maybe this plane over here, maybe it does something like this.
Maybe it intersects over here and over here.
And so it pops out like that and then it goes below it like that
and then it goes like that. I'm just doing this for visualization purposes.
And so the intersection of this plane - the x, y and z coordinates that would satisfy
all three of these constraints the way I drew them - would be right over here.
So that's what we're looking for. And a lot of times these three equations with three unknown systems
will be inconsistent. You won't have a solution here, because it's very possible to have three planes
that all don't intersect in one place. A very simple example of that is
well, one, they could all be parallel to each other, or they could intersect each other but maybe they
intersect each other in kind of a triangle, so maybe one plane looks like that, then another plane maybe
pops out like that, goes underneath. And then maybe the third plane cuts in.
It does something like this: where it goes into that plane
and keeps going out like that, but it intersects this plane over here.
So you see kind of forms a triangle and they don't all intersect in one point
so in this situation, you would have an inconsistent system. So with that out of the way, let's try to
actually solve this system. And the trick here is to try to eliminate one variable at a time from all
of the equations, making sure that you have the information from all three equations here
so what we're going to do is we could maybe - it looks like the easiest to eliminate
since we have a positive y and a negative y and then another positive y
it seems like we can eliminate the Ys.
We can add these two equations and come up with another equation
that will only be in terms of x and z. And then we could use these two equations
to come up with another equation that will only be in terms of x and z.
But it will have all of the x and z constraint information embedded in it because
we're using all three equations. So let's do that. So first let's add these two equations right over here.
So we have x plus y minus three z is equal to negative ten.
And x minus y plus two z is equal to three. So over here if we want to eliminate y, we can literally
just add these two equations. So on the left hand side, x plus x is two x. Y plus negative y cancels out
And then negative three z plus two z - that gives us just a negative z
and then we have negative ten plus three, which is negative seven.
So using these two equations we got
two x minus z is equal to negative seven - just adding these two equations.
Now let's do these two equatons. And we can reuse this equation as long as
we're using new information here. Now we're using the extra constraint of this bottom equation.
So we have x minus y plus two z is equal to three.
And we have two x plus y minus z is equal to negative six.
If we want to eliminate the Ys, we can just add these two equations.
So x plus two x is three x. Negative y plus y cancels out. Two z minus z - well that is just z.
And that is going to be equal to three plus negative six, which is negative three.
So if I add these two equations, I get three x plus z is equal to negative three. Now I have a system
of two equations with two unknowns. This is a little bit more traditional of a problem. So let me write
them over here. So we have two x minus z is equal to negative seven. And then we have three x plus z
is equal to negative three and the way this problem is set up, it gets pretty simple pretty fast, because
if we just add these two equations, the Zs cancel out. Otherwise if it didn't happen so naturally, we'd
have to multiply one of these equations, or maybe both of them, by some scaling factor.
But we can just add these two equations up.
On the left hand side, two x plus three x is five x. Negative z plus z cancels out.
Negative seven plus negative three - that is equal to negative ten.
Divide both sides of this equation by five and
we get x is equal to negative two. Now we can substitute back to find the other variables.
Maybe we can substitute back into this equation to figure out what z must be equal to.
So we have two times x. Two times negative two minus z is equal to negative seven.
Or negative four minus z is equal to negative seven.
We can add four to both sides of this equation and then we get
negative z is equal to negative seven plus four, which is negative three.
Multiply or divide both sides by negative one and you get z is equal to three. And now we can go and
substitute back into one of these original equations. So we have x. We know x is negative two.
So we have negative two plus y, minus three times z.
Well, we know z is three (so minus three times three)
should all be equal to negative ten. And now we just solve for y.
So we get negative two plus y minus nine is equal to negative ten. And so negative two minus nine,
that's negative eleven. So we have
y minus eleven is equal to negative ten. And then we can add eleven to both
sides of this equation. And we get y is equal to negative ten plus eleven, which is one.
So we're done!
We've got x is equal to negative two. Z is equal to three and y is equal to one.
Now I can actually go back and check it.
Verify that this x, y and z works for all three constraints
that this three dimensional coordinate lies on all three planes.
So let's try it out. We've got x is negative two, z is three, y is one.
So if we substituted - let me do it into each of them - so in this first equation
that means that we have negative two plus one (remember y was equal to one).
Let me write it over here - y is equal to one, x is equal to negative two, z is equal to three.
That was the result we got. Yup, that's the result we got.
So when we test it into this first one, you have negative two plus one minus three times three.
So minus nine. This should be equal to negative ten. And it is.
Negative two plus one is negative one, minus nine is negative ten.
So it works for the first one. Let's try it for the second equation right over here.
So we have negative two minus y (so, minus one) plus two times z (so, z is three, so two times three)
So, plus six needs to be equal to three.
So this is negative three plus six, which is indeed equal to three.
So this satisifies the second equation. And then we have the last one right over here!
We have two times x, so two times negative two, which is negative four. Negative four.
Plus y, so plus one. Minus z, so minus three. Minus three.
Needs to be equal to negative six. Negative four plus one is negative three,
and then you subtract three again. It equals negative six.
So it satisfies all three equations, so we can feel pretty good about our answer.