We're asked to simplify log base 5 of x to the third
and once again we're just going to rewrite this in a different way
you could argue whether's going to be more simple or not
and the logarithm property that I'm guessing we should use for
this example right here is
the property if I take log base x
of, of, let me fix more letters here
of log base x of y to the zth power
that this is the same thing as z times
log base x of y
so this is the logarithm property. If I'm taking the logarithm of a given base
of something to the power, I could take that power upfront
and multiply that times the log of the base of
just the y in this case. So we apply this property over here
and the second once I do this problem I'll talk about why this actually makes a lot of sense
it comes straight out of exponent properties. If we just apply
that over here we get log base 5 of x to the
third. Well this is the exponent right over here. It's the same thing
as z so that's going to be the same this as
that three is the same thing. We could put it out front
that's the same thing as three times the logarithm
base five of x. And we're done this is just
another way of writing it using this property so you can argue this is a
maybe this is a simplification because you took the exponent outside of the logarithm and you're multiplying
the logarithm by that number now. Now that out of the way, lets think about why that actually makes sense.
So lets say that we know that "a" to the "b" power is equal to "c"
and so if we know that, that's written as an exponential equation, if we want to write
the same truth as a logarithmic equation
we would say, "logarithm base 'a' of 'c' is equal to 'b'"
To what power do I have to raise 'a' to get 'c'?
I raise it to the bth power
'a' to the 'b' power is equal to 'c'. Fair enough.
So lets take both sides of the equation over here and raise it to the 'dth' power.
Instead of doing in place I'm just going to rewrite it over here.
So I wrote the original equation, 'a' to the 'b' is equal to 'c', which is just rewriting the statement.
So let me just take both sides of this to the dth power and I should be consistent
I'll use all capital letters so this should be a 'b'
actually I'm using all lower cases so this is a lower case 'c'
I'm going to raise this to the dth power and I'm going to raise this to the dth power.
Obviously these two are equal to each other if I raise both sides to the same power
The equality is still going to hold.
Now, what's over here
is we can use what we know about exponent properties
Say if I have 'a' to the bth power, then I raise that to the dth power
our exponent properties say that this is the same thing
this is equal to 'a' to the b*d power
this right over here using what we know about exponent properties
this is equal to 'a' to the bd power. So we have 'a' to the bd power
so we have a to the bd power this is equal to c to the bd power
Now this exponential equation, if we write it as a logarithmic equation
we would say, log base 'a' of 'c' to the dth power
is equal to b*d. What power do I have to raise 'a' to
to get to 'c' to the dth power? To get to this I have to raise it to the b*d power.
But what do we know that 'b' is? We already know that 'b' is this thing right over here.
So if we substitute this in for 'b' and we can write this as b*d
we get logarithm base 'a' c to the dth power is equal to bd or you can also call that db
and so that's equal to d times b, be is just
log base 'a' of 'c'
So there you have it we just derived this property
log base 'a' of c to the dth, that's the same thing as d times log base 'a' of c
which we applied right over here.