Good morning.
It's the morning after Thanksgiving
and I'm still feeling sick with food,
but I will move forward and do SAT videos.
So we are on the third test
in The Official SAT Study Guide on page 518.
This is section two,
so it's the first math section in this third test.
And let's get started with the problems.
The first problem is 3x plus 9 is equal to 5x plus 1,
and they want to know x.
So this just a straightforward algebra problem.
Well, what we can do is,since we don't have negative numbers,
let's subtract 1 from both sides.
So you get 3x plus 8 is equal to 5x.
Subtract 3x from both sides,you get 8 is equal to 2x.
Divide both sides by 2, you get 4 is equal to x,
or x is equal to 4, choice D.
Problem number two.
That was just a straightforward problem.
They give us a little sequence here,
so let's see, 7, 15, 31, 63, and it just keeps going.
And it says, the first term in the sequence was 7,
and each term after the first is determined
by multiplying the preceding term by m, and then adding n.
So we multiplied by m and then added n.
OK, what is the value of m?
Well, you can just look at what they're doing, right?
What do you have to multiply 7 by and add to get to 15?
Well, 7 times 2, plus 1 is equal to 15, right?
7 times 2, plus 1 is equal to 15.
And then if you do 15 times 2, plus 1, you get 31.
15 times 2, plus 1 is equal to 31, and so forth.
31 times 2, plus 1 is equal to 63, right?
So in general, you're taking-- they're saying,
each term after the first is determined
by multiplying the preceding term by m, and then adding p.
So we're multiplying by 2 and then adding 1.
And they want to know what m is,so we're multiplying by 2.
So the choice is B.
Next problem, number three.
And I'll switch colors for this one.
On number three, I went to a bolder yellow.
OK, so that was two tables,
they're T-shirts, so there's color.
They have red, white,and blue.
And then under size they have small, medium, large,
and extra large.
The table above shows the different colors and sizes
of T-shirts that are available at Independence High School.
How many different combinations of color and size
are possible?
Well, for each color there are four sizes, right?
So you just multiply the number of colors
times the number of sizes, right?
There's four reds, four whites, four blues.
So it's 3 times 4 is equal to 12, choice B.
Once again, that was just a very straightforward problem,
no real tricks there.
Problem number four.
We're just going through these problems.
For which of the following functions is-- and they write--
let me clear this because this might take some space.
OK, so they say,
for which of these functions is the following true:
f of negative 3 is greater than f of 3?
And here are their choices.
So choice a: f of x is equal to 4x squared.
Well, in this situation, we can just look at this.
f of negative 3 and f of 3 is going to be the same thing,
because when you square the x term,
f of negative 3 is going to be 4 times 9,
which is the same thing as f of 3, right?
So that's not going to help us.
I got the 9 because I squared the negative 3,
or squared the 3, so this isn't the right choice.
f of 3 is equal to f of negative 3, choice a.
Choice b: f of x is going to be equal to 4.
Well, once again, this isn't going to be our choice,
because f of x is the same number no matter what, right?
It's 4, so there's no way that f of negative 3
is going to be greater than f of 3.
So b is not our answer.
Choice c says f of x is equal to 4 over x.
Well, this has possibility.
So f of negative 3 is what?
Minus 4/3.
And f of 3-- well, no, this isn't going to work.
It's going to be positive 4/3,so actually f of 3
is larger than f of minus 3.
So that doesn't work.
Choice e: f of x is equal to 4 minus x to the third.
This has potential, because f of negative 3 is what?
It's 4 minus minus 27, which equals 31,
while f of 3 is 4 minus 27, which equals minus 24.
So f of negative 3 is larger than f of 3.
So our answer is e.
Next problem.
We don't have to do the last one,
because we already found one that fits our answer
and that solves our problem. Different colors.
OK, I will switch to this color.
OK, five.
The force required to stretch a spring
beyond its natural length is proportional
to how far the spring is being stretched.
And if you've taken physics,you'd probably see this.
The force necessary is equal to some k, right?
Which is the proportionality constant times
how far you're stretching.
That's all they're saying, right?
The force required to stretch a spring
beyond its natural strength
is proportional--so that's what k means, proportional--
to how far the spring is being stretched.
x is how far its being stretched.
If a force of 15 pounds-- so when F--
if a force of 15 pounds stretches a spring 8 centimeters--
so 15 pounds stretches 8 centimeters--
what force, in pounds,
is needed to stretch the spring 20 centimeters
beyond its natural length?
So we can just solve for k in this equation
and then apply it here, right?
This is x.
So 15 is equal to k times 8,
or we could say k is equal to 15 over 8.
So we know that k is equal to 15 over 8.
And then here we have--
well,what happens when x is 20, what is F?
Well then, F is equal to k, 15 over 8,
times how far this thing needs to be stretched
beyond its natural length.
So 15 over 8 times 20. What is this?
So we can divide the top and the bottom by 4.
So this goes 5, 2. And what's 5?
What's 5 times 15? 5 times 15, 75. So it's 75 over 2.
And that's a strange number,
but it looks like we do have choices that match that.
And that's 37.5, which is choice E.
Next problem.
Actually, I've probably run out of time,
so I will do the next problem in the next video.
See you soon.