Multiply negative four x squared by
the whole expression
three x squared plus twenty five x
minus seven
So if you multiply anything
times a whole expression you really just use
the distributive property to multiply each term
of the expression by
the negative four x squared
so we're going to have to distribute
this negative four x squared
over every term in the expression.
So first we can start with
negative four x squared times
three x squared
so we can write that
we're gonna have negative four x squared
times three x squared
and to that we're going to add
negative four x squared times twenty five x
times twenty five x
and to that we're going to add
negative four x squared times negative seven
times negative seven
So let's just simplify this a little bit
Now we can obviously swap the order
we're just multiplying negative four times
x squared times three times x squared
and actually I'll do out every step
eventually you can do some of this in your head
this is the exact same thing as negative four
times three times x squared times
x squared
And what is that equal to?
well negative four times three
is negative twelve
and x squared times x squared
same base, we're taking the product
that's going to be x to the fourth
so this right here is
negative twelve x to the fourth
Now let's think about this term over here
this term over here
This the same thing as
And of course we have this plus out here
We have this plus
And then this part right here is
the exact same thing as twenty five
twenty five times negative four
times x squared times x
So let's just multiply the numbers out here
These were the coefficients.
Twenty five times negative four is
negative a hundred.
So it'll be plus negative a hundred
or we could just say it's minus one hundred
And then we have x squared times x
or x squared times x to the first power
Same base, we can add the exponents.
Two plus one is three.
So this is negative a hundred x to the third power
And then let's look at this last term over here
We have negative four x squared
So this is going to be plus
That's this plus right over here
We have
We have negative four
We can multiply that times negative seven
And then multiply that times x squared
I'm just changing the order
in which we multiply
So negative four times negative seven is
positive twenty eight.
Positive twenty eight
and then I'm gonna multiply that times
the x squared
times the x squared
There's no simplification to do
No like terms
These are different powers of x.
So we are done.