We're in the Glyptothek in Munich, this is
an extraordinary museum devoted to ancient
Greek and Roman antiquities,
and that's all thanks to Prince Ludwig of Bavaria, who in the early 19th century
said he wanted to found a collection of antique works of sculpture, because, as he said,
we must also have in Munich what in Rome is known as a museum. I love that,
you know, a museum wasn't even a commonly used word, the idea of a public collection
was just coming into being, in Britain, in France, and here in Germany, and Ludwig was ambitious for Munich.
He wrote, "I will turn Munich into a city of the arts, so that no one can claim to know Germany, who has
not also seen Munich." So, art was a way of really putting a city on a map; it spoke to its
cultural superiority, and Ludwig put together an incredible collection, and we're looking now
at one of the great treasures of the museum, the sculptures from the pediment of the temple of Aphaea
on the island of Aigina, just off the coast of Greece. This is an island that is visible from Athens,
so it's very close to the Greek mainland. And we really shouldn't say pediment, we should say pediments.
Let's unpack that just a little bit. On a greek temple, imagine the Parthenon. This is a long structure
with a gable either end, that is,above the colonnade. At either short end of the temple,
there is a low triangle, and historically, those were areas that were filled with sculptures.
On the temple of Aphaea, there was a pediment on the East side and on the West side,
on the two short ends of the temple. The sculptures that filled these pediments were
discovered in the early 19th century when some German architects were surveying the
ruins of the temple, and they were soon put on auction, and Ludwig was very pleased to acquire
them for his new museum. The pediment sculptures were not made at the same moment, and that makes them
even more interesting, because it helps us see the evolution of greek sculpture.
The West pediment was earlier, and we think that those sculptures were carved when the temple
was actually built, about 490 B.C.E.. The East side was later, and what's really interesting
is those older West sculptures are in the archaic tradition, but the East pediment sculptures
are just taking on the characteristics of the style we'll come to know as the Classical.
We can say it's an early moment of the Classical for the sculptures on the East pediment,
this moment of transition as the style really was just being invented.
Now the subject for both pediments was the Trojan War, the war between the Trojans and the Greeks.
Now this war was really a mythic war, but we know about it because it is the subject of
Homer's great epic poem, "The Iliad," and some of the heroes of the Trojan War were from the Island of Aegina,
so it makes sense that they would make an appearance on the pediment.
So, let's start off by looking at the sculptures on the Western pediment. In terms of
being a space that gets filled with sculpture, a pediment is kind of an awkward environment.
It's incredibly awkward, because you have these two narrow areas of the triangle
that are very hard to fill, and so one of the ways you can do that is to have reclining figures.
Well, that's right, that's almost as if the sculptures have to play limbo, they get lower and lower
as you move to the edges. But in this case, the sculptor has really been inventive, and he's found
a marvelous solution. In the very center of the pediment, on both the East and the West sides,
we have a standing figure, noble, looking outward, the Goddess Athena.
And Athena was known as the Goddess of War, in addition to being the Goddess of Wisdom.
On the west pediment, we see Athena, now holding a modern shaft, that is meant to represent
a spear that would have originally been there perhaps in wood, more likely, in bronze or some other metal.
When we look at Athena, we see a figure who looks typically archaic in style.
She's frontal, she's rather rigid, fairly symmetrical, and there's a linear quality to her.
She has a typical archaic smile, that removes her from emotion, removes her from the
everyday world. She seems like a transcendant goddess. On either side of the
standing Athena are two warriors, and they move outward. They're actually
lunging with spears. One has their shield facing us, one has turned in the other direction,
the shield is facing away from us, but they move our eye in either direction outward with real energy and
real velocity, and of course, they are both slightly lower since their knees are bent,
so that they fit under the eve of the gable. On either side of those figures we see kneeling archers, who are shooting bows.
The archer on the left we can actually identify as Paris, and we can see his
cap is tied in the back, his weight is on one knee, and on one heel. The bow is missing,
but we can certainly see arm movement that suggests that he was in the middle
of loosing his arrow. And then behind him, a striding figure with a weapon, who's attacking a figure
who is falling to the ground. Look at the complexity of that group of three, the way in which they overlap,
there's a real sense of energy, there's a real sense of dynamism, which is pretty extraordinary
for the archaic moment. And then on the far left corner, another wounded figure, just fits
into that corner space. Let's focus for a moment on the wounded warrior that is on the right side of the
West pediment. We can see that he's fallen back, he's on his left hip, and he's on his left elbow,
and his right hand seems to be clutching, or perhaps trying to remove a spear that has wounded him.
Alright, let me stop you for a moment, because he doesn't really look like he's in the position of a
wounded warrior. His knee's bent, it comes over his left leg, he's propped up on his left arm,
and his right elbow comes up in a rather awkward way. This figure really doesn't seem believable
in terms of what he's supposed to be doing, pulling the spear from his body. Well, that's right,
this must be tremendously painful, probably would kill him, and yet look at his face, it still retains
the archaic smile. For all of us, it is important to remember that this is not naturalism.
This is not an attempt to render the feelings of the embodied, this is a highly stylized,
very schematic structure, and in a way, the figure is a symbol,
more than a real figure, a symbol of the fallen warrior in the Trojan War.
One art historian has likened this figure to vase painting, where there was often an attempt
to raise torsos up so that you could see the full musculature of the entire front.
This is not about naturalism, it's about revealing the body in a way. The same art historian likened this
figure to a reclining kouros, and that's exactly how he looks. It's as if a standing kouros figure has
been tipped over. This is so different than what we see on the East pediment, which dates from
only a decade or two later, where we see the beginnings of the Classical style. Let's take a look.
The East pediment is much more fragmentary on the left side, but the one figure, of the fallen soldier,
is in great condition, and so different from what we saw of the early archaic West facade.
While this figure still has a bit of that archaic smile, everything else about the position of his body
tells us that this is a wounded figure taking his last breaths. You can see that he's holding a sword with his right hand,
but he's also trying to push himself back up, but he doesn't seem to be able to do it.
His left arm is still in the shield, and he seems to be balancing himself, just a moment before that shield
falls over with a bang. And so there's a sense that he's propping himself up, but also falling
at the same time, lowering his body as he dies. He's looking down at the ground, and his body is more
mature than the other figure,it's also much more naturalistically rendered. We're seeing that
origin of the Classical tradition. In the archaic period, we see hard divisions between the muscles
and the parts of the body. Outlines, almost, to the parts of the body, and here,
one muscle flows into another, and there's a real sense of skin lying over a skeletal structure.
Well thats right, a moment ago, you had said that the archaic sculpture was nothing but really a set of symbols.
And here, it's as if the artist has actually observed the human body, and thought about it, what it must be like, for a figure to fall.
Instead of having that back leg coming over the front leg in a very unnatural way, and instead of having that elbow lifted up,
the right arm of the figure comes over his torso fully. There's no attempt to reveal the whole body
tipped forward to us the way we had in the archaic figure. Now, look at the torso. Look at the
muscles of the leg, this is a far more complex rendering of the human body in a complex pose.
Just like on the West pediment, as we look at the East pediment,we've got a central figure, again, Athena.
To the right of Athena, we have figures that are much more intact. We have a lunging figure, we saw that on
the West pediment as well, who is in the process of impaling a man who has lost his helmet,
his shield is falling off his arm, and he's tottering; he has lost his balance.
He looks as though he's about to collapse. We know he's lost his helmet because the young man
who's in back of him, who seems to be trying to aid him and running towards him.
He's holding a fragment we know that would've originally been his helmet.
His body forms a diagonal in the lunge, so it fits nicely to that triangular space of that pediment,
and behind him is another archer just like we saw on the West pediment. Archaeologists think that
that archer is actually the one who has hit the wounded warrior on the opposite side, the one who we were discussing before.
That's right. So we have this wonderful unification of action among all of these figures on the East pediment.
We have this more complex narrative even though the same story is being told. We have a much
more complex musculature, and much more careful attention to the human experience, and this
makes us ask what has changed. It's just been a few years between these pediments, yet they are
so different. This is always the question art historians ask as we look at works of art that are separated
not by a very long period of time, in this case, what has happened in the values of the ancient Greek culture
that has led them to represent the human figure so differently. If you go back in Greek history,
the Greeks were deeply influenced by monumental Egyptian sculpture. You can still get a sense
of a trace of that in the archaic tradition, but now, there's a sense of self-awareness.
These are mobile figures out in the world that are almost enacting human emotion,
human expression, and human experience, and that is so different from the idea of representation as symbolic,
which it's so in formed in earlier Greek art. So, in the Classical period, we have figures who we can
believe are part of a story, it's a story that we can begin to feel for them, we can sympathize with them as we
watch them. And this is a moment in ancient Greek history when the Greeks have just defeated
the Persians in battle. This is an epic victory for Greek culture when many of the
Greek city states united to fight their enemy, the Persians. That's right, this common enemy that really
should have been victorious, the Persians should have won. It was a much larger army, and the
Greeks knew it. The fact that they were victorious suggested to them that there was a kind of
an order in the universe. There's a sense now that the world isn't a place that just operates arbitrarily
according to the laws of the gods, but it's a place that the human mind, with its sense of the rational,
can understand. So, there is a much greater burden placed on the Greeks, with this realization.
They are now responsible for their own society, they are not part of kind of a random order, they're part
of an order that they actually devise. So art historians see the origins of the Classical style
in this historical moment. We have an obligation, even here in the 21st century, to try to put ourselves,
even though it's an impossible task, in the minds of the ancient Greeks, and to truly understand
these works of art from their point of view, and so it's really important to remember that these sculptures
were painted, just like all ancient Greek sculptures, and with very bright colors.
This completely destroys our image of Greek art. When we think about Greek art, we think about
these pristine, brilliant, white, marble surfaces, and they were garish! They were yellow!
They were blue! They were green! Art historians and archaeologists have done scientific analyses
of these sculptures, and found traces and residues of pigments, and they've determined pretty accurately
at least the red and blues that we find here in some of these geometric patterns. It's so jarring, for me, to try to imagine these colors back,
and it's not just that the figures themselves were painted, but the architectural spaces in which these
figures were placed were painted as well. Well, there are some anyways that we're not looking at
these the way that the ancient Greeks did. First of all, these were outside, in the open air, they were high up
on a pediment, on this island. Well, certainly, the color would have made it much easier to see these figures
we're trying to fit in the shade of the architecture. You know, there's another element that we can re-imagine,
which is these figures were not only holding things that have since disappeared, they were holding spears,
and bows, and arrows, but they also had other pieces of metal work that have since been lost.
There was hair, sometimes actually hanging kind of like bangs, over the forehead, and also long locks that came down and framed the faces.
In this case, they were made of lead, and you can actually see the pieces of the remaining lead that are still there,
and so we know precisely where they came out of the stone, and that would've helped, I think, create not
these figures as single stone objects the way we see them, but as these much more complex figures
that interact with their architectural environments. Let's not forget, too, that these are temples, these are
places of religious worship, and that they were homes to the Gods, and that the central figure on both East and West pediments is the Goddess Athena.
And of course, the Greek idea of Gods and Goddesses is entirely different from our own today of
Christian tradition. So, these are all important things to keep in mind, as we look at Greek sculptures in museums.