So let's say we are in the apple market.
What I want to do in this video is
think about both demand and supply for the apples at different prices.
So let's draw ourselves a little graph here.
And we already know:
this, right over here, the vertical axis, is the price axis.
We're going to say it's price per pound.
And the horizontal axis, this is the quantity.
The quantity of apples.
And let's put some tick marks here.
Let's say that's one dollar a pound,
two dollars a pound,
three dollars a pound,
four dollars a pound,
and five dollars.
And let's say that this is thousands of pounds produced.
And we have to set a period,
so let's say that this is all for the next week.
And so this is one thousand pounds,
two thousand,
three thousand,
four thousand,
and five thousand.
Now let's think about both the supply and the demand curves for this market,
or potential supply and demand curves.
So first I will do the demand.
so if we, if the price of apples were really high
I encourage you to always think about this
when you're about to draw your supply and demand curve
if the price of apples were really high
what would happen to consumers?
well, they wouldn't demand much
so the quantity demanded would be low
so if the price were high,
maybe the quantity demanded is 500 apples.
Once again. Be very careful. This is a quantity demanded is 500 dollars.
And nothing the demand is 500 dollars. The demand is entirely relationship. The actual specific quantity we call that