We're asked to solve the equation
"three plus the principle square root of five x plus six is equal to twelve"
And so the general strategy to solve this type of
equation, is to isolate the radical sign on one side
of the equation, and then you can square it to
essentially get the radical sign to go away.
But you have to be very careful there, because when you
square radical signs you actually lose the information that
you were taking the principle square root, not the
negative square root or not the plus-or-minus square root.
You're only taking the positive square root. And so
when we get our final answer, we do have to check
and make sure it gels with taking the principle square root.
So let's try, let's see what I'm talking about.
So the first thing I want to do, is I want to isolate
this on one side of the equation. The best way to isolate that
is to get rid of this three. And the best way to get rid of the
three is to subtract three from the left hand side. And of
course if I do it on the left-hand side I also have to do
it on the right-hand side. Otherwise I would
lose the ability to say that they are equal. And so the
left-hand side right over here simplifies to the
principle square root of five x plus six. And this is equal to
Twelve minus three. This is equal to nine. And now we can
square both sides of this equation. So we can square
five, the principle square root of five x plus six
and we can square nine. When you do this, when you do this,
when you square this, you get five x, five x plus six.
If you square the square root of five x plus six you're
going to get five x plus six! And this is where we actually
lost some information, because we would have also gotten
this if we squared the negative square root of five x plus six.
And so that's why we have to be careful with the answers
we get, and actually make sure it works when the original
equation was the principle square root. So we get
five x plus six on the left-hand side, and on the right-hand side
we get eighty-one. And now this is just a straight-up linear
equation. We want to isolate the x terms. We'll subtract
six from both sides. Subtract six from both sides.
On the left-hand side we have five x, and on the right-hand
side we have seventy-five. And then we can divide both sides by five.
Divide both sides by five, we get x is equal to... Let's see..
x it-it's fifteen. Right? Five times ten is fifty,
five times five is twenty-five, which is seventy-five.
So we get x is equal to fifteen. But we want - We need to
make sure that this actually works for our original equation.
Maybe this would have, maybe this would have
worked if we were taking - If this was the negative
square root. So we need to make sure it actually works
for the positive square root, for the principle square root.
So let's apply it to our original equation. So we get
three plus the principle square root of five times fifteen.
So seventy-five plus six, seventy-five plus six
plus six, so I just took five times fifteen over here, I've put
our solution in, should be equal to twelve. So we get
three plus square root of seventy-five plus six is eighty-one
it's equal to twelve. And this is the principle root of
eighty-one, so it's positive nine. So it's three plus nine
needs to be equal to twelve, which is absolutely true.
So we can feel pretty good about this answer.