we're asked to simply log base 3 of 27x
and frankly this is already quite simple,
but I'm assuming they want us to use
some logarithm properties and manipulate this some way
maybe actually make it a little more complicated
and let's give this our best shot at it
so the logarithm property that jumps out at me
because this, right over here, is saying
what power do we have to raise 3 to in order to get 27x
27x is the same thing as 27 times x
and so the logarithm property it seems like they want us to use is
log base b of a times c
this is equal to
the logarithm base b of a plus logarithm base b of c
now this comes straight out of the exponent properties
that if you have two exponents with the same base
you can add the exponents
now let me make this a little bit clearer to you
now if this part is a little confusing the important part for this example is
is that you know how to apply this,
but it's even better if you know the intuition
so let's say that log, let's say that log base b of a times c is equal to x
so this thing right over here evaluates to x
let's say that this thing right over here evaluates to y
so log base b of a is equal to y
and let's say that that this thing over here evaluates to z
so log base b of c is equal to z
now, what we know is
this thing right over here, this thing right over here
or this thing right over here tells us
tells us that b, to the x power is equal to a times c
now, this right over here is telling us that
b to the y power is equal to a
and this over here is telling us
that b to the z power is equal to c
let me do that in that same green
so i'm just writing the same truth
i'm writing as an exponential function
or exponential equation
instead of a logarithmic equation
so b to the zth power is equal to c
these are all, this is the same statement
this is the same statement
or they're the same truth said in a different way
and this is the same truth said in a different way
well if we know that, if we know that
a is equal to this, is equal to b to the y,
we can, and c is equal to b-z
then we can write
b to the x power is equal to b to the y power
that's what a is, we know that already
times b to the z power
and we know, from our exponent properites
we know from our exponent properties
That if we take b to the y times b to the z
this is the same thing as:
b to the, I'll do it in neutral color, b to the y plus z power
this came straight out of our exponent properties.
And so if b to the y plus z power is the same thing
b to the x power -- that tells us that x must be equal to y plus z.
x must be equal to y plus z.
If this is confusing to you -- don't worry too much.
The important thing, or at least the first important thing is
that you know how to apply it and then you can think about this
a little bit more and you can even try it out with some numbers.
You have to just realise that logarithms are really just exponents.
I know, when people at first tell me: what does that mean?
But when you evaluate a logarithm - you're getting an exponent
that you would have to raise b to, in order to get a times c.
But let's just apply this property right over here.
So if we apply to this one we know that
log base 3 of 27 times x -- I'll write it that way --
is equal to log base 3 of 27 plus log base 3 of x.
And then this right over here we can evaluate,
this tells us: what power do I have to raise 3 to get to 27.
You can view it this way: 3 to the question mark is equal to 27.
Well, 3 to the 3rd power is equal to 27.
3 times 3 is 9, times 3 is 27.
To this right over here evaluates to 3.
So if we were to simplify -- or I guess I wouldn't even call it
simplifying, I'll just call it expanding it out or using this property.
We now have two terms, where when we started of with one term.
Actually if we started with this, I'd say that this is the more simple version of it.
But when we rewrite it, this first term becomes 3.
So this first term becomes 3
and then we're left with plus log base 3 of x.
So this is just an alternate way of writing this original statement.
Log base 3 of 27x.
So once again -- not clear that this is simpler than this right over here.
It's just another way of writing it using logarithm properties.