Let's say we've got company A over here
and it takes out a $1,000,000 loan
and pays a variable interest rate on that loan
it pays LIBOR plus 2%
and LIBOR stands for:
London Interbank Offer Rate
it's one of the major benchmarks for variable interest rates
And so it pays that to some lender,
this is the person who lent company A the money
it pays them a variable interest rate every period
so for example, in period 1
if LIBOR is at 5%
then in that period company A will pay 7%
or $70,000 to the lender in that period.
In Period 2, if LIBOR goes down a little bit to 4%
then company A is going to 4 + 2 which is 6%
or, 6% which is $60,000 in interest.
Let's say we have another company
company B, right over here
It also borrows $1,000,000
but it borrows it at a fixed rate of 8%
8% fixed interest rate
so in each period
regardless of what happens to LIBOR
or any other benchmark
and so this is to probably another lender
a different lender than the person that A borrowed it from
and it could be a bank, or it may be a company
or another investor of some kind
We'll call this Lender 1 and Lender 2
So, regardless of the period
right now company B will pay
8% of $1,000,000 in each period
which is exactly $80,000 each period
Now let's say neither of these parties
are really happy with that situation
Company A doesn't like the variability
the unpredictability and what happens to LIBOR
They can't plan for how much they have to pay
Company B feels like they're overpaying for interest
they feel like
"wow, the people who're doing variable interest rates,
they're paying a less amount of interest every period"
and maybe company B also thinks that
interest rates are going to go down
or that short-term, or that variable rate is going to go down
LIBOR, is going to go down
so that's an even bigger reason
why they want to become a variable rate borrower.
So what they can do
and neither of them
can get out of these lending agreements
but what they can do is agree to essentially swap
some or all of their interest rate payments
so for example, they can enter into an agreement
this would be called an "interest rate swap"
where company A agrees to pay B
maybe, let's make up a number here
7% on a notional $1,000,000 loan.
So the $1,000,000 will never change hands
but company A agrees to pay B
7% of that notional $1,000,000
or $70,000 per period
and in return
company B agrees to pay A a variable rate
let's say it's LIBOR plus 1% right over here
And this little agreement
And they agree they would do this for some amount
And once again: this is LIBOR plus 1%
on a notional $1,000,000
And that word "notional" just means that
that $1,000,000 will never change hands
they're just going to exchange
the interest payments on $1,000,000
And this agreement right over here
is called an interest rate swap
And I'll leave you there and the next video
we'll actually go through the mechanics to see that
A is truly now paying a fixed rate
when you put in all of their different payments
into both the swap and the lender
and company B
after entering into this swap agreement
is now really paying a variable interest rate.