We are on problem number 11.
I wrote out that chart, although you probably can't read it.
So they say, according to the table above,
car engine oil with a rating of 5w
flows how many times as fast as a car engine oil
with a rating of 20w?
So how much faster is 5w versus 20w?
So let's read the chart.
It says 10w is half as fast as 5w,right?
So 5w is twice as fast as 10w. So 5w is 2 times 10w,right?
Then they tell us that 15w is half as fast as 10w.
So 10w is double the speed of 15w.
Actually, let's do it that way.
10w is double the speed of 15w, right?
And then 15w is double the speed of 20w,right?
So you have two doublings.
So 10w is going to be 4 times as fast.
It's 2 times as fast as this,
which is 2 times as fast as this.
So 10w is 4 times faster than 20w.
So 10w is 4 times 20w. And 5w is twice 10w.
So 5w is going to be 8 times 20w.
And really,
the most confusing thing about this is the fact that
these labels for these ratings involve numbers
that aren't proportional to actually
how much faster they are than each other.
You could actually change this to x, y, z,
and then it might be a little bit easier.
But that's all there is to it.
This is twice as fast as this,which is twice as fast as this.
And if you were at 5w up here,
so 5w is twice as fast as this,
which is twice as fast as this,
which is twice as fast as that.
So you're doubling three times,so it's 8 times as fast.
And that's choice C.
Next problem. Let me draw that. We have a line like that.
Straight line at the bottom. Then we have a line.
Looks something like that.
And this is P, A, Q, B, R.
This is line m. This is line l.
Figure not drawn to the scale. Sure.
In the figure above,
points P, A, and B are equally spaced on line l.
Equally spaced.
So that means that the distance from P to A
is equal to the distance from A to B.
They're equally spaced. That's good to know.
And points P, Q, and R are equally spaced on line m. OK.
So P, Q, and R are equally spaced.
It didn't look like it the way I drew it.
But so this is equal to this.
If PB is equal to 4-- so that entire thing is equal to 4.
So we immediately know that this is 2 and this is 2, right?
Because they're equally spaced. PR is equal to 6.
So this entire thing is equal to 6.
So we know that this is 3 and this is 3. And AQ is 4.
What is the perimeter of quadrilateral QABR?
Let's see, where is Q? QABR.
So we know this side. We know this side. We know this side.
We just have to figure out this side.
And I'll tell you right now that
this is going to be a similar triangle problem,I believe.
Because these triangles are going to be proportional
to each other.
How do I know that? I'm going to draw two triangles for you.
You have this big triangle,
and then you have this smaller triangle.
And the big triangle is similar to the smaller triangle.
And how do I know that? Well, they share an angle here.
and we know that the bigger triangle,
two of its sides are just double
the sides of the other two angles.
Or-- I'm sorry.
We know that, for example,
this side on the big triangle
is double this side on the small triangle, right?
Similar. We know this big side on the big triangle
is double this side on the small triangle.
So two sides are proportional to each other.
We have one common angle.
We know that this is a similar triangle.
So we know that this side is going to be double this side.
So this side is going to be 8.
And you could have probably guessed that
even if you didn't want to prove that
they're similar triangles. So this is 8.
The perimeter that we had to figure out to begin with--
this is the quadrilateral right here.
It's going to be 8 plus 3 plus 4 plus 2.
And what is that? That's 8 plus-- 17. Right?
6, 9, right. 17. And that is choice E.
Next problem. Problem 13.
OK. 13 and 14 refer to these functions.
So g of n is equal to n squared plus n.
h of n is equal to n squared minus n.
So the first problem.
They want to know what g of 5 minus h of 4 is.
So g of 5. Let's stick in 5 into g.
So you get 5 squared plus 5. I just replace 5 where n is.
And then we're going to subtract h of n.
So what's h of n? Oh, sorry, h of 4. It looked like an n.
And h of 4. So h of 4 is 4 squared minus 4.
And so let's simplify this.That's 25 plus 5 minus 16 plus 4.
So that's what? 30 minus 16 plus 4.
30 minus 16 is 14, plus 4, so it's 18.
So that is choice D.
All right. Problem 14 also applies to this.
So I'll do it right here.
Which of the following is equivalent to h of m plus 1?
So we essentially just, everywhere we see an n here,
we put an m plus 1.
So h of m plus 1 is equal to--we see an n,
so we put an m plus 1 there.
m plus 1 squared minus-- instead of an n-- m plus 1.
Multiply that out.
You get m squared plus 2m plus 1, and then minus m minus 1.
Let's see. So this 1 and this 1 cancel out.
And then 2m minus m.
So you're left with m squared minus m.
So h of m plus 1 is equal to m squared minus m.
But isn't that the same thing as h of m?
Reminds me of that store.
That's H&amp;M, not h of m,
although that would be a fun name for a store as well.
h of m. Well, what's h of m?
You put an m where you see an n.
So that also equals m squared minus m.
So the answer is h of m. And let me now look at the choices.
And that is not there. So I have made a mistake.
m squared plus 1.
They're saying, which of the following is equal to h of m--
let me clear things. OK.
So they say,
which of the following is equivalent to h of m plus 1?
And that is equal to h of m, right? Right.
That is equal to m plus 1 squared minus m plus 1.
That's m squared plus 2m plus 1, minus m, minus 1.
So that's m squared-- plus m. Oh, sorry. Plus m.
m squared plus m. And then this cancels out.
So h of m plus 1 is equal to m squared plus m. Right?
And what's m squared plus m?
Well, that's the same thing as g of m.
Because take g of n,
or take g of m and that's also m squared plus m.
So that is choice A.
Before I cleared it, my mistake was when I did 2m minus m,
I got, for some silly reason, minus m instead of positive m.
Should be a positive m. That was my mistake.
I'll see you in the next video.