Problem one: For zero less than or equal to [t] less than or equal to six, a particle is moving along the x-axis.
The particle's position x(t) is NOT explicitly given; the velocity of the particle is given by v(t) is equal to all of this business right over here;
the acceleration of the particle is given by a(t) is equal to all of this business over here. They actually
didn't have to give us that, because is acceleration is just the derivative of the velocity.
And they also give us- they don't tell us the position function but they tell us where we start off
x(0) is equal to 2. Fair enough. Now let's do part a):
Is the SPEED of the particle increasing or decreasing at the equals 5.5 give a reason for your answer.
It looks like they did something a little sneaky here. because they gave us the velocity
function and they ask about the speed.
You might say, "Wait- aren't those the same thing?"
And I would tell you "No!" they aren't quite the same thing.
Velocity is a magnitude and a direction- it is a vector quantity.
Speed is just a magnitude- it is a caller quantity.
And to see the difference, you should have a velocity-
and this is particular to this problem-
because they don't give us the units- but you could have a velocity
or -5 meters per second and maybe if you were talking about on
the x-axis, this would mean we're moving leftward at 5 meters per second
on the x-axis. So the magnitude is 5 meters per second,
this is the magnitude, and the direction is specified by the negative number.
and that is the direction. Your velocity could be -5 meters per second, but your speed
would just be 5 meters per second. So, your speed is 5 meters per second whether
you're going to the left OR the right. Your velocity you actually care
whether you're going to the left or the right. So let's just keep that in mind while we try to solve this
problem. So the best way to figure out whether our rate of change is increasing
or decreasing is to look at the acceleration. Because acceleration is, really, just the rate of
change of velocity. And then we can think a little but about the velocity
vs. speed question. So what us the acceleration at time 5.5?
Get the calculator out- we can use calculator for this part of the AP exam.
I assume they intended us to because isn't something that easy to calculate by hand.
So the acceleration at time 5.5- we just have to put [t] which is 5.5 and evaluate this function.
So 1/2- I'll just write 0.5- times [e] to the [t] over 5. We'll