We're in the last section of test 6.
Section 9, page 743. Problem number 1.
For which of the following values of m
will the value of 3m minus 1 be greater than 10?
So we add 1 to both sides.
3m is going to be greater than 11.
Divide both sides by 3,
and you don't have to switch the inequality
because 3 is positive.
So you get m is going to be greater than 11/3,right?
And 11/3, this is what? This is equal to 3 and 2/3.
So anything greater than 3,really,any integer greater than 3.
If you look at all the choices,
the only one that's greater than 3 and 2/3 is choice A, 4.
Next problem. If a times k is equal to k--
sorry, if a times k is equal to a for all values of a,
what is the value of k?
And the reason why they have to say all values of a is
because if a was 0, then that would work for any k.
But if it's for all values of k,
you divide both sides of this equation by a,
you get k is equal to a/a which is equal to 1.
So k would have be equal to 1, which is D.
And you knew that. You didn't have to do any algebra.
If I multiply something times some number
and I get the original thing, that number's going to be 1.
Problem 3. So let me draw what they've drawn.
So I have one parallel line like that.
I'm assuming they're parallel,
because they look parallel in the picture.
And then there's a line that comes down like this.
There's another line that goes up like that.
And what do they tell us about it?
They tell us that this is x degrees right here.
This is z degrees. This is y degrees.
This is line l. This is line m.
In the figure above,l is parallel to m.
If x is equal to 80 degrees-- so this is 80 degrees--
and y is equal to 70 degrees, what is the value of z?
So the trick here is just to see the opposite angles.
In fact, the information that
they're parallel lines is actually just extra information
to start making you do corresponding angles
and all that kind of fancy stuff.
Which you could do.
But the really easy thing is to realize that x,
this angle, is the same thing as this angle,
which is going to be 80 degrees. Right?
Because they're opposite angles of intersecting lines.
And this--
if that's 70, then this angle is also going to be 70.
And now 80 plus 70 plus z has to equal 180,
because they're all in the same triangle together.
Subtract 150 from both sides,
you get z is equal to 30 degrees.
The other way you could have done it
is you could have used the information
about the parallel lines.
And you could have said,
well,the corresponding angle here is here,
so that this is also 80 degrees.
And you could have said the corresponding angle here
is also here, so this is 70 degrees.
And then you could have said
all three of these are supplementary,
and that they would have to add up to 180.
And you'd get z equals 30 either way. And that is choice A.
Next problem. Problem 4.
The scenic route from Mia's home to her office
is 5 kilometers longer than the direct route.
So I'll call S for scenic.
S is equal to the direct route plus 4.
The scenic route is 4 miles longer than the direct route,
or 4 kilometers.
When she goes by the scenic route
and returns by the direct route,
the round trip is 35 kilometers.
So that means what? The distance of the scenic route
plus the distance of the direct route
is equal to 35 kilometers.
How many kilometers is the direct route?
So we want to solve for this.
So this top equation,
we can rewrite this as S minus D is equal to 4.
And actually just to make things-- well,
let me write that down right here.
So you get S minus D is equal to 4.
And we can multiply this equation by negative 1,
so you cancel out the S's instead of the D's,
but since it's so convenient already,
let's just cancel out the D's and solve for the scenic route.
The S's.
So this is just a system with two equations and two unknowns.
So let's add these two equations.
So you get 2S-- D plus D is 0-- is equal to 35 plus 4 is 39.
The numbers look strange. The scenic distance is 39/2. Right?
That's 39/2 kilometers. And what is that equal to?
If I were to write that as a mixed number.
Let's see. 38 is-- that's 19 and 1/2 kilometers.
A little less than 20 kilometers. That's the scenic route.
The direct route is 4 less than that, right?
We said the scenic route is 4 more than the direct route.
So the direct route is going to be that minus 4.
So what's 19 minus 4?
It's 15, and then you still have that half there.
15 and 1/2 kilometers.
And I don't see that choice there,
so I must have made a mistake.
Let me do it here, just to see where--
I don't see that choice.
The scenic route from Mia's home to her office
is 5 kilometers longer than the direct route. Right.
The scenic route-- we could even say scenic route minus--
oh, sorry, it's 5 kilometers longer.
Sorry. This is 5. That was my mistake.
5 kilometers longer. Scenic minus direct is 5.
They normally don't give weird numbers like that.
So this is 5. This is 40. This is 40/2. This is 20.
Hope I'm not confusing you.
And then if you're going to be 5 less than 20,
it's going to be 15 kilometers, right?
I hope you see what I just did.
I wrote 4 kilometers longer instead of 5.
That was my mistake, which you should avoid.
Next problem. Let me switch colors.
I think that yellow induces careless mistakes. 5.
A complete cycle of a traffic light takes 80 seconds.
During each cycle, the light is green for 40 seconds.
Amber-- I guess that's red--amber for 10 seconds.
Oh, I guess amber is yellow. I don't know my colors.
And red for 30 seconds.
And the whole cycle takes 80 seconds.
If you add those up. At a randomly chosen time,
what is the probability that the light will not be red?
So the probability that the light will not be red
is the probability that it's going to be green or amber.
And it's green or amber for 40 plus 10,
for 50 seconds out of a total of 80 seconds, right?
So the probability that
when you randomly walk up to the light,
that it's going to be green or amber--
or not red-- is going to be 50 seconds.
50/80, which is 5/8. And that is choice B.
Next problem. Problem 6.
For a certain hot water heater,
the increase in heating expenses
is directly proportional to the increase
in the water temperature setting.
If heating expenses increase by $24
when the water temperature
is increased by 20 degrees Fahrenheit-- so
expense goes up by 24
when temperature is increased by 20 degrees Fahrenheit.
By how much will heating expenses increase
when the water temperature setting
is increased by 15 degrees Fahrenheit?
So this is just a ratio problem.
So you say, well, the expenses go up $24
when we have a 20-degree increase in temperature.
So then how many dollars will it increase
when you have a 15-degree increase?
The denominator in both cases was the change in temperature.
And then this is the change in expense.
The triangle means change, right?
So you just have to make sure that
the ratios are consistent and let's just multiply.
You get 20--actually,and so we don't have to get big numbers,
let me reduce this fraction. Divide the top and the bottom.
This is the same thing as 6/5 is equal to x/15.
This is easier to multiply now.
You get 5x is equal to 15 times 6.
Divide both sides by 5.
You get x is equal to 15 times 6 divided by 5.
That's 3, that's 1, that's 18.
So the change in expense will be $18, and that's choice B.
See you in the next video.