Welcome to the second set of presentations
on age word problems.
I have one typed out here.
Let's see what it says.
It says, Salman- that's me- is one hundred and eight years old.
And so this is clearly at some vast time in the future.
And this'll only happen if my caloric restriction works out.
But Salman is one hundred and eight years old.
Jonathan is twenty-four years old.
How many years will it take for Salman to be exactly four
times as old as Jonathan?
Well, let's figure this one out.
What we're trying to solve for is how many years will it take.
So let's use the variable y, for years.
So y equals years until, let's just say Sal, for short.
Sal is four times Jonathan's age.
Well, if today, I, or Sal, if Salman, it's hard to speak
in the third person.
If Salman is one hundred years old today, in y years, Salman
will be one hundred and eight plus y is equal to Sal in y years.
We'll say y years.
Sal in y years is going to be one hundred and eight plus y.
And then Jonathan in y years, that's pretty easy.
He's going to be twenty-four plus y.
So that's, I'll say Jon for short.
In y years.
Not years.
y years.
And what else does the problem say?
It says, in how many years would take for Salman to be
exactly-- I should put that in another color for emphasis--
Exactly four times as old as Jonathan?
Well, and the exactly is important.
Because Salman is already more than four times
as old as Jonathan.
But they want to figure out exactly when is Salman going to
be four times as old as Jonathan.
Well, in y years Salman is going to be one hundred and eight plus y.
So we know that.
one hundred and eight plus y.
And after y years, he's going to be four times
as old as Jonathan.
Exactly four times.
And Jonathan's going to be twenty-four plus y years old.
And now we just solve the equation.
Get one hundred and eight plus y is equal to four times twenty-four.
Well, four times twenty-five is one hundred.
And we can subtract four from there.
So it's ninety-six.
Plus foury.
And now we just solve this equation.
We get three.
three, I'm going to skip some steps, because I think this
part is easy for you.
threey will equal one hundred and eight minus ninety-six.
So we get threey is equal to, what is that, twelve, right?
So y is equal to four.
So our algebra has told us that in four years Salman is going
to be exactly four times as old as Jonathan.
Let's see if that's true.
Well, if Salman is one hundred and eight right now, in four years
he's going to be one hundred and twelve.
And if Jonathan is twenty-four right now, in four years he's
going to be twenty-eight.
And let's see.
twenty-eight times four is eighty plus thirty-two.
Yep, exactly.
He'll be one hundred and twelve.
Looks like that problem worked.
Excellent.
Let's do another one.
Hope you didn't hear that, it was my stomach growling.
See how hard I work on this site?
Don't even eat properly.
Let's do another problem.
I'll type it in green this time.
Tarush is five times as old as Arman is today, eighty-five years ago.
We're dealing with huge swathes of time.
eighty-five years ago.
Tarush was ten times as old as Arman.
How old is Arman today?
Let's see if we can tackle this quite interesting
problem, I think.
Settings.
Pen tool on.
OK.
Well, I think this might be useful to do one of those
charts like we did in the first video presentation.
Well, we're trying to solve for how old is Arman today's.
So let's say Arman.
And we're going to have today.
And we're going to have, what's the other time
period we're dealing with.
We're dealing with eighty-five years ago.
So, let's say.
eighty-five years ago.
In a galaxy far, far away.
OK, Arman and Tarush.
Well, we're trying to solve for how old is Arman today's.
So let's just make that x, for simplicity.
It says Tarush is five times as old as Arman today.
So let me underline that.
Tarush is five times as old as Arman today.
So if Arman is x, that tells us that Tarush is going to be fivex.
eighty-five years ago.
So, eighty-five years ago, well, Arman is x today, then eighty-five years ago,
Arman would have been x minus eighty-five.
And if Tarush is fivex today, then Tarush would be fivex minus eighty-five.
I just subtracted eighty-five from the current age.
Because we're going eighty-five years in the past.
And now we have this extra piece of information.
Which tells us that eighty-five years ago, Tarush was ten
times as old as Arman.
So this number is going to be ten times more than this number.
That's what that sentence tells us.
eighty-five years ago, we're in this situation.
Tarush, which is this, was ten times older than Arman.
We just write that out algebraically.
eighty-five years ago, Tarush is fivex minus eighty-five.
And the sentence tells us that he was ten times older than
Arman, who is x minus eighty-five.
Now we just solve the equation.
We get fivex minus eighty-five is equal to tenx minus eight hundred and fifty.
And then you get-- and I'm going to do this, skip some
steps, just to confuse you-- fivex is equal too-- well, I think
I just confused myself.
fivex is equal to eight hundred and fifty minus eighty-five.
Let's see, what's eight hundred and fifty minus eighty-five.
It'll be thirty-five less than eight hundred.
So we could say that fivex-- thirty-five less than eight hundred.
thirty less than eight hundred gets seven hundred and seventy.
So seven hundred and sixty-five.
And then x is equal to, let me see.
five goes into seventy.
one times five.
twenty-six.
five times five is twenty-five.
fifteen.
So x is equal to one hundred and fifty-three.
We have some long-lifespanned people.
So we get the solution that Arman is one hundred and fifty-three years old.
Today.
Let's see if that makes sense.
Well, if he's one hundred and fifty-three, then, no, that can't be right.
Because then he's five.
Huh.
Well, actually I'm almost out of time.
Let me see where I might have messed up on this.
If Arman is x, Tarush is fivex.
That makes sense.
Oh, right, right, right.
I think this could make sense.
So, I thought that Tarush had to be younger than Arman.
But no, Tarush is five times one hundred and fifty-three.
So Tarush is actually seven hundred and sixty-five years old.
We should call him Methuselah.
So, Tarush is seven hundred and sixty-five years old.
And then if we go eighty-five years into the past, Tarush would have
been-- what did we say?
If we go eighty-five years into the past, so let's write this down.
This is equal to, I'm about to run out of time, so you might
have to check this yourself.
If that's equal to one hundred and fifty-three, then fivex is equal to seven hundred and sixty-five.
These numbers are big.
And then one hundred and fifty-three minus eighty-five.
Well, one hundred and fifty-five minus eighty-five would be seventy-three.
So this would be seventy-two.
And then Tarush, eighty-five years ago.
No, I think I messed up someplace.
Well, actually, I only have ten seconds before YouTube
won't let me upload it.
So we'll have to stop there.
Thank you.