So we have fourteen x plus four over negative three x minus two
is equal to eight.
And I'll give you a few moments
to see if you can tackle it on your own.
So this equation right here -
at first it doesn't look like a straightforward linear equation
We have one expression on top of another expression.
But as we will see we can simplify this
to turn it into a linear equation.
So the first thing that I want to do is -
I don't like this negative three x plus two sitting here in the denominator -
it makes me stressed.
So, I want to multiply both sides of this equation
times negative three x minus two...times negative three x minus two
What does that do for us?
Well, on the left hand side you have
this negative three x minus two
is going to be over negative three x minus two
They will cancel out.
And so you are left with on the left-hand side
your fourteen x plus four
and on your right-hand side
you just have to multiply eight times negative three x minus two.
So you are left with...
well, eight times negative three x is negative twenty-four x.
And eight times negative two is negative sixteen.
And there you have it -
we have simplified this to just a traditional linear equation -
we've got variables on both sides
so we can just keep simplifying.
So, the first thing that I want to do is -
let's say we want to put all of our x terms on the left-hand side.
So I want to get rid...
I want to get rid of this negative twenty-four x right over here.
So the best way to do that -
I'm going to add twenty-four x to the right hand side.
I can't just do it to the right-hand side,
I have to also do it to the left-hand side.
And so, I am left with, on the left-hand side,
fourteen x plus twenty-four x is thirty-eight x.
(and then I have the plus 4)
is equal to -
well, negative twenty-four x plus twenty-four x -
those cancel each other out.
And we are left with just the negative sixteen.
Negative sixteen.
Now, we just have to get rid of this four here -
Well, let's subtract that four from both sides.
And we are left with -
this is the home stretch now -
we are left with
thirty-eight x...
thirty-eight x is equal to
negative sixteen minus four,
is negative twenty.
And so we can divide both sides of this equation
by thirty-eight...
by thirty-eight.
And we are left with x is equal to
negative twenty over thirty-eight
which can be simplified further -
both the numerator and the denominator is divisible by two
so let's divide the numerator and denominator by two
and we get negative ten over nineteen.
X is equal to negative ten over nineteen.
And we are done.
I encourage you to validate this for yourself -
(it's a little bit of a hairy number right over here)
but to take this number,
substitute it back into our original equation
and validate that it actually does satisfy
that equation.