Everyone's talking about "inflation" and "deflation" these days, including myself.
And that's because it's important.
And in order to really have an informed view on it,
I think it's important to actually look at how "inflation" is defined.
(And right here, I actually took a screenshot (from my Bloomberg terminal)
of the basket of goods that makes up the Consumer Price Index --
the index that sets everything from the coupons on Treasury-inflation-protected securities --
This is the index that dictates what Social
Security payments are going [to be],
how fast they're going to grow -- I'm sure a bunch of union agreements and
pension agreements are dependent on the CPI.
So this is the underlying basket of goods
that really tells us what inflation is.
At a first level, it's just fun to look at.
Because you can compare your own household
to what the government thinks is a typical household.
For example, the government says that the typical
household spends 15.7% of their disposable income on --
-- and that's essentially the income that you take home after paying taxes --
that they spend 15.7% on food and beverages.
That seems reasonable.
What's even more interesting is that they break it down.
They get very granular.
They try to figure out how much do you spend on eggs,
and fish, and poultry, and bakery products.
And that's good because, let's say, everything else stays constant,
but the price of eggs goes through the roof,
because, [for example,] the Atkins diet becomes popular again.
Then you can actually make an informed decision
as to why inflation is going up or whether inflation will go up going forward.
So that's just interesting to look at.
If you look at the major categories:
they have food and beverages, housing --
And I'm going to come back to housing.
Because this is, in general, just a very interesting area to focus on
because it makes such a big portion of the CPI.
And it's been such a big
portion of the economic picture
especially
the last 10 years.
And obviously, it's become a big problem, has become a big factor
in terms of what's causing the financial crisis right now.
But housing is about 43% of disposable income.
Apparel: 3%.
Transportation: 15%.
This includes things like new vehicles, 4%, used cars and trucks.
And I think the way they calculate this is, they say,
what percentage of Americans are driving new vehicles versus used vehicles?
And they put fuel in here.
A lot of people, when I have this inflation-deflation argument,
they make this argument that China and India are going to continue growing.
And because of that, commodities like oil and fuel will continue to increase.
Although people were making that argument more last summer
but even now people are making that argument.
But in a developed country, you see that motor fuel
even though it hits your pocketbook on the margin
it isn't that big a part of your total expenditure.
Especially when you compare it to things like housing.
And if you keep going down, medical care: 6%.
And then recreation.
They break it down and you could look this up.
I think the Bureau of Labor
Statistics has this broken down as well
although it was much easier to get it on the Bloomberg terminal.
Education: on average, 3%.
Obviously, if you're sending your kids to college that's a much higher number.
But, on average, if you take the average household.
And finally, other goods
and services: tobacco, et cetera, et cetera.
So that one is just interesting
to look at.
So whenever you have a
discussion on the things that may or may not drive inflation
it's important to weight them by these weightings
that the CPI gives them
to actually figure out what the actual
impact on how we measure inflation really will be.
With that said, if you think
about it, really the biggest portion of this is the
housing piece.
I think that's fair. Housing is a large percentage
of most people's disposable income
especially in
a Western society
You can imagine, if you live in
a Third-World country, and you're barely getting by.
Food
might be a huge part of your expenditure
maybe rivaling
housing if you've just kind of built a house someplace.
But in a developed society,
housing is a huge percentage of it.
And I want to focus on one
thing, and a lot of people have talked about this.
And actually Mish -- once again,
from Global Economic Analysis --
he really encouraged me
to highlight this.
So within housing, obviously
some people rent, some people buy.
And so, they give a 6% weighting
of the whole basket to rent
and then they give a
roughly 24%, 25% weighting to something that they call
owners' equivalent of rent of primary residence.
So this is essentially their
attempt to measure
how much it costs to live for people
who own houses.
What's interesting, and you
probably have caught onto it,
is they use the words "owners'
equivalent rent."
So what they do -- and this is the
current methodology --
They don't say, "How much
is your mortgage?"
They don't say, how much does
it cost you to buy the house
and amortize it over the
reasonable life of the house?
They actually just say, how
much would it cost to rent that house?
And they've kept waffling back
and forth between-- sometimes
they just look for equivalent
houses, and they say, well,
how much would that
cost to rent?
At one point they were actually
surveying people
and they would ask them, how
much would it cost to rent your house?
Which is probably even
a worse number.
But the bottom line is, they're
not factoring in actual mortgages.
And you can even see it
on the weighting.
Right when I looked at these
numbers, I was like, well,
roughly 66% of people
own houses.
How come this number isn't
66% relative to this number, right? It's closer to 80%.
I was like, oh, I know that's
fair because more people actually live in homes.
You could say that 66% of
overall households own
but in general, homes are bigger,
there might be more people in it.
So you could either think of it
on a person basis or maybe on a square footage basis.
It makes a little bit more sense
to weight houses higher.
But what's interesting here,
is that this number,
especially if you add these
two, housing in general is about 30% of disposable
income.
And traditionally that was the
rule that a bank would use
to decide whether you can
afford a house.
It shouldn't be more than a
third of your disposal income,
or at least a mortgage
payment shouldn't be more than a third
We know, especially over this
last real estate bubble,
that's become a much, much
larger percentage of people's actual disposal income.
So you wonder, why is this
weighting only 30% of disposable income?
Well, that's because they use
owners' equivalent rent.
They didn't actually
say what people's mortgage payments are.
So even though mortgage payments
might be going through the roof
even though
the price of a house might be going through the roof
it does
not get reflected in the CPI number as of
the early `80s.
This is straight from
the Bureau Of Labor Statistics website.
And they wrote-- and they're
actually using doublespeak here
I just copied and pasted
it straight from their website
--"until the early 1980s, the
CPI used what is called
the asset price method to measure
the change in the cost of owner-occupied housing."
That makes sense and I'm not
sure whether they just looked
at how much houses cost this
year relative to last year
and then they put that into the
weighting
or they determined the weighting based on people's
average mortgage.
But in general, that's a good
way to measure it, right?
Either your mortgage payment, or
how much houses cost.
They said, "the asset price method
treats the purchase of an asset
such as a house, as it
does the purchase of any consumer good." Fair enough.
"Because the asset price
method can lead to inappropriate results--" And
this is the key line.
"Because the asset price method can lead
to inappropriate results for goods
that are purchased
largely for investment reasons." I agree with that.
If something is purchased
largely for investment reasons
if I'm purchasing gold,
maybe that shouldn't be included in the CPI
because
it's largely for investment reasons or for stocks.
But then they use this kind of
completely disjointed logic.
They say, you know, "because
asset price method can lead to
inappropriate results for
goods that are purchased largely for investment reasons,
the CPI implemented the rental equivalence approach
to measuring price change for owner-occupied
housing."
To me, that makes no sense.
Owner-occupied is not purchased for investment reasons.
That's a fair enough argument
if you're doing it for rentals
or if you're doing
it for vacation homes.
But for actual owner-occupied
housing, this sentence makes no sense.
Based on their own rationale,
there's no reason to transfer to this rental equivalent
approach.
The whole reason why I'm going
here is,
because in the early `80s, I think 1983-- they say
it right here, in January, 1983--
because they switched
over to this,
this kind of inflation that we've seen
in the price of houses,
especially the real estate
bubble we've seen the last 10 years,
in no way got
incorporated into the inflation numbers.
So it essentially understated
them.
You can see that here.
Well, two things: not only did
it understate it,
but it probably understated the
weighting itself.
And Mish, he's had a couple
of posts about this.
You really should use
something like the Case-Shiller Index on this line
right here,
instead of doing this for owners'
equivalent.
But I'd argue one
step further.
Not only should you use
something like the Case-Shiller Index
but to
actually gauge this weighting
you should actually survey
people
and say what percentage of your disposable
income is dedicated to
your mortgage and other things
related to owning a house?
And especially over the last
seven years, I would guess, and I'm almost sure about this,
that it would be much larger than 30% of your
disposal income.
So not only was this number
being understated
or the growth in that number, because
it didn't incorporate the increase in housing prices,
but
this weighting itself was understated.
And just to get a sense of
how much, this is the Case-Shiller Index.
And you could look up the
Case-Shiller Index
but, in my opinion, it's the best index
for actual increases or decreases in the
price of homes.
You see from 2001 to 2006
roughly, houses were increasing by 10%
to 15% a year.
So if you use that instead of
the rental equivalent
then over the same timeframe-- I
don't have a chart for rent,
but rent was not increasing at
anywhere near this pace.
If anything, people were leaving
apartments to buy houses
so rent was actually
staying pretty stable.
But 10% to 15%-- this is year
over year growth, this is what this chart is.
So 10% to 15%, if you weight
that at 30% of the CPI basket,
then really the reported
inflation number was being understated by 3%
to 5% a year.
And I'd argue that this
weighting should have grown over that time period
because
people were spending more and more
of their disposable
income on their mortgage payments.
Then this weighting should've
been more like 40%
and you could have said you're
understating it by 4% to 6%.
And if you look here,
this is the actual reported CPI numbers.
What I'm saying is, over that
timeframe, the real inflation number should have
been up here.
And then, now that we have
actual deflation in home prices, this is zero.
So now, the most recent
Case-Shiller numbers say that housing has depreciated
by 20%.
We're essentially understating
the deflation now.
So although right now the CPI
has us at kind of the zero mark
if you actually
incorporated the real prices of homes
and you didn't use
rents as a proxy for it
you would actually get a much more
negative number here.
And Mish actually did
that on his blog.
And if you actually want to read
his blog, which I highly recommend,
do a Google search
for Mish, M-I-S-H. And this is directly from his
blog
so I have to give him credit for that. And what he did here is
he actually charted the actual inflation numbers that
were reported. That's in blue.
And then on top of that, he
put what he calls the Case-Shiller CPI Index
and that's in red. And you see here, especially
over the housing boom--
These are the inflation numbers we
got from the government.
They peaked out in the 4% or 5%
range, which isn't low by any stretch of the imagination,
and that's probably why the Feds started
increasing interest rates right around here
arguably at
the worst possible time.
But if you look at the CS CPI,
or the Case-Shiller CPI
you could almost say that the real
inflation actually peaked out in the 8% range back here.
And you could argue that, if
this was the actual number that the Fed was using
it would
have actually been a much better policy tool
because
they would have seen the inflation pop up back
here in January '03.
And they would have known that
they were keeping their monetary policy too loose back
here
and they could've avoided this whipsawing that they did
and in 2007 and 2008.
And I'd argue even further
that even this number is understanding the reality
because back here, as a percentage of the actual CPI
basket,
he just took the CPI numbers and replaced the year
over year change essentially
into the same weighting as
the current CPI numbers.
But if you actually weighted it
based on the actual amount of disposable income
people
were spending on their mortgages
I would guess that it
would have looked something more like this.
And you would have seen actual
inflation peak out here, probably in the 10%
or 11% range.
There's a lot of social
commentary about this; why they do it.
One argument is
that a lot of
the government's or even corporate liabilities are
indexed to inflation.
You have an inflation index.
On the other hand, the sale of
homes
essentially transfers wealth from one generation
to another.
Especially when you have
a huge increase in the price of homes.
If they did this on purpose,
and I'm guessing that they did
it allows housing prices
to increase dramatically.
And when housing prices increase
dramatically
it transfers wealth from the new
buyer generation to the retiree generation
so it helps
subsidize the retirees.
And, at the same time, by taking
it out of the actual CPI index
it keeps the
government's, and actually a lot of other corporate,
liabilities low.
Because now Social
Security, it's indexed to the CPI numbers.
So if the CPI numbers are not
incorporating, are not raising up here
you don't have to
increase people's Social Security payments.
And you kind of get to project
this farce to people.
You say, oh, in inflation
adjusted terms, you're doing better than your parents'
generation did.
Oh, but, by the way, you can
afford 1/3 the house now.
And to some degree that's been
propagated-- it's obviously all falling apart now.
But the big takeaway from this,
if I had to give you just one,
is that the
CPI index is a government created tool.
It's based on a survey and, not
only has it not been the same survey,
but it's actively
changed over the years.
And it's changed in ways that
significantly impact the actual numbers that are reported
and, to some degree, play into what I think
the government wants people to believe.
Anyway see you in
the next video.