Let's think a little bit about powers of zero.
What do you think zero to the first power is going to be?
I encourage you to pause this video.
Let's just think about it.
One definition of exponentiation is that you start with a one,
you start with a one,
then you multiply this number times a one once.
This is going to be one times--
Let me do it in the right color.
one times zero.
You're multiplying the one by zero once.
One times zero.
That's just going to be equal to zero.
What do you think zero squared,
or zero to the second power is going to be equal to?
Once again you could--
One way of thinking about this is, you start with a one,
you start with a one and we're going to multiply it by zero two times.
So, times zero, times zero.
Well, what's that going to be?
You multiply anything times zero, once again,
you are going to get zero.
I think you see a pattern here.
If I take zero to any non-zero number,
so to the power of any non-zero--
This is a non-zero number.
Non-zero number.
Then this is going to be equal to zero.
This is going to be equal to zero.
This raises a very interesting question.
What happens at zero to the zeroth power?
So here, zero to the millionth power is going to be zero.
Zero to the trillionth power is going to be zero.
Even negative, or frational, exponents--
Which we haven't talked about yet.
As long as they're non-zero this is going to be equal to zero.
It kind of makes sense.
Now let's think about what zero--
Let's think about what zero to the zeroth power is,
'cause this is actually a fairly deep question.
I'll give you a hint.
Actually, why don't you pause the video,
and think a little bit about what zero to the zeroth power should be.
There are two trains of thought here.
You could say, well, zero to some non-zero number is zero,
so why don't we just extend this to all numbers,
and say zero to any number should be zero.
Maybe you should say zero to the zeroth power is zero.
Then there was another train of logic that we already learned,
that any non-zero number--
So, non-zero number.
If you take any non-zero number and you raise it to the zeroth power, is--
we have already established that this is--
You start with a one and you multiply it times that
non-zero number zero times, so this is always going to be equal
to one for non-zero numbers.
This is always going to be equal to one.
Maybe say, 'hey, maybe we should extend
this to all numbers including zero.
Maybe zero to the zeroth power is going to be equal to one.
We could make the arguement that zero to
the zeroth power should be equal to one.
You see a conundrum here, and there are actually really good cases.
You could get fairly sophisticated with your mathematics.
There are really good cases for both of these.
For zero to the zeroth being zero and zero to the zeroth power being one.
So, when mathematicians get into this situation where they say,
'There are good cases for either.
There is not a completely natural one.
Either of these definitions would lead to difficulties in mathematics.'
What mathematicians have decided to do is, for the most part,
and you will find people who dispute this will just say,
'I like one more than the other',
but for the most part, this is left undefined.
Zero to the zeroth is not defined by, at least, more conventional mathematics.
In some use cases it might be defined to be one of these two things.
So zero to any non-zero number, you are going to get zero.
Any non-zero number to the zeroth power you are going to get one.
But zero to the zero, that's a little bit of a question mark.