The basic tools are the same as the ancients.
It's hard and just giving a list of tools,
how does that translate into a beautiful work of art?
Working by hand, everything slows down and you can
think about what you're doing while you're doing it.
You start roughing out, taking the bulk of weight off
with a point chisel which concentrates all the
force of your blow at one point
and bursts the stone away.
Your next step after that, having removed
the bulk of the material is to model your form
with a tooth chisel.
A tooth chisel is basically a comb and you use
a tooth chisel to model form while at the same time
remove stone fairly quickly.
Something to remember about marble carving,
it's very tactile.
The way the stone bursts from a point chisel
or the way your tooth chisel just kind of swims
through the stone.
It's a hard material but you can jump into a piece
of space with these tools.
If you cut at a very oblique angle to the stone
you can get a finer surface.
If you're forcing the tool straight into the stone,
you can get quite a different texture.
The rasp is just a whole row of fine little teeth
cut into a piece of metal and you can then just rub
or grind this tool into the stone removing material
and really refine a plane.
Depending on how you use the tool you can really
emphasize certain forms.
If you kind of lose your ego
and just flow into the stone through your tools,
there's no end of possibilities of what you can do
inside that space.