Let's figure out what eleven and twelve
sixteenths minus five in eight
sixteenths is. We might have to
simplify it down to lowest terms.
So the way I like to do these is the kind of
separate out the whole number part of
the mixed numbers from the fractional
part.
So I can rewrite this number right over
here as eleven
plus twelve over sixteen.
And from that I'm going to subtract and
I'll put parentaces here because I'm gonna break
this part open
I'm going to subtract, I'm going to subtract five plus
eight over
sixteen. Five and eight sixteenth, same thing
as five plus eight sixteenth,
but remember I'm subtracting it
I'm subtracting this whole thing so I
can rewrite it as a rewrite this part
eleven
plus twelve over sixteen.
And I'm substracting five plus eigth sixteenth so I can distribute the negative
sign.
So it's going to be minus five,
minus five, negative one times five. The
negative one times positive eight sixteenth
so it's going to be minus,
minus eight over sixteen.
Minus eight over sixteen. And then I like
to do the whole number part separately
and the fractional part separately.
So let's do the whole number parts. We have
eleven minus five, right here, eleven
minus five. Will do that part that's a
whole number part
and then we have plus
plus
twelve sixteenth - let me do this in pink maybe - plus
twelve sixteenth minus
eight sixteenth
minus eight
over sixteen.
And eleven minus five is six.
And I have six plus - and the denominators are
same here - so we're gonna get something
over sixteen
and twelve minus eight is four.
So this is the same thing as six plus
four over sixteen, which is the same
thing as writing is a mixed number
six and four sixteenths.
Six and four sixteenths. And this is
the right quantity
but we can simplify it. Four over sixteen
can be simplified. Both the numerator and the
denominator are divisible by four. They both
have the factor four. Let's divide both
the numerator and the denominator by four.
Divided by four, divided by four, since we're dividing by the same thing we're not
changing its quantity.
And so this is equal to
we still have a whole number part six
but the fraction part is now one,
one over four, so we get six and one
fourth.