I have a statement here in yellow
which for the sake of this video, we will assume is true, that "Eating spinach makes you stronger."
And then after this, in white, I've written a bunch of other statements,
and I want to figure out if these are reasonable things to say,
given the assumption that this first statement is true:
"Eating spinach makes you stronger." We can even put it over here.
Eating spinach makes you stronger.
So hear this first sentence. "If you eat spinach, then you will get stronger." So this is just really a rephrasing of the first one. This is really just putting it in "if/then" form.
You have your "if", and your "then" but its really saying the same thing.
"If you eat spinach": That's the same thing as "Eating spinach". "then you will become stronger. "then you will be stronger", "you'll get stronger".
This is saying the exact same thing
i will say that if you assume that first statement is true
the second statement is definitely true.
Now that third statement