What I want to do in this video is
think about the idea of fraction.
And for the sake of this video, as we learn
what a fraction is, you can think of it
as a part of a whole.
Later on we will think of it in even more ways.
What do I mean by a "part of a whole"?
Let's imagine we have a pizza,
and let's say I divide it into 4 equal parts.
So there is a total of 4 equal slices of pizza.
And let's say on 3 of these slices
I have cheese, only cheese.
And in the fourth slice I have cheese and olives.
So we can ask ourselves what fraction
of this pizza has olives on it?
Well, we have 4 total slices, all equal sections,
and 1 of those has olives.
So we can say 1/4 of this pizza
has olives on it, 1 out of the 4.
Now, someone says, what fraction
of this pizza only has cheese?
Well, this slice has cheese but also olives,
so we don't count that, but we have 3
of this 4 slices with only cheese.
So, 3/4 of the pizza has only cheese.
Let's do a couple more examples,
because this is probably one of the most important
and useful idea you can have in your brain.
Let's imagine instead we were looking at some fruit,
let's say that I have an orange, a banana,
a lemon, an apple and some grapes.
If I were to ask you what fraction of the fruit
I have is, let's say, yellow?
Well, we could say we have a total of 5 pieces of fruit.
What fraction of those pieces of fruit are yellow?
Well, I have 2 yellow pieces right over here,
so let's say 2/5 of the fruit is yellow.
Let me do one more example,
just to make the point clear.
Let me draw a candy bar, so that's all food-related.
Let's say I have a candy bar, just like that,
and let me divide it into 5 equal pieces.
Let's assume these are all equal pieces,
and I'm hungry, so I eat this piece and this piece,
so they essentially go away.
So, what fraction of these pieces have I eaten?
Well, I have a total of 5 pieces,
and I ate 2 of them, so 2/5 of this bar
have been eaten.
So I'll leave you there,
maybe I'll make another video that
doesn't have as many food analogies,
but this is a super useful concept
and I encourage you to think about it
as much as possible and then try the exercises
here on Khan Academy.