In this video I want to see if we can
understand the idea of a hedge fund
a little bit better
These tend to be pretty mysterious
and sometimes get a bad name
because some hedge funds do do some
fairly strange things and secretive things in the market
and people are so, rightfully so, suspicious
of many of them but the real difference
between a hedge fund and the types of mutual funds
that we just talked about are that
they are not regulated by the SEC
Not regulated by the SEC
And because they are not regulated
they can't market themselves - they can't market
-that's why when you watch, when you watch
when you watch financial shows
or you get a magazine, a finance magazine
you will not see ads for hedge funds
the mutual funds are all over the place
marketing them left and right
Hedge funds, the most, the largest hedge-funds in the world,
are definitely not even household names
No-one - very few people even know
what those largest hedge funds in the world are
that's because they can't market themselves
no matter how good of a track record
or really how reasonable of a fund they might be
some might not be reasonable, some are
they can't market themselves
and they also can't take money from the public
can't take money from the public
so in general, in order to invest in a hedge fund
you have to be an accredited investor
which means you have a certain net worth
or you have a certain income, or maybe
by virtue of your education you can prove
that you have a certain level of sophistication to invest
in these things that aren't regulated
I guess you don't need the SEC to watch
your back.
So the regulation is a key difference - no marketing
no money from the public and the other
key difference is how the managers tend to be
incented - I know incented is not a word
or motivated. In the mutual fund world
managers get a percent of assets
so for a mutual funds manager, larger is better
the more undermanagement, the more money the mutual fund manager is going to make
so they really just want to keep marketing and marketing
they don't get a cut of the profit
so really there's not a lot of incentive for them to
to try to really beat the market here
because if they don't beat the market one year
then all the sudden, they are you know, their fund will shrink
so they really just get a fee on the size of the fund
and a hedge fund, usually the implication is that hedge fund will be more actively managed
so larger management fee, so larger management fee, instead of the 1%, 1% is actually a lot for mutual fund
instead of that, hedge funds tend to be 1-2 percent
so 1 to 2 percent management fee, sometimes even larger than that
but the even bigger difference, this is where hedge fund are very different
from traditional mutual funds, is that the management company
the general partner gets a percentage of the profits
so the hedge fund manager, or the management company
the going rate tends to be about 20 percent of the profits
of the funds. Sometimes it's less, sometimes it's a lot more.
Some very successful hedge funds gets 25, 30 percent or even a larger percentage of the profit
so with that out of the way.
In the next video, I am going to do a slight difference
some different mechanics of essentially the same returns
but one by a hedge funds, and then one by traditional mutual funds.