We already know that the sum of the interior angles of a triangle
add up to 180 degrees
If the measure of this angle is A,
the measure of this angle over here is B, and
the measure of this angle is C, we know that A + B + C = 180 degrees
What happens when we have polygons with more than 3 sides?
a quadrilateral
probably applies to any quadrilateral with four sides,
not just things that have right angles and parallel lines
and all the rest
Actually, that looks a little too close to being parallel
so let me draw it like this
The way you can think about it, with the 4-sided quadrilateral is,
we already know about this:
the measures of the interior angles of a triangle add up to 180
so maybe we can divide this into 2 triangles
From this point right over here, if we draw a line like this,
Then if measure of this angle is A, measure of this is B,
measure of that is C
We know that A + B + C = 180 degrees
Then if we call this over here, X, this over here, Y and that, Z
Those are the measures of those angles
We know that X + Y + Z = 180 degrees
So, if we want the measure of the sum of all of the interior angles,
all of the interior angles are going to be:
plus this angle, which is going to be A + X
A + X is that whole angle for the quadrilateral
Plus this whole angle, which is going to be C + Y
And where you know A + B + C is 180 degrees
And we know that Z + X + Y = 180 degrees
So plus 180 degrees which is equal to 360 degrees
I think you see the general idea here
We just have to figure out how many triangles
we can divide something into
Then we just multiply it by 180 degrees,
since each of those triangles will have 180 degrees
can we fit into that thing
Let me draw an irregular pentagon
1, 2, 3, 4, 5
Looks more like a bit of a side-ways house there
Once again, we can draw our triangles inside of this pentagon
That would be one triangle there
That would be another triangle
that perfectly cover this pentagon
This is one triangle, the other triangle and the other one
We know each of those have 180 degrees,
if we take the sum of their angles
We also know the sum of all those interior angles are equal
to the sum of the interior angles of the polygon as a whole
To see that, clearly this interior angle is
one of the angles of the polygon
This is, as well
When you take the sum of this one and this one,
We take the sum of that one and that one, you get that entire one
Then when you take the sum of that one, plus that one,
plus that one, you get that entire interior angle
So if you take the sum of all the interior angles of
all of the interior angles of the polygon
In this case you have 1, 2, 3 triangles
3 times 180 degrees is equal to what?
300 +240 = 540 degrees
To generalize it,
we have up to use up four sides
We have to use up all the four sides of this quadrilateral
We had to use up four of the five sides right here in this pentagon
1, 2, and then 3, 4
So four sides give you two triangles
It seems like maybe every incremental side you have after that,
you can get another triangle out of it
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 sides
and I can get one triangle out of these 2 sides
1, 2 sides of the actual hexagon
I can get another triangle out of these 2 sides of the actual hexagon
And it looks like I can get another triangle
out of each of the remaining sides
So one out of that one, and then,
one out of that one right over there
S-sided polygon
or 6 sides
So we can assume that S is greater than 4 sides
I want to figure out how many non-overlapping triangles
that perfectly cover that polygon
How many can I fit inside of it
Then I just have to multiply the number of triangles
times 180 degrees
to figure out what are the sum of the interior angles of that polygon
as a function of the number of sides
Once again, four of the sides are going to be used
to make two triangles
and we have two sides right over there
I can have, I can draw one triangle
what happens to the rest of the sides of the polygon
You can imagine putting a big black piece of construction paper
There might be other sides here
So out of these 2 sides I can draw one triangle just like that
Out of these two sides, I can draw another triangle right over there
So 4 sides used for two triangles
Then, no matter how many sides I have left over,
if I have all sorts of craziness here
Let me draw a little bit neater than that
So I can have all sorts of craziness right over here
It looks like every other incremental side
I can get another triangle out of it
one triangle out of that side, one triangle out of that side
and then one triangle out of this side
For example, this figure that I have drawn is a very irregular
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, is that right?
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7 ,8 ,9 10 It is a decagon
In this decagon, four of the sides were used for two triangles
Then the other 6 sides I was able to get a triangle each
I have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10
Did I count, am I just not seeing something?
Oh I see, I have to draw another line right over here
These are two different sides
I can get another triangle out of that right over there
There you have it
I have these two triangles out of 4 sides
Then out of the other 6 remaining sides I get a triangle each
Plus 6 triangles, I got a total of 8 triangles
So we can generally think about it
Let me write this down
Our number of triangles is going to be equal to 2,
The remaining sides, I get a triangle each
The remaining sides are going to be S minus 4
The number of triangles are going to be 2 plus S minus 4
So, if I have an S-sided polygon, I can get S minus two triangles
that perfectly cover that polygon
Which tells us that an S-sided polygon if it has S minus 2 triangles,
that the interior angles in it are going to be
S minus 2 times 180 degrees, which is a pretty cool result
So someone told you that they had a 102-sided polygon
So, S is equal to 102 sides
You can say, okay the number of interior angles are going to be
Which is equal to 180, with two more zeros behind it
of a 102-sided polygon