Were asked to subtract all of the craziness over here. and it looks daunting but if we really focus,
it should actually be really easy to subtract and simplify this thing. Right from the get go i have four
time the fourth root of 81 x to the fifth and from that, i want to subtract two times the fourth root
of eighty one x to the fifth and so you can really just say that i have four of something, and this
something, i will just circle it yellow. i have four of these--it could be lemon-- i have four of these
things, and i want to subtract two of these things. These are the exact same things. there the fourth
root of eight one x to the fifth, and the fourth root of eight one x to the fifth. So, if i have four
lemons and i want to subract two of them, im gonna have two lemons left over. If i have four of this
thing and i have to take away two of this thing, im gonna have two of these thing left over. So these
terms right over here simplify to two times the fourth root of eight one x to the fifth, and i got this
two just by subtracting the quantity of four of some by two of something, and this is equal to two of
something. And of course, we still have this minus the regular principle square root of x to the third.
now i wanna try to simplify, i wanna try to simplify whats inside of these- under the radical signs-
so that we can on, on this example take the fourth root and over here, actually take maybe a principle
square root. So first of all lets see if eighty one is either a, is something to the fourth power, ot