In this video I will attempt to prove or -actually in the next several
videos attempt to prove a special case version
of stokes' theorem or essentially stokes'
theorem for a special case and I'm doing this
because that the proof will be a little bit
simpler but at the same time it's pretty convincing
and the special case we're going to assume is
that the surface we're dealing with is function
of x and y so if you give me any particular x and y
it only determines one point on that surface
so a surface like this would be the case
so it's kind of a mapping of this region of the x y
plane into three demensions so for any x y we can
figure out the height so essentially z is going to be a function of
x and y and we can get a point on the surface
so this proof would not apply to a surface
that's like a sphere or something like that where any
point on the x y plane could actually determine two
points on our surface but this is a pretty good start
the other thing that we are going to assume, we are going to assume
that z which is essentially a function of x and y
and that this function of x and y has continuous
second order derivatives so continuous
second derivatives and the reason why I'm
going to make that assumption
is it's going to help us in our proof later on
it's going to allow us to say " that the partial of our surface
or the partial of z with respect to x and then taking the derivative of that
with respect to y is going to be the same as
the partial of z with respect to y and taking the n
derivative of that with respect to x
and in order to be able to make this statement we have to
assume that z or or z right over here z is a function of
x and y has continuous second order derivatives
and over here we've just written our vector field f
that we're going to deal with when we're trying
to play with stokes' theorem
and we'll assume that it has continuous first-order
derivatives now with that out of the way
let's think about what stokes' theorem tells us,
and then we'll think about for this particular case
how we can write it out and hopefully
we will see the two things are equal!
so let me write it out
so stoke's theorem tells us that
if x dot dr over some path
and the path that we care about is essentially
this path right over here I'll do it in blue
it's this path right over here
this is the boundary this is the boundary
of our surface
so this is c right over here
stokes' theorem tells us that this should be the same
thing this should be equivalent to the surface
integral over our surface
--over our surface of curl of f--- curl of f DOT ds
dot- dotted with the surface itself
and so in this video I want to focus
or probably this and the next video
I want to focus on the second half
I want to focus this I want to see how we
can express this given the assumptions
we've made and then after that we're going to
see how we can express this given the same assumptions
and then hopefully we'll find that we get them to
be equal to each other!
so let's just start figuring out what the curl
of f is equal to
so the curl of f
the curl of f
is equal to
you can view it as the dell operator crossed
with our vector field f which is equal to
can write our components so i- let's do it in different colors-
i, j and k components
i j and k components and then I need to
write my dell operator or my partial
operator or my partial operator as I guess I could call them
so the partial with respect to x
the partial with respect to y
the partial with respect to z
and then I have to write i, j and k
components of my vector field f
and I will do that in gre- well, I'll do that in blue
and so we have p which is a function of x y and z
q which is a function of x y and z
and r which is a function of x y and z
and so this is going to evaluate as
it's going to be i* so blank out that column that row
it's going to be the partial of r with respect to y
minus the partial of q with respect to z
and then checkerboard pattern
minus j and then times the partial of r