The fair value of a futures contract is the price of the contract
at which a buyer of the stock would be neutral between
buying it on an actual stock exchange, and actually buying the stock.
And agreeing to buy the futures contract, or the seller of the stock
would be neutral between selling it right now in the actual exchange
versus agreeing to go short. Or agreeing to be on the selling side for a futures contract.
And the fair value tends to be quoted for the front month.
Or the next expiring future's contract. And to see how this works,
why someone would be neutral between, say, buying something now for a hundred dollars
and, agreeing to buying it, maybe, next month at a hundred and two dollars,
think of it this way: If they want to just hold that stock a month or two or three from now.
they could pay a hundred dollars right now, or they could take their hundred dollars,
so they could either just buy right now, or they could stick it maybe in a money market account.
They could get some interest for the next few weeks, and then they could buy the futures contract.
So they got interest of two dollars if they kept that hundred dollars in let's say,
a money market account for the next, until the actual contract date for that future's contract,
they'd be neutral. I could spend a hundred dollars today,
or I could put a hundred dollars in a money market account
and get two dollars in interest, and I'm not going to worry about the dividends right now,
if the dividends happened then, obviously, you would want to pay less for this thing
where didn't get the dividend. But assuming no dividends, you'd say,
"Well, I'd be willing to pay a hundred and two dollars for that."
If this was only a hundred and one dollars, if the price of the futures contract was
a hundred and one dollars, then you'd say,
"Wait, if the price of the future's contract was a hundred and one dollars,
I would rather put my money in a money market account and get two dollars of interest and buy it in a
month for a hundred and one dollars. I'll essentially get an extra dollar if I do that."
If the price is at a hundred and three dollars, you'd say,
"Well gee, if I want to hold that stock a month or two from now, I'm way better buying it right now."
Or, another way to think about it if the price is at a hundred and three dollars,
and I'm a seller of the stock. Instead of selling it today for a hundred dollars,
I'm better off, let's say I need a hundred dollars right now,
I'm better off borrowing a hundred dollars right now, paying maybe two dollars in interest,
and then selling it a month later for a hundred and three dollars.
So the fair value is the price at which a buyer or seller is neutral between
buying and selling the stock or entering into a future's contract.
I'll go into it a little more into detail in the next video, but its main use is an
indicator of what is likely to happen once a market opens.
And that is because futures markets trade have much longer trading hours, sometimes twenty four hours, than
traditional stock markets. So if you can imagine,
If the price of a futures contract is trading below its fair value,
the only reason why that would happen is if a lot of
people are actually expecting once the stock, the stock market opens, that the stock price is going to go down.