We’re in Madrid, at the Prado,
And we’re looking at a Velazquez, a large painting.
This is the Vulcan Forge.
It’s been described by some
art historians as a kind of burlesque,
actually.
Here’s Apollo, who we can see, the god of
the Sun and the god of poetry
with the halo on his head on the left
who is here telling Vulcan,
who is forging armor -
-a suit of armor -
and is very hard at work all day
and Apollo is just come to tell him that
his wife Venus has been having an affair with Mars
the god of war.
Now, look just at the attitudes of those two faces.
They forget about the rest for just a moment.
Apollo’s back arches, his head is up.
He’s rather full of himself actually.
As he has this very powerful message to Vulcan.
Vulcan looks horrified and dangerous.
He’s holding this red hot metal
in one hand he’s got a hammer in the other
and he looks like he’s ready to strike anything.
And look at his body
He’s got this beautiful torso, muscles and his ripples
and his abdomen. But his face has that kind of Caravaggio feel of his
He’s not ideally beautiful (-Up this world).
I mean he’s got this ideally beautiful body.
In fact, all of the male figures have ideal bodies,
as though Velazquez is looking at ancient Greek and Roman sculpture,
looking at the artists of the Renaissance, maybe Michael Angelo
and also looking at the art of Caravaggio.
But the heads are different, aren’t they?
They are. They are not so idealized, as you pointed out.
In fact, the heads are incredibly naturalistic,
even though they’re painted in a fairly loose manner.
So, this is conflict in this painting between
this kind of realism and down to earthness
and the figures and
and what are they doing,
and their gestures and the emotions that they convey.
But also the sense of their kind of standing like classical sculptures,
their bodies look like classical sculptures.
But here’s the thing is that
I don’t think the French whether Italians
would have rendered
an important mythological subject
with this
much almost with comedy involved, right? – yeah
Look at the man who is second from the right.
He looks astonished, I mean he’s really absurd.
So, there is a kind of …human sort of sense of conflict, humor.
It seems very debasing in some way,
really not treating the classical
with the kind of honor
that is usually accorded.
A the same time though, it looks like an academic exercise,
because we have the three male figures in the center
shown from three different points of view.
The one on the left, Vulcan, shown front door,
the next one show from behind
the third one shown in profile
and the last figure on the right shown,
for sure coming up towards us.
Those first three almost like if they were female figures,
like the Three Graces.
-Exactly! It looks very orderly and composed and balanced.
And a little bit like a performance for maybe possible future patrons.
I mean here’s Velázquez’s still relatively young.
He’s made a trip to Rome with the urging of Ruben’s
and perhaps demonstrating his skill
as an artist who can paint the male nude.
It certainly shows an artist who’s willing to sort of reinvent
or push the boundaries, the ways in which stories are told.
[music]