so this is the first video in a short
series introducing some of the major
ideas of the protestant reformation
And in this video we just want to lay
the groundwork
what was it like to live in europe
before the protestant reformation
That is before fifteen seventeen when
martin luther a german monk and
professor of theology nailed his
ninety-five theses
to the door of the catholic church in
Wittenberg
and we'll get back to that
I was driving around my neighborhood
about a week ago
and I took photographs of some of the
churches that were there and within only
fifteen or twenty minutes I had
photographed the signs in front of six
different kinds of churches and this is
a really good place to start because
it's at the time of reformation that
we get this explosion
of different kinds of christianity so tell
us what you took pictures of. I took
pictures of a lutheran church of the baptist
church of the united methodist church
there was a catholic church there there
was a congregational church
there's a presbyterian church
and so
five of those six churches were created
as a result of the protestant
reformation so let's go back to a time
when it was only one kind of
christianity in western europe
and that's religion we today call
roman catholicism no we didn't need to
use that phrase roman catholicism
because there was nothing to
differentiate it from
the term catholic really means universal
and so that makes the point
that this was the universal church or
that was their ambition to be
the universal church and we use the
term roman catholic
because the head of the church is
in Rome and that's the pope
That man was enormously important
because he would lead the way to salvation and to heaven
according to the catholic tradition that
is one found one's way to salvation
which was tremendously important because
the alternative was hell and it's important
to remember I think that back then the
concern for most people was salvation
was how to get to heaven
and the path was one path
It was through the teachings of the church
through the sacraments
In a way it was a simpler time to live because
you get one choice you don't have to say
what religion should I be except for
those very few people
in Europe, for instance,
very few jews and even if you are
Muslims. So the church really infused
everybody's life it was the vehicle
to salvation and just for the average
person
in a small town
the church's would tower over the
other buildings. The bells in the tower would
ring on the hour.
The church would celebrate the saint's feast days what
we call holidays
that is holy days
and it was in a sense the church that
marked the days of your life and the
major events in your life as well and
through the sacraments you helped to
earn God's grace you have to secure
yourself a place in heaven and the
sacraments included baptism,
confirmation, communion, which you might know as the
Eucharist
penance, also known as confession,
marriage,
last rites,
and ordination for priests.
so it's good reminder of how
important the church was
in the lives of every day people and
those everyday people although they
might look to their local priest would
look to the pope in rome
as the ultimate authority on earth
and the pope at this point in fifteen
seventeen was Pope Leo X (the tenth)
so Pope Leo X (the tenth) was intent on
rebuilding the church of Saint Peter's
and the plans
for Saint Peter's were very
ambitious. In fact, Pope Julius II
who commissioned the rebuilding of Saint
Peter's (the pope before Pope Leo X)
said he wanted to create the most
grandiose church in all of christendom
and they did
the church itself Saint Peter's Basilica
was tremendously important to the authority
of the pope
by tradition Saint Peter is buried under
that church and Saint Peter was charged by
Christ himself to lead the church
so Saint Peter is understood
to be the first pope
and so every succeeding pope
is taking on the job of Saint Peter from
Christ himself
and so the very authority
of this office is vested in this
building. The problem is
the building was really expensive to
construct and the question was where
were they going to get the money.
Well there was a pretty common way to get
money and that was
selling indulgences.
Now an indulgence was a piece of paperwork that
made it possible
for you to get to Heaven more quickly.
most people when they died
you had throughout your life confessed
your sins you had atoned for your
sins but
it would probably be something
that you hadn't quite atoned for
and so for most people you wouldn't go
straight to Heaven
you would go instead to this place in the
betveen the way station before you get to
Heaven
a place called
purgatory
and it was indulgences that bought you time
off from purgatory. So this is a little
tricky because indulgences were actually a
very old tradition
where if you did a good work
you could, in fact, receive an indulgence
that is a kind of certificate that would
speed your soul out of purgatory to
Heaven. Even in certain extraordinary
cases
it might allow you to circumvent
purgatory entirely and go directly to
Heaven.
The problems began
not so much in the actual indulgences
but in the perception of the selling of
indulgences and here's what happened.
Leo X
granted indulgences to his
representatives to raise money for the
building of Saint Peter's. But this was
misunderstood to mean
that one could simply pay money and then
gain access to heaven directly.
But keep in mind that money was for the
rebuilding of...
Saint Peter's
and so you were doing a good work and
according to the catholic church doing
a good work is one of the ways you can
assist in the process of gaining
yourself a place in heaven.
And it does make sense that even a
monetary donation to doing good
christian work
would be itself a kind of holy act.
But it did come to be seen as a money
exchange
for getting to Heaven.
And the one example that really got
under Martin Luther's cross, so to speak,
was a man named Tetzel who was selling
indulgences not far
from Wittenberg where Luther was Professor of
Theology. Tetzel said,
"as soon as the coin in the coffer rings,
the soul from purgatory springs."
So you can see right there
money is going in and the soul is going
up to Heaven. It sounds so crass and
you're absolutely right
Martin Luther who was a monk and was
a very devout professor of theology was
really rubbed the wrong way by
people saying they had bought these
indulgences and therefore they were
freed of their sins.
And as a monk, Luther felt oppressed by the sinfulness
of human nature of his own
nature
and so the idea that you can pay money
to erase those sins and get quicker entry to Heaven
was really an issue for
him
he took these issues very seriously and
really struggled with them
and then he did
what any good
doctor of theology would do. He wrote out
a series of arguments. But in his case
he posted them at least according to
tradition
to the doors of the castle church in
wittenberg
ninety-five theses ninety-five arguments
that took issue primarily
with the selling of indulgences
Luther sent them to the local archbishop
and they made their way around
and so we have the beginnings of the
protestant reformation
in fact if you think about those words
protestant reformation for just a moment
i think it's interesting to note that
the word protestant is formed out of the word
protest and reformation out of the word
reform
so this was a kind of protest against
the church
and it was an attempt to reform it