Swirling spiral arms of galaxy M33
can be seen in visible light, but the true extent of these
spiral arms are revealed in ultraviolet light. Just as a dog
can hear a whistle just outside the range of human hearing,
bugs can see light just outside the range our eyes can see.
A bug zapper emits this ultraviolet light to attract insects.
Johann Ritter conducted an experiment in 1801 to find
out what, if any, electromagnetic waves are beyond violet.
Ritter knew that photographic paper would turn black more rapidly
in blue light than in red light. So he tried exposing the paper
beyond the violet end of the visible spectrum. Sure enough,
the paper turned black proving the existence of light beyond violet, ultraviolet rays
These ultraviolet rays,
or UV radiation, vary in wavelength from
400 nanometers to 10 nanometers and can be subdivided into
3 regions: UV-A, UV-B and UV-C.
Visible light from the Sun passes through the atmosphere
and reaches the Earth's surface. UV-A,
long wave ultraviolet, is the closest to visible light.
Most UV-A also reaches the surface. But shorter
wavelengths, called UV-B, are the harmful rays that cause sunburn.
Fortunately, about 95% of these harmful UV-B
rays are absorbed by ozone in the Earth's atmosphere.
UV-C rays are the shortest and most harmful
and are almost completely absorbed by our atmosphere.
The Ozone Monitoring Instrument aboard NASA's Aura satellite
detects ultraviolet radiation to help scientists study and monitor
the chemistry of our atmosphere, including UV absorbing ozone.
While atmospheric protection from harmful UV radiation
is good for humans... it complicates the study of naturally
produced UV rays in the Universe, by scientists here on the Earth's surface.
Young hot stars shine most of their light beyond
the visible light spectrum at ultraviolet wavelengths.
Scientists need telescopes in orbit above the Earth's UV absorbing atmosphere
to find and study these UV-bright regions of star formations
in distant galaxies. New young stars in the spiral
arms of galaxy M81 can be seen in this
Galaxy Evolution Explorer, GALEX, image from NASA.
Chemical substances, both atoms and molecules, interact
with UV light making this region particularly interesting to scientists.
An ultraviolet instrument aboard Cassini has
detected hydrogen, oxygen,
water ice, and methane in the Saturn system.
UV data have also revealed details
of Saturn's aurorae.
Scientists also use UV waves shining from distant stars to view
permanently shadowed regions of lunar craters. The Lyman-Alpha Mapping Project,
or LAMP, instrument aboard NASA's Lunar Reconnaissance Orbiter
can use this faint star-shine to look for possible
water ice on the moon. Ultraviolet rays may be harmful
to humans, but they are essential to studying the health of our planet's
protective atmosphere and give us valuable clues to the formation and
composition of distant celestial objects.