A fundamental role of a museum is to care for
its collection and preserve it for future generations.
European drawings from the 1300s
to the late 1800s
-or old master drawings-
are particularly vulnerable-
they are on paper
and hundreds of years old.
Conserving an old master drawing
is a balancing act.
All drawings have their own set of condition issues
that need to be assessed individually.
Here, a Getty Conservator carefully examines
a 500-year old German drawing.
She first removes the drawing from its mount
(or support).
She inspects the drawing lit from below.
This makes it easier to see the marks left
by the wires of the paper mold;
stains;
a watermark;
a tear-
with a darkened area that shows where it
had been previously repaired;
and at the corner,
the shadow of the piece of paper that had been used
to attach the drawing to a mount.
Next she examines the drawing under
ultraviolet light.
The brown spots are called "foxing."
These are marks left by mold.
Finally, she studies the drawing under a microscope.
Now, the conservator tests the solubility
of the ink to ensure it won't bleed during treatment.
She places the drawing on a vacuum table,
a device that
extracts the liquids used in the treatment,
out of the paper.
She uses this small brash to apply an ammoniated
water solution
to reduce the brown "foxing." This solution subtly
releases the color of the foxing,
which distracts from the appearance of the drawing.
She carefully alternates the application of
ammoniated water
with that of ethanol, in order to reduce
"tide lines"-
irregular lines or blemishes
left behind as the ammoniated water solution dries.
Wearing magnifying lenses,
she examines tears and prepares them for mending
and reinforcement.
She takes the piece of Japanese tissue
and carefully applies wheat starch paste to
mend the tear.
Japanese paper has very strong fibers,
is chemically neutral,
and can easily be identified and removed.
She allows the paste to set
by putting the drawing between blotters
and weighing it down with glass blocks and weights.
To complete the conservation treatment,
the entire drying is humidified
and then placed under weights with blotters
to remove the moisture and flatten it.
This process extends over a two-week period
and the blotters are repeatedly replaced
to facilitate drying.
The goal of conservation isn't to make a drawing
look "new" again.
Rather, it's to safely reduce the damage
that distracts from the design
and bring the sheet closer to the artist's original intent.
Evidence of age is still present,
but now recedes into the background
so that you may focus on the drawing.