A farmer grows 531 tomatoes
and is able to sell 176 of them
in three days.
Given that his supply of tomatoes decreases by 176,
how many tomatoes does he have remaining
at the end of three days?
So he starts with 531 tomatoes
let me give myself a little more space to work with
-- he starts with 531 tomatoes
and he is able to sell 176.
He is essentially going to subtract
the 176 that he is selling.
If we want to figure out
how many he is left with,
we are going to subtract 176.
That‘s how many he sells in three days.
They're asking us:
how many does he have left at the end of three days?
We just have to subtract those 176
from the amount he grew.
It turned into this straight up subtraction problem.
Lets see if we can do it.
If we go straight to the ones place
right over here
and actually let me do it in parallel
because i think that might be interesting over here.
I'm going to do it the way
you traditionally do it here on the left
and then I'm going to show you
what's happening here on the right.
So 531 is the same thing
as 500 + 30 + 1
and if you subtract 176
that is the same thing as subtracting 100
and subtracting another 70 and subtracting another 6
I wrote it this way
because the 5 in 531 is the same thing as 500
The 3 in 531 is in the tens place
so it's really representing 30
the 1 in 531 is in the ones place
so it represents one
and now
it'll be a little bit clearer
what we're doing
when we're borrowing or regouping
on this problem right over here
and so let's start off with the ones place
one is less than 6
It'd be great if we can regoup some of the value
from the rest of the places
so we can go straight to the tens place
the tens place we can borrow
or regroup ten from it
so if we take ten from here
this becomes 20
we're going to take that 10 and add it to the 1
so this will become 11
we just added 10
we moved over 10 from the tens place
to the ones place
if you look at it over here
you could say: Look! we're taking 10 from the 30
that becomes a 20
and then the 1 becomes an 11
the way when I was first in school
people'd say, "You borrow one
from the three"
and you kind of just stick that one right over here
but what you're really doing
is you're taking a 10 from a 30
and making it into a twenty
and you're getting a- you're adding the ten to the one
getting 11
but either way you'll end up with 11
in the ones place
and now you can subtract
11 - 6 is 5
now we go over to the tens place
in the tens place
we now have 2-7
which is really representing 20-70
well we - thats 70 is bigger than the 20
so we want to add some more
to the tens place
well we can go the hundreds place
to find some more value to regroup
so let's see if we can do that
we have 500 here
so what happens when we take a hundred from that
so we're just left with 400 from here
and we take that 100 and we put it in
the tens place
so instead of 20 we now have 120
if you look at it on this problem
since we are using the places here
we're going to take 100 from the 500
and have 400
and then we're going to take that 100
that we took and take it to the tens place
well 100 is 10 tens
so we're going to add 10 to this
so this is going to become a 12
once again, the way-
the kind of more mechanical rope way of thinking about it is that
-oh- you took one away from the four
and you stick that one in front on the two
but you're really taking a 100 from the 500, making it 400
and then adding that 100 to the 20 here
and making it 120
but your writing here is a 12
because it is 12 tens
you're at the tens place
so let me write it down
this is the ones place
this is tens place
and this is the hundreds place
so now that our numbers on top in the tens place
is bigger than the numbers on the bottom
we can subtract
so we get 120-70 that is 50
or 12 minus 7 is 5
5 is in the tens place
so it's really representing 50
let me circle it with the same colour
so you recognise that
this 5 is representing 50
then finally we're in the hundreds place
so 400 -100 is 300
4-1 is 3
but this 3 represents 300
this 5 represents 50
this 5 represents 5
so we're done
we get 355
the farmer is left with 355 tomatoes
at the end of 3 days
or 300+50+5 tomatoes.