The last really essential or salient piece
for understanding the mechanics of how bitcoins work
is what we call the transaction block chain.
If you recall, in the previous video
we had an example of a user Alice,
who wanted to, let's say, send some numer of bitcoins to another user Bob in the system.
What Alice had to do to initiate that transaction
was to construct a transaction record of sorts
that contained information about the transaction
and that was signed with Alice's signing key
and that actually contained Alice's public verification key and Bob's public verification key as well.
That transaction information was basically broadcast out
to the entire Bitcoin ecosystem,
to all the nodes on the bitcoin peer-to-peer network.
The various nodes in the Bitcoin ecosystem
are gonna receive information about this transaction.
They are also gonna be getting information about a lot of other transactions
that are taking place around the same time.
What these nodes are gonna start doing
is they are going to work on incorporating this transaction record
into a ledger of all the transactions that have ever taken place in the Bitcoin system.
What happens is that each node basically starts off by taking all of the previously unincorporated transactions
that they've ever received.
That will be all these transactions that have kind of happened within a given time window.
So these are all these bitcoin transactions kind of floating around.
And these nodes, these bitcoin miners as they are called,
are gonna receive information about all these different transactions
and they are gonna start working on incorporating those transactions.
Their first goal is to collate these transactions
into what's known as a transaction block.
If you recall our ledger analogy,
a single bitcoin transaction essentially corresponds to a proposed entry in a ledger.
In that capacity, a transaction block will basically correspond to a page in a ledger
where you have multiple transactions that are listed in that page of the ledger.
The bitcoin miners' goal is to take that page and get it added to the global ledger book,
the global comprehensive ledger book.
They engage in this sort of work
but it isn't all they basically do.
First, take all the transactions that have been broadcast,
let's say these four transactions have been broadcast out,
and they are gonna basically hash these transactions in pairs
in the tree-like structure
They'll take these two transactions and apply cryptographic hash function
and they'll get a corresponding digest,
they'll do the same to these two,
and they'll take these two digests and hash them to get a single digest value.
This digest effectively encodes all of the transactions that were previously unincorporated
and were received by these individual nodes.
This digest is going to be combined with the hash of the transaction block
that was previously accepted by that network.
You can imagine that the network will have a series of transaction blocks that were previously accepted.
In fact, every transaction block incorporates the previous transaction block.
So, this transaction block will incorporate the one that was used just before it.
And this transaction block will incorporate the one that was used just forward.
It's gonna go on literally to the beginning of bitcoin times.
This is really the beginning of time for the Bitcoin system.
This is the time equals zero for Bitcoin.
They are gonna take this last block
and combine it with this most recent block.
If you imagine that you have now not just individual block,
because each individual block incorporates the block before it,
we are not dealing anymore with an isolated or distinct block of transactions,
but rather with a chain of blocks
that starts literally at the beginning of the entire Bitcoin system.
When you do all this combination,
at the end of the day, you are gonna do some cryptographic hashing,
and you basically will end up with the sequence of numbers.
This sequence of numbers will be derived by incorporating all these blocks together.
You will get the sequence of numbers
and what we're gonna do is take this sequence of numbers
and convert that sequence of numbers
into a challenge in a proof of work protocol.
I did a suport video on proof of work protocols.
I would encourage you to watch that
if you want to get a better sense for how they work.
But the short of it is that, what the bitcoin mining node has to do with this point
is he'll take the challenge and will have to come up with a separate sequence of numbers,
which we typically term the proof, for the proof of work.
This proof of work has to have a very specific mathematical property.
What that property entails
is that if you take the challenge numbers
and you take these proof numbers
and you concatenate them together
and you make them the input to a cryptographic hash function
the resulting output has to have a large prefix of zeros.
It doesn't have to be all zeros but a large portion of the beginning, the prefix
has to be all zeros.
If you think about it for a moment,
giving the cryptographic hash functions,
giving that their output tends to look thoroughly random,
it is unlikely that in any given instance
you are going to see a proof that provides you with a large string of zeros at the beginning.
What the bitcoin miner will have to do
is on average he'll have to try many possible choices for these proof numbers
until he finally gets lucky
and he stumbles upon what has this off-beat or strange statistical property.
The actual difficulty of finding these proof numbers
is dependent on exactly how many leading zeros are required.
The more leading zeros you require in this proof,
the longer it takes to actually solve the problem.
The longer it takes to actually come up with the proof
that works with respect to a given challenge.
The fewer zeros you require,
the less time it will take.
The exact numer of zero bits required in the bitcoin protocol
actually does change over time.
It gets
The average time taken across the whole system
should be about ten minutes.
So you wanna take about ten minutes for at least one node
to come up with a valid proof.
But keep in mind that a lot of nodes are working on this proof concurrently.
Once this proof of work is found...
Let's say that proof of work is eventually found.
...the bitcoin miner will announce the result to the overall peer-to-peer network.
It's gonna take this proof and all the challenge and so on
and it's gonna announce it to all the other nodes.
They are not gonna say that: "Hey, there is this proof out there,
somebody found it! Let's drop the other stuff we were doing
and we are gonna now start to work and build on top of this new proof."
Remember, this new proof and this new challenge
incorporate all the previous transaction blocks.
What they are starting to do is
they are starting to work out a new, updated transaction block chain.
They are gonna incorporate any new unincorporated transactions
into that new transaction block chain.
There are a couple of points I wanna make.
First of all, as part of constructing these transaction block chains,
really as part of incorporating them into a transaction block chain,
bitcoin miners are atually allowed one little special treat.
They are allowed to include in that transaction block
a special node for themselves.
This node will basically be a little reward that they can get...
Let me use the grittish colour for that reward.
...they can take the first block,
the first transaction record,
and they can put in that transaction record,
they can assign the reward to themselves.
The amount of that reward will change over time.
I do wanna point out that what this transaction is typically called
this is called the coinbase transaction
or a generation transaction.
This is how new coins get included in the Bitcoin system.
Whenever a miner succeeds in coming up with a proof,
as part of that he will have been allowed to come up with his own transaction
to reward himself a special reward
for expanding the effort necessary to come up with this proof
and for doing all this work
associated with adding a new transaction block
to the existing transaction block chain for Bitcoin.
I think, that is reasonable after all these nodes are using a lot of computational power
to come up with these proofs.
It's using computational power that must mean
that somewhere along the line somebody is spending money on electricity and so on.
I also wanna point out to an addition to this coin base of a word.
The nodes who are doing the bitcoin mining,
the ones who succeed
also get to collect the transaction fees that were specified in the transaction record.
So if you recall, a person issuing a transaction with Bitcoin
can allocate or set aside a certain amount of money,
maybe it could be a bitcoin or a fraction of a bitcoin,
for the node who succeeds in coming up with the actual proof of work
and succeds in being able to add that transaction
to the overall bitcoin transaction block chain.
So, that node that does the work and succeeds
gets a reward of the transaction fee.
This could actually become quite a large,
because the node that will normally get the transaction fee for one transaction
will get the transaction fee for all the transactions
that appeared in the current block.
It's gonna get the aggregate over all these different transactions.
The second point I wanna make is that it might be possible
for two nodes to solve the proof of work independently of each other.
Somehow they may both end up trying to add to that existing chain in some way,
so you may get some weird chain forking happening.
If that happens, the peers in the Bitcoin network
will basically break a tie
by sticking with the longest chain.
By longest I don't mean the one that has to mean the most transactions in it.
I really mean the one that has the highest aggregate difficulty
associated with thet underlying proof of work protocol
in each of the transaction blocks.
I'll basically look at the total amount of effort
that was required to generate that chain,
but regarded that proof of work,
and whichever chain has the most work associated with it
is the chain that everybody will accept.
You may get some more discrepancies because of network and so on,
but the idea is that after a couple of rounds
when there are ties, they'll quickly resolve themselves
as long as most of the nodes are behaving honestly
and stick to their implementation of the protocol.
Since bitcoin miners are generating bitcoins
I think there is an interesting question that comes up here,
which is how is the Bitcoin money supply controlled
and how is it managed.
I am gonna talk about that concept in a subsequent video.