Newton´s 3rd Law tells us that to every action there is always a equal and opposite reaction.
When I´m shooting the ball I´m clearly applying force to it.
Where is the equal and opposite reaction?
That´s a excellent question LeBron.
So as you mention if someone shooting a ball there clearly applying force to that ball.
Let me see if I can draw that for you. Let´s say that this is the force
that your hand is applying on the ball.
And this force is what accelerate the ball upwards and towards the basket.
So forces applied by hand on the ball.
So where is this equal and opposite force that´s Newton´s 3rd Law tells us about?
That´s going to be the force that the ball is applying to your hand.
So I will draw the force right here, I can drawn anywhere on the hand but I draw it right here,
just you can see the exact opposite direction. It´s going to be the exact opposite direction.
And it has a equal magnitude.
So it´s a equal, but opposite force. Opposite is the direction, so just like that.
So that is the force apllied by the ball on your hand.
Then you might say that this doesn´t make a lot of sense.
The ball is clearly getting accelerated in that direction
but my hand isn´t accelerating backwards in kind of that opposite direction.
And the reason why your hand isn´t accelerating backwards, isn´t just flopping backwards,
because of this force of the ball applying on the hand.
The reason is because of your hand or your fingers had other forces acting on it.
They´re counting on act this force.
So for example, the reason why your fingers and your hand don´t flop backwards,
don´t accelerated backwards because of the force,
is because you have muscles in your forearm.
You have muscles in your forearm ruffled right there
that are pulling on your fingers and your hand and they´re underacting this force.
So ok fair enough, I can see why the fingers are not flopping back,
my hand doesn´t flopping back it is because of these muscles right over here.
Why is that my entire forearm being pushed or accelerated back by this force applied by the ball on my hand?
And the reason is its you have other muscles in the back of your upper arm, particularly your triceps,
that are keeping, that are tagging on your forearm
it´s contracting, they are contracting,
that more then offset any net forces on your forearm that would make it go that way,
it´s pulling on your forearm
and in the fact that what´s contracting on your forearm to go in actually that direction.
We can keep going, i mean the fun or the complicated thing about Newton´s 3rd Law is that every force has the equal opposite force.
Well everyone of these have equal and opposite force
and we can keep going on, as ok there is equal and opposite force of the triceps tagging on the forearm.
Well that´s the forearm tagging on the triceps.
Why is not the triceps move?
Well the triceps is attached to the other parts of your body.
We can keep going on and on and on.
But just to focus on a question.
Your hand is definitely applying force to the ball,
but the equal and opposite force is the force that the ball is applying to the hand.
But we actually even when we said that your hand isn´t flopping back because of being balance
you actually can sense this force.
And the reason why you do sense this force is
you actually do have the ball compressing against the palm of your hand.
And if you didn´t do that you wouldn´t even feel the ball.
So that gives you at least the sensory clue of Newton´s 3rd Law.
If Newton´s 3rd Law wasn´t true you wouldn´t even feel the ball,
you wouldn´t even have the ball compressed against the skin of your palm.