Let's say you were in a orange stand
And this right here is the demand curve for your orange stand or your marginal benefit curve
or really called the willingness to pay
that very hundredth pound, someone would be willing to pay 3 dollars per pound
but the 101st pounds would be a little less than that
So that's the willingness to pay, or the marginal benefit of that incremental pound
But let's say you decide to set the price at 2 dollars
and you are able to sell 300 oranges in that week
I want think about what is the total consumer surplus that your consumers got
The way to think about consumer surplus is how much benefit above and beyond what they paid
So for example, the person who bought--let's just think about the exact hundredth pound
The hundredth pound, they paid two dollars
but their benefit looks like $3.30
but they only paid two dollars, so their benefit on that 1 pound
or their consumer surplus is 3.30 minus [2]
So that person that bought 100th pound--
not all of the 100 lbs, just that 100th pound--
got a consumer surplus of 3.30-2 dollars
which is a $1.30 consumer surplus
So if you want to figure out the entire consumer surplus
you just have to do it for all of the pounds
So that was the 100th pound, you would find--
you could do this as the area of this little thing here
Let me zoom in to make sure that you understand what was going on
That thing that I just drew if I zoom in will look something like this
It was one pound wide
and this here was two dollars
Then we had our marginal benefit curve or demand curve sloping down like that
This point right over here was $3.30
So to figure out the consumer surplus for that pound, we say, for that pound
they were willing to pay $3.30, the benefit to them was $3.30, but they only had to pay $2
So the height of this here was $1.30
So consumer surplus is $1.30 per pound times 1 pound
and so that's what we got, the $1.30 consumer surplus
Now we can do that for every one of the pounds
So we can do that for the 101st pound. We would do it like that
Then the 102nd pound, you would do it like that
103rd pound, like that; you do it for the 99th pound, like that
You can imagine if you want to find the total consumer surplus what are we doing
We're essentially just finding the area between our demand curve
and this line where the price is 2
So we're just to sum up this area
And if you're familiar with calculus you might know
that you can actually make these things arbitrarily small
you can take smaller and smaller--you don't have to take a 1-pound wide rectangle
You can take a half-pound wide rectangle, a quarter-pound wide rectangle
then you'll just have more rectangles
It doesn't matter so much if you have a linear demand curve
but if you have a nonlinear demand curve
then it would matter. You want to get thinner and thinner and thinner rectangles
so you can get better and better approximations for the consumer surplus
But needless to say what you're really doing especially if you get unbelievably thin
rectangles and you have unbelievably high number of them
you're really just estimating the area under the demand curve and above the price equals $2
And so if you want to know the consumer surplus--
I really want you to understand why this was. Just think about it for each pound
just whoever bought that pound, how much more value they get, relative to what they paid
and we're just summing that up across all of the pounds
So to really figure the total consumer surplus
we just have to find the area, this blue area. That's just finding the area of a triangle
So this here, you have a base of 300. This length here is 300 lbs
And our height over here--we can just use this as the area of a triangle
because this is a simple linear demand curve
You would actually have to use a little bit of calculus if this was a nonlinear curve
but the height here is 2
So our area, the area between the demand curve and our price equals two is equal to
1/2 times base times height which is 1/2 times 300 lbs times two dollars / lb
The pounds cancel out; 1/2 times 2 is 1, times 300 is 300
So we get 300 dollars
So the total consumer surplus in this case is $300
This really is the area between the demand curve and this price=2 line right over there