In the last video I hinted that things were about to get wacky,
and they are! So if we start where we left off in the last video,
we started right over here, looking at the distance
to the nearest star and, just a reminder
in this drawing right here this depiction right here this circle right here
this solar system circle, its not the size of the sun, its not the size
of the orbits of the Earth or Pluto or the Kuiper belt this is close
to the size of the Oort cloud. The actual orbit of earth is
about one, well the diameter of the orbit of earth is about one
fifty thousandth of this so you wouldn't even see it on this. it wouldn't even make
up a pixel on this screen right here, much less the actual size
of the sun or something much smaller.
And just remember that orbit of the earth that was at a huge distance. It takes
8 mins for light to get from the sun to the earth. It's a super long distance.
If you shot a bullet at the sun from earth, it would take you 17 years to get to the sun.
So this huge distance wouldnt even show up on this picture.
Now what we saw in the last video is that if you travel at unimaginably fast speeds,
if you travel at 60,000 km/h, and I picked that speed 'cause that's how fast
Voyager 1 actually is travelling
that's one of the fastest, I think one of the fastest objects we have
out there in space, right here, and is actually kind of leaving the solar system
as we speak. But even if you were able to get that fast,
it would still take 80,000 years, 75 or 80,000 years to travel the
4.2 light years to the Alpha Centauri cluster of stars. To the nearest star,
it would take 80,000 years, 80,000 years.
And that scale of time is already an amount of time I have trouble comprehending
You can imagine all of modern civilization has occured definitely in the last 10,000 yrs
but most of recorded history is in the last 4 or 5000 years.
So this is 80,000 years to travel to the nearest star.
So its a huge distance.
Another way to think about it, is that if the sun
were the size of a basketball and you put that basketball in London,
if you wanted to do it in scale, the next closest star which is actually a smaller
basketball right over here, Proxima Centauri, that smaller basketball you'd have to put
in Kiev, Ukraine. in order to have a similiar scale.
So these are basketballs, sitting in these cities and you would have
to travel about 1200 miles
to place the next basketball. and these basketballs are representing these super huge things
that we saw in the first video, the Sun. If you actually made the earth
relative to these basketballs, these would be little grains of sand
so if there are any little small planets over here they would have to be grains
of sand in Kiev, Ukraine versus the grain of sand in London.
So this is a massive, massive distance. Already, at least in my mind, unimaginable. And when it gets
really whacky is when you start realising that this, even this, is a super
super small distance relative to the galactic scale.
So this whole depiction of kind of our neighborhood of stars this thing over here
is about, give or take, and we're doing rough estimates right here
its about 30 light years. I'll just do LY for short. So thats abt 30 LY
Now and once again you cannot actually, you can take pictures of our galaxy
from our point of view but you actually can't take a picture of the whole galaxy from above it.
So these are going to be artist depictions, but if this is 30 LY
This drawing right here of kind of our local neighborhood of the galxy
this right here is roughly, these are all approximations, this is about
let me do this in a darker color, this about 1 thousand LY
and this is the 1000 LY of our suns neighborhood if you can even call it a neighborhood
even this isn't really a neighborhoood if it takes you 80,000 yrs to get to your nearest neighbor
but this whole drawing over here it would take forever to get anywhere over here
it would be 1/30th of this so it would be about that big
this whole drawing and what's really going to blow your mind is
this would be roughly a little bit more than a pixel on this drawing right here
that spans a 1000 LY but then when you start to really put it into
perspective so new lets zoom out a little bit. So this drawing right here
this 1000 LY is now this 1000 LY over here. so this is our local vicinity of the sun
and once again the word local is used in a very liberal way
at this point
so this right here is a 1000 ly
if your sitting here and your looking at an object that is sitting (let me do this in a darker color)
if we're sitting here on earth and we're looking at an object sitting here
that's 500 LY away we're looking at it as it was 500 years ago
becasue the light that is reaching our eyeballs right now or our telescopes
right now left this guy over here 500 yrs ago. in fact he's not even going to be there anymore
he'll probably have moved around a little bit. So just even on this scale, we're alredy
talking abt these unimaginably huge distances and then when we zoom out
this is kind of like our local part of the galaxy over here. This piece right here
this is called the Orion Spur and people are still trying to work out
exactly what the actual details of the actual shape of the milky way galaxy is
the galaxy that we're in but we're pretty sure we have these spiral arms
and we have these spurs off of them, but its actually very hard to come up with the actual shape
especally because you can't see a lot of the galaxy because it's kinda on the other side,
on the other side of the centre
but really just to get a sense, I mean at least it blows my mind if you really
think about what it saying these unbeleivable distances show up as a lil dot here
this whole drawing shows up as a dot here. now when we zoom out over here
that dot would no longer even show up
it wouldn't even register a pixel on this drawing right over here
and then this drawing this whole thing right over here
this whole pic is this grid is this grid right over here it is this right over here
so hopefully that gives you a sense of how small even our local neighborhood
is relative to THE galaxy as a whole
the galaxy as a whole just to give you a sense has 200,
200-400 billion stars
or maybe i should say solar systems just to give you a sense that you know
when we saw the solar system its not just the sun
its all this neat dynamic stuff in there, planets and asteroids
and solar winds and so there's 200 to 400 billion stars
and for the most part 200 to 400 billion solar systems so its and
unimaginably complex or huge place
and just to make it clear you know even when we zoom into this pic right here
and i think its obvious based on this that these lil white pockets right here
these aren't this isn't one star this isn't two stars these are thousands of stars
here so when you go over here
each little blotch of white that you see that's not a star that's not a thousand stars
we're starting to talk in the millions of stars when you look at certain blotches here and there
i mean it maybe one star that closer to you or it might be a million
stars that are far apart and that are just relatively close
together and eveything has to be used in kind of
loose terms here. And we'll talk more about other galaxies
but even this isn't the upper bound of galaxies
people believe the Andromeda Galaxy has a trillion stars in it
a trillion sources and we're talking about these huge
huge immense distances and so just to give you a sense
of where we fit in the picture this is a rough location of our sun
and remember that lil dot i drew just now
is including millions of stars, millions of solar systems
already unimaginable distances but if you really wanna get the sense
relative to the whole galaxy, this is an artist's depiction
once again we could never obviously get this perspective on the galaxy
it would take forever to travel this far
so that you could see the galaxy from above but this is our best guess
looking at things from our vantage point we actually could never even see
we actually can't even see this whole area over here
'cause it's on the other side of the centre of the galaxy which is super super
dense and super bright and so its very hard to see things on the other side
we think or actually there's a super massive black hole at the centre of the galaxy
and we think that they're at the centre of all or most galaxies
but you know the whole pint of this video or actually this whole series of videos
is just to put you in awe a lil bit of just how huge this is
'cause when you think about the scales it's just, i dunno no, words can reallly describe it
but just to give you sense we're about 25000LY from the centre of
the galaxy so even when we look at things at the centre of the galaxy that's how they
were 25000 yrs ago
it took 25000 yrs for that light to get to us, I mean when that light left the centre
of the galaxy I won't even guess to think what
humanity was like at that point in time
so its these huge distances and the whole galaxy of here
and like solar systems its hard to say the edge of the galaxy
'cause there's always gonna be a few more stars and other things orbiting
around the galaxy as you go further and further out but the main
density the main disc is about 100,000LY
is the diameter roughly of the main part of the galaxy and it's about a 1000 LY thick
so you kind of imagine it as a disc its fairly flat
but its a 1000 LY thick! It's a 1000 LY thick you would have to do this distance
250 times just to go from the top part of the galaxy to the bottom part
much less going across the galxy
so it might sem relatively flat but it's still immensely
immensely thick. and just as another way to visualise it
if this thing right over here that includes the Oort cloud
roughly a LY in diameter it is a grain of sand
a mm in diameter grain of sand
then the universe as a whole is gonna be the diameter of a football field
and those are two tractable things, i can imagine a grain of sand
a mm wide grain of sand in a football field. but remember that's a grain sand
that grain of sand is still 50 or 60, 000 times the diameter of the Earth's orbit
and it would still take a bullet or something travelling as fast as a jet plane
15 hrs to just go half of that or sorry 15 yrs or 17 yrs I forgot
the exact number but you knpw 15, 16 , 17 yrs to even cover half of that distance
30 yrs to cover an entire diamtere, so 30 yrs to cover the entire diameter
of earths orbit tahts one 60,000th of our lil grain of sand in the football field
and just to kind of really i dunno have an appreciation for how amaz- i dunno how mind blowing this
really is , this is a picture of the milky way galaxy, our galaxy
from our vantage point as you can see we're in the galaxy so we're
seeing and this is looking towards the centre and
even this picture you start to appreciate the complexity of what a 100
billion stars are but what i really wanna point out is that even in this pic
when yu're looking at some of these things that are like stars
those arent stars! those are thousands of stars or millions of stars
maybe it could be one star closer up but when we're startin
to approach the centre of the galaxy these are thousands
and thousands and millions of stars or solar systems
that we're actually looking at so its really, it starts to
boggle the mind to imagine what might actually be going on over there.