Simplify the expression using rational exponents.
So we have the cube root of all of this stuff over here which would be the same thing, or which is the same thing by definition as
all of this stuff 64 a to the 6th, b to the 3rd, c to the 9th, raised to the 1/3rd power. These are equivalent, by definition.
And if we take the product of a bunch of things and raise it to an exponent, thats the same thing as raising each of these things
that we take the product of to the exponent first and then multiplying. So this is going to be equal to 64 to the 1/3rd power times
a to the 6th to the 1/3rd power times b to the 3rd to the 1/3rd power times c to the 9th to the 1/3rd power. And we've seen this
in several examples already. Well, first lets try to simplify this. 64 to the 1/3rd - you might recognize that already - but we can factor
64 as , well, I won't do pure prime factorization, cause you'll see its just 4 to the 3rd power. Actually you could verify that for yourself,
or I encourage you, if thats not obvious to see that this is 4 to the 3rd power - 64, multiply it out for yourself, or if you're
like how did you know that, do the prime factorization. What you're going to do is, well, let me just show you. If you do the prime
factorization, you have 2 times 32, 32 is 2 times 16, 16 is 2 times 8, 8 is 2 times 4, 4 is 2 times 2, so you can have 2 multiplied
by itself 3 times, or you could have a ..oh! a 2 multiplied by itself 3 times, and that happens twice, or you could have 4 times
4 times 4. So if you,you,it it didn't immediately jump into your head that 64 is 4 to the 3rd power, you can literally do a brute force prime
factorization here and see that you have 6. You can factor this into 2 to the 6th power or, the same thing as 4 to the 3rd power. So I'll
, I'll let you think about that a little bit. But this right here simplifies - 64 is 4 to the 3rd power, and you raise that to the
1/3rd power, that is the same thing as - actually let me write it that way, then I can make it more interesting - so this right here,
this is 4 to the 3rd power, so if I have 4 to the 3rd power, and that raised to the 1/3rd power, so if I want to rewrite that term to
right over here, thats going to be 4 to the 3 thirds power - I'm literally multiplying the 3 times 1/3rd. 4 to the 3rd, and then
that to the 1/3rd. Then over here, I have a to the 6th, and then that to the 1/3rd power. That is going to be a to the 6 times 1/3rd
power, or a to the 6 thirds power. Then I have b to the 3rd, and then that raised to the 1/3rd, so thats going to be, we literally
can multiply exponents here, so we have b to the 3 over 3 power, and then finally, we have c to the ninth, and then that raised, and then that raised to
the 1/3rd power. So that is c to the 9 over 3 power. And if you simplify it, this first term here - 4 to the 3 thirds, thats just
4 to the 1st power, so thats just 4. We have a to the 6 thirds - 6 thirds is just 2 - so that just becomes a squared. b to the 3
thirds power - that's just b to the first , or b, and then finally c to the 9 thirds - that's just c to the third power. So let me
write c to the 3rd here. And we are done.