So we have these 2 parallel lines
Line segment AB and line segment CD they're parallel
I should say they're parallel line segments
And then we have these transversals that go across them,
so you have this transversal BC right over here
and we have transversal AD
And what this diagram tells us is that the distance
between A and E this little hash mark says that this line segment
is the same distance as distance between between E and D
And another way to think about it is that
point E is the midpoint of line segment AD
and what I want to think about in this video is:
Is point E also the midpoint of line segment BC?
So, we have this is the question right over here
So, is E the midpoint of line segment BC
And you can imagine based on a lot of videos
we've been seeing lately maybe
it has something to do with congruent triangles
So, let's see if we can set up some congruency relationship
between the two obvious triangles in this diagram
We have this triangle up here on the left
and we have this diagram down here
This one kinda looks like it's pointing up,
this one on this looks like its pointing down
So, there's a bunch of things we know about vertical angles
and angles of transversals
the most obvious one is that we have this vertical we have
we know that angle AEB is going to be congruent
or it's measure is going to be equal to the measure of angle CED
So we know, we know that angle AEB is going to be congruent
AEB is going to be congruent to angle DEC
which really just means they have the exact same measure
and we know that because they are vertical angles
they are vertical angles
Now we also know that AB and CD are parallel
So this line right over here this is transversal
so we know for example
There's actually several ways that we can do this problem
but we know that this is transversal
And there's a couple of ways to think about it right over here
so let me just continue the transversal
so we get to see all the different angles
You could say that this angle right here angle AB, angle ABE
So this is its measure right over here you could say
that this is alternate interior angle to angle ECD
to this angle right over there
And if you didn't just if that didn't if jump out of you
You would say that the corresponding angle
to this one right over here
is this angle right up here
if you were to continue this line off a little bit
this is the corresponding angle and this one is the vertical
but either way angle AEB let me write this down
angle sorry angle ABE let me be clear careful angle ABE
is going to be congruent to angle so that's ABE
is congruent to angle DCE
And we could say because its alternate interior angles,
alternate just write a code here so alt interior angles
And then we have an interesting relationship we have
an angle congruent to angle another angle congruent to an angle
and then the next side is congruent to the next side over here
so pink green side, so pink green side
So, we can employ AAS angle angle side
And this is in the right order
So now we know that triangle
we have to make sure that we get the letters right here
that we have the right corresponding vertices
We can say that triangle AEB triangle AE
Actually let me start with the angle just to make it interesting
Angle BEA so starting with the magenta angle going
to the green angle going to the one that we have unlabelled
So, angle BEA we can say is congruent to angle,
we start with the magenta at vertices C go the center E
and then go to the unlabelled one, D
And we know this because of angle-angle-side
and they correspond to each other magenta, green side,
magenta, green, side they're all congruent
So this is from AAS and then if we know that they're congruent
that means corresponding sides are congruent
So then, so then we know that this side
so we know these two triangle congruent
so that means their corresponding sides are congruent
so then we know that length of BE that we know that BE
The length of that segment BE is going to be equal
and that's the segment between the magenta and the green angles
The corresponding side is side CE between the magenta
and the green angles is equal to CE
And this just comes out of the previous statement if we number them
That's one, that's two, and that's three and so that is comes out
of the statement 3 and
so we have proven that E is the midpoint of BC
It comes straight out of the fact that BE is equal to CE
so I can mark this off with hash
This line segment right over here
is congruent to this line segment right over here
Because we know that those two triangles are congruent
And I've inadvertently write here a total of two column proof
This over here on the left hand side is my statement
And on then on the right hand side I gave my reason and were done