In this video we're going to talk about Eratosthenes
who was a Greek scholar that lived about
two thousand years ago.
Eratosthenes found a way, using none of the modern tools that we have,
to measure the circumference of the Earth
and in this video we're going to see how he
did this.
So the heart of Eratosthenes' measurement
is a simple geometry problem.
So, consider circle shown here,
which has points A and B,
and let's say that we know the
distance that A and B
make on the circumference of the circle.
So we know the measure of arc AB.
Now, the question is,
with this knowledge can we determine the circumference of our circle?
and i'm sure you all
are thinking that the answer is obviously no, because A and B are just two random
points on the circle, so
just knowing they're distance doesn't help us very much.
What we need is some information that makes A and B not just random points on a
circle anymore.
We need to know the angle
that A and B make with the center of the
circle.
Once we know this, we know
how far around A and B go around the circle
because we know that every circle has
in it 360 degrees
in one full revolution.
So, by knowing theta we know the fraction of the circle
that the arc AB takes up and we can simply extrapolate to find the
circumference.
So let's make this point a little clearer with some concrete examples.
Let's look at the circle
on the right now
and again we have points A
and B.
And here you can clearly see
that the angle that A and B
make with the center of the circle is 90 degrees.
And since we know that 90 goes into 360 four times
arc AB is 1/4 around the circle,
meaning that the piece shown here,
the shaded piece,
will fit in the circle four times.
So in this case the circumference of the circle is four times the length of
arc AB.
now let's just try that one home further
with this other circle again we have
point sandy
uh... and hear the angolan between
points in the let's say we measured
turns out to be
thirty six degrees
so since thirty-six goes into three
hundred sixty ten times
we know that ten of these pieces will
fit in the circle
and in this case the circumference is
and number of pieces
times the length of one piece
now in general
these are coming to the circle is given
by the number of pieces we have
times the length of one piece
and just friends explicitly the number
of pieces is three hundred and sixty
degrees
divided by data
the angle of the day and be in a percent
of the circle
and length of one piece is simply abt
so now if we just know that these two
things dark a b
and the angle in the middle of the
senate the circle
we can determine the circumference and
this is really the heart to be a tough
news as method
so now it's a place
now we have another circle but this time
with explicitly identify the circle as
the earth
uh... and pointed becomes a city
alexandria
mississippian uh... you get
and um... this is where you're totally
slipped
point b now becomes the city of saying
so in your classes a day it was known
did the distance between alexandria and
saying
was about five hundred mice
because back then utorrent miles but we
know the conversion factor so we don't
have to worry about the old system of
units
the distance between alexander and
saying this time in months
and now
looking back at our previous problem we
see that all we have to do to figure out
the circumference of the earth given
this information
is to figure out the angles that
alexandria and saying make with the
center of the earth
and the relieved
uh... they really brilliant thing about
their cousins as method is that he found
a nice way to measure this angle
so how did he do this
it was known that insane there was a
well along the well such that at noon on
the summer solstice
you could see the sun's rays light up
from the bottom of the world
and if you can buy this what this means
is that since as well as such uh... deep
thing
disney into the sunset is a must have
been coming into the earth
parallel to the world
to redraw these arrays uh...
miss his son is very far away from the
earth
and because the sun is so far away
we can't read there is coming in from
the sun at different points
so here we ground the ray that comes in
at alexandria and there are a at saint
now it's an interesting property of
reliance
if we have these dibrle and shown here
that you raised
and we have
the radio station
the single to be called beta two
is equal to the end of the we're trying
to find beta one
this is something is the fact that you
might've been exposed to a new job that
requires as it's called uh... property
of corresponding angles
because it's pretty easy to prove
yourself
so since we know this
now we can transform the heart problem
of measuring data one
to the relatively easier problem of
measuring putative
so i realize that they did too
three straight forward towards him and
on this region
we have hit the surface of the earth
as one of the important months and then
the radius
get translated into
vertical stick
and we also have the sun with one of
interest so this great cast a shadow on
the ground
and by knowing the length of the shadow
and the height of artistic
we can construct this triangle and
simply measure the angle
there to all we had to do is look at the
shadow created optimistically
and this is exactly what it does in his
dad
and he measured that the angle data to
was equal to
seven point two degrees
so now we have this information the
angle
which is called better now
is equal to seven twenty degrees
and the measure of the art gave the or
alexander saying
is the five hundred must
still with us information now all we
have to do speed this into the formula
that we got earlier pushes recall it c
equals
three hundred fifty degrees divided
right there
times abt
so this is very simple to do
with morgan seven point two degrees but
they don't put in five hundred miles
arabian
and in the end we find it's easy for the
fifty eight times five hundred miles
or twenty five thousand miles
so this is our estimate or beer dozens
estimate for the circumference of the
earth call that c
nearsightedness
and so good to see how simple it was for
us to get this
noticed that
according to our modern measurements the
average circumference of the earth
because not a perfect sphere is around
twenty four thousand nine hundred miles
so we're only about two hundred miles
off with this seemingly primitive method
which is about to have a percent
so this is a very impressive thing for
someone who lived so long ago without
the access to these tools that we now
use