All right
I re-read the question
and now I realize the error in my logic
I misread the question
I had misread it and I said, oh, there are 60 siblings
No, there are 60 sibling pairs
So that means in each class there-- so 60 siblings pairs
that means there are 120 siblings
But that tells us that in each class there aren't 30
there are 60 members of a sibling group, right?
So let's go back through our logic again
Let's say I pick someone from the junior class first
What is the probability that I even pick someone
from a sibling pair?
That's going to be 60/1,000,which is the same thing as 6/100
which is the same thing as 3/50, right?
Fair enough.
So there's a 3 in 50 chance that
I pick someone who's a member of a sibling pair
Now, in order for me to have a complete sibling pair
when I go to the senior class and pick someone
I have to pick this junior sibling
and that junior only has 1 sibling in the senior class
So there's only a 1 in 800 chance that I pick their sibling
It doesn't matter that--
the other 59 siblings in that are useless
because they're not this guy's sibling
So I have a 1 in 800 chance of doing that
You multiply them, you get 3/40,000
And that's choice A
If you don't see your choice
make sure to read the question again
Almost out of space so let me clear all of this
Let me clear all of that
And we're on problem 218
Which of the following cannot be the median of the three
positive integers x, y, and z?
So the median, the middle number
They say A is x
Well, no, that's not true
What if this was the order? x y, z
then x would be the median
So it's not A
B, z
No reason why z can't be the median
The order can be y, z, x
It's not B
C, x plus z
Well, let's see, could x plus z be the median?
x plus z, could that be the median?
Let me think about it
If we have x, z, and y, I mean
by definition one of these numbers has to be the median
We have three numbers
one of them has to be the middle number
Under what circumstances-- because x plus--
I mean, if x plus z is the median
that implies that neither x nor z is the median, right?
Do they tell us that those are-- right
they're positive integers
None of these are zero
So in order for x plus z to be the median
that tells us that neither x nor z is the median, right?
And if neither x nor z is the median
then y has to be the median
And then that tells us that x plus z has to be equal to y
But if y is the median, the order is this: x, y, z
And there's no way that I can add x and z and get a smaller
number than z
because all of these numbers are positive, right?
Yeah, they said three positive integers
So I go with choice C
That cannot happen
The median cannot be x plus z
Problem 219
What is the 25th digit to the right of the decimal point
in the decimal form of 6/11?
And whenever they ask you for something ridiculous
there must be some type of pattern we can exploit to
figure out what the 25th digit is
Let's just start dividing
11 goes into 6
so we're going to have to have some decimals there
11 goes into 60 five times
5 times 11 is 55, and remainder 5
And you're going to 50, you get a 4
4 times-- I already see the pattern-- 44
Oh no, never mind
Wait, let me make sure that's right
55, you get 50 remainder, 11 goes into 50 four times
You get 40
So then you get 60
11 goes into 60 five times
and you repeat so on and so forth
I just want to make sure
Let's see, the first digit to the right is 25
The second digit to the right is 4
The third digit to the right is 5
And so, you know, we could keep going
The fourth digit to the right is 4
So every odd digit to the right of this is what?
It's 5
So they want to know the 25th digit to the right
and that's an odd number, 25
So it has to be 5 as well
So that's choice C
Next question
Oh, I thought I had to erase that
OK, question 220
John and Mary were each paid x dollars in advance
to do a certain job together
Fair enough
John worked on the job for 10 hours,so John worked 10 hours
and Mary worked 2 hours less than John
So Mary worked 8 hours, right?
John worked on the job for 10 hours
and Mary worked for 2 hours less than John
so she worked 8 hours
If Mary gave y dollars of her payment
so that they would have received the same hourly wage
what was the dollar
amount in terms of y that John was paid in advance?
OK, John and Mary were each paid x dollars in advance to
do a certain job together
OK, so how much money did they-- so John got x dollars
and Mary got x dollars
They both got x dollars, right?
So if you think about it
let's ignore who did what, right?
We had how many total hours of labor?
We had 18 hours of labor
and they were paid how many dollars?
They were paid 2x dollars for 18 hours of labor
So the average wage should be--
you could kind of do it the fair--
you know, per hourly 0wage should be--
let's see, we could divide by 9,you get a 1 and you get a 9
You get x/9 dollars per hour
That's the fair way
So let me re-read the question
If Mary gave John y dollars of her payment
so that they would have had the same hourly wage
what was the dollar amount
in terms of y that John was paid in advance?
Actually, let's think of it this way
So Mary pays John-- let me ignore this
I just thought of a better way of doing it
So they were each paid x hours in advance to do a certain job
John worked on the job for 10 hours
and Mary worked 2 hours less than John
If Mary paid John y dollars of her payment
so that they would have received the same hourly wage--
so after Mary pays John y
what-- so that means John got a total of y dollars
and Mary has paid y dollars
So now John has x plus y, and Mary has x minus y dollars
And so, if Mary paid of her payment
so that they would receive the same hourly wage
what was the dollar amount
in terms of y that John was paid in advance?
So let me think about this a little bit
So they got the same-- they received the same hourly wage
So Mary should have 8/10 the money of John, right?
So x minus y should be equal to 0.8 times x plus y
Am I thinking about that right
or is there an easier way to think about it?
Well, let's think about it this way
John worked 2 hours more than Mary, right?
So Mary, essentially, if she pays him for 1 hour-- no
yeah, this is the right thing. x minus y is equal to 0.8
times x plus y, but I'm going to still end up with an x here
So you get x minus y is equal to 0.8x plus 0.8y, right?
And all the logic here I just said is--
well, Mary's total money
if we're going to be fair
should be 0.8 of John's total money
because she worked 0.8 as much hours
And so, let's see
Oh, actually,they want to know what John was paid in advance
so that's x
So actually, OK, we're fine
So they just want to know what x is in terms of y
So we're cool
So let's subtract 0.8x from both sides
So you get 0.2x minus y is equal to 0.8y
And then add y to both sides
You get 0.2x is equal to 1.8y
And then multiply both sides by 5
you get x is equal to-- what is that?
5 times 18 is 50 plus 40
Add a decimal point is 90 is equal to 9y
And that is choice E
I got a little confused with the wording of it
when they say what was the dollar amount in terms of y
that John was paid in advance?
They should've said what was x?
And that would've been a little bit easier
Anyway, I'm all out of time
Sorry for bumbling through that problem
See you in the next video