I have these 3 star patches –
I guess you could call them –
right over here.
And so I could say,
"If I had 1 group of 3 star patches,
how many star patches do I have?"
So I literally have 1 group of 3 star patches.
Well that means that I have 3 star patches.
1, 2, 3.
This is my 1 group of 3.
Now let's make it a little bit more interesting.
Let's say that I had 2 groups.
Let's say that I had 2 groups of 3.
So that's 1 group.
And then here's a second group.
Here's 2 groups of 3.
So how many total star patches do I have now?
Well I have 2 groups of 3.
2 groups of 3.
Or another way of thinking about it is this is 3 + 3.
This is equal to 3 + 3, which is equal to 6.
So we see 1 × 3. 1 group of 3 is 3.
2 groups of 3, (which is literally 2 3's), is 6.
Let's make it even more interesting.
Let's have 3 groups of 3.
Now what is this going to be equal to?
Well it's 3 groups of 3.
So I could write this as 3 groups. 3 × 3.
And how many of these star patches do I now have?
Well this is going to be 3 + 3 + 3.
It's going to be 3 + 3 + 3.
Notice I have 3 3's.
I have 2 3's.
I have 1 3.
So this 3 + 3 + 3 is equal to 9.
And you could count them.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.
Or you could just count by 3's.
3, 6, 9.
And I think you see where this is going.
Let's keep incrementing it.
Let's get 4 groups of 3.
So let's think about what 4 × 3 is.
1, 2, 3, and 4.
This right over here is 4 groups of 3.
We could write this down as 4 × 3,
which is the same thing as 3 + 3 + 3 + 3.
Notice I have 4 3's.
1 3, 2 3's, 3 3's, 4 3's.
1 3, 2 3's, 3 3's. 4 3's.
So we get 3, 6, 9, 12.
12.
So what I encourage you to do now ,
now that the video is almost over ,
is to keep going.
I want you to figure out what 5 × 3 is.
5 × 3.
And 6 × 3.
And 7 × 3.
And 8 × 3.
And 9 × 3.
And 10 × 3.
And I'll give you a little hint.
You don't always have to draw the star patches.
But it's nice to visualize it.
We saw that 4 × 3 is literally 4 3's.
Well 5 × 3 is going to be 5 3's.
So 2 3 4 5.
5.
– which is equal to 3, 6, 9, 12, 15.
15.
So I encourage you to think about
what all of these are after this video is done.