I have this article right here from WebMD
And the point of this isn't to poke holes at WebMD.
I think they have some great articles, and they have some great information on their site.
But what I want to do here is to think about
what a lot of articles you read, or a lot of research you might read, are implying
and to think about whether they really imply what they claim to be implying.
So this is an excerpt of an article, and the title of the article says:
"Eating breakfast may beat teen obesity."
So they're already trying to create this cause and effect relationship.
The title itself says: 'If you eat breakfast, then you are less likely,
or you won't be obese, you are not going to be obese.'
So the title right there sets up this, that eating breakfast may beat teen obesity,
and then they tell us about the study.
In the study, published in 'Pediatrics', researchers analyzed the dietary and weight patterns
of a group of 2,216 adolescents over a five-year period
from public schools in Minneapolis, St. Paul, Minesota.
and I won't talk too much about -this looks like a good sample size,
it was over a large period of time, I'll just give the researchers the benefit of the doubt,
assume that it was a broad audience, and that they were able to control for a lot of variables,
but then they go on to say that the researcher's right,
that teens who eat breakfast regularly had a lower percentage of total calories from saturated fat
and ate more fiber and carbohydrates.
- than those who skipped breakfast-
and to some degree this first sentence is obvious
breakfast tends to be things like cereals, grains, um, you know,
you eat syrup, you eat waffles,
that all tends to fall in the category of carbohydrates and sugars,
and frankly, that's not even necessarily a good thing,
not obvious to me whether bacon is more or less healthy than downing a bunch of syrup
or fruit loops, or whatever else, but we'll let that be right here
'In addition, regular breakfast eaters seemed more physically active than their breakfast skippers'
So over here they're once again trying to create this other cause and effect relationship
'Regular breakfast eaters seemed more physically active than their breakfast skippers'
So the implication here is that breakfast makes you more active
And then this last sentence over here, they say:
'Over time, researchers found teens who regularly ate breakfast tended to gain less weight,
and had a lower body mass index (BMI) than breakfast skippers'
So they're telling us that breakfast skipping -this is the implication-
breakfast skipping is more likely, or can be a cause, of making you overweight,
or maybe even making you obese.
So the entire narrative here, from the title all the way to every paragraph,
is: 'look, breakfast prevents obesity,'
'breakfast makes you active',
'breakfast skipping will make you obese'
so you say, 'boy, I HAVE to eat breakfast'
- you should always think about the motivations and the industries around things like breakfast -
But the more interesting question is:
Does this research really tell us that eating breakfast can prevent obesity?
Does it tell us that eating breakfast will cause some to become more active?
Does it really tell us that breakfast skipping can make you overweight, or make you obese?
Or, what's more likely, are they just showing that these two things tend to go together?
And this is a really important difference
And let me kind of state, slightly technical words here
and they sounds fancy, but they really aren't that fancy,
Are they pointing out 'causality', which is what it SEEMS like they're implying?
'Eating breakfast CAUSES you to not be obese'
'Breakfast CAUSES you to be active'
'Breakfast skipping CAUSES you to be obese'
So it looks like they're kind of implying causality,
they're implying cause and effect,
but really what the study looked at is 'correlation'
So, the whole point of this is to understand the difference between causality and correlation
'cause they're saying very different things.
'... causality versus correlation...'
And, as I said, causality says: 'A causes B'
while correlation just says: 'A and B tend to be observed at the same time'
'Whenever I see B happening, it looks like A is happening at the same time,'
'whenever A is happening, it looks like it also tends to happen with B.'
And the reason that it's super important to distinguish the distinction between these
is you can come to very, very, very different conclusions.
So the one thing that this research does do, assuming that it was performed well,
is it does show correlation.
so this study does show correlation.
it does show, if we believe all of their data, that breakfast skipping correlates with obesity,
and obesity correlates with breakfast skipping
we're seeing it at the same time
activity correlates with breakfast, and breakfast correlates with activity
and all of these correlate
What they don't say, and there's not data here that lets me know one way or another
'What is causing what?'
or maybe you have some underlying cause that is causing both.
So, for example, they're saying breakfast causes activity,
or they're implying breakfast causes activity, they're not saying it explicitely,
but maybe activity causes breakfast,
maybe, people who are more active are more likely to be hungry in the morning
'...maybe activity causes breakfast ...'
And then you start having a different takeaway.
Maybe you say, 'wait, maybe if you're active and you skip breakfast'
- and I'm not telling you that you should-
'maybe you'll lose even more weight, maybe it's even a healthier thing to do'
we're not sure, so, they're trying to say
'look, if you have breakfast, it's gonna make you active, which is a very positive outcome'
but maybe you can have the positive outcome without breakfast
who knows?
Likewise, they say breakfast-skipping, or they're implying,
that breakfast-skipping can cause obesity,
but maybe it's the other way around
maybe people who have high body fat, maybe for whatever reason
they're less likely to get hungry in the morning
so maybe it goes this way, maybe there's a causality there
or what's even more likely, maybe there's some underlying cause which causes both of these things
to happen
and you can think of a bunch of different examples of that
one could be the physical activity
so physical activity - and these are all theories, I have no proof for them -
but I just wanna give you different ways of thinking about the same data
and maybe not just coming to the same conclusion that this article
-it seems like- is trying to lead us to conclude that we should eat breakfast
if we don't want to become obese.
So maybe if you're physically active, that leads to you being hungry in the morning,
so you're more likely to eat breakfast,
and, obviously, being physically active makes it so that you burn calories,
you have more muscle, so that you're not obese
so notice: if you view things this way, if say that physical activity is causing BOTH of these,
Then all of a sudden you lose this connection between breakfast and obesity
Now you can't make the claim that if somehow breakfast is the magic formula
for somebody to not be obese
So let's say that there is an obese person,
Let's say that this is the reality, that physical activity is causing both of these things,
and let's say there is an obese person, what will you tell them to do?
will you tell them 'eat breakfast and you won't become obese anymore'?
well, that might not work, especially if they're not physically active
I mean, what's gonna happen if you have an obese person who's not physically active,
and then you tell them to eat breakfast?
maybe that will make things worse,
and, based on that, that the advice or the implication of the article is the wrong thing,
physical activity may be his thing, that he should be focused on
maybe it's something other than physical activity
maybe you have sleep
maybe people who sleep late and they're not getting enough sleep
maybe that leads to obesity
and obviously because they're not getting enough sleep they wake up as late as possible
and they have to run to the next appointment
- or they have to run to school, in the case of students -
and maybe that's why they skip breakfast
so, once again, if you find someone's obese, maybe the rule here isn't
to force some breakfast down their throats,
maybe it'll become even worse, because maybe it is their lack of sleep
that's causing their metabolism to slow down, or whatever
so it's very very important, when you're looking at any of these studies,
to try to say 'is this a correlation? or is this causality?'
If it's correlation, you cannot make the judgement that,
'hey, eating breakfast is necessarily gonna make somebody less obese,'
all that tells you is that these things move together.
A better study would be one that is able to prove the causality.
And then we can think of other underlying causes that would kind of
break down the narratives that this piece is trying to say
-I'm not saying it's wrong!
maybe it's absolutely true that eating breakfast will fight obesity
But I think it's equally or more important to think about what the other causes are,
not to just make a blanket statement like that.
So, for example, maybe poverty causes you to skip a breakfast, for multiple reasons,
maybe if both of your parents are working, there's no one there to give you breakfast,
um, maybe there's more stress in the family, who knows what it might be,
and so, when you have poverty, maybe you are more likely to skip breakfast,
and maybe when there's poverty, maybe you have two
- the parents are working, and the kids have to make their own dinner, and whatever else-
maybe they also eat less healthy, so eat less healthy at all times of the day,
and that leads to obesity.
So, once again, in this situation, if this is the reality of things,
just telling someone to also eat breakfast regardless of what that breakfast is,
even if it's fruit loops or syrup,
that's probably not going to help the situation
Maybe eating unhealthy dinners is the underlying cause
'... unhealthy dinner...'
And if you eat an unhealthy dinner,
maybe by breakfast time, you're not hungry still,
'cause you binged so much on dinner, so you skip breakfast,
and this also leads to obesity.
but once again, if this is the actual reality,
doing the advice that that article is saying may actually be a bad thing.
If you eat an unhealthy dinner, and then force yourself to eat a breakfast when you're not hungry,
that may make the obesity even worse.
So the whole point of this video isn't to say that the implications from that article are necessarily
wrong
But the important thing is to just realize that it might be wrong,
and just because you saw this correlation with the data,
it doesn't mean that eating breakfast is somehow magically going to fight obesity