In the video on black holes
several people asked what is actually a pretty good question, which is: If the mass of
say a black hole is only 2 or 3 solar masses,
why is the gravity so strong? Obviously the sun's gravity isn't so strong
that it keeps light from escaping. So, why would something or even a star that is 2 or 3 solar masses,
it's gravity isn't so strong that it keeps light from escaping
why would a black hole that has the same mass keep light from escaping?
And to understand that, let's just think a little bit about it.
I'll just do a Newtonian
classical physics right here.
I wont get into the whole general relativity and things.
This will really just give us the intuition of why a smaller, denser thing with the same mass
can exert a stronger gravitational pull.
So let's imagine-- so let's take two examples
Let's say I have some star here
that has a mass-- let's just call that mass m1
and let's say that its radius,
lets just call this "r"
and lets say that I have
some other mass right at the surface
of this star. Somehow able to survive those surface temperatures
and this mass over here
has a mass of m2.
The Universal Law of Gravitation tells us that the force between these two
masses is going to be equal to the gravitational constant
times the product of the masses.
So m1 times m2
all of that over the square of the distance
"r" squared.
Now, let me be very clear.You might say: Wait, this magenta mass
right here is touching this larger mass.
Isn't the distance 0?
You need to be very careful!
This is the distance between their center of masses.
So the center of mass of this large mass over here is "r" away from this mass on the surface
Now, with that said, let's take another example.
Let's say this large massive star or whatever it might be, eventually condenses
into something a thousand times smaller.
So let me draw it like this.Obviosly I'm not drawing it to scale.
So let's say we have another case like this (I'm not drawing it to scale)
So this object, maybe it's the same object or maybe it's a different object,
but it has the exactly same mass as larger object, but now has a much smaller radius.
So that radius now is 1/1000.Let's say it's 1/1000 of this radius over here.
So it's r/1000.If this had a million kilometer radius,
so that will make it roughly about twice the radius of the sun.
And this was a million kilometer radius right over here.
This would be a thousand kilometer radius,
so maybe we are talking about something that is approaching a neutron star.
But we don't have to think about what it actually is,just think about the thought experiment here.
So,let's say I have this thing over here and let's say I have something
on the surface of this.So let's say I have the same mass that's on the surface of this thing.
So, this is m2 right over here.
So, what's going to be the force between these 2 masses?
What's the force pulling them together?So that's the Universal Law of Gravitation again.
The force, let's just call this F1(force 1) and let's just call this F2(force 2).
Once again, it's going to be the gravitation constant, times the product of the masses
So, the big m1, times the smaller mass m2, all of that over this distance squared.
This radius squared.
Remember, it's the distance to the center of masses.
This center of mass here we are considering m2 to the kind of view
just to point match right over there.
So what's the radius squared?
It's going to be "r" over 1 thousand squared ( r/(1000^2)).
Or, if we simplify this,what would this be?
This is the same thing as the gravitational constant times m1 times m2
over "r" squared over 1 thousand squared or over 1 million.That's just a thousand squared.
Or, we can multiply the numerator and denominator by 1 million
and this is going to be equal to 1 million times the gravitational constant
times m1 times m2, all of that over "r" squared.
Now, what's this things right over here?
That's the same thing as the F1.So this is going to be 1 million times F1.
So, even though the masses involved are the same, this yellow object right here
is the same mass as this larger object over here.
It's able to exert a million times the gravitational force on this point of mass
So they are both being attracted.They are both exerting this on each other.
And the reality is that because this thing is smaller,because this m1 on the right here,
this one I'm coloring in,because this one is smaller and denser, this particle is able to
get closer to its center of mass.
Now you might be saying: Ok,well..I can buy that.That you know, this just come straight
from the universal law of gravitation.But what if something closer to this center of mass
experience the same thing?
If this is a star, wouldn't photons that are over here wouldn't this experience the same force
If this distance right here is "r" over a thousand(r/1000), wouldn't some photon here or
atom here or molecul or whatever it's over here, wouldn't that experience the same force?
This milllion times the force of this thing and you got to remember,
all of the sudden when this thing is inside of this larger mass, what's happening?
The entire mass is no longer pulling on it in that direction.It's no longer pulling it in that inward direction.
You now have all of this mass over here is pulling it in outward direction.
All that mass is doing is that mass itself is being pulled inword.
It is pushing down on this.It is exerting pressure on that point.
But, the actual gravitational force that that point is experiencing is actually going to be less, it's actually going to me mitigated
by the fact that there are so much mass over here pulling in the other direction.
So, you can imagine that if you are in the center of a really massive object,
there will be no gravitational force being pulled on you,because you are at the center of the mass
The rest of the mass is outward,so at every point it will be pulling you outward.
So, that's why you as you enter the core of the star,
you will get a lot closer to the center of the mass.
It's not goint to be pulling on you with this type of force and the only way you can get this
type of forces is if the entire mass is contained in a very dense region,
in a very small region.
And that's why a black hole is able to exert such strong gravity that
not even light can escape.
Hopefully that clarifies things a little bit.