We have been doing a bunch of these videos with these convex lenses,
where we where we draw parallel rays and rays that go through the focal point,
to figure out what the image of an object might be.
What I want to do in this video is to come up with
an algebraic relationship between the distance of the object from the convex lens,
the distance of the image from the convex lens (usually on the other side)
and the focal length.
So lets see if we can do this.
To save you the pain of having to watch me draw straight lines I drew this ahead of time.
And so we can imagine this green thing right here is the object
This is the object.
And these two little pink points here are the focal points.
They are the focal length away.
And I did what we always do:
I drew one parallel ray from the tip of that arrow to the actual convex lens
and it gets refracted, so it goes through the focal point on the right hand side.
It goes all the way over there.
Then I drew a ray that goes through the focal point on the left hand side
and when it gets refracted it becomes parallel.
Then it actually intersects with that previous ray, up, right over here,
and so this gives us a sense of what the image will look like:
It is inverted, it is real and in this case it is larger than the actual object.
W\hat I want to do is to come up with a relationship with these values.
Lets see if we can label them here,
and then just do a little geometry and a little algebra
to figure out if there is an algebraic relationship right here.
So the first number, the distance of the object. That is this distance from here to here.
Or we can just label it here, since it is already drawn for us.
This is the distance of the object.
This is the way we drew it.
This was the parallel light ray.
But before it got refracted it traveled the distance from the object to the actual lens.
Now the distance from the image to the lens, that is this right over here, this is how far this parallel light ray had to travel.
So this is the distance from the image to the lens.
Then we have the focal distance; the focal length, and that is just this distance right here.
Or we can view it on this side as well. This right here is also our focal length.
So I want to come up with some relationship
and to do that I am going to draw some triangles here
so what we can do is; and the whole strategy, I am going to keep looking for similar triangles
and then trying to find a relationship or ratios that relate these three things to each other.
So let me find some similar triangles.
The best thing I can think of to do is to redraw this triangle over here.
Let me just flip it over.
Let me just draw the same triangle on the right hand side of this diagram.
If i were to draw the same triangle it would look like this.
Let me just be clear, this is this triangle right here, I just flipped it over.
and so if we want to make sure we are keeping track of the same sides
if this length right here is d sub zero [ d0 ] or d nought or sometimes we can call it d zero, whatever we want to call it
Then this length up here is also going to be d zero [ d0 ].
The reason why I wanted to do that is now we can do something interesting.
We can relate this triangle up here to this triangle down here
and actually, we can see that they are going to be similar.
And then we can relate, we can get some ratios of sides
and then what we can do is show that this triangle over here is similar to this triangle over here
get a couple more ratios and then we might be able to relate all of these things.
The first thing we have to prove to ourselves is that the triangles really are similar.
So the first thing to realise is that this angle right here is definitly the same thing as that angle right over there
something called opposite angles or vertical angles
they are on opppsite sides of lines that are intersecting, so they are going to be equal.
Now the next thing, this comes out of the fact that both of these lines
this line is parallel to that line over there
and you can look at, I guess you can call it alternate interior angles
if you look at the angles again with the parallel lines, with the transversal of parallel lines from geometry.
We know that this angle, since they are alternate interior angles
this angle is going to be the same value as this angle, right.
Cause they are both, you can view this line here as a transversal of two parallel lines.
These are alternate interior angles, so they will be the same.
Now we can make that exact same argument for this angle and this angle.
And so what we see is that this triangle up here has the same
three angles as this triangle down here.
So these two triangles are similar, these are both
and this is really more of a review of geometry than optics
these are similar triangles.
They are similar.
Because they are similar the ratios of corresponding sides are going to be the same
so d0 corresponds to this,
they are both opposite that pink angle.
So the ratio of d0 to d1 is, let me write this over here, so the ratio of d0 to d1 ...
This is the ratio of corresponding sides, is going to be the same thing.
Let me make some labels here. That's going to be the same thing
As the ratio of this side right over here, we call that A
it is opposite this magenta angle right over here
that is going to be the same thing as the ratio of that side to this side over here. To side B.
And once again we can keep track of because side B is opposite the magenta angle on this bottom triangle.
So that is how we know this side, its corresponding side of the other similar triangle is that one
they are both opposite the magenta angles.
So we know that d0 to d1 is as A is to B
So that is interesting.
We have been able to relate these two things to these kind of two arbitrary lengths.
We somehow have to connect these two things to the focal length.
To connect them to a focal length,
What we might want to do is relate A and B, A sits on the same triangle as the focal length right over here.
So lets look at this triangle over here.
Let me put it in a better colour.
So lets look at this triangle over here that I am highlighting in green.
This triangle in green.
and lets look at that in comparison to this triangle that I am also highlighting in green.
Now the first thing that I am going to show you is that these are also similar triangles
This angle right over here and this angle are going to be the same.
They are opposite angles of intersecting lines.
And then we can make a similar argument, alternate interior angles,
or there is a couple of arguments we can make,
one you can see that this is a right angle over here, this is a right angle,
if two angles of two triangles are the same then the third angle also has to be the same.
So we can also say that this thing, let me do this in another colour, I don't want to be repetitive too much with the colours,
we can say that this thing is going to be the same thing as this thing.
Or another way we could have said it is that this line over here,
which is kind of represented by the lens
or the lens or the line that is parallel to the lens,
is parallel to the object over there,
and you could make the same alternate interior argument there.
But the other thing is just look, I've two triangles, two of the angles in those two triangles are the same so
the third angle has to be the same. Now, since all three angles are the same, these are also both similar triangles, so we can do a similar thing
we can say A is to B; remember both A and B are opposite the 90 degree side, they are both the hypotenuse of these similar triangles
So A is to B as, we can say, this base length right here
it got overwritten a little bit, but this base length right over here is f
That is our focal legnth.
As f in this triangle is related to this length in this triangle
they are both opposite that white angle
so as f is to this length right over here
so what is this length
This whole distance is di, but this length is the whole distance minus the focal length
this is di minus the focal length
so A is to B as f is to di minus the focal length
And again we have a relationship between the distance
of the object, the distance of the image and the focal length
And now all we have to do is a little bit of algebra.
This is equal to this, and this is equal to that
so this blue thing has to be equal to thist magenta thing
and now we just have to do some algebra
So lets do that
So we got d_0 to d_i is equal to the ratio of the focal length to the difference of the image distance
minus the focal length.
And here we just have to do some algebra, lets just simplify this, let's cross multiply it
lets multiple d_0 times this thing over here
we get d0di - d0f [we are just distributing it]
Just cross multiplying, which really is just the same thing as multiplying both sides by both denominators.
That is going to be equal to di*f.
and now we can add this term over here to both sides of this equation.
I am just going to switch to a neutral colour.
So we get d0di = dif + d0*f.
So lets see here we could factor out the f, our focal length
so we get d0*di is equal to f(di+d0)
and then what can we do, we could divide both sides by f
So this will become over f
essentially cancelling it out, and then
Lets me just re-write what we have here.
d0*di / f = di + d0
now lets divide both sides by d0*di
Cancels out over here,
So we are left with on the left hand side
one over the focal length is equal to this thing over here
and we can separate this thing out
this thing over here, this is the same thing, we just separate out the numerators, is the same thing as
= di/( d0 x di) + d0/( d0 x di)
but the di's cancel out, and we just have a one, here the d0s cancel out and you just have a one
So this is equal to one over the distance of the object
and this is plus one over the distance of the image.
So from the get-go this was a completely valid formula,
we actually had acheved what we wanted.
But this is a neater formula, you dont have the di's or d0's repeated
right here we have an algebraic relationship for a convex mirror
that relates the focal length to the distance of the object and the distance of the image.
Any way, that is pretty neet how itt came out to be a clean formula.