So I've got an arbitrary triangle here, we'll call it triangle ABC
What I wanna do is look at the midpoints of each of the sides of ABC,
So this is the midpoint of one of the sides of side BC
Let's call that point D
Let's call this midpoint E
And let's call this midpoint right over here F
And so this is the midpoint,
we know that the distance from BD
is equal to the distance from D to C
So this distance is equal to this distance
We know that AE is equal to EC,
So this distance is equal to that distance
And we know that AF is equal to FB,
so this distance is equal to this distance
Instead of drawing medians going from this midpoints to the vertices,
What I wanna do is I wanna connect
these midpoints and see what happens
So if I connect them I clearly have three points
So if you connect three nonlinear points
like this you will get another triangle,
And this triangle that's formed from the midpoints
of the sides of this larger triangle,
we call this a medial triangle
Medial triangle and that's all nice and cute by itself
But what we're gonna see in this video,
is that the medial triangle actually have some very neat properties
What we're actually going to show is that divides
Any triangle into four smaller triangles
They are congruent to each other
That all four of these triangles are, are identical to each other
And they are similar to their larger triangle
And you could think of them
Each has having one fourth of the area of the larger triangle
So let's go about proving it,
So first let's focus on this triangle down here
Triangle CDE and it looks it looks similar to the larger triangle
The triangle CBA, but let's prove it to ourselves
So one thing we could say is well look
Both of them share this angle right over here,
Both the larger triangle, triangle CBA shares has this angle
And the smaller triangle CDE has this angle
So they definitely share that angle
And now let's look at the ratios of the sides,
We know that the ratio of CD
We know that the ratio of CD to CB,
the ratio of CD to CB is equal one over two
This is half this entire side is equal to one over two
And that's the same thing as the ratio of CE to CA
CE is exactly half of CA,
Cause E is the midpoint
It's equal to CE over CA
So we have an angle and corresponding angles that are congruent
And then the ratio of two corresponding sides
of either the side of that angle
Or the same CD or CB as one half
CE or CA as one half
And the angle in between is congruent
so by SAS so by SAS similarity,
SAS similarity, similarity
We know we know that triangle CDE, CDE
is similar to triangle to triangle CBA, CBA
And just from that you can get some interesting results,
Because we know that the ratio of these
sides of the shorter triangle or the smaller triangle
To the longer triangle is also going to be one half
Cause the other two sides have a ratio of one half
What we are gonna do with similar triangles,
so this is gonna be one half of that
And we know one half of AB
is just going be is just going to be the length of the FA
So we know that this length right over here
Is going to be the same as FA or FB
We can get that straight from similar triangles
Because these are similar,
we know that DE, DE over BA over BA
has got to be equal to these ratios,
the other corresponding sides which is equal to one half,
and so that's how we get that right over there
Now let's think about let's think about that this triangle up here
Let's thinks about this triangle up here
Triangle we can call it BDF, triangle BDF
So first when we compare triangle BDF to the larger triangle,
they both share this angle right over here angle ABC,
they both have that angle in common
And we're gonna have exact same argument
We can just you can just look at this diagram
You know that the ratio of BA
The ratio let me do it this way
The ratio of BF to BA, the ratio BF to BA
Is equal to one half, which is also the ratio of BD to BC BD to BC
The ratio of this to that is the same ratio
of this to that which is one half
Cause BD is half of this whole length
BF is half of this whole length
And so you have corresponding sides have the same ratio
On the two triangles and they share and angle in between
So once again by SAS similarity,
by SAS similarity SAS similarity
We know that triangle, we know that triangle right this way
DBF, triangle DBF is similar to triangle CBA,
Is similar to triangle CBA
And once again we use this exact same kind of argument,
that we do with this triangle
Well if it's similar with the ratio to all the corresponding sides
Have to be the same and that ratio is one half
So the ratio of this side to this side
So the ratio of FD the ratio of FD to AC has to be one half
or FD has to be one half of AC
Which when one half of AC is just the length of AE
So that is just going to be that length right over there
I think you see where this is going
And also, because it's similar
to all of the corresponding angles have to be the same
And we know that this is that, that the larger triangle
has a yellow angle right over there
So we have that yellow angle right over here
And this triangle right over was also similar to the larger triangle
So it will have that same angle measure up here,
We are to show that in this in this first part
So now let's go to this third triangle,
I think you see the pattern
I'm sure you might be able to just, pause this video,
And just prove it for yourself
But we see that the ratio of AF over AB
Is going the same as the ratio AE over AC
AE over AC which is equal to one half
So we have two corresponding sides with the ratio
is one half from the smaller to the larger triangle
And that they share a common angle
they share this angle in between the two sides
So by SAS similarity so this is getting repetitive now
We know that triangle we know that triangle EFA triangle EFA
is similar to triangle CBA to triangle CBA
And so the ratio of the corresponding sides it will be one half
So the ratio of FB to BC needs to be one half
or FE needs to be half of that
Which is the length of BD
So this is going to be that length right over there
And you can also say that since we show all that this triangle
This triangle and this triangle we haven't talked about this middle one yet
They're all similar to the larger triangle,
so they're all going to be similar to each other,
so they're e all going to have the same corresponding angles
So if the larger triangle had this yellow angle,
Then all of the triangle will have this yellow angle right over there
And the larger triangle will have this blue angle right over here
Then the corresponding vertex all of the triangles
were going has that blue angle
All of the ones that we've shown are similar
We haven't thought about this middle triangle just yet
And of course, if this is similar to the whole,
it'll also have this angle at this vertex over here
because this corresponds to that vertex
based on the similarity
So that's interesting,
Now let's look at the let's look at
Let's compare the triangles to each other
We've now shown that all of these triangles
Have the exact same three sides,
Has this blue side or I should have this one marked side
This two marked sides of this three marked side
One marked two marked three marked,
And that even applies to this middle triangle right over here
So by side, side, side,
So by side, side, side congruency, congruency
We now know and we wanna be careful
when we get our corresponding sides right
We now know that triangle, triangle CDE
is congruent to triangle D to DBF, DBF
When we look at the corresponding sides,
I'm looking at the colors
I want from the yellow to magenta to blue,
The yellow to magenta to blue
which is going to be congruent to triangle to triangle EFA, EFA
Which is going to be congruent to this triangle and here,
We wanna make sure that we're getting
we're getting the right corresponding sides here
So make sure when we do that,
We just have to think about the angles
So we know, we know this is interesting,
That the ,the because the, the interior angles
of a triangle add up to 180 degrees
We know that this magenta angle plus this blue angle
plus this yellow angle equal a hundred-eighty
Here we have the blue angle and the magenta angle,
And clearly they all add up to 180
You must have the blue angle the blue angle
The blue angle must be right over here
Same argument blue angle as I,
Yellow angle and blue angle
we must have the magenta angle right over here
They add up to 180,
So this must be the magenta angle
And then finally magenta and blue,
This must be the yellow angle right over there
And so when we wrote the congruency here,
we started at CDE
Yellow magenta blue,
So here we're gonna go yellow magenta blue
So this is going to be congruent to triangle FED to triangle FED
And so that's pretty cool we just show that all three that this triangle
This triangle this triangle and that triangle are congruent
And also we can look at the corresponding
and that they all have ratios relative to the larger triangle,
They're all similar to the larger triangle the triangle ABC
And that the ratio of between the sides is one to two,
And also because we've look at corresponding angles
We see for example, we see for example
that this angle is the same as that angle
So if you viewed DC if you viewed BC as transversal
All of the side becomes pretty clear that FD is going to be parallel to AC
Because the corresponding angles are congruent
So this is going to be parallel to that right over there
And you can use that as the same exact argument
to say well then this side
because once again, corresponding angles,
corresponding angles here and here
You can say that this is going to be parallel to that right over there
And then finally,
With the same argument over here you have
You have I wanna make sure I get the right corresponding angles
You have this this line and this line
and this angle corresponds to that angle
They are the same
So this DE must be parallel to BA to BA
So that's another neat property of this medial triangle
I thought that all of these things just jumped out
When you try to do something fairly simple with the triangle