We're asked to solve the equation 2x squared plus 3 = 75.
So in this situation looks like we might be able to isolate the x squared pretty simply. 'Cause
there's only one term that involves an x here. It's the only
x squared term. So lets try to do that. So let me just rewrite
it.
So 2x squared + 3 = 75. I'm going to try to isolate this x squared
over here. The best way to do that
or at least the first step, would
be the subtract 3 from both sides of this equation.
So lets subtract 3 from both sides.
The left hand side we're just left with 2x squared. That was the whole point of subtracting 3 from both sides.
And on the right hand side 75 minus 3 is 72.
Now I wanna isolate this x squared, I have a 2x squared here.
So I could have just have an x squared here if I divide
this side
or
really both sides by 2. Anything that I do on 1 side,
I have to do the other side.
If I want them to mantain the quality.
So the left side just becomes x squared.
And the right hand side, the 72 divided by 2 is 36. So we're up with x
squared
is
equal
to
36.
And then to solve for x we can take the positive plus or minus
squared root of both sides. So we can say the plus or
let me right it this way.
If we take the squared root of both sides, we would get x
is
equal
to
the plus or minus square root of 36. Which is equal to plus or minus
6. let me just write it on another line.
So x is equal to plus or minus 6.
And remember here!
If something squared is equal to 36, that something could be the negative
version, or the positive version.
It could be the principle root, or it could be the negative root.
Both negative 6 squared is 36 and positive 6 squared is 36.
So both of these work. And you can put them back into the original
equation, to varify it. Let's do that. If you say
2 times 6 squared plus 3, that's 2 times 36 which is 72
plus 3 is 75. So that works.
If you put negative 6 in there, you're going to get the exact same result.
Cause negative 6 squared is also 36, 2 times 36 is 72,
plus 3 is 75.