We are asked to determine the amplitude and the period of y=-1/2 cos 3x.
So, the fist thing we have to ask ourselves, is what does the amplitude even refer to?
Well the amplitude of a periodic function is just half the difference between the minimum and maximum values it takes on.
So, if I were to draw a periodic function like this, and it would just go back and forth between two (Let me draw a little bit neater).
It goes back and forth between two values, like that.
So between that value and that value, you take the difference between the two and half of that is the amplitude.
Another way of thinking of the amplitude, is how much does it sway from its middle position?
Right over here, we have y=-1/2 cos 3x.
So what is going to be the amplitude of this?
Well, the easy way to think about it it's just, what is the coa... what is multiplying the cosine function?
And you could do the same things as if this was a sine function.
We have -1/2 multiplying it, so the amplitude. (The amplitude) The amplitude in this situation is going to be the absolute value of negative 1/2.
Which is equal to 1/2 and you might say, well do I not care about the sign, why do I take the absolute value of it?
Well, the negative just flips the function around, it's not going to change how much it sways between its minimum and maximum position.
The other thing is, well how it just simply the absolute value of this thing?
And to realize the why, you just have to remember that a cosine function or a sine function varies between positive and negative, if it's just a simple function.