[Steven Zucker] We're looking at one of the single canvases from a series of canvases
of the Campbell Soup cans by Andy Warhol, from 1962, at the Museum of Modern Art.
And one of the really important questions that comes up about, especially modern art,
is, "well, why is this art?"
[Sal] When you ask me that, a bunch of things kind of surface in my brain.
It does evoke something in me, so I'm inclined to say yes,
but then there's a bunch of other things that say, well, if I didn't see this in a museum,
and if I just saw this in the marketing department of Campbell's Soup
would you be viewing it differently?
[Zucker] Because it's advertising then. [Sal] Yes.
[Steven] But in the context of the museum, or in the context of Andy Warhol's studio,
it's not quite advertising, right?
[Sal] Even if it`s the exact same thing. [Steven] Yeah.
[Sal] And the idea here is by putting at the museum, it's saying
"look at this in a different way."
[Steven] Well, that's right. It really does relocate it,
it does change the meaning, it does transform it
and thats really one of the central ideas of modern art
Is that you can take something that`s not necessarily based
in technical skill,
cause I don't think you'd say
that this beautifully rendered. [Sal] Right.
[Steven] But relocate it and makes us think about it in a different way.
[Sal] And so, i guess he would get credit for taking something
that was very, almost mundane, something you see
on everyone, in everyone's cupboard, and making it a focal point
Like, "you should pay attention to this thing."
[Steven] I think that`s exactly right. And i think that he is doing it
about a subject, that was about as low a subject as one could go.
I mean cheap advertising art was something that was so far away
from fine art, from the great Masters
and then to focus on something as lowly as a can of soup
and ... and cream of chicken no less.
[Sal] And, and, and I mean, you know
A lot of it is, if he did it 50 years earlier people would have though this guy's a quack.
And if you did it now, they'd just think "he's derivative".
I mean right it's really just that time where people happened to think this was art.
[Steven] I think that that's right.
In 1962, what Warhol is doing is saying what is it about our culture that is really authentic and important
and it was about mass production, it was about factory
in a sence he said let's not be looking at nature as if we're an aguarian culture
we're now an industrial culture.
what is the stuff of our world now
I thik I'm 80% there
I remember when I was in college there was a student run art exhibit
and as a prank a student actually put a little podium there and put his lunch tray
he put a little placard next to it you know Lunch Tray on Saturday
so he did it as a prank and everyone thought it was funny
and to some degree it sounds like what he did was art
well i think that's why it was funny, because it's so close
and to some degree when someone took a lunch tray and gave it the proper lighting
and gave it a podium to look at it and write a whole description about it
I did view the lunch tray in a different way
It's kinda the same idea. It's a mondane thing and you use it every day
Was that a prank, or was that art?
Well, I think it is a prank, but it's very close to art that some important art
He had liscense to do that thanks to Marcel Duchamp
Inn fact Warhol had the same sort of license to not focus on the making of something
to not focus on the brushwork, to not focus on the composition, not focus on the color
but to refocus on the making of ideas.
and the reason why we talk about warhol or duchamp or any of these guys
is that as you say, it's not like they did anything technically profound
campbell's soups' marketing department had already done something as equally profound
it's more that they were the people who looked at the world in a different way and highlighted that
Well, I think that that's right. Warhol is consiously working towards, asking the same questions
that the prankster at your school is asking
He's saying can this be art?
and in fact, he's really pushing it.
Look at the painting closely for a moment.
this is one of the last paintings he actually painted.
He's really defined the calligraphy of the campbell's soup
the reflection of the tin at the top.
But then he stopped. and he said, I don't want to paint the flore de leafs,
You see the flore de leafs at the bottom.
I don't want to paint those, so he had a rubber stamp made and placed them down mechanically.
What does that mean for an artist, to say, I don't want to even paint these?
I'm just going to find a mechanical process to make this easier.
Warhol is doing something which is important which is reflecting the way
that we manufacture, that we construct the world
think about the things that we surround ourselves with.
Almost everything was made in a factory
Almost nothing is singular in the world anymore
It's not a world that we would normally find beautiful.
I know sometimes I feel, correct me if I'm wrong, that a decision was made
that Warhol was interesting or great, and then
people will interpret his stuff to justify his greatness
that oh, look he used a printer instead of drawing it which shows that he was
reflecting the...
But if he'd don'e it the other way, handdrawn it or drawn it with his elbow
or finger painted it or something
people would say "This is tremendous. We would normally see this printed by machine
but now he did it with his hands"
How much do you think this is the case? Or am I just being cynical.
No, I think that there's value in a certain degree of cynicisim
and i think in some ways what we're really talking about here is
What does it mean to be an avant guard artist what does it mean to sort of change
the laguage of art and try to find ways that relate to our historical moment
in some sort of direct and authentic way
and maybe it's easy for me to say this because i remember looking at this
when I was in fifth grade art class Andy Warhol and all that
And now it seems almost not that unique
But what I'm hearing is in 62, what I'm hearing is Warhol was really noteworthy because he pushed how people were thinking
I think that Warhol was looking for, in 1962, a kind of subject matter
that was completely outside of the scope that we could have considered fine art
And one of his contemporaries, Roy Lichtenstien, was asked to define what pop art was
and he said well we were looking for a subject matter that was so dispicable, so low
that nobody could possibly believe that it was art
And I think you're right and we think it's so much a part of our visual culture
that we accept it.
This is fascinating. I think there's a lot of potential there.
It's psuedo art created for other purposes, but if you shine a light on it
In the way a light have been shown on this
In your mind, does this cross the barrier into being art?
Well, I think that, you mentioned before, if someone did this now, it would feel derivative.
And I think that that's right, it underscores how hard it is to find in our culture now
ways of making us see the world in new ways
Yea, fascinating.