In the graph below,
for what values of theta does cosine of theta
equal one and for what values of theta does
cosine of theta equal negative one? And they have very nicely
graphed it for us. The horizontal axis is the theta axis
and the vertical axis is the y axis and so
this is the graph of y is equal to cosine of theta.
And it makes sense with the unit circle definition
and I'll just make sure we're comfortable with that because the unit circle definition
so let me draw ourselves a
unit circle and I'm going to draw it very roughly just so we get the general idea
of what's going on here. When theta is equal to zero
Where this point right over here on the unit circle. Well
what's the x coordinate of that point? Well it's one and you see when theta
is equal to zero on this graph, cosine
of theta is equal to one
when theta is equal to pi over 2 we're at this point
on the unit circle and the x coordinate is what