In a typical organic chemistry
problem set or exam, they'll
give you some type
of reaction.
In this case, we have--
what is this molecule?
We have one, two, three,
four, five carbons.
It is an alkene.
It starts on the number two
carbon if we start numbering
from here, and the number
two carbon also
has a methyl group.
So this is 2-methyl-pent-2-ene,
usually
naming it-- we don't have to
name it when we worry about
mechanisms. But they'll give
you a molecule like
2-methyl-pent-2-ene.
They'll draw it out like this
and they'll draw a reaction.
They're saying in the presence
of water and catalyzed by
hydronium ions, we end up with
this thing over here.
And then they'll give you a
bunch of white space below it,
and they say how did
this happen?
Give us the mechanism.
And that's what we're going
to do in this video.
So let's start with this
molecule right there, the
2-methyl-pent-2-ene.
So let me draw it right here.
So we have double-bond carbon.
I have a hydrogen.
I have two carbons right over
here, and then I have a
carbon, H3C, and then-- and we
put H3 before the C just to
make it clear the carbon
is what's bonded
to the other carbon.
That's why we don't write CH3,
but that wouldn't be
completely incorrect, and then
you have HC3 over here.
And then we're going
to have some
hydronium molecules around.
So let me draw a hydronium
molecule.
So it is an oxygen in
the middle and then
we have three hydrogens.
One, two, and three.
And oxygen also will have one
unbonded pair of electrons,
and it has a positive
charge here.
And the reason why this has a
positive charge, if you think
about regular water, regular
water looks like this: six
valence electrons.
Let me do the valence electrons
in another color.
One, two, three, four,
five, and six.
The other half of these
bonds comes
from hydrogen's electrons.
Now, in the case of a hydronium
molecule you have a
proton sitting out here.
It has absolutely no electrons,
and to form the
bond, one of oxygen's unpaired
valence electrons go to the
hydrogen, and that's what
forms the bonds.
You could imagine that that
electron is right over there.
That's why it has a
positive charge.
Now, oxygen wants that
electron back.
It doesn't like having this
positive charge, and we've
seen in the last videos that
sometimes the carbons, one of
the carbons in the double bond,
is pretty predisposed to
at least temporarily giving
up an electron.
And we saw that the one that's
most likely to give up an
electron is the one that's
bonded to the most carbons.
And in this case, this guy right
here is bonded to the
most carbons.
He's bonded to two carbons.
This guy's only bonded to one.
He is a secondary, or if he
loses his electron, it will be
a secondary carbocation as
opposed to if this guy loses
his electron, it will be
a primary carbocation.
This one will be more stable.
So what we can do is, we'll
say, look, this electron
that's at this end of this bond
right here, it goes to
the hydrogen right over there.
And then the electron that this
hydrogen was taking from
the oxygen will go back to the
oxygen, and it all kind of
happens simultaneously.
This electron is attracted, I
guess you could say, to the
partial positive charge, because
maybe this electron
spends more time over there.
And then this electron
goes back to the
oxygen to make water.
So what happens after this end
of the reaction or this part
of the reaction happens?
So after that happens, we will--
let me clear out this
water, actually.
That's not essential to
our mechanism, to
our reaction mechanism.
So after that happens, what
will everything look like?
Well, we'll have our
basic molecule.
So we have a H3C, we have a
carbon, we have another H3C.
It is now a single bond to the
other carbon, which is bonded
to a hydrogen and two other
carbons, CH2-CH3.
Now, this guy has lost
his electron.
That electron went
to the hydrogen.
So this guy now is a positive
carbocation.
Carbocation by definition is
positive so maybe I'm being a
little redundant there.
So it's positive.
And then this bond-- let
me do this in orange.
This bond is now between this
carbon and the hydrogen.
The electron went to that
hydrogen to form a bond.
So this bond is now with this
hydrogen over here and then
this thing that was a hydronium
molecule will now be
just water.
So I'll draw it like this.
It got its electron back.
Let me draw its two electron
pairs, just like that.
And then it has two hydrogens.
It is H2O.
And you can imagine that maybe
that was one of the electrons
that was on oxygen end, and
then this was the electron
that it had given essentially to
the hydrogen, but it's now
giving back, and now they're
both back with the oxygen.
That's the one it always had
on its end, and this is the
one that it just got back
from the hydrogen.
Now, what do you think
will happen next?
Well, when you can just look at
the final products of this
reaction you say, well, at some
point, I have to have an
OH attached right over here, and
that's usually a good way
to figure out what's going
to happen next.
So somehow, it looks like
this might attach to
that positive charge.
It was attached to a positive
charge before.
It was attracted to that
hydrogen proton, so why can't
it do it with the carbocation?
And then once it does
that, maybe we lose
one of these hydrogens.
And actually this reaction-- I
shouldn't draw these strict
arrows here, because every
step of this reaction is
really-- there's some
form of equilibrium.
It doesn't only go
in one direction.
Things can go in both
directions here.
So let me clear this.
And let me show that these
aren't just one-way reactions.
They can go in both
directions.
But if we are trying to show a
mechanism, we're assuming that
we're going in the direction
that we're
drawing this out in.
So in the next step, let's
making that oxygen attack that
carbocation.
Or another way, I guess a better
way, the carbocation is
attacking the oxygen.
It's going to take
back an electron.
So let's do that.
Let's make it-- lets draw it
taking back electron or an
electron being given back
to this carbocation.
So then we'll have, let's say,
that orange electron right
there-- let me do it in
a different color.
Let's say we have this.
That orange one is
attracted to the
carbocation and forms a bond.
Now, what's going to happen?
Let me draw it as an equilibrium
reaction.
But we're going to go in this
direction just to see how we
can get that final
end product.
We have H3C.
We have the carbon that
was a carbocation.
We have H3C.
Now, we have the single bond to
a hydrogen to two carbons
right over here.
We have this business, that bond
that was formed in the
early part of our mechanism.
Let me draw that.
And then we have that blue
hydrogen there that helps us
keep track where things
came from.
And now this has attached.
We have gotten that orange
electron to the carbocation.
It will form a bond.
It's going to form a bond.
And what's that bond
going to look like?
Let me draw this oxygen
over here like that.
It has that electron pair
still all to itself.
It has the two hydrogens.
It had that green electron, but
now it's not just paired
up with this orange electron.
That orange electron went.
It left the oxygen and went
to that carbocation.
So now the orange electron
is right over there and
it formed this bond.
Now carbon has four
valence electrons.
This carbon has one, two, three,
four valence electons.
This oxygen just lost an
electron again and so it now
has a positive charge again.
Now, what do you think
will happen next?
We're very close to
the final product.
The thing we have here looks
almost identical to the thing
that we have to end up at,
except we have a whole
hydronium group, I guess
you could say, or
actually a whole water.
We have H2O attached here.
They only have an OH.
And this oxygen right here,
it's a positive charge.
It wants to get one of
its electrons back.
It could take it back from here
or it could take it back
from one of these hydrogens.
And if it takes it back from one
of these hydrogens, then
we will be at our final
end product.
We will have a neutrally charged
OH group right there.
So how would that happen?
Well, we're in an aqueous
solution.
There is water all around us.
There are molecules of water,
so let me draw one of those
molecules of water that's just
floating around, and maybe one
of its electrons right here.
Let me color code it.
That makes it a little
bit more fun.
Maybe one of it's electrons are
attracted to the partial
positive end of this molecule
or this hydrogen.
So I'll do it in green.
It goes to this hydrogen.
This hydrogen no longer needs
this electron on this end of
the bond, and so it goes back
to the oxygen like that.
And then what is going
to happen?
What do we have left at that
end, or, in general, after
that part of the reaction
happens?
We have all of this
stuff over here.
Maybe I should just copy-- well,
let me just redraw it.
So we have H3C, a carbon-carbon
single bond.
I'm going to draw everything in
yellow that we started off
with in yellow.
CH2-CH3, H3C, and then we have
that first hydrogen that got
attached on this end.
We figured out it was going
to be this end more likely
because of Markovnikov's rule.
One way to remember is this
carbocation was more stable.
The other way is the side that
has more hydrogens will get
more hydrogens.
The side that has more
functional groups will get
more functional groups.
But now we have all
of this business.
We have this magenta bond here,
and we have an oxygen in
the middle.
It is still bonded to that
hydrogen over there.
This pair of electrons, I'm
just going to do it on the
side, just so we can
draw it how we can
conventionally draw it.
And now we had-- and
let me make it very
clear with the colors.
We had this electron on one end
of a bond, so it's still
there on that end of the bond.
And then we have this electron
that was with the hydrogen,
but now it's gone back
to the oxygen.
So now we have two
pairs again.
We have six valence electrons
around the oxygen: one, two,
three, four, five, six.
It is neutral.
And now one of those water
molecules has become a
hydronium molecule.
So now that water
looks like this.
That thing that was a water
molecule looks like this.
It has its lone pair.
And then it has one end, that
electron right there, but this
blue electron went and
joined the hydrogen.
Let me draw it little closer to
the hydrogen right there.
And then it has that bond.
So when all is said and done,
we were able to get to the
molecule that the mechanism,
or that the reaction
described, and it was
actually the most
reasonable path to follow.
We followed Markovnikov's
rule.
We figured out that this was the
most stable carbocation,
and then we just added
the water.
This is an addition reaction of
water in the presence of an
acid, in the presence
of hydronium.
Hopefully, you found that
vaguely useful.