We're outside of the city wall in Pompei in the Villa of Mysteries. so this is called the villa of mysteries because of this room we're looking at. It's a very mysterious room painted with figures engaged in something that we really can't figure out entirely. The frescos that we're discussing in this room exist in this large villa overlooking the sea, filled with other frescoes from different periods of Roman wall painting. So many of the houses in Pompei are eclectic in their styles. They incorporate styles from one period but then a new room perhaps is constructed or renovated and then a new style is added. So it's a bit of mix. Just like you might have a bathroom in your house left over from the 1960's. This villa had once had large windows that looked out onto the sea, but if we look towards
the scene now it's actually very distant. The eruption of Mt. Vesuvius added a tremendous amount of shore to the coastline and the Villa of Mysteries is now quite a distance from the beach. It's quite a luxurious villa. Roman wall painting is freso; it's painted directly onto wet plaster. And these are true fresco, or what the Italians call bon fresco, but the ancient Romans also added seco fresco to the top; in other words, the underlayer was a mixture of lime plaster that was basically stained with a kind of watercolor that wouldn't remain on the surface but would actually stain the full depth of that new plaster. But once that had dried sometimes finishing touches would be added with what is called seco fresco or dry fresco. The colors are still very deep; we see reds and greens and purples and blues.
These may not have originally been quite as deep when the excavations were first taking place.
This particular fresco cycle had oil and wax added to it. It'll preserve it but it actually darkened the color.
The room is entered though a very small door, and it has two windows, so that adds to the sense that this was a room that had a special purpose.
There's been a lot of debate about what these figures depict.
These are large-scale figures painted on three walls
that we think depicts a Dionysian cult ritual.
At this time, what we call mystery cults, which were religions that came from the east,
were not entirely ok. The state religion was still the only official religion that was allowed.
Right, and so if you were involved in something like a Dionysic cult or another eastern cult you had to keep it somewhat secret.
So lets start by looking at the figures closest to the doorway, where one would enter.
We see a woman with her hand bend against her hip.
She is fully dressed and has an aristocratic air to her.
And she seems literally to be entering in from the doorway.
She wears a veil and pulls the veil down around her shoulder and chest,
and because of the veil we think that she is a bride
In fact we think that this entire ritual that's being rendered on these walls is about a mystical marriage to the god Dionysus.
He appears on the next wall.
Before we get to him, we see a small child, a boy, who is stark naked and seems to be reading intently from a small scroll
We think that this is some sore of liturgy, some sort of ritual.
Behind him is a seated female figure,
and then next to her another
female figure, who seems to be carrying
something, which we really can't identify
Sometimes figures are grouped together,
but then other times figures are alone,
and seem to be very much in their own world
There is a sense of continuous space though,
and continuous time
They could be going about their own activities
independent of each other.
When we look toward the feet of the figures,
we see a ground that they're standing on.
We have a sense of an illusion of space,
and this division of the wall into horizonal bands
and the creation of an illusion of space
is part of what we consider second style wall painting
This is different than that flatness
that we saw in the first stlye
Characteristic of second-style wall painting
it is as if the room itself
is architecturally extended
It's as if this wall breaks out
and there's enough room on a platform
for these figures to stand on.
But this is unusual in that we have
such a dense frieze of figures and at this scale.
That's right.
In the next scene, we see a group of figures
around a table, who are involved in some
kind of ritual it seems,
although it's very difficultto identify
to identify exactly what
Some art historians have suggested that this
is a kind of cleansing ritual.
You can see some sort of liquid
being poured onto a tabletop.
There's a drape that's being lifted up.
The figure who's facing away from us--
look at the way that one of her hips
pushes over the stool that she sits on.
There's a purview of illusionism
It's extraordinarily successful
And even though her back is facing towards us
we are engaged with her.
We are looking towards that table
almost the way that she is.
We have a sense of psychology, of emotion,
of individuality.
The seated figure seems to be looking toward
a standing, drunken, figure,
who we've identified as a Silenus,
or a drunken older satyr figure.
Well, satyrs hung around with Dionysus,
and everybody drank a lot so no surprise there.
Yeah, he looks quite tipsy.
Next to him are three figures.
Most people are struck
by the one figure of the three that is standing.
She seems shocked.
There's a kind of recongnition,
but also a kind of surprise.
And fearfulness...
And fearfulness, absolutely.
And, of course, that entire upper body
is framed beautifully by that cloak
that billows in back of her
It's picked up the wind.
And look at the way it turns in space,
light and shadow are used exquisitely
in order to construct that volume in back of her.
And she moves toward the right but
she looks back to her left.
So there's a sense of reacting and moving away,
and her left hand, her left forearm is foreshortened.
Her expression, looking over to the back wall,
bridges that gap.
We seamlessly move over the corner of the room
without even realizing it.
This is really thoughtfully conceived.
She seems to be reacting to a mask
held up by a figure on the next wall.
That's a young figure
standing above another Silenus.
Now we're at the back panel where Dionysus sits.
And we can see he is absolutely drunk.
When we think about Dionysus,
we think about unbridled pleasure.
That's indicated in his body
as he lounges across the lap of Ariadne,
his mortal lover.
He's got his own staff draped over him,
but look at the way that the body's
beautifully articulated...
almost completely nude,
his drape is just falling away,
but there's a way in which
his body's absolutely relaxed.
This is not the way the Greeks or Romans
represented their athletes.
But we do see often images of Dionysus in this pose,
sleeping, dreaming, reclining, drunken, awakening.
I love the way that Ariadne, a mortal...
her hand is over his shoulder,
and there's a kind of intimacy there.
He is enjoying himself.
And as we move toward the right,
we see a kneeling figure
who is unveiling something under a purple cloth
that has just been removed from its case
that's on the ground.
Right. Some have called this a basket of some sort.
Art historians have spend a lot of time
trying to determine what exactly is there.
Many people think it's a phallus.
One art historian has suggested
it might be a rendering of Mt. Vesuvius,
which is visible from just outside this house.
Next to that, we have a winged figure,
who's foreshortened, moving towards us,
but looking over to her left,
and she's whipping a figure who's kneeling
across the next corner.
The winged figure's body
has this wonderful torsion,
as she reaches back
in order to really get a good strike
with that whip.
So just like the back left corner,
the artist, whoever it is--
and we don't have a name--
has been able to bridge that corner seamlessly,
and we know that the velocity of that whip
will move our eye right over to its victim.
The woman's back is exposed.
Her head is down, in the lap of a woman
that seems to be comforting her.
And beside them another woman,
who is nude, who seems to be dancing.
Look at the elegance of this figure,
and that way the her drape creates a crescent
that frames her body just beautifully.
We have figures who are in groups together,
comforting each other,
enacting something together,
and then a figure who is isolated,
or seems to be somewhat separated from that group.
The scene is then interrupted by a large window,
and concludes with three figures on the right.
We have a small, angelic figure--
a kind of putti, that seems to be dancing.
And then another figure who's seated,
who's doing her hair,
being helped by a standing woman.
Perhaps she's already gone through the ritual,
and is a bride of Dionysus,
or perhaps the next initiate--we really don't know.