We are asked to add the complex number 5 + 2i
to the other complex number 3 - 7i
and as we'll see when we are adding complex numbers
you can only add the real parts to each other
and you can only add the imaginary parts to each other.
So let's add the real parts:
so we have a 5 plus a 3
And then the imaginary parts:
we have 2i so plus 2i
and then we have a -7i or we're adding or we're subtracting 7i
So minus 7i right over here.
And 5+3. That's pretty straight forward:
that's just going to be 8.
And then if I have 2 of something
and from that I subtract 7 of that something
and in this case the something is the imaginary unit,
the number i,
if I have 2 i's and I take away 7 i's then I have -5 i's.
2 minus 7 is -5.
So then I have -5i
So when you add these two complex numbers you get 8 - 5i.
You get another complex number.
It has a real part and an imaginary part.