Is ( -1, 7) is solution for the equations below.
The first equation is x + 2y =13, second equation
is 3x - y = -11, Inorder for -1,7 for solution for the system
it needs to satisfy both equations.
x = -1 and y = 7, need to satisfy both equations to
be a solution. Lets try with the first equation.
If x=-1 & y =7 we will test if it satisfies this equation.
So we have -1 + 2x7 = 13 ?I put a ? because we don't
know if it satisfies. -1 + 14 = 13
So 13 =13, so it satisfy the first equation.
Now lets us look at the second equation. We have
3 ( -1) - 7 = -11 ? Put ? as i don't know if it satisfies.
-3 - 7 = -11?
-3 -7 = -10. So we get
-10 = -11, no It is not true. So x = -1 & y=7
does not satisfy the second equation.
This over here is not a solution for the system.
The answer is No as it satisfies the first equation,
but not the second.