and a right angle at C. So let's just try to draw that.
let's draw that, let's draw the right angle maybe we have to use some coordinates, so let's draw
the right angle at the origin.
So, let's say that this is C right over here.
AC = 7, so A will be put over here, this distance here
is going to be seven
and then we have the hypotenuse of our triangle.
and this can be
B, this distance over here they tell us, BC
is equal to twenty four.
All right.
Now point M is the midpoint of AB so point
M is right over here let me do that in a different
color
point M
is the midpoint
it's the midpoint of AB so this distance
is equal to that distance
and D is on the same side of AB.
So, D is on the same side of AB as C, so C is on this side you can call that
left of the bottom left-hand side of AB
So that AD is equal to BD is equal
to fifteen.
So D is going to be some place over here.
It's going to be
equal distant between enviada see all of
a point equal distant between a and b_ are
going to sit on a line that looks
something like that this is the midpoint of
abt so do you going to sit right over here
and it's fifteen away from both they and b
sold look something like that that distance
over their is fifteen
and then at this distance this distance over
here it is also going to be fifteen
given that the area of triangle cd and
so the area of triangle cd and this is d so
see
the
and is the triangle that
they wanna
think about given to the area title cbm maybe
expressed as and times of squirted andover
p were and and and pr positive integers
and an end
pr relatively prior to that just means you
can simplify and and is not the divisible
by the square of any prime so kind and his
uh... you've simplify the radical as much
as possible
find and plus and plus peace researcher unified
the area the area of this green triangle of
the cd m over here and so if you look at what
we can do
to figure it out so we could try some of the
court it's for some of these points
so displayed right over here a
is going to be it's excise going to be seven
i could rub quarter to cc what i'm doing that
could be the x-axis
and in this
side is on the y_ axis
quartet for a would be seven
common zero
cornett for c_ would be zero com zero and
quartet for be would be twenty four
so i would be zero twenty four
zero twenty-four so the court date four and
would just be the average of dna_
so the court it for and the average of zero
and seven eighths seven house
and the court that four
the white cord at governor twenty four and
zero is
toward alpha
that's fair enough now to what we can figure
out about the side so you know this is a right
triangles or got reaction is always to use
the protagonist and we know the side and that
side
before one of the red in b
we could just say that
we just know that twenty-four squared
plus seven squared
is equal to
is equaled two a v is equal to a be squared
and twenty-four squared is five hundred and
seventy-six plus forty-nine is equal to
a the squared
and a c five seventy six post forty nine
if it was plus fifty would give us two five
twenty who is a six twenty six points one
lesson that's a six twenty five
so six twenty five is equal to
ab
squid aired so it be is going to equal twenty
five
so a v
is equal to twenty five so this distance thus
the distance of this big harp on this year's
twenty five
half of the distance this is going to be twenty-five
over too
from the dam
from mta_ is also going to be
twenty-five over to you
now the other thing we know
the other thing that we know
is that
am right over here
amma right over here and the triangle see
and is a nice also leads triangle how do we
know that
wool and if you look at specs quartet it's
excoriate is directly in between the export
its for cnn_ seven have since the average
this is seven
this is the url it's important as writer of
this directly above the midpoint of this base
over here
so this is going to be a nice awfully strangle
some after cubic foot the triangle oversold
this length
this length of the seems useful 'cause this
is kind of the base of the area that of the
truck
the base of the triangle we care about
the kind of you this is the base of cd m
this is also going to be twenty-five over
to you
twenty-five rotors i softly strangled this
is going to be the same is that because we're
symmetric around this
right over here
so c we know one side of this triangle
but if we could figure out decide over here
seems pretty straight forward this is going
to be a right
triangle right over here because in this line
from deep dam is going to be perpendicular
to a b
all of the points that are equal distance
between in b
are going to be on the line that is perpendicular
those perpendicular
to ab
so this is going to be a right wrangle so
we can figure out dm
using the protagonist theorem again
we get twenty-five over to squared
twenty-five over too
school where'd
plus dm squared
plus the and squared
plus the and squared is going to be equal
to fifteen square is what he called a hypothesis
this triangles twenty equal two hundred
and twenty five
and so what do we get we get dm squared
dn
squared is equal to
to twenty-five minus
six twenty five over
four sauce for the soul force of two twenty
five or four or to twenty-five with for the
nominee of the same thing is nine hundred
nine hundred over four
in the last video actually figure
died mistakenly said that it over for was
one twenty five agassi boneheaded mistake
with the number show up again here so to twenty-five
obscene niner
over for
amra subtract from that
six twenty five over four
minus six twenty five
over four
and uh... this is he cool too
cian taryn numerator
let's see we have not heard my six twenty
five would be three hundred minus twenty is
going to two hundred
two hundred and seventy-five
over four
and so dm
is going to be equal to the square root of
this citicorp to the square root
of two seventy five or four to seventy five
is twenty five
times eleven twenty five times twelve would
be three hundred twenty-five times eleven
or for
so this is going to be equal to five square
roots of eleven
over too
sodium is five square roots of eleven or her
too
now if we could just figure out
so when you do here is figure out the height
of this triangle right over here we could
figure out the height of that triangle where
we're pretty much done one-half the base times
a height
but we don't know who see we could figure
that if we know the loft co-signed into something
over there for another sign of the single
right over here
if we know the sign of that angle the side
of that angles going to be this
over
the side we just figured out
sofa to figure out the side of that angle
then we'd be done or robi very close to being
done that's not any obvious way
but one thing we can do if you look at this
bigger triangle overhear salami highlighted
so if you look at triangle be and c
redraw triangle bmc
devote artist
from destroying right over here and want to
get to overload of the triangle b
amma
see right over here
we know this side twenty-five over to we know
this side over here twenty five or two
we know this side over years twenty four
and we know this
so what we want to do is figure out the sign
of the single right here the sign of data
of anglesey and d
now that's hard to do but what we can't do
is use a lot of course i had the stayed up
last ninety
so let's let me let me redraw are triangle
so triangle pcm
i could redraw like this
i could read right actually nice awfully struggle
so we have b
c
and what is this a will right over here
it's going to be art fair that we care about
plus a ninety degrees
so this angle right here is data
data plus ninety degrees
and this overhears twenty four this is twenty
five over too
and this is twenty five over to you
if they're using this week a diesel off ko
signs to figure out
to figure out what
data actually is here
so listen to that
raise a little bit of trig identities but
love co side so we get
the opposite to the angle squared so we get
twenty-four squared
twenty-four squared is equal to twenty five
over to squared
twenty-five over to squared plus twenty five
plus twenty five over to squared minus
two times twenty five over too
times twenty five over too
times of the co-signed of this angle
times of misc rollover
the cosign
data
data plus
data plus ninety degrees now you're saying
hey sal you know
this has it in terms of cosign the state a
plus side agrees huckabee figure out the side
of
data that's what we actually care about
to figure out the area of the strike a lecture
to figure out the height
of this triangle
and to do that you just have to
maker of the realization that we know the
trader identity
we know the trigger identity the because side
of data
is equal i want you state archives are overloaded
a cosigner acs
is equal to sign
of nineteen minus x
so the co-sign if they don't plus nine degrees
so the co-sign of data plus ninety degrees
is going to be equal to the sign of
preferences ninety minus whatever zern nineteen
minus data
minus ninety
which is are called to
the nineties cancel out
sign of negative data
and will sign a mega date is equal to
the negative assigned uh...
so this over here simplifies too
this is a negative sign the status of the
right the scientist data here
and then put the negative out here in this
becomes a positive so what is a simple fight
with twenty-four squared
which is five hundred and seventy-six
five hundred seventy six is equal to
let's see we have
loudest i won't skip any steps here so we
have twenty five square plus twenty five squared
this is to times twenty five
this is too
two times twenty-five or two
school where'd
squared plus
to times this is twenty five over to squared
again two times twenty five over to squared
times signed uh...
now we just have to sulfur sign of paid us
so this is going to be equal to
five seventy six
is the called too
to trying to play five over to squared
factoring that out
one plus sign us data
one-plus sign of kato or
we can just divide both sides of the equation
by this yeshiva me to simplify it this thing
overhears
six twenty five
four
for the remarkable i dot by two so this thing
over here is the six twenty five
over too
source the by both sides of this by six twenty
five over to and we get
five seventy six
times
times to over six twenty five
to smoke applying both sides by the inverse
is equal to a new model bible time either
said this asa cancels out
is equal to
one
plus sinus data
scientist a that we just subtract one from
both sides we get sign of state a
is equal to five seventy six times to see
say six times tues one fifty
plus a thousand sos one thousand one hundred
and fifty two
over
six hundred and twenty-five that's that part
of their minus one
recive one mostly six twenty five or six twenty
five so minus six
twenty five
and uh... this is he pulled to after dual
math on the side
so one thousand one hundred fifty two
minus six hundred and twenty five
you get a twelve there's becomes a for twelve
months five seven four minus two is to eleven
minus six is five
so this is equal to five hundred and twenty
seven over six twenty five
now you might not realize it more in the home
stretch alice let's draw
let me broaden this cd and triangle on that
is really the focus of the problem of the
drug a little bit differently
let me try it
you dropped slightly differently so now we
know it's a very interesting things about
cd into the sissy
this is d
and this is an we know this side over here
mr dot is five hafte
squared eleven
five over to times the square root eleven
that's the length
of the and
we also know
that cm right over here is twenty five over
too
we also know that sign of data here
we also know that sign of data is equal to
five hundred and twenty seven
over at six twenty five that's what we just
figured out
and we can use that to figure out the height
the heights of this triangle
because we know that side is is the opposite
over the hype on his if we draw our right
triangle right here so scientist data
which is five twenty seven or six twenty five
is equal to the opposite is equal to the heart
of this triangle
is equal to the higher this triangle over
the hype on his over
five over to square roots of eleven
so d'amato by both sides of this by five squirts
of
five over to squirts eleven
and we get
the high of the triangle is equal to five
hundred and twenty seven
over six hundred and twenty five
times
five
over too
square roots
of eleven relatively can divide
six twenty five divide by five is one hundred
and twenty five so you get up
one here and you have a one hundred and twenty-five
over here
so this is equal to
five hundred and twenty seven
square roots eleven
over
one twenty-five times too which is two hundred
two hundred and fifty that's the height now
with the area of the triangle it's one-half
base times height
area is able to one-half base
which is twenty five over too
twenty-five over two times a height
which we just figured out is
five twenty seven two square roots of eleven
over two hundred and fifty
the seat twenty five divide the numerator
by twenty five by the nominal by twenty five
years tender
so this is equal to
five hundred and twenty seven
square roots of eleven
over two times two times ten which is sporty
so that's our area the whole problem they
didn't want to find the area they want us
to find and plus and plus p
and plus and plus pizza they want us to find
essentially five twenty seven plus eleven
plus forty
five twenty seven
plus eleven
plus forty
so five twenty seven plus the eleven is five
penetrated this five hundred thirty-eight
and then plus forty is five hundred and seventy-eight
and were done