So in a normal economy
We know that employment will drive overall demand
if we have high employment or low unemployment
then people are going to have more jobs
and they're going to have higher wages
and that will have higher demand
or if the other way goes around
if they lose their jobs
demand is going to go down
wages will start to go down
and people aren't going to have money in their pockets.
So that employment drives demand,
and we can view demand
and I'm making a huge simplification here
demand will drive production
or maybe we can think of it as supply
it will drive supply
and it can also be a driver of price.
And of course
there is a little bit of a negative feedback loop
for both of these things
if the demand is high, the price goes high
that might produce a little bit of negative feedback
on the demand
this type of a sort of an arrow, this line here
means negative feedback
or I'll put a little negative sign here
and let's say the demand is high
then the supply goes high
well that might also make the demand
actually the supply going high
would drive the price going down
so maybe I should draw a negative feedback like here.
High supply would mean lower price
but that's not what I want to focus on in the video.
And we could keep adding more lines here
but this is a roughly simple take on it
but the general idea is supply and price
will then drive corporate profits,
or just profits in general
even for an individual business owner
and then profits are going to drive employment
Now, let's imagine a scenario
we are in a bad economy
maybe a depression-like economy.
So that situation you could start really at any point in the circle
I'll just start at employment
So let's say employment is really low
that's going to make demand really low,
and if demand is really low
then supply is going to go down
and price is going to go down
and then that's going to make profits go down
and that's going to make employment even lower.
and so what we find ourselves
in this kind of recessionary or depressionary environment
this would be called a deflationary spiral
and it's a spiral
because a bad economy is driving lower prices
which is in turn driving a bad economy
and to make matters worse
if this continues long enough
or if these price declines are severe enough
you could imagine people saying
"Look, I have this dollar in my pocket
I'm not going to spend this dollar
because one, I might lose my job at any moment
or, and I know that dollar is becoming more powerful
I can buy more every minute that I wait."
So as the price goes down
so as all of this scary stuff happens
so the employment is going down
profits are going down
price is going down
this makes people not hoard goods and services the way
or at least hoard goods the way
that they would do in an inflationary spiral
but it makes them hoard money.
And why it's ultra scary
for central bankers or for governments
is they start to not have as much control over the economy.
They can't just run the printing press
and try to stimulate the economy in this situation
because if they did
people are so conservative right now
you can imagine maybe
depression is going on for years and years and years
and let's say they take some type of a helicopter
and this isn't how you actually distribute money
to the money supply
but it's just to show an extreme example
so they take a helicopter
and they start dumping cash on people
they print cash, and they start dumping it on people
so every man and woman and child in the country
gets a $10 bill
Well, if people are really scared, they're really afraid
they're just gonna take that $10 bill
and stuff it under their mattress
and it's not going to change anything
the dollar isn't going to actually enter into the money supply
the velocity on it will be zero.