What I want to do in this video is think about
the antiderivative of one over x
or another way of thinking about it is
the antiderivative of x to the negative one power
Now we already know that if we somehow try
to apply that anti-power rule,
that inverse power rule over here,
we would get something that is not defined.
We would get x to the zero over zero,
which doesn't make any sense.
And you might have been saying, OK, well I know what to do
in this case. When we first learned about derivatives
we know that that the derivative with respect to x
of the natural log of x is equal to one over x
So why can't we just say that the antiderivative of this right over here
is equal to the natural log of x plus c?
And this isn't necessarily wrong.
The problem here is that it's not broad enough.
And when I say it's not broad enough, it's that the domain
over here for our original function that we are taking
the antiderivative of is all real numbers except for x equals zero.
So over here x can not be equal to zero.
While the domain over here is only positive numbers.
So in this expression, x has to be greater than zero.
So it would be nice if we could come up with an antiderivative
that has the same domain as the function we're taking
the antiderivative of.
So it would be nice if we could find an antiderivative
that was defined everywhere the original function was
so pretty much everywhere except x equaling zero.
So how can we rearrange this a little bit so this
can be defined for negative values as well?
Well, one possibility is to think about the natural log of
the absolute value of x.
The natural log of the absolute value of x.
So I'll put a little question mark here because
we don't really know what the derivative of this thing is
going to be.
And I'm not going to rigorously prove it here,
but I'll give you kind of the conceptual understanding.
So to understand it, let's plot the natural log of x
And I'd done this ahead of time
So that over there is roughly what the graph of the natural log
of x might look like.
So what would the natural log of the absolute value of x look like?
Well for positive x's, it's going to look just like this
For positive x's, you take the absolute value of it
and it's just the same thing and taking that original value.
So it's going to look just like that for positive x's.
But now this is also going to be defined for negative x's.
If you're taking the absolute value of negative one,
that evaluates to just one.
And so it's just the natural log of one
so you're going to be right there.
As you get closer and closer to zero from the negative side
you're just going to take the absolute value
so it's essentially going to be exactly this curve for the natural log of x
but the left side of the natural log of the absolute value of x
is going to be its mirror image if you were to reflect around the y-axis
It's going to look something like this
So what's nice about this function is that it's defined everywhere
except for x equals zero.