I think now's as good a time as
any to play around a little bit
with the formula for variance
and see where it goes.
And I think just by doing this,
we'll also get a little bit
better intuition of just
manipulating sigma notation
or even what it means.
So we learned, several
times, that the formula for
variance-- and let's just do
variance of a population.
It's almost the same thing
as variance of a sample.
You just divide by n
instead of n minus 1.
Variance of a population is
equal to-- Well you take each
of the data points, x sub i.
You subtract from
that the mean.
You square it.
And then you take the
average of all of these.
So you add the squared distance
for each of these points from i
equals 1 to i is equal to N.
And you divide it by N.
Let's see what happens if we
can-- Maybe we want to multiply
out the squared term and
see where it takes us.
So let's see.
And I think it'll take us
someplace interesting.
So this is the same thing
as the sum from i is equal
to 1 to N of-- Let's see.
This, we just multiply it out.
This is the same thing as x sub
i squared minus-- This is your
little algebra going on here.
So when you square it-- I
mean, we can multiply it out.
We could write it x sub i minus
mu times x sub i minus mu.
So we have x sub
i times x sub i.
That's x sub i squared.
Then you have x sub i times
mu-- times minus mu.
And then you have minus
mu times x sub i.
So when you add those two
together, you get minus
2 x sub i mu, right?
Because you have it
twice. x sub i times mu.
That's 1 minus x sub i mu.
And then you have another one.
Minus mu x sub i.
When you add them together,
you get minus 2 x sub i mu.
I know it's confusing with me
saying sub i and all of that.
But it's really no different
than when you did
a minus b squared.
Just the variables look a
little bit more complicated.
And then the last term is minus
mu times minus mu, which
is plus mu squared.
Fair enough.
Let me switch colors just
to keep it interesting.
Let me cordon that off.
OK.
So how can we-- Well the sum of
this is the same thing as the
sum of-- Because, if you think
about it, we're going
to take each x sub i.
For each of the numbers in
our population, we're going
to perform this thing.
And we're going to sum it up.
But if you think about it, this
is the same thing as-- If
you're not familiar with a
sigma notation, this is a good
kind of thing to
know in general.
Just a little bit of intuition.
This is the same thing as--
I'll do it here to have space
--as the sum from i is equal to
1 to N of the first term, x sub
i squared minus-- And actually,
we can bring out the
constant terms.
You just can't take-- When
you're summing, the only thing
that matters is the thing
that has the ith term.
So in this case, it's x sub i.
So x sub 1, x sub 2.
So that's the thing that you'd
have to leave on the right-hand
side of the sigma notation.
And if you've done the calculus
playlist already, sigma
notation is really kind of like
a discrete integral
on some level.
Because in an integral, you're
summing up a bunch of things.
You're multiplying them
times dx, which is a
really small interval.
But here, you're
just taking a sum.
And that's what-- Well we
showed-- In the calculus
playlist I said that an
integral actually is kind of
this infinite sum of infinitely
small things, but I don't
want to digress too much.
But this is just a long way of
saying that the second-- The
sum from i equals 1 to N of the
second term is the same thing
as minus 2 times mu of the sum
from i is equal to
1 to n of x sub i.
And then finally you have
plus-- Well this is just
a constant term, right?
This is just a constant term so
you can take it out --times
mu squared times the sum i
sub-- from i equals 1 to N.
And what's going to be here?
What's going to-- It's
going to be a 1, right?
We just divided a 1.
We just divided this by 1
to get out of the sigma
sign, out of the sum.
And you're just left
with a 1 there, right?
Actually we could have just
left the mu squared there.
But either way, let's just
keep simplifying it.
So this is-- This we
can't really do.
Well actually we
could-- Well, no.
We we don't know what
the x sub i's are.
So we just have to
leave that the same.
So that's the sum-- Oh sorry.
This is just the
numerator, right?
This whole simplification.
We're just simplifying
the numerator.
And later, we're just
going to divide by N.
So that is equal to
that divided by N.
Which is equal to this
thing divided by N.
I'll divide by N at the end.
Because it's the numerator
that's the confusing
part, right?
We just want to simplify
this term up here.
So let's keep doing this.
So this is equal to the
sum from i equals 1 to
N of x sub i squared.
And let's see.
Minus 2 times mu.
Sorry.
That mu doesn't look good.
Edit, undo.
Minus 2 times mu times the sum
from i is equal to 1 to N x i.
And then what is this?
What is another way
to write this?
Essentially we're going to add
1 to itself N times, right?
This is kind of saying just
whatever you have here just
iterate through it N times.
If you had an x sub i here, you
would use the first x term,
then the second x term.
When you have a 1 here, this is
just essentially saying add
1 to itself N times, right?
Which is the same thing as N.
So this is going to be
plus mu squared times N.
All right.
Then-- See if there's anything
else we can do here.
Remember this is
just the numerator.
So this looks fine.
We add up each of those terms.
And we just have
minus 2 mu, right?
From i equals 1 to-- Oh.
Well think about this.
What is this?
What is this thing right here?
Well, actually let's
bring back that N.
So this is this simplified to
that divided by N, which
simplifies to that whole thing.
Which simplifies by this whole
thing divided by N, right?
Which simplifies to this
whole thing divided by N.
Which is the same thing as each
of the terms divided by N.
Which is the same
thing as that.
thing as that, right?
And now, well how
does this simplify?
This is the interesting part.
Well this-- Nothing
much I can do here.
So that just becomes the sum
from i is equal to 1 to N x sub
i squared divided by big N.
Now this is interesting.
What is-- If I take each of the
terms in my population and I
add them up and then I divide
it by N, what is that?
This thing right here.
If I sum up all the terms in my
population and divide by the
number of terms there are,
that's the mean, right?
That's the mean of
my population.
So this thing right
here is also mu.
So this thing
simplifies to what?
Minus 2 times what?
Mu times-- This whole
thing is mu too.
So times mu squared, right?
Mu times mu.
This is the mean of
the population.
So that was a nice
simplification.
And then plus-- What
do you have here?
Let's see.
You have mu.
Well you have n over n.
Those cancel out.
So you just have
plus mu squared.
So that was a very
nice simplification.
And then this simplifies to--
Can't do much on this side.
So the sum from i is equal to 1
to N of x sub i squared over N.
And then you see we have minus
2 mu squared plus mu squared.
Well that's the same thing
as minus mu squared, right?
Minus the mean squared.
So this, already, we've kind of
come up with a neat way of
writing the variance, right?
You can essentially take the
average of the squares of all
of the numbers in your, in
this case, a population.
And then subtract from that
the mean of your population--
the mean squared of
your population.
So this could be, depending on
how you're calculating things,
may be a slightly faster way
of calculating the variance.
So just playing with a little
algebra, we got from this
thing, where you have to, each
time, take each of your
data points, subtract
the mean from it.
And then square it.
And, of course, before you
do anything, you have
to calculate the mean.
Then you take the square, then
you sum it all up, then you
take the average, essentially,
when you divide it-- when
you sum and divide it by N.
We've simplified it, just using
a little bit of algebra,
to this formula.
And this is-- We're getting
to something called
the raw score method.
We could-- What we want to do
is, write this right here
just in terms of x i's.
And then we really are at, what
you call, the raw score method.
Which is, oftentimes, a
faster way of calculating
the variance.
So let's see.
What is mu equal to?
What is the mean?
The mean is just equal to the
sum from i is equal to 1 to N
of each of the terms, right?
You just take the sum
of each of the terms.
And you divide by the number
of terms there are, right?
So that is equal to-- So
if we look at this thing.
This thing can be written as--
Let me draw a line here.
This thing can be written as
the sum from i is equal to
1 to N of x sub i squared.
All of that over N.
Minus mu squared.
Well mu is this.
So this thing squared.
So this thing squared is what?
This is, let's see, x sub
i-- take the sum --to N.
i this is equal to 1.
You're going to take-- You're
going to square this thing.
And then you're going to divide
it by-- We squared right?
You divide it by N squared.
And what's-- This might seem
like a more-- Out of all of
them, this actually seems like
the simplest formula for me.
Where you, essentially, you
just take-- If you know the
mean of your population, right?
You say OK.
My mean is whatever and I can
just square that and just
put that aside for second.
But first, I can take each of
the numbers, square them,
and then sum them up, and
divide by the number of
numbers I have, right?
I don't know if I wrote-- No.
I've erased the last
set of numbers I had.
But we could show you
that you'll get to
the same variance.
So to me, this is almost
the simplest formula.
But this one's even faster in a
lot of ways because you don't
really have to even calculate
the mean ahead of time.
You can just say for each x i,
I just perform this operation.
And then I divide by N squared
or N accordingly and I'll
also get to the variance.
You don't have to do this
calculation before you figure
out the whole variance.
But anyway, I thought it would
be instructive and hopefully
give you a little bit more
intuition behind the algebra
dealing with sigma notations.
If we kind of worked out these
other ways to write variances.
And frankly, some books
will just kind of say,
oh yeah you know what?
The variance could be written
like this or-- And we're
talking about the variance
of a population.
Or it could be
written like this.
Or maybe they'll even
write it like this.
And it's good to know that you
can just do a little bit of
simple algebraic manipulation
and get from one to the other.
Anyway, I've run out of time.
See you in the next video.