The height of a triangle is 4 inches less than the length of the base.
The area of the triangle is 30 in^2. Find the height and base.
Use the formula A=1/2 base times height for the area of a triangle.
Ok. So let's think about it a little bit. Let me draw a triangle here.
So this is our triangle and let's say the length of this bottom side, that's the base, lets call that 'b'.
And then this is the height, this is the height, right over here.
And then the area is equal to one-half base times height. A = 1/2 b h .
Now this first sentence is telling us that height of a triangle is 4 inches less than the length of the base.
So the height is equal to the base minus 4. That's what the first sentence tells us.
The area of the triangle is 30 inches^2. So if we take one-half the base times height we will get 30 inches^2. Or we can say that 30 inches^2 is equal to one-half times the base times the height.
Now instead of putting that 'h' in for height we know that the height is the same thing as 4 less than
the base. So let's just put that in there.
And then let's see what we get in here.
I'll put this in yellow. We get 30 equals one half b/2 times b-4
Now let's distribute the b, so 30 is equal to b squared over 2- be careful. b/2 times b is just b squared over 2- and then b/2 times -4 is -2b
now just to get rid of this fraction here, let's multiply both sides of the equation by two
So let's multiply that side by 2 and that side by two. On the left hand side you get 60
on the right hand side, 2 times b^2/2 equals b squared, -2b times 2 is -4b
And now we have a quadratic here, and the best way to solve a quadratic is to get all of the terms on
one side of the equation and have them equal 0. So let's subtract 60 from both sides of the equation.
And we get 0 is equal to b squared minus 4 b minus 60. So what we need to do is factor this thing right
now, and then know that if we have the product of some things and that equals zero, that means that either
one or both of those thing need to be equal to zero, so we need factor b squared minus 4b minus 60. So
what we want to find 2 numbers whose sum is -4 and whose product is -60. Now given that the product is
negative, we know that they will have different signs. And this tells us that their absolute value will
be four apart. So let's look at the factors of 60: 1 and 60 are too far apart. If you made one of them
negative, you would get positive 59 or negative 59 as a sum. 2 and 30, still to far apart. 3 and 20,
still to far apart. If you made one of them negative, you would either get negative 17 or positive 17.
Then you could have 4 and 15- still to far apart. If you made one of them negative, you would either
get -11 or positive 11. Then you have 5 and 12- still too far apart, you could either have positive 7
or negative 7. Now you have 6 and 10: now this looks interesting. They are 4 apart, and we want the larger
number to be negative so that their sum is negative. So if we make it 6 and negative 10, their sum will
be negative 4, and their product is -60. So that works. So you can say that this is equal to b+6 times
b-10. Let me be careful. This b over here is different than the b that we are using in the equation. I
just used this b to say look, we are looking for 2 numbers that add up to this second term. It's a different
'b.' I could have used x and y. In fact let me do it that way. now x plus y = -4, and x times y is -60.
so we have b + x times b + y. x is six and y is negative 10. You could also solve this by grouping. We
know that either b + 6 is equal to zero, or b - 10 = 0. If we subtract 6 from both side of the equation
you get b = -6, and if you subtract be from both sides of this equation you get b = 10. The other way
to solve this is break up this -4b into its consitutents. So you could have broken this up into 0 = b
squared, and you could have broken if up into +6b -10b, and then factor is by grouping. Group these first
two terms, group these second two terms. Just add them together. the first one you can factor out a b
to you have b times b + 6, the second one you have factor out a negative 10, to -10 times b + 6 all of
that is equal to zero, now factor out a b + 6. Then you get 0 = b-10 times b+6. We are just factoring
out this out of the expression. Either way, the solutions are b = -6 or b = 10. remember, this is a word
problem. We have to think about whether this makes sense in the context of the actual problem. We are
talking about lengths of triangles, we cannot have a negative length. So we can cross out -6 and we
are left with 1 solution. The only possible base is 10. They say "find the height and the base." So the
base is 10 and the height is 4 inches less, so the height is 6. And then you can verify. The area is
6 times 10 times 1/2, which is 30.