It is common misconception that price levels are dictated purely by the quantity of money out there.
To see why this is not the case, let's imagine an island that has two players in it.
So it has a farmer, who will obviously produce food and it also has, let's call him a landlord/builder,
who will either rent out buildings or can build you more buildings or build themselves more buildings to rent out.
And we are living in a reality where all you need is food and shelter. And let's imagine one reality,
where this island or whatever, this country, whatever you want to call it,
they have not discovered a lot of currencies.
So they only have a little bit of gold.
So maybe the farmer only has a couple of gold coins to start off with
and the landlord/builder also only has a couple of gold coins to start off.
They are very currency poor, only a little bit of gold.
But they are very optimistic. The farmer says hey, you know what, things are looking good landlord,
I want to rent a nice building from you for my family and
I want you to build more buildings. So here take both of these coins
and build me or rent me out something nice. And he gets both coins over here.
And then the landlord/builder says wow, things are good, the farmer seems pretty optimistic.
Farmer, I want you to buy me, I want you to grow me a ton of really good food because things are good.
So here take four coins from me and really grow me a ton of really nice food.
You know stuff that is really hard to grow. So he gets those four coins now.
These are now gone. The farmer doesn't have those anymore.
Now the farmer is feeling really great, really optimistic.
And these are now gone, now the landlord has given them to the farmer.
The farmer is feeling really optimistic and says, landlord, you know what,
I'm feeling even better than I did before. Why don't you build me even a few more buildings.
I want to expand my house even more. But now the landlord is like man, you know,
you already have given me a lot of money and I already have a lot of work to do.
you gotta pay me more, if you want me to work overtime, because that is going to take time away
from my family and all the rest.
And the farmer says, sure. Last time I paid you two gold coins for some buildings and now
I pay you three gold coins for the same number of buildings.
And so he gives three gold coins and all he is going to get for return is what he used
to get for two gold coins.
And if you think about it, the price has gone up for whatever service or product the builder is providing.
And he gives those three gold coins to the landlord/the builder.
And then the builder says, oh you know, things are really good, I'm getting a lot of business
from the farmer, I can get even more food from the farmer.
And he goes to the farmer and says, hey give me what you just gave me that last time
for two gold coins. The farmer says, no you know what, I'm really busy now.
I'm almost tapped up. If you want me to work overtime or expand my facilities,
you gotta give me three gold coins for what I gave you before.
And besides that the cost of my houses has just gone up to three gold coins,
so you have to give me three gold coins now. So the builder says, oh sure, I will give you three gold coins.
So the one thing I want you to notice in this video is, we only started off with two gold coins
for each of these players but because they were really confident, because they kept spending
with each other, because there were a lot of transactions, there was a high velocity of the actual money
that you actually had an increase in prices.