What I want to introduce you to in this video,
is the idea of a Keynesian Cross.
This is one of the tools of analysis of Keynesian thinking.
Which is really the idea that
maybe every now and then the GDP, when it's at
equilibrium, isn't at an optimal state
it's operating well below potential.
And the way that we might be able to get,
if you are a follower of Keynesian thinking,
the way we can get it closer to potential;
closer to full employment is by somehow affecting
aggregate demand in some way.
What we will see is;
we're going to build up our Keynesian cross
analysis based on what we understand from
the consumption function.
So were going to first start thinking about
planned expenditures. Think about what happens
when planned expenditures deviates from
actual output, from actual expenditures.
So right over here. So this is very similiar
to what we have done before, but we're actually
thinking about it in terms of planning.
so lets say we have planned expenditures, expenditures planned.
And we could just write the components of
aggregate expenditures here.
Well you're going to have consumer spending
you're going to have investment,
and i'm going to be careful here, I'm going
to call it planned investment. This is exactly
what firms are looking to produce.
The reason why I differentiate this here is because,
if for whatever reason aggregate expenditure
is less than they expect, then they might
build up inventory, and those inventories
get counted as investments.
So those would be excess inventories above and beyond
planned inventories. If actual demand is higher
than expected, then it might eat into inventories
and when inventories are eaten into
it actually takes away from planned investment.
so you would actually be eating into total investment in that situation.
So that's why I'm going to differentiate
between planned investment, and actual investment.
And then of course you have government spending,
and then finally you have net exports.
And for the sake of analysis of the Keynesian Cross,
and once again this is a super over simplification,
were going to assume that at any given level
of GDP or aggregate output that these are all constant.
That these are not really dependent
on aggregate output or GDP.
Which is of course a huge over-simplification.
So if we were to plot any of these, verses
aggregate income we'd say that they are really a flat line.
So maybe planned investment might look something like that.
maybe government spending would look something like that.
At some level it's pre-planned,
it's kind of exogenous to our model,
it's not dependent in any way,
it's an external factor, assuming it's fixed
it's not dependent on aggregate income.
So government spending would look something like that.
And net exports maybe it looks something like that.
The factor that you can imagine,
cause I said we were going to build on top of the consumption function,
that we are going to assume is driven by aggregate income,
is consumption right over here.
And so the way that this thing will look is, you have.
So let me draw another plot right over here.
We have aggregate income,
that is going to be our independent variable.
And then over here we can just view this as expenditure.
So if we were to just plot consumer spending,
we've seen that before;
especially if we assume a linear consumption function.
So what we studied in the last few videos
these are all linear consumption functions,
and depending on how you write it.
But they all look something like this;
they all have a positive vertical axis intercept,
and they all have an upwards slope that is less then one.
So consumption by itself would look something like this.
This would be consumer spending
as a function of aggregate income.
And if you add all of these constants to it,
then your graph for aggregate planned expenditures,
would look something like this.
So if you added just net exports it would be a little higher.
Because these are constant, at any point you just add this much.
If you add government a little higher then that,
and if you add all of them, including planned investments,
you might get something that looks,
and i'll do it in this color over here,
you might get something that looks like this.
So im just starting off with consumer spending.
I'm using a linear consumption function.
You dont have to but it makes the Keynesian Cross analysis,
a lot more cross like, and easier to analyse.
And then if you add all of what we assume
to be constant things, then aggregate expenditures
is going to be up here.
So this right over here is aggregate planned expenditures,
I should say.
now we know, from the circular flow in the economy,
that when an economy is at equilibrium,
your aggregate output is equal to your aggregate expenditures,
or your aggregate expenditures is equal to your aggregate income.
So really in an equilibrium these two things are going to be equal.
And we can actually plot a line that shows
all the points that those are equal.
That would be a line that has essentially a slope of one.
Where Y is always equal to expenditures.
So it might look something like this,
and this is where the name Keynesian Cross comes from.
Cause essentially you have planned expenditures,
and then right over here you have the equilibrium line,
or what I call the equilibrium line.
Because these are all points where income is equal to expenditure.
So when you look at aggregate planned expenditures.
Or you could even, kind of, view this as aggregate demand,
as a function of aggregate income.
This is the actual point where the economy is at equilibrium.
Where expenditures are actually equal to output.
And actually it's a little skewed the way I drew it
this should acually be a square
actually let me see if I can draw it a little clearer then that
just so it looks like a 45 degree line
so maybe it looks
it shoudl really be a 45 degree line, so that seems a little bit better
so thats the point at which we are at equilibrium
and actually I dont like that cause it makes it a little more difficult to analyse
this should be a line where expenditures should be equal to aggregate income
so ill do it like this,
so that it intersects at a point thats a little easier to analyse
now this is where the Keynesian cross kind of becomes an interesting tool
because we can start to think about a situation
so this is an equilibrium level of GDP
what happens if for whatever reason
aggregate input is higher then that level
so let's think about that scenario
so lets say were over here. let's call that y1
so what is going on over here at y1?
over here the aggregate output,
which is the same thing as aggregate income
is right over here, well this is the actual planned expenditures
is right over here
so all of this excess above the planned demand
is going to be inventories building up
the economy is producing
more then it actually needs, inventories are going to build up
firms are not selling all of their product
and that excess build up in inventory is going to be reflected in investment
so in this case this delta is going to be added
to your planned investment to get what your actual investment will be
and when an economy is at that state
then firms say "Oh my God were building inventories, were not selling our product,
were going to lower our output" so there's
sort of a natural feedback mechanism for the
GDP to go back to equilibrium
and lets think about what happens if were below that equilibrium point
lets say that GDP is right over here
so that's Y2, actually i could write it as a subscript
I wrote it as a super script there
but we can call this Y2
so over here aggregate demand, at this level of output
is more than what is actually being output
people want more goods and services
so this is kind of a deficite of output
and so this shows that people will be digging into
inventories that the existing inventories, or the existing investment
was not enough. Inventories will be contracting.
So if I had a business, say a lemonade stand
I just keep an inventory of 5 cups on hand
if I sell a cup every hour
if people suddenly start buying two cups an hour
my inventory is going to start getting depleted
so this is whats reflected
actual output is below what's demanded
and when firms start seeing that their inventoreis
are getting depleted they say
"Oh my God, I dont want to run out of my goods and services,
let me start producing more"
and when were talking about inventories were really talking about goods
so let me produce more. So output once again again will naturally want to go to
that feedback point
so hopefully that makes a little bit of sense
in the next few videos we are going to be using the
Keynesian Cross to think about how the Kenesian line of reasoning