We're in Nablus, at the archaeological museum,
looking at one of the most famous sculptures from all the antiquity.
It was discovered in the Renaissance during archaeological excavations in Rome
of the Baths of Caracalla.
This is the so called Farnese Hercules and it gets that name,
because it was excavated by the Farnese Family.
They've been looking for building materials to take from ancient sited to build a new palace.
But what they found in the Baths was an extraordinary array of ancient sculptures.
We could reconstruct the original site for this collossal sculpture.
There were mosaic floors, walls made of different coloured marble.
An incredibly luxurious bathing complex, used by thousands of Romans every day.
And it was decorated with hundreds of sculptures, many of them collossal, like this one.
These were really complex structures, these bathing facilities.
They were the baths themselves, some were cold, some were hot,
there were rooms for transition from ane temperature to another,
there were places, where one could exercise.
And this sculpture makes perfect sense in this environment.
This is a place, where you would go to work out, or you would go to exercise.
And you could look at this wildly muscular figure and have a bit of a goal.
Many of the sculptures that were found in the Baths of Caracalla
were not the typical ideal athletic copies of Greek sculptures, that we think of,.
but they were especially bulky, like the Hercules that we see here.
Well, we know that some successful Greek athletes would sometimes dedicate sculptures to Hercules
in a way thanking him for their successes.
He was a symbol of strength and hero.
And you can see that here, but there's also irony in Lysippos' treatment,
because even as we see this wildly powerful figure, this incredible musculature,
we also see a figure, that is exhausted.
He really is. He leans almost his full weight on a club,that is propped up under his arm.
And so right, there is light irony between the brut strength of his muscles
and the === of his pose.