Let's say we have two people in identical jobs
Person A and Person B
and this past year they both got paid in their identical jobs
they got paid $350,000 in salary
now let's assume that Person A has no deductions
so they just calculate their taxes
and for the sake of simplicity I'm just going to make up a number
I'm not going to go through. . .
and especially because the tax code changes every year,
let's just say their regular taxes are $150,000
150,000 in regular taxes, regular taxes
when you just file taxes, the straight. . . well not the straightforward but just the regular way
let's say Person B on the otherhand, even though they have the exact same job
they donate a bunch to charity
they have all of these deductions, they have all of these things that they can write off on their income
and so Person B's taxable income, let's say that it goes down
with all of these deductions, it goes down to $200,000
and on that taxable income of $200,000
Person B has to pay $70,000 in regular taxes
and once again, I'm just making up simple numbers
just for the sake of simplicity
I'm not actually figuring out exactly what Person B's taxes are
$70,000 in regular taxes
Now, the US government or the IRS says