In the last video
we got some practice
adding what we could consider smaller numbers.
For example, if we added 3 + 2
we could imagine that if
maybe I had three lemons -- 1, 2, 3 --
and if I were to add to those three lemons
maybe two lime-- Is it lime or limes?
Let's just -- Well, two green lemons --
or two more tart pieces of fruit
How many-- how much tart, sour fruit do I have now?
Well, we learned in the last video
we have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 pieces of fruit.
So 3 + 2 = 5.
And we also saw that
that's the exact same thing as if
we add 2 + 3.
And I think that makes sense.
Because this is the same thing as
starting with -- Maybe you have 2 lemons
and you add 3 limes to it.
You're still going to end up with 5 pieces of fruit.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
Just like that.
So it doesn't matter what order you add in.
You're still going to get five.
And this way of thinking about addition
I view as the counting way of thinking about addition
The other thing we saw in the last video
is the number line version
And they're essentially the same thing
So we could draw a line.
And all a number line is
it lists all of the numbers in order.
It lists all of the numbers.
And you can actually go as high as you need to go
You could go up to a million, gazillion, trillion.
We won't do that.
I wouldn't have space or time in this video to do it.
And you actually can go as low as possible.
We'll start at 0, assuming --
In future videos, I'll tell you
about numbers smaller than 0.
Maybe you can think about what that might mean tonight.
But let's start at 0, and 0 means nothing.
If I have 0 lemons, it means I have no lemons.
So: 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11 --
Let's go pretty high.
12 --
That way I can reuse the number line.
13, 14.
I could keep on going
But maybe 14 will be enough for this video
But let's use a number line
for these addition problems up here.
So in the last video -- just as a bit of a review --
you can view 3 + 2 as starting at 3 --
and then adding 2 to it.
Or going two greater than 3.
And just going greater --
or adding on the number line --
is just moving to the right -- or moving up by two.
So let's move up by two.
I'll do that in this orange color.
So let's go up by 2.
So we started at three and we go up by one.
And then we go up by 2, or we're jumping,
and we end up at 5.
Which is exactly what we got before.
If we have three lemons
we add one lemon, we have four lemons.
We add another lemon, we have 5 lemons --
or limes -- or tart pieces of fruit.
Whatever you might want to say.
And when you look at this version of it --
when you switched the order --
We started at 2
and we're adding 3 objects to it.
In this case, they were lemons or limes.
So we're going to add three to it.
1, 2, 3.
And just like we expected,
we got the same thing.
We got 5 again.
Now what I want to do in this video --
and hopefully this was just a bit of a review --
-- is I want to tackle harder problems.
I want to tackle slightly larger numbers.
And then in the next video --
And in this video I want to just
give you practice dealing
with the slightly larger numbers.
And then, in the next video
we're going to dig a little deeper
and think about what numbers even mean
But let's just get some practice understanding
"How do you actually do the addition problems with larger numbers?"
Let me write it in a nice, soothing, purple color.
Let's say I wanted to add 9 + 3.
Well, there are a couple of ways we could do it.
We could draw circles again.
We could say, let's see, I have --
Maybe I'll draw stars. 1, 2, 3, 4 --
My stars are degrading,
-- 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.
That's 9 stars. And then I add 3 stars to it.
So I add 1, 2, 3 stars.
And then if you were to count
the total number of stars, you would say --
(Let me do that in a different color.)
-- 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12.
I now have 12 stars.
So, you would say that 9 + 3 = 12.
It's equal to 12.
If you looked at the number line --
If you looked at the number line, you're, starting at 9.
Maybe you have 9 stars
and you add 1 star, 2 stars, 3 stars to that.
And you end up with 12 stars.
Which is the exact answer we got before.
So you can do the same process when you start
adding larger numbers, even though that now --
And I want you to notice, the difference now is
our answer has two digits in it.
(And we'll talk more about digits in a future video.)
But all a digit is is a numeral. Right?
It has a 1 and a 2.
That's what 12 is.
I won't go into -- I won't dig too deep into that right now.
I think you're pretty familiar with the number 12.
But what I want to do is --
Now what happens when you start adding more?
When you start adding
two-digit numbers like this?
For example, if I were to add 27 plus -- let's say --
I don't know -- plus15. (27 + 15.)
Now, if you had a lot of time on your hands
and you didn't care about how people judged you
you could draw out 27 circles,
and then draw out another 15 circles and then
count the total number of circles you had.
And that would give you an answer.
Or you could draw a number line
You could draw a number line that
went all the way to whatever 27 + 15 is.
So it's going to be this really, really large number,
but that wouldtake you forever.
So what I'm going to do
is show you a way to
do this type of problem
where you really just have to know your addition
almost have it memorized, or at least
if you don't have it memorized
be able to do something like this for
relatively small numbers.
And by doing it for the relatively small numbers,
you can do the harder problems like this.
So what you do, this is the fun part.
You add, and I'll talk more about
what this means in the future.
You look at each of the digits.
So we call this place, the rightmost place
we call that the ones place.
And why do we call that the ones place?
Because 27 is 20 and 7 ones.
It's twenty plus seven.
It's twenty plus seven ones.
You could view it as it's twenty plus seven pennies.
And this place right here is called the tens place.
Now why is it called the tens place?
I mean there's a two right there.
It's the place that's called the tens place.
So putting a two here means two tens.
The number twenty, that's two tens.
If I have one dime and you gave me another dime
I now have two dimes, and that's twenty cents
So that's what the tens place is.
I don't want to confuse you
I just want to show you how to
do these problems right now.
We'll dig a little bit deeper in future videos.
But I just want to give you that idea.
But the way to do these problems is
you look at the numbers in the ones place
and add those up first.
So you say, OK, I'm not going to worry about
this whole thing right now.
Let me just add the seven and the five.
So I'm going to add the seven and the five.
And if you don't know what that is
hopefully you'll be able to do that
in your head fairly shortly
-- you could look
at the number line.
Let's look at the number line here.
So if you add seven
if you take seven, and you add five to it.
-- 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 --
We end up at twelve.
Or if you started at five and added seven
you'd also end up at twelve.
So let's write that down.
We know that 7 + 5 = 12.
So what we do is we say 7 + 5 is equal to
-- and now this is a new thing.
It might be a little bit of a mystery
magical thing for you right now.
And in future videos I'll explain to you why this works.
We write -- we want to write the 12.
7 + 5 is 12. But we just write the 2 here
and we carry the 1.
12. one, two
Well, we wrote the 2 there,
but we put the 1 up here, right?
And the reason --
(I'll give you a simple reason for doing that right now.)
(I'll give you a better reason in the future.)
-- Is that you only had space to put one digit here
and twelve is a two-digit number
so we had to think of some
other place to put that 1.
If you really want to think about it even more
12 is the same thing
as 10 + 2, right?
That's the same thing as 12.
So if we say 7 + 5, that's the same thing as 12
which is the same thing as two ones. Right?
Two 1s. 2 pennies, plus 1 dime.
Plus 1 ten. Plus 1 dime.
So we put that 1 dime in the 10s place.
So we really just said 7 + 5 is one 10 plus two 1s.
Or 1 dime plus 2 pennies.
If that confuses you, just write, just say,
well I just write the 1s digit of the 2 there
and I carry the 1.
And then you do the exact same thing in the 10s place.
You add the 1 plus the 2 plus the 1.
So 1 + 2 -- Let's do that on a number line.
This is fun.
So let's see.
1 + 2.
Let's start -- let me do it in a vibrant color.
(Let me do it in this magenta.)
So we start at one.
We're going to add two to it.
1 + 2.
We take that 1 from our 12..
1 + 2. So you go up 1, 2.
You end up at 3.
Then you're going to add up another one.
So you add another 1.
You're going to end up at 4.
So you ended up at 42.
And this was pretty neat, right?
Because we didn't have to
draw a number line all the way to 42.
And we'd didn't have to draw 42 objects.
Just by knowing what 7 + 5 was
and by knowing what 1 + 2 + 1 was
we were able to figure out that
27 + 15 = 42.
Let's do another example.
Maybe I'll do a little bit of a simpler example.
Let's say I had 78 + 3.
We do the exact same thing as before.
We just look at the 1s place only.
So we look at 8 + 3.
What's 8 + 3?
Hopefully, we can do that
in our heads at this point.
But let's just think about it.
8 + 1 = 9.
8 + 2 = 10.
8 + 3 is going to be equal to 11.
You could do that on the number line
if it makes it easier to visualize for you.
So 8 + 3 = 11.
So what we do here, we just have 8 + 3 = 11.
Put this one right here, put that there
and carry the other one.
Because eleven is
one ten -- one dime -- plus one penny.
That's eleven.
And then we add the tens place.
1 dime plus 7 dimes is equal to 8 dimes.
So 78 + 3 = 81.
And now there's one thing I want to show you.
You don't always have to carry numbers like that.
Only if the answer to one of these
has more than one digit in it.
11 is a two-digit number.
So, for example, if I have 56 + 2.
Here, I could just say 6 + 2 is 8. Right?
Hopefully, we're getting good practice at this.
So 6 + 2 = 8.
And then, I don't have anything to add this 5 to.
So, I just bring the five down here.
So 56 + 2 = 58.
Just like that.
And this is one you actually
could have drawn on the number line.
It wouldn't have been too hard.
So, if you were to draw the number line like that,
0 would be way off to the left some place.
But let's say I had 50, no I think you'd have 49
you could keep going to the left
but you have 51, 52 --
Actually let me start a little higher than that.
Because I'm going to run out of space.
Let me start at maybe 55, 56, 57, 58, 59 --
And I could go in both directions -- keep going.
But if we start at fifty-six right there and we add two
We go up one, we go up two.
We end up at 58.
So just like, that we're able to do that problem.
I'll see you in the next video.