We're asked to determine a function
of the form y = a sign bx or y= a cosign represented by the graph below
so we need to figure out maybe what a's are or maybe what the b's are maybe this is a sign or a cosign
function, so lets see what clues there are,
so the first thing I notice is that whatever this function is, when x = 0
it does not = 0, it is = to -2 so based on that
do you think based on what we know on sign and cosign function do you think this is going to be able to form
y is = to a sign of the x or of the form that y is = to a cosign of the x
without even knowing what the a's and b's are do you think this is going to be a sign function or a cosign function
well, lets think about what the sign of 0 is, if you take sign of 0, we already know
that is = to 0, what is cosign of 0
cosign of 0 is = to 1 so it would be very hard, in this form it would be impossible
to if sign of 0 is 0 to multiply 0 by something to get to -2