99.9...% of mathematicians agree
0.9... equals 1.
If because I said so works for you you can go ahead and do something else now.
Maybe you're like 0.9... equals one?
That's just 0.9...derful!
Otherwise on to reason number 2,
or reason 1.9...
See, it's weird because when we think of the number 1 or 2
in most contexts we mean it as a natural number like 1, 2, 3, 4, 5...
In this sense that the next number after 1 is 2.
9.9... may equal 10 but you wouldn't say you had 9.9... lords-a-leaping
In the same way you wouldn't say you had 9.75 plus a quarter lord-a-leaping.
Lords, leaping or otherwise come in natural numbers.
So what does this statement mean?
0.9... is the same as 1?
It looks pretty different,
but it equals one in the same way that a half equals 0.5.
They have the same value.
You can philosophize over wether, if 1 is the loneliest number,
0.78 plus 0.22 is just as lonely.
but there is no mathematical doubt that they have the same value.