That entire set of 23 human chromosomes
is called a genome.
The human genome is composed of
3 billion base pairs.
Variation at a single base pair is called a SNP,
or single nucleotide polymorphism.
When the body makes new cells,
it doesn't make many mistakes,
but nobody is perfect.
Sometimes, when the genome is copied, to make a new cell,
a single base pair gets lift out, added, or substituted.
Single base pair substitutions create SNPs.
There're around 10 million SNPs in the human genome,
which account for many of the genetic differences
between you and everyone else on the planet.
Some SNPs account for differences in appearance,
others can affect how we develop diseases,
or respond to drugs.
Most SNPs, however, seemed to lead to
no observable differences between people at all.
Since variance are passed down
from one generation to the next,
the number of differences between your DNA,
and your neighbors can tell you how closely
you're related to each other.