We are in Prado in Madrid and we are looking at large canvas by Francisco Goya.
It is the Family of Charles IV.
Here is a direct reference to Velázquez's Las Meninas.
We can see the artist is actually self-portrait
a bit more in shadow than Velázquez painted themself
behind a large canvas pretty much at the same angel
as one founded in Las Meninas
and of course the royal family array before us
although in this case the king and queen are here not as a reflection in a mirror but directly before us.
I think what distract us today as an unflattering I think we are much more used to real portraits
that have a kind of idealism to it
and here we have a range of that
Some of the figures look more ideal and their poses and their faces and others
but there is certainly a way that the quene herself looks very much I think the way she really looked
and even the king to some extent
as supposed to more idealize, more useful figure.
And I think that Goya is doing something quite extraordinary
by instead pushing those boundaries and the royal family is allowing him to
but well, there is a kind of particularity to the faces and a kind of psychological depth to each of the faces
and striking beauty in terms of representation the children.
The costume cross the free of bodies is spectacular.
The sense of ornamental, the sense of military medals
of the gold and the silver sort of glittering in the light.
You can catch the glistening jewelery if your eye just wonders cross the canvas.
And Goya has ranged that just brilliantly.
Yeah, very very loosely in very inversely way
that is also very reminiscent to Velázquez.
Now, it is interesting that the royal family is looking in the sense back to Velázquez in this portrait
who is in this time quite different.
This is Charles IV not Filip IV.
Spain is in a kind of crisis at this moment.
And you know the French revolution has taken place.
The royal family is cross wondering whether or not they are going to able to maintain order, maintain their rule.
And in fact this family will not be able to.
No, not at all.
Fernando who is seen on the left in the blue is actually collude with Nepolian and Nepolian invasion of Spain
and Nepolian opposite brother on the throne of Spain very soon.
So this is a royal family that does not have much longer to live in this way
and it is hard not to read the enlightenment in a different way
that in the modern world we look upon royal families.
We do not see them as the having that kind of divine right
and a kind of royal lineage and blood line that makes them different from us
in the way they look very human and many of them do
and it is hard not to see that enlightenment thinking in Goya's mind
We know in fact that he was sympathetic with enlightenment and critical with monarchy.
There is certainly a kind of informality that almost feels a bit like disarray in a composition of the figures
different from informality that one finds in Velázquez
but again I think it is interesting that Goya and the royal family are both looking back to that period of stability
and in the sense we try to capture that and a moment
when everybody I think is congruous that Spain is threshold of a moment
when there may be a significant change.