This is the exact same problem
that I did in the last video, but I realized after looking
at the problem that I just mindlessly did the problem.
But there's actually a much simpler way of doing it.
So once again they're telling us to subtract and state the difference
in simplest form.
Now, what I did in the last video is I said, "Okay let's find
a common denominator and then I found it and then I
did the subtraction. But what I could have done
that would have simplified all of the math is that I could
have simplified each of the expressions first.
So let's do that!
So this first expression right over here,
both the numerator and the denominator is divisible
by "m", so let's divide them both by "m".
If you divide the numerator by "m" you get 1
if you divide the denominator by "m", "m"-squared
divided by "m" is just "m". This
second term right over here, both of them,
both the numerator and the denominator are divisible by
"n" to the third power. So let's divide the numerator by
"n" to the third power
you get a 1. You divide the denomintor,
you divide "n" to the fourth by "n" to the third power
you just get an "n".
And so we can rewrite this as 6 over, 6 times 1
so that's just 6, 6 over 7mn, minus 5, 'cause that's just 5 times 1
over 3mn. And this really simplifies the problem.
So let's think about a common denominator over here
So it's gonna be something minus something.
So a common denominator has to be divisible by both 7 and 3,
so the least common multiple of 7 and 3 is 21,
and it has to be divisible by "m" and it has to be divisble by "n"
21mn, and that also takes care of this.
21mn is clearly divisble by 7mn
and it's clearly divisible by 3mn, so it's got the mn
there it's divisible by 3 it's divisible by 7.
So that's our least common multiple, or you could say it's
our common denominator and to get from 7mn to 21mn,
you've gotta multiply by 3. And if you're multiplying
the denominator by 3, you've gotta multiply the numerator
by 3 and you get 3 times 6 is equal to 18,
and to go from 3mn to 21mn, you gotta multiply by 7.
It's over here, you gotta multiply it by 7.
And if you multiply the denominator by 7,
you gotta multiply the numerator by 7, if you don't
want to change the value of the expression.
So 5 times 7 is, is equal to 35
and then, so, this is going to be equal to
18 minus 35, so we have the, let me write it down,
we have a common denominator here of 21mn,
and we're gonna have to calculate 18 minus 35 in the numerator.
I'll just write it over here: 18 minus 35 in the numerator
and 18 minus 35 is negative 17
so we get -17 in the numerator over 21mn, and we are done
and I think that was a good bit simpler
than the way we did it in the last video.