After coursing throughout the blood vessels of our bodies,
a hormone eventually meets a receptor that was created
specifically for it by the target cells it was sent to stimulate.
The way that hormone interacts with the receptor
happens in one of two very characteristic ways.
I want to show you today how that happens.
The first major mechanism of hormone action at the cell
that i'm going to start with, is by secondary messengers.
I'm going to start with secondary messengers because,
historically, they're a little more confusing.
Essentially what's happening is a hormone is binding to a receptor on a cell.
So let me draw a cell and it's receptor.
And I'll draw a hormone binding to it.
The process of that binding, instead of just stimulating the effect,
it sets off this chain reaction that leads to secondary
messengers inside the cell being released.
So let me draw those.
You've got these secondary messengers being released,
and these are actually what is stimulating whatever effect is desired.
Whether that may be insulin being released,
glucose being taken up inside the cell,
or any of the coutless other things taking place in our
bodies that are controlled by hormones.
In order to give you a visual for how this might take place in a cell,
I have pre-drawn some pictures.
So let me pull those in here.
I want you to understand that these drawings are not to scale in any way.
This is the best I can do in explaining the process,
because all of this is happening at the atomic level, and atoms are really tiny.
Anyway, what we have in this picture is a receptor,
I have drawn that in pink, and it's located inside the cell membrane.
This is the phospholipid bi-layer of this cell membrane
and we've got the inside of this cell and the outside.
Then also in the cell membrane, we've got a G protein, and I have drawn that in green.
It's called a G protein because it binds to molecules that include the nucleotide guanine.
Which is the same G from the DNA bases which you might be a little more familiar with.
It's currently bound to a molecule called guanine diphosphate.
We'll see how that changes, but we also have this
adenylate cyclase enzyme that's in the cell membrane.
Remember that enzymes speed up reactions,
so we're going to see how adenylate cyclase speeds up a reaction.
What start's this process off is the hormone is going to bind to the receptor.
It's going to look like that.
You're going to have the hormone bound to the receptor.
Once that hormone binds to the receptor, it's going to change shape.
That's going to allow it to interact with the G protein here.
That looks like this.
What you saw happen as the G protein interacts with
the receptor and hormone complex, it's going to
exchange that GDP that it started with, that guanine diphosphate, for GTP.
Essentially, it is exchanging a guanine bound to two
phosphates for a guanine bound to three phosphates.
What happens is, that enables the G protein to move
through the cell membrane and interact with adenylate cyclase.
That activates adenylate cyclase.
As an enzyme, the activated adenylate cyclase facilitates
the conversion of ATP, which is the energy currency of the cell, into cAMP.
And cAMP stands for cyclic adenosine monophosphate.
We've taken this ATP, Adenosine triphosphate, and created cyclic adenosine monophosphate.
We also have the additional two phosphates.
It's the cAMP molecule that activates the protein inside the cell,
who's effect is really being targeted by the hormone in the first place.
Eventually the system resets, but not before several adenylate cyclase
enzymes were activated, resulting in a lot of cAMP being produced.
We call this signal amplification.
What I mean by signal amplification is that,
in theory, one hormone can bind to a receptor.
That process can set off a chain reaction that leads to a lot of cAMP being produced.
It can mean that less hormone is required to, ultimately,
activate the protein or the effect that's being desired.
Secondary messengers are a means in which hormones act on the cell.
But, really, if I'm being honest, this effect happens differently for a lot of cells,
and all of of the mechanisms of secondary messenger
hormone action aren't known right now.
Also, there are a lot of secondary messengers other than cAMP.
Really, the take away, is that, for the majority of the hormones in your body,
binding to the cells surface activates series of reactions
that initiate a response inside the cell.
It's very similar to the use of a phone service provider.
Because we, as people-- let me draw us.
Because we are unable to communicate directly with people sometimes--
because of separation or convenience or lack of efficiency.
We use a phone service to project our voice to them through a phone conversation.
Through a phone conversation we'll direct our voice to people
that we want to communicate with, or maybe we use the delivery of a text message.
A text message will trasmit some intended message that we have
for people that we can't communicate directly with.
That's very similar to how secondary messengers assist hormones
that can't communicate directly with a receptor inside a cell.
Peptide hormones and catecholamines,
both of which can't cross the cell membrane,
use secondary messangers to communicate.
The other method of hormone action on a cell is as a primary messanger.
Certain hormones, like steroids and thyroid hormones, can cross the cell membrane.
This eliminates this entire middle man system that we set up before.
Let me pull in another cell membrane.
The hormone crosses the cell membrane and binds to a receptor
that's located in either the cytosol or the nucleus.
We could imagine a nucleus, there might be DNA inside,
but when the hormone binds to the receptor
that's either in the cytoplasm, or inside the nucleus,
that binding process is going to directly affect transcription in the nucleus,
or translation in the cytoplasm of the protein that's being activated by the hormone.
This process has quite a few less moving parts than the secondary messenger system did.
Again, it stems back to the fact that these are steroid and thyroid hormones
that are typically lipid bases and are capable of
crossing through the cell membrane all on their own.
They don't need all of that extra machinery set up for them.
Anyway these are both primary messengers and secondary messengers.
Those are the two main processes by which hormones act on the cell they are created to target.