what i want to do first is just
show you what the angle bisector theorem is
and then we'll actually
prove it for ourselves
so i just have an arbitrary triangle right over here
triangle A, B, C
and what im going to do is im going to
draw an angle bisector
for this angle up here we could have done it with any
of the three angles but i'll just do this one
it'll make our proof a little bit easier
so im just gonna bisect this angle, angle ABC
so lets just say that that's the angle bisector of angle ABC
And so this angle right over here is equal to this angle right over here
And let me call this point down here
let me call it point D
the angle bisector theorem
tells us that the ratio between the size that aren't this bisector
so when i put this angle bisector here it created two smaller triangles
out of that large one
the angle bisector theorem tells us that the ratios between the other
sides of these two triangles that we now created
are going to be the same
so it tells us that the ratio of AB
to AD is going to be equal to the ratio of BC to - you could say
to CD,so the ratio of - i'll color code it - the ratio of -
that, which is this, to this, to this
is going to be equal
to the ratio of this -which is that- to this
right over here
to CD - which is that over here
so it kind of - once you see the ratio of that to that
is going to be the same as the ratio of that to that
so that's kind of a cool result
but you cant just accept it on -on- faith
because its a cool result!
you want to prove it to ourselves
and so you could imagine right over here
we have some ratio set up
so we're gonna prove it using similar triangles
and unfortunate for us
these two triangles right here -
aren't necessarily similar!
we cant really
we know that these two angles
are congruent to each other
but we dont know whether this angle
is equal to that angle
or that
we dont know we cant make any statements like that
so in order to actually set up this type of a statement
we'll have to construct
maybe another triangle!
that will be similar to one of these
right over here
and one way to do it-
-would be-
to draw another line
and this is a bit of
this proof wasn't obvious to me the first time
that i thought about it
so dont worry if its not obvious to you
is that what happens is if we can
continue this bisector - this angle bisector
right over here
so lets just continue it
it just keeps going
on and on and on
and lets also maybe we can construct a similar
triangle to this triangle over here
if we draw a line that's parallel
to AB down here
so lets try to do that
So i'm just gonna say
well you know - you could always find
if C is not on AB you can always find a point
that goes through or a line that goes through C
that is parallel
to AB
so lets just -by definition- lets just
create another line right over here
and lets say lets call this point
right over here F
and lets just pick this line in such a way
that FC is parallel to AB
so this is parallel to that
- right over there so FC is parallel to AB
and we can just construct it that way
and now we have some interesting
things and we did it that way so that we can make
these two triangles would be similar to each other
so lets see that - lets see what happens
so before we even think about similarity
lets think about some of the angles
or what we know about some of the angles here
we know that we have alternate interior angles
so just think about these two parallel lines
so i can imagine that AB keeps going like that
FC keeps going like that
and line BD right here is a transversal
then whatever this angle is
this angle is going to be as well
for alternate interior angles
which we've talked a lot about
when we first talked about angles with transverals
and all of that
so these two angles are going to be
the same
but this angle and this angle are also going to be
because this angle and that angle
are the same
this is a bisector and because this is a bisector
we know that angle ABD is the same
as angle DBC
so whatever this angle is - that angle is
and so is this angle
and that gives us kind of
an interesting result
because here we have
a situation where if we look at this larger triangle
BFC - we have two base angles that are the same
which means this must be an isosceles triangle
so BC - must be the same as FC
so that was kinda cool
we just used the transversal
and the alternate interior angles
to show that these are isosceles
and that BC and FC are the same thing
and that could be useful
because we know that
we want to - we have a feeling
that this triangle and this triangle
are going to be similar
we haven't proven it yet
but how will that help us get something
about BC up here?
but we just showed that BC and FC
are the same thing
so this is going to be the same thing
as what we wanna prove it
and if we can prove that FC - the ratio
of AB to AD is the same thing
as the ratio of FC to CD were gonna be there
because BC - we just showed - is equal to
FC
but lets not start with the theorem
let's actually get to the theorem
so FC is parallel to AB
able to set up these - this one - isosceles triangle
show these sides are congruent
now lets look at some of the other angles
here - and then we'll make ourselves
feel good about it
but we have this -
- if we look at triangle ABD
so this triangle right over here
and triangle FDC
we already established
that they have one
set of angles
that are the same
and then they also both
- ABD has this angle
right over here
which is going to be
which is a vertical angle
with this one
over here
so they're congruent
and we know if two
tringles have two angles
that are the same
- actually the third ones going
to be the same one as well
or you could say by the
angle - angle similarity postulate
these two triangles are similar
so let me right that down
you wanna make sure you get the corresponding sides right
we now know by angle - angle
and im gonna start at the green angle
that triangle B - and then the blue angle
BDA is similar to triangle
so once again lets start with the green angle -
- F then go to the blue angle FDC
and here we want to eventually get to the
angle bisector theorem
so we wanna look at the ratio between
AB and AD - similar triangles - either you could find
the ratio between corresponding sides
are going to be the same
on similar triangles
or you could find the ratio between
two sides of a similar triangle
and compare them to the ratio of the same
two corresponding sides on the other similar triangle
and they should be the same
so by similar triangles we know that
the ratio of AB
and this by the way - was by
angle - angle similarity
wanna right that down
so now that we know
that they're similar
we know that the ratio of AB to AD
is going to be equal to
and we could even look here
for the corresponding sides
the ratio of AB
the corresponding side is
gonna be CF
its going to equal CF
over AD - AD is the same thing
as CD - over CD
and so we know that the ratio of
AB over AD is equal to CF over CD
but we just proved to ourselves
because this is an isosceles triangle
that CF is the same thing as BC
right over here
so CF is the same thing as BC
and then we're done!
we just proven AB over AD
is equal to BC over CD
so there's kinda two things
we have to do here
- one - construct this other triangle
that allowed us
assuming this was parallel
that gave us two things
that gave us another angle
to show that they're similar
and also
allowed us to establish
- sorry - I have a - something stuck in my throat -
so we're able to
using - constructing this triangle here
we're able to both show its a similar
and to construct this larger
isosceles triangle to show
look if we can find the ratio between
two sides of this triangle
and this one
then that's going to be the ratio
of this - if we can find
the ratio of this side to this side
its the same as the ratio
of this side to this side
that's analogues to showing
that the ratio of this side to this side
is the same
as BC to CD
and we are done.