When the Federal Reserve does traditional Open Market Operations
what they do is the Fed over here
will literally print money, so it prints money
it doesn't necessarily have to be cash,
it could be electronic money,
and it uses that money to buy usually short-term treasury securities
in the open market. That's why it's called open market operations.
So in exchange it gets treasury securities.
Treasuries. Now the whole purpose of this,
it does increase demand for treasuries,
and therefore increase the price on treasuries,
and lower the interest rate,
but the main point is is it takes this printed money
and it puts it in the banking system.
Because it buys treasuries, just from people or from banks or from institutions,
and then those people take that cash
that they just got for these treasuries,
and they'll deposit it in banks.
So they'll go and they'll deposit it in maybe bank 1 over here,
then over here in bank 2,
and since there's more money in bank 1 and bank 2
you have the supply of money going up
supply going up
and also the demand for reserves is going up
this cash right here, these are reserves.
These are reserves. So you have the demand for reserves going down.
Maybe before this money entered the system,
maybe bank 2 was running low on reserves,
but now people have deposited money in bank 2
so bank 2 doesn't need it as much.
So if you have the supply of money going up
you have the demand for money going down
and in particular I'm talking about reserves,
I'm talking about base money right over here
then the overnight borrowing rate between banks
will go down. The price of money will go down,
that's what the federal funds rate is, it's the target rate,
so I'll say Fed Funds Rate,
it's the target rate that the Fed sets for the
overnight borrowing of reserves between banks,
that's the Federal Funds Rate, and it will go down
and that's how the Fed tries to set the Federal Funds Rate.
Now, fast forward to a situation like we are right now
and the Federal Funds Rate is already at zero.
But the Fed still wants to pump more money into the economy
and it wants to do it in a more directed way
so now what it's doing is it's still printing money
but it's using that money to buy other things
it could buy longer-term debt,
so it could buy longer-duration treasuries,
longer, so things that are maybe going to
maybe 10 year treasury bonds, or further out
than even that. Or, it could even buy completely
different assets, it could maybe buy
mortgage backed securities,
and the point here isn't just to increase the money supply
the point in quantitative easing is maybe to kind of
smooth over what's happening in certain parts of the market
and so they thing that there's log jam in the
mortgage backed security market
that's why they're participating there.
So this right over here, that is
Quantitative Easing.