Electronegativitiy is probably the most important concept to understand in organic chemistry
We are gonna use the definition of Linus Pauling in his book about the nature of a chemical bond
So Linus Pauling says that electronegativity refers to
the power of an atom in a molecule to attract the electons to itself
So, if I am looking at the molecule and going to compare it to two atoms in that molcule
and going to compare carbon with oxygen in terms of the electronegativity
and to do that I need to look over here right on the periodic table which shows the elements
most commonly used in the organic chemistry
And then in blue, it gives us the Pauling scale for electronegativity
So, Linus Pauling actually calculated the electronegativity values for elements and
put them into table and that allows us to comopare different elements in terms of
their electronegativities. For example, we are concerned with carbon which has an electrogativity
value of 2.5 and compare that to Oxygen which has an electronegativity value of 3.5
So oxygen is more electronegative than carbon and the definition tell us that
the oxygen is more electronegative and it has greater power to attract electrons to itself than carbon does
So, think about the covalent bond between carbon and oxygen atoms that is shared
It is shared unequally because oxygen is more electronegative
Oxygen is going to pull those electrons in red closer to itself
But since electrons are negatively charged, the oxygen is going to get a little bit more negative charge
and that's what we call partial negative charge on it
And that is represented by lower case greek letter delta
And so the oxygen is partially negative, it's pulling the electrons towards itself
Another way to show the movement of those electrons in red would be this arrow here
So the arrow points in the direction of the movement of the elctrons in red
So, carbon is loosing some of those elctrons in red. Carbon is loosing electron is electron density
and carbon is losing a little bit of negative charge
So, carbon used to be neutral but since it is loosing a bit of negative charge,
this carbon ends up being partially positive
The carbon is partially positive and oxygen is partially negative
That's a polarized situation, a little bit of negative charge on one side
and a little bit of positive charge on the other side
So, it's still a covalent bond but it's a polarized covalent bond due to the difference in electronegativity
Few more examples here will show the difference in electronegativity
So, if I think about the molecule that has two carbons in it
and I am thinking about what happens to electrons in red
Well, for this example each carbon has same value for electrongeativity
So, carbon on left has a value of 2.5, the carbon on the right has a value of 2.5
That's a difference in electronegativity of zero which means that the electrons in red
are not going to move towards any carbon, they are going to stay in the middle
where they can be shared between the two atoms
So, it's a covalent bond but there is no polarity created here since there is no difference in electrongativity
We call this a non-polar covalent bond like that
Let's do another example. Let's compare carbon to hydrogen
So, if I have a molecule and I have a bond between carbon and hydrogen and I want to know
what happens to the electrons in red
we have seen that carbon has an electronegativity of 2.5 and we go up here to hygrogen
which has a value of 2.1. So that's a difference of 0.4
So, there is a difference in electronegativity between those atoms but it's a very small one
So, we consider the bond between carbon and hydrogen to still be a non-polar covalent bond
Right, let's go ahead and put the example we did above and compare the elctronegativity of carbon and oxygen
Carbon had an electronegativity value of 2.5 and oxygen had a value of 3.5 for a difference of 1
and that's enough to have a polar covalent bond
Polar covalent bond between carbon and oxygen
The elctrons in red are pulled close to oxygen giving it a partial negative charge
and since the electron density is moving awat from carbon, it gets a partial positive charge
So, we can see that if there's a difference in electronegativity of 1, it's considered to be
a polar covalent bond and if difference is 0.4, it's considered to be a non-polar covalent bond
So, somewhere in between them must be the difference between a non-polar and a polar covalent bond
Most textbooks will tell you approximately somewhere 0.5 range
So if the difference is greater than 0.5, you can go ahead and consider it a polar covalent bond
and it it is less than 0.5, we consider it to be a non polar covalent bond
Now, I shouuld point out that we are using Pauling scale of electronegativity here and
so these numbers are not absolute, it's more the relative differences and
it's relative differences in electronegativity that we care the most about
Let's compare oxygen to hydrogen, let's think about what happens to the electrons between oxygen and hydrogen
We've already seen the electronegativity values for both of these elements,
oxygen had a value of 3.5 and hydrogen 2.1, so that's a difference of 1.4
and so that's a polar covalent bond. Since oxygen is more elctronegative that hydrogen,
the elctrons in red are going to move close to oxygen
So, oxygen is going to get partial negative charge and hygrogen partial positive charge like that
Let's do carbon and lithium now
If I draw a bond between carbon and lithium, once again we are concerned with two electrons
between carbon and lithium
the electronegativity value of carbon is 2.5 and we find that of Lithium to be 1