[MUSIC]
What I want to do in this
video is try to give a
reasonable understanding of the
different players involved
that issue and process
your credit cards.
So let's start off with
the processors.
Sometimes you could say that the
network or the processors
are the people that maintain the
credit card networks and
the examples of those are Visa,
MasterCard, American
Express, Discover.
And what they do is they
essentially maintain networks
of IT and policies
that connect a
bunch of banks together.
But for just the sake of this
video, we'll do a very
simple-- so let's say that this
is network one, maybe
that's Visa.
Maybe this right here is network
two, this right here
could be MasterCard.
And right now the networks are
just circles, but you'll see
that they're networks as I build
out this explanation.
Now let's say that I'm
some bank out there.
Let me call myself Bank A.
And I decided, you know what?
It would be good for my business
for me to issue a
credit card.
I could extend credit to my
customers, they'll pay me
interest, maybe I'll make some
fees off of that and it'll be
a good business for my bank.
So I go up to, let's say, Visa
and I say, hey, can I be a
member of your network?
Visa has some policies and if
you're, I guess, a legitimate
bank and you agree to all those
policies, you'll become
a member of that network.
So I've joined that network, and
I'm of course not the only
person on that network, there's
tons of other banks on
that network.
So that could be Bank B, this
could be Bank C, this could be
Bank D and, of course, each of
these are networks, so they
all have their own member
banks on them.
That's MasterCard's network
right there.
And so in this situation, let's
say I'm a customer of
Bank A, and they say, do you
want a credit card and I say
sure, that'll be convenient.
I don't like carrying
cash in my pocket.
So give me a credit card.
And they'll issue a credit
card that looks
something like this.
I think we've all seen credit
cards, it will say Bank A
really big up at the top.
I'll have a credit card number
that's unique to me.
My name will be there, some type
of maybe expiration date,
and then here in the bottom
right corner, they're going to
say what network
I'm a part of.
In this case, it
would be Visa.
A credit card issuer over here
would say MasterCard or if it
was American Express, they'd put
American Express here and
maybe there's some type
of a hologram.
So great, I have a
credit card here.
I think we all have a general
sense, I could use it and then
I'll build a balance.
And then in the future I could
pay off that balance to this
bank or I could carry a balance
and they'll charge me
interest, which is usually
reasonably high interest, so I
want to pay it off
fairly quickly.
But how does this actually
work in the
context of a network?
So let's say I go to the local
grocery store, let me draw
that in orange.
So let's say I go to some
grocery store over here, I'll
say G for grocery.
And I buy a $100 worth of
groceries and I want to pay
with my newly-issued
credit card.
Let me write this down, this
is the issuing bank.
I go to the grocery store and
I say, hey, I'd like to pay
with a credit card.
The grocery store, if they
accept credit cards, they need
to have some relationship with
another bank some place on
this Visa network in order for
them to accept a Visa card.
So let's say that they have a
relationship with Bank B over
here, this would be the merchant
bank or we could say
the retailer's bank or, it's
often in credit card lingo
called the acquiring bank
or the acquirer.
You might wonder why they
called it the acquirer.
It's called the acquirer because
this is the player
that goes out and goes to each
of the merchants and says hey,
right now you only accept cash
or you'll only accept American
Express, wouldn't be great if
you also accepted Visa or
MasterCard?
That way you'll have more appeal
to more customers and,
you know, it'll be more
convenient for customers, and
every time a transaction happens
we'll just take a
little bit of a cut of
that transaction.
And so they go out and acquire
different retailers.
This was the grocer, maybe Bank
B goes off and acquires
the shoemaker.
Maybe he goes and he gets the
tailor on the network.
These are all different
retailers who will now all of
a sudden accept Visa because
their bank, their merchant
bank, is a member of
the Visa network.
Likewise, it could have been
a member of the MasterCard
network, it doesn't matter.
This is the processor and
this is their network.
Now, this guy would, in this
context, he would accept Visa.
So I would give them my Visa
card and the first process is
called authorization.
And that's literally to check
whether I'm good for the
money, whether this card is
valid to buy $100 worth of
say, groceries.
So when I swipe the card or
when the grocer swipes the
card, it's going to send a
message from that little unit,
from that point of sale unit,
to the acquiring bank.
That's going to be forwarded to
Visa, then visa will say,
oh, that's Bank A's card, and
it'll give the number to Bank
A on their own proprietary
network.
Then Bank A will look into their
database, and say, oh
yeah, Sal has got $1,000
of credit.
He hasn't used any of it,
he is good for it.
I authorize that transaction.
That message goes back through
the network to Bank B and so
then we get authorized.
And then the transaction goes
forward and eventually, you
know, as you could imagine,
you can't just authorize a
transaction and then I walk
away with the groceries.
At some point this guy here
expects to get his money back
for giving me the groceries.
He expects to get $100 back.
And that $100 is going
to come from Bank A.
But they're not going to get
a complete $100, because
obviously each of
these players,
they're providing a service.
This guy, he's plugged
into the network and
he's offering credit.
The network operator or the
processor is offering their
network, and there's other
services they might provide
for security mechanisms. If they
say, hey, Sal lives in
Chicago, but all of a sudden
he's buying $100 worth of
groceries in Salzburg or some
place that would seem
unlikely, then it might send
some type of warning trigger.
Some people might have their
own security mechanisms.
But they're all providing
a service.
This guy is going out there,
he might be providing the
actual point of sale terminals,
the actual network.
So they're all going to get a
little bit of a cut of things.
And so out of the $100 worth of
groceries, there will be a
2%-- and it's not always 2%,
that's a round number, but it
also is a ballpark not
completely outlandish relative
to what tends to be the case.
So of that $100 that this guy, I
guess, could have gotten for
his groceries, he has to pay
a 2%, or in this case, $2--
that's 2% of $100-- he's got to
pay a $2 discount rate to
his acquiring bank.
And you might say, gee, the
acquirer, that's great.
They got $2, they got 2%
of all of these guys'
transactions, but of course
they're going to have to share
it with these other
people up here.
And actually the bulk of
it ends up with Bank A.
So of this $2-- and I'm doing it
in roundabout numbers-- so
now we're going to split up
the $2, Bank A is going to
get, let's just say, $1.70.
And these aren't that far off
from what the real numbers
might be, and they change and
they depend on the banks and
the network and all of that and
the networks might change
their rates.
$1.70 goes to Bank A.
So the issuing bank, besides
now that I have a credit
balance, it'll be able to charge
interest on it, it also
got $1.70 for that
transaction.
That $1.70 of the $2, this is
called an interchange fee.
And it generally gets set by
the individual networks,
although the networks don't
share in that interchange fee.
The just say our standard
interchange fee is x percent
of transactions plus, I don't
know, $0.10 and that's what
Bank B is going to
pay to Bank A.
So it's essentially Bank A's cut
of the discount rate, of
the $2 this guy is charging.
That guy.
And then the network, they make
their money in several
ways but, in general, they
make money off of every
transaction as well.
So in this situation, they make
roughly about 1/1000 of
the transaction or 0.1%.
So in this example, $0.10 of
this discount rate that this
guy charged would go to the
processor or the network.
So every time you transact,
the processor gets a small
fraction of your actual purchase
and then this guy
will be left with-- well,
let's see: $1.70, $0.10,
$1.80, we're coming from $2,
this guy is going to be left
with $0.20.
So when the whole transaction
gets settled, which
essentially means everyone
gets the money
they need to get.
This bank is going to send
Visa's settlement bank $100
minus the $1.70 that it gets
to keep as part of its
interchange fee.
So it's going to send Visa, what
is that, $98.30 to Visa.
Visa will keep $0.10 of it,
send it to the acquirer.
So the acquirer is going
to get $98.20.
And then the acquirer is going
to keep $0.20 for himself and
give the retailer $98.
So my numbers aren't exact,
but I want to give you the
general idea of how
all this works.
So in order for this retailer to
be able to use all of this
infrastructure out there, he
essentially had to pay 2% of
the actual transaction.
That's always not going to be
2%, but it gives you a nice
round figure.
So this guy benefits because he
gets access to a network,
it's convenient for the
customers, this guy obviously
is getting some type of fee.
The more retailers he signs on
or the more retailers he
acquires, the more cuts
of transactions
he's going to make.
Visa makes a small cut on many,
many, many, many, many
transactions, so that's where
they make their money and they
obviously have to use some of
that money to support all of
this infrastructure.
And then Bank A is going to
make that interchange fee,
which was the bulk of really
that discount rate, that
retailer discount rate, not
related at all to the federal
funds discount rates.
And then, of course, they
extended credit to me, so that
$100 might not be paid
immediately.
They might be able charge me
15% to 20%, an annualized
percentage rate interest, on
that money until I pay it off.
And of course I have some type
of minimum balance to pay.
So hopefully that explains
things a little bit.
I'll see you in the
next video [MUSIC]