What is the average rate of change of y(x)
over the interval -5 < x < -2?
So this is x = -5.
When x = -5, y(x) = 6.
And when x = -2, y(x) = 0.
So to figure of the average rate of change –
so the average rate of change of y(x) with respect –
and we can assume it’s with respect to x –
with respect to x –
And let me make that a little bit neater.
– with respect to x …
This is going to be the change in y(x) over that interval
over the change in x over that interval.
And the shorthand for 'change' is this triangle symbol ‘delta.’
Delta y –
I’ll just write y.
I could write delta y(x).
It’s delta y –
– change in y over our change in x.
That’s going to be our average rate of change
over this interval.
So how much did y change over this interval?
So y went from a 6 to a 0.
So let's say that this is –
We can kind of view this as our end point, right over here.
So this is our 'end' and this is our 'start.'
And we could have done it the other way around,
and we would [have gotten an identical] result.
Since this is higher up on the list,
let’s call this the 'start.'
And this is – the x is a lower value.
We'll call that our 'start.' This is our 'end.'
So we start at 6.
We end at 0.
So our change in y is gong to be -6.
We went down by 6 in the y direction.
It's -6. You could say that's a 0 - 6.
And our change in x –
well, we were at -5, and we go up to -2.
We increased by 3.
So we increased by 3.
So we went –
When we increase x by 3, we decreased y(x) by 6.
Or, if we want to simplify this right over here,
(-6)/3 is the same thing as -2.
So our average rate of change of y(x)
over the interval from -5 to -2 is -2.
Every time, on average, x increased by 1, y [changed] by -2.