PROBLEM: "What is the image of
the polygon below after the translation T
[with the subscript] (5, 2)?"
So that means, "Let's translate 5
in the horizontal direction,
and 2 in the vertical direction."
So let's do that.
So I'm going to focus
on this point right over here –
so that point is the point 3, 3.
If I want translate 5 in the horizontal direction,
the x value is going to get to 8.
So the x value will increase by (1, 2, 3, 4) 5.
And then we want to increase the y value by 2.
1, 2.
Let's check our answer.
Let's do a couple more of these.
That was a lot of fun.
So here we need to shift it by
-8 in the horizontal direction.
So this one right over here, its x value is 0.
So we need to go essentially -8.
[Counting as he shifts]: -1, -2.
Or we need to move to the left 1.
(1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7) 8.
And then we have to move it down by 2.
So we have to move it down 1, 2.
And we're done.