Part C: find the average vaulue of f on the intERVAL -1 TO 1
So the average value of a function ovewr an inerval is just going to be
lets just write "average"
The average value of our function is justgoing to be the integral over the interval
the integral over the interval
-1 to 1
of f(x) dx
divided by our change in x
and our change in x is 1 minus -1
so this is going to be equal to 1/2 times the
integral
and here, f(x) is peicewise defined.
so what we can do is break up this integral into two invtervals
we can say the integral from -1 to 0 of f(x) dx
plus, the integral from 0 to 1 of f(x) dx.
and the reason why I broke it up like this is because this
function is peicewise defined.
it's different when we are less than or equal to 0,
than when we are greater than zero
so then we get, this is equal to 1/2 times,
this first part we can right as
the integral from -1 to 0.
what is the what is f(x) from -1 to 0? its 1- 2 sin (X).
dx
plus the integral from 0 to 1,
and what is our function from zero to one?
its e to the -4 x
dx
and now we can do each of these integrals seperately
so this is goin to be equal to
1/2, open brackets,
and now lets take the anti-derivative
of 1-2 sin(x)
antiderivative of 1 with respect to x, is just x
-2 sin(x),
well the derivative of cos(x) is -sin(x),
so this is just going to be 2 cos(x)
and you can verify that,
so we're going to evaluate that at zero,
and at -1
and to that we are going to add,
lets do this integral over here
the antiderivative of e to the -4x,
the antiderivative is going to be equal to,
-e to the -4x over 4
and the way you realize that is if you just had e to the x
the antiderivative would be e^x
if you have an e^-4x
then you know that whatever it's anitiderivite is is going to have