So we are looking at one of my favourite works of art
from last 30 or 40 years.
This is Damien Hirst.
And I'll admit that one of my favourite aspects of this work is its title.
I fell just those words could be a work of art.
I mean I'm not even looking at the shark.
The idea of the physcial impossibility of death
in the mind of someone living.
And there's different ways to parse that actually
It's either word play or deep and ı haven't figured that out yet.
It strikes me as this rage truth.
The impossibility of really coming to terms with death as someone
who is living.
In many ways the history of art is a coming to terms with mortality of
transcending the physical body of the after life.
Art through history has dealt with big questions
This is a work of art taking on those big questions.
Exactly. the title I'm gonna think about all day.
That's why we are so afraid of that.
because we just can't process it.
but what we are looking at is I'm assuming a non living shark.
It's a very large shark.
In a tank.
But what am I looking at actually?
It's a real shark that was caught and
and killed and suspended in a tank of formaldehyde.
It is stationary. Although it looks like moving.
It is stationary and it is in a kind of beautiful tank something that the artist
has sort of framing the shark in for us to see it.
And so I mean well just go back to I guess both the title and it being a work of art.
And I'm starting to appreciate because you could put this in a natural history museum.
This is a shark. This is what a shark looks like.
Study it. It's like a stuffed bison or mammouth or something like it.
I mean the title combined with this makes me think.
I mean there is some obvious things here. It is dead.
I mean I mean I can interpret it.
I just feel like I've been making up stuff though.
I think that's part of the idea.
When artists make things in the 20th and the 21st century
they are more open to interpretation than art in the Renaissance.
We are looking at art which is meant to be kind of open to interpretation.
It is not just what the artist said it meant.
But we are allowed to bring our own ideas and associations to it, to fill out its meaning, to complete it.
In fact Duchamp said that our work of art is completed by the viewer.
So lets talk about our associations with it.
Yes we are almost challenged that it is physically impossible to comprehend that in the mind of a living.
I believe I am living. So basically a title like this can.. I'm being told that I can't comprehend that.
And then I'm just being faced with death right there. I mean I'm faced with a very big version of death.
On kind of multiple dimensions I mean there's the.. The shark is dead although it looks like swimming.
But is also something that could kill me.
If I were..as you know. this is poster of the movie Jaws. So it's a shark.
There's few animals that according to humans as scary more than a big shark.
And when you stand in front of this it is scary to look at.
It is like Oh My God I'm very close to something that could kill me.
And and I guess your brain keeps going back and forth am I really processing that here or am I fearful of this thing that I can't process and that's waht I'm afraid of.
Why couldn't he put a tiger?
And maybe he could.He just chose to use a shark.
Or a shark is more convincing or is just different. I mean he does use other animals.
This is famous series where he slices sheep length wise and puts them in tanks.
This is not the original shark.
In other words this sculpture now has a second shark.
Because the first one dissolved.
Despite the formeldehyde it decayed and the formeldehyde is of course is trying to maintain the intactness of the shark.
And perhaps even its viciousness and its notion of livingness.
But we fail. You know this still dissolves.
this still in a sense ..
That wasn't by design though.
He intended this to be permanent.
I think he is struggling to keep this shark intact.
that's exactly right.
But we don't have the means to do that.
But who isn't struggling to keep themselves intact?
But but I guess here I'm feeling that there is a I guess I havent completed this level of interpretation.
Because this feels like a completely inaverted side effect of how...
The fact that you put a shark in formeldehyde. To me it implies that he was hoping that this would be around for a long time.
His design did not hold up to time and so it is kind of falling apart.
But that wasn't the artists intention.
Well it's interesting. By the time we get to the late 20th century artists are well versed in this idea of the impermenance of art.
That said a minute ago that art for its entire history it is trying to transcend human death.
And in fact one of the definitions one of the philosophical definitions about work of art is it is something that outlives us.
That it is trans generational.
But here is something that is not paint, here is something that is not marble,here is something that is flesh like we are.
And yet there is this vein attempt to have it outlive us and it doesn't.
I think he knew.
So it wasnt just the design for it I mean. He could have stuck this in amber? or something. ..
There's too much too much art that has changed over time for him not to know.
He is just too sophisticated.
The ancient Egyptians mummified bodies. I mean there's a whole history of human beings trying to stop time.
We all know that we can use our best chemicals we can do plastic surgery we can do all sorts of things and nothing is going to stop the inevitability of...
I mean he could have stuck it in the amber or something and...in that much more preserve..
It would have been slower.
It would have been yess..
Or he could have done something much more traditional which is he could have represented a shark and made it more permanant and that would..
right right right.
but by choosing the thing itself he created the impossibility of its own preservation.
Yeah I mean my brain just keeps going back and forth.
what is I mean the title by itself is all you need.
so you have a whole conceptual dimension.
but then you have this absolutely physical dimension and you have this clash between the physical and that poetic.
it is in that contradiction. it is in that confrontation that I think the art really exists.
Yeah I don't think it's just in the title. The title is lovely and really speaks to me. I admit it.
But the title together with the sculpture is a really complicated experience.
I feel like there should almost be a new type of museum called a philosophy museum.
I mean especially if you look at like a classical art museum it is I mean it is about the history and the conversation that people are having in the.. but it is a lot about aesthetics.
And it seems like I mean you see that maybe actually modern art should be called philosophical art or a museum of philosophy.
Because it really is I mean when I hear the word museum I feel it is wrong the museum seems to be let's preserve something that someone else has created.
Well it seems like a lot of this modern art is really about kind of put the philosophy in your face right now without an answer.
I I I don't know whether I'm being ??
Think that question about sort of always being a little bit worried about this being a kind of grand joke in some way.
is always there and it is something that it gets given voice quite a bit in part because
in art now almost nothing is off limits.
And artists find ways of asking profound questions about things that can be very mundane or seem overtly silly.
but can actually
or intentionally shocking.
absolutely.
I think in some ways the art world asks for that cyncism.
But on the other hand that doesn't mean the profound ideas aren't being asked.