I was interrupted in the last video
by a phone call.
I was actually expecting a phone call
from someone whose call I wanted to take,
but that ended up being one of those robocallers.
So, anyway, I was on problem 163.
Let me just start it over
so that I don't interrupt your train of thought.
A fruit salad mixture consists of
apples, peaches, and grapes in the ratio of 6:5:2.
So the ratio of apples to peaches to grapes
is equal to 6:5:2 by weight.
If 39 pounds of the mixture is prepared,
the mixture include
how many more pounds of apples than grapes?
So they essentially want us to figure out
what the apples minus the grapes are equal to.
So we have 39 pounds,
so the pounds of apples plus the peaches
plus the grapes,that equals 39 pounds.
And to do a ratio problem like this,
the easiest way is to say
let's just define the number of pounds of apples
being 6 times some number x.
If the apples are 6 times some number x,
what are the peaches?
We know that
the ratio of the apples to the peaches are 6:5,
so the peaches are going to
have to be 5 times some number x.
By the same logic, the grapes are going to
have to be 2 times some number x.
And if you try out the ratio the apples
to the grapes is 6x over 2x, which is 6:2.
So it all works out.
So let's use this information to
substitute back there and see what x is equal to.
So we get 6x plus 5x plus 2x is equal to 39.
6 plus 5 is 11 plus 2 is 13.
13x is equal to 39.
x is equal to 3.
And so how many apples are there?
6x, there are 18 apples.
We don't have to figure out the peaches,
but we can do it fast.
There are 15 peaches, and then there are 6 grapes.
And if you want to know
how many more apples there are than grapes,
18 minus 6 is equal to 12
--actually these are all in pounds.
There are 12 pounds more of apples than grapes.
And that's choice B.
Problem 164.
Louise has x more dollars than Jim has.
So L is equal to Jim plus x,
and together they have a total of y dollars.
So L plus J is equal to y.
Which of the following represents
the number of dollars that Jim has?
So they want Jim equals,
and they want it in terms of x and y.
So let's take this L and substitute it here
so that we have an equation
that this has J's, x's, and y's in it.
So if L is equal to J plus x, we can substitute.
So we get J plus x, instead of an L,
plus J is equal to y.
That is that, just that.
And you get 2J plus x is equal to y.
Subtract x from both sides.
2J is equal to y minus x.
And we get J is equal to y minus x over 2.
And that is choice A.
Problem 165.
Let's switch colors.
During a certain season, a team won 80%
of its first 100 games, and 50% of the remaining.
If the team won 70% of its games for the entire season,
so they won 70% of the total,
what was the total number of games
that the team played?
So how do we figure out
the total number of games that they played?
It'll be 100 plus remainder.
So let's think of it this way.
If we wanted to figure out
the total percentage that they won,
we would want the number that they won.
So how many games did they win?
They won 80% of their first 100 games, so that's
80 games, plus 50% of the remainder games.
So plus 0.5 times the remainder.
That's how many games they've won.
Now, how many games did they play?
The total number of games is going to be 100
plus whatever this remainder number of games are.
That's their total number of games.
And the problem tells us that this ratio,
the total percentage
this is of all the games they won
divided by all the games they played--
that that is equal to 0.7 or 70%.
If we multiply both sides of this equation
by 100 plus r,
we get 80 plus 0.5r is equal to--
--0.7 times 100 is equal to 70 plus 0.7r.
Now let's subtract 70 from both sides.
You get 10 plus 0.5r is equal to 0.7r.
And then
if we subtract 0.5r from both sides, we get
10 is equal to 0.2r, or r is equal to 10 over 0.2.
And 10 over 0.2, 0.2 is the same thing as 1/5.
So this is 10 times 5, so that's equal to 50.
So the remainder games were 50,so they want to
know the total number of games the team plays.
So it's going to be the first 100 games
plus the remainder games.
So 100 plus 50.
They played 150 games,which is choice D.
We're on problem 166.
Of 30 applicants for a job,
14 had at least 4 years of experience.
So experience greater than 4, we have 14.
I just make up notation as we go.
Of 30 applicants for a job,
14 had at least 4 years of experience,
18 had degrees-- so we say degrees, we have 18--
and 3 had less than 4 years of experience and
did not have a degree.
So experience was less than 4 years' experience
and no degree, and that is 3 people.
How many of the applicants had at least 4 years
of experience and a degree?
So let's see how we can think about it.
There's 30 applicants for a job.
So let me draw our universe.
If I did all of the applicants,
let me draw it like this.
So that's the whole applicant universe,
and that's 30
And we know that
14 had more than 4 years of experience.
Let me do that in this color.
So this attribute, I'll make it look like that,
so that's the 14
that have experience greater than 4 years.
And that's 14 of them.
And then 18 have a degree.
And I'm assuming that
there's some overlap between the degrees in the 14
We don't know that for sure, but let's say that
this point right here I'll draw another circle.
So let's say that circle looks something like that
So let's call this the degreed people.
And there's 18 of them in this whole circle.
And then they say that there were 3 people
with experience less than 4 and no degree.
So they're outside of both of these circles.
So this right here is 3.
Now, what are they asking?
I've already forgotten that.
How many of the applicants had
at least 4 years experience and a degree?
So they're asking for this intersection right here
So there's one question we can answer.
What's the sum of this population,
the population that
has more than 4 years of experience or a degree?
So let me circle.
What's this sum right here?
This and this.
It's going to be whatever's left
after you take out the 3 people who have nothing.
So that's going to be 27 people.
So 27 people have at least 4 years of
experience or a degree.
Now, how can relate that to the 14 and 18?
So what happens if we just add the 14 and the 18?
When we have the 14, we're going to count
these people once.
And if we were add that to 18,
we would count these people twice.
So if we wanted this number--
--if we wanted the number of people
who are in this circle or this circle--
what we would want to do is
add the 14 to the 18, but then subtract out
once the people who are this intersection.
Let's call them B.
That's a B.
I know you can't read it.
Let's say there B people in that intersection.
You'll subtract that out once.
I want that to really make sense for you.
If we want to know the total number of people
in this circle and this circle combined,
when we say 18 people,
that's including some people here.
And if we were add that to 14 people,
where once again some of those 14 are here again,
are these people.
So when we just add 18 to 14,
we're counting this twice.
So if we want to know the actual number
in the circle or the circle,
since we add 18 to 14 we count it twice,
we wants to subtract these people out once.
Hopefully that makes sense.
But anyway, now we're ready to solve.
We get 27 is equal to--14 plus 18 is
equal to 32 minus B.
27 from both sides, you get 0 is equal 5 minus B.
Add B the both sides.
You get B is equal to 5.
And that is choice E.
See you in the next video.