in the previous video
we have already talked about the idea that there are times of earth orbit
when it is closer to the sun
and when it is further from the sun
let's say this is the times of the earth when it is closer to the sun
this is the perihelion.. perihelion.. perihelion..
and when it furtherest from the sun
and I'm exaggerating the difference
this is aphelion.. this is the aphelion in our orbit.
when we are furthest from the sun.. maybe our orbit looks something like this
so maybe our orbit looks something...
so maybe our orbit looks something like this over here
and what i point our in the first video we discussed is that
this is not the cause of the season
even-though we are 3% closer.. right now
when are orbited... will see in the future video..
that the difference or the eccentricity or how ellecptical
the orbit is
does change over time
how much it deviates from being circular
that's how.. that one way to think about eccentricity
that does change over time
right now
when we we are closest to the sun
we are 3% closer than we are furthest from the sun
3% closer than at aphelion
and we point out in the first video that we discussed
that this is not the cause of the seasons
and in particular
perliion where we are closest to the sun
where we actually have the most radiation from the sun
that's actually when we have the northern hemisphere
when we have the northern hemisphere winter
so this occurs right over here.. this occurs in January
this occurs in January.. aphelion occurs in July.. occurs in July
now based on this, this might lead to an interesting question
because.. so let's think about January.. let's think about January
when we are perhelion
and let's think about July.. let's think about July.. we are in aphelion
let me draw a quick globe right over here
and let's make that the equator
and I'll write that in both the situations.. in both the situations
so in January is obviously when we have the northern hemisphere's winters are cold
painted in blue right over here..
it is winter
and July it's when we have northern hemisphere's summer
or the southern hemisphere's winter.. so then we have winter.. winter during July.
in the southern hemisphere
let's me put summer in a more summery color. i guess that orange is a pretty good color.. that's not orange..
hers' orange.. alright..
that's orange and that's orange.. so these are summer..
summer
so that's the summer in southern hemisphere
which occurs during the winter in northern hemisphere
and vice versa
summer in the northern hemisphere occurs during winter in the southern hemisphere
and so the question might be rising in your head
and i did see a few comments in that first video asking this question
and it's a good one
and if we are closer.. if we are closer to the sun in January
or we are really closest to the sun in January
this is the perihelion right over here
and so we are getting more solar radiation in January
does that moderate the winter
so does that moderate the winter..
in the northern hemisphere
or i guess another way to think about it..
does it make summer in the southern hemisphere when we are closer to the sun
does it make it more extreme
does it make it more extreme or hotter and vice versa
in July, when we are
when we are furthest from the sun
does that moderate the northern hemisphere winter
because it is hot out there
but hey it's little bit further from the sun
and does that make the southern hemisphere winter colder
so once again does it make this more extreme
because it's already winter and we are further from the sun
so maybe we are also getting less radiation
and there's a couple of way to think about this
1 -- it is true that when we are further, we are getting a little bit less radiation
from the sun or we are getting heated up a little bit less
but the one reality is that the southern hemisphere climate as a whole
is not more extreme despite getting heated up
getting more solar energy in the summer
and getting less solar energy in the winter
and the reason why this is not an extreme
we draw the equator here.. just that we can separate our hemispheres
the main reason it is believed
that it is not more extreme.. it is that the southern hemisphere has a lot more water in it
so just if you look at the surface of the southern hemisphere you are looking at a lot more water
than the surface of the northern hemisphere
this is of course the locator projection
this distorts things so that the things near the pole
gets really kind of built up to look really huge even though they really aren't that big..
Greenland really isn't larger than south america
it just spreads the mouth so that you can kind of
so that you can... flat the map to speak...
so the southern hemisphere has more water
as you may have learned in chemistry class
water has the highest specific heat
highest specific energy.. it takes more energy, more heat to raise water a degree
than it does takes to raise land a degree
and so water can absorb more energy
or when there is less energy, water will release more energy
without droping as much of a temperature
so water has a moderating influence
water has a moderating influence on the climate
so eventhough summers in the southern hemisphere
actually are getting more radiations than the summers in the northern hemisphere
that's moderating on the actual temperature.. because the water is believed to absorb
more of that heat without changing the temperature as dramatically
now with that said, it is true
that in general Antarctica is colder.. Antarctica is colder.. it is than the north pole
but the main reason why antartica is colder besides the fact
that it is in land.. as suppose to antartica being...
...as suppose to the north pole being the centre of the artic ocean
is that it is actually a huge.. very high altitude of ice sheet
and so for the altitude for most of the Antarctica is around 8000 feet
so it's like an alphine altitude
so the main reason why it's colder is
you know it's possibly being further away from the sun
and winter might play some role there
but the main reason why it's colder is that it's at a much higher altitude
and it's some degree insulated from the water
or I guess you could say it's on the land
so especially during the long winter it's going to get that much colder
but i'll leave you there and
and to some degree this is the other aspect of it
during the summers... you know.. all of this stuff is super complicated
so you can.. you can just drop one rule of thumb and say this it the reason..
these are all are influencers
is that if you have a large super-large ice shield sheet
it's also more likely to reflect more of the energy
because it's white as suppose to a darker color like the ocean or the land
so you can think about all of those factors but the general answer is -- it's a good question
but overall the climate in the southern hemisphere (actually it has to be northern hemisphere) is
not more extreme than the climate in the southern hemisphere
even though antartica is colder