Oh Hi, Arthuro Petori here
But you can call me Art.
This is explorations in Art History
Starring: Me! and The Hand!.
What about rest of me?
Oh people watching from arround the world, stuck lanes, or some five fingered primadona
Oh, oh that's better, right? see?
It looks like we will be talking about
the Medieval and Byzantine periods
It had taken many lifetimes and countless battles
to conquer and maintain the vast regions of the Roman Empire
When Emperor Theodosius the first took power,
he ruled over lands that stretched from Portugal to Palestine
The question of succession of power
had always been a problem in the Empire and
for Theodosius it came down to a choice beetwen two sons.
Or did it?
In 395 AD, Theodosius, instead, split the Empire in half.
The Western half became domain of his son Honorius
We call it the 'Western Roman Empire'
The Eastern half was awarded to his son Arcadius
and became known as the Byzantine Empire
The two kingdoms both considered themselves Roman,
though they spoke Latin in the West and Greek in the East
Honorius and the Western Roman Empire were besieged
by barbarian hordes from the beginning.
Huns,Goths, Vandals and Franks all took turns
invading Western territories.
Sacking Rome became a barbarian pastime.
And the Vandals, thanks to their exceptional
act of destruction and violence gave us the world the 'vandalism.'
It was a rough and tumble time.
Only 81 years after the death of Theodosius,
the Western Roman Empire ceased to exist.
With the Empire spindled into separate countries, the one unifying force to remain is the Catholic church and the Pope
The Byzantine Empire, on the other hand, would last another thousand years
In 730 AD, Emperor Leo the third initiated the movement called the Iconoclasm
based on strict interpretation of ten commandments which forbade the making and worshipping of the grave images
and perhaps due to rising influence of Islamic culture. The Iconoclasm sacked the removal or destruction of paintings subsculptures
There's one.
This way man arhhh
Get him, I got that one, There's one, there's another one go and get it. Ohh we are too late
Yea, stop him. Stop him now! Hurry!
After Iconoclasm ended, the Byzantine artists were limited to copying approved images from the past
I'm a copy, of a copy of a copy of a copy of a copy
Back in Rome, Pope Gregory the second rejected iconoclasm and denounced it as heretical.
He even sent a letter excommunicating Iconoclasm
It's byzantine blasphemy. Excommunicate them!
As a result, artist in the West had more creative freedom. The church was the major patron of the art and so most medieval art had reliogious themes
Western artists of the later middle ages were interested in visionary experiences.
Over time, in the search to create more convincing and powerful images. Their art became more realistic in its patrial of people and natural world
I have dimension
This is Art saying thanks for sharing another fascinating exploration into... heyy.. I am not finished