What I want to do in this video is introduce you to the idea of a budget line
And that probably isn't a new idea
It's kind of a derivitive idea
What you've seen often in the introductory algebra course
Where you've got a certain amount of money
and you can spend it on a certain combination of goods
what are all the different possibilities
that you can actually buy,
so that's really what a budget line is.
So let's say that you have an income
and I'll do it both in the abstract and the concrete
So I'll do it with variables and then I'll do it with
actual numbers
So let's say your income
in 1 month is Y,
And let's say that you spend all of your money
so that your income is equal to your expenditures
So we're assuming in our little model here
that you're not going to be saving any money
and, to show how overly simplified we can make
a model
We are going to only assume that you can spend
on 2 different goods.