We're in the Musee de Louvre and we're looking at
Jacques-Louis David's "Brutus and his Sons".
This is one of my favourite paintings by David
and dates to the very year of the Revolution itself 1789.
And it was tied beautifully to
the revolutionary sentiment in subject.
Brutus has led the revolution against
the kings in Rome, this is an Anient Rome.
Brutus has discovered that
his sons have commited treason
in attempting to restore the monarchy throne.
So Brutus has judged,
has taken the extraordinary step of
sentencing his own family to death for their treason.
Putting the state above his own personal family,
above his own feelings, above his own needs.
And that's the theme that
we also see in "Oath of the Horatii".
The triumph of reason,of being morrow and virtuous
over personal feelings and personal priorities.
But this is also a painting about the cost of that.
It's not blind patriotism, there is a true,
emotional power and cost there, and it's tragic.
Brutus sits in shadow, under a statue of Rome,
holding his edict in his hand.
His feet crossed beneath him, his hand up,
he's obviously in thought,
he is back turned to the body of his son
to be seen being carried in behind him,
while his wife and children
who form the other half of the composition
call out fully illuminated,
shielding their eyes, passing out.
They cant't believe what Brutus has done.
Brutus is quiet, he's calm, he's resigned,
even if there's a kind of deep tragedy there,
the woman on the other side
and the children have given into their emotions.
In many ways this fits in with
ideas that were around during the Revolution
that only men really have
the capability of sacrificing for the state,
of being true citizens because
only men could rise above their emotions
and their personal concerns
to think about these greater goods.
That stoicism seems to be echoed
in a very architecure of this space.
We have a fairly complex classical environment.
Door, columns the most pared down
and this is the truest of Greek architecture.
But then that softened
especially in the sphere of the women
in the that's drape of cloth, the soften material...
This is a painting that's clearly
informed by David's research
into classical architecture, into classical furnisgings.
And the figures themselves resamble
ancient Greek and Roman sculptures.
The way that the drapery clings to their bodies,
the importance of anatomy here is so clear,
of a clarity of space, of a clarity of line.
The colours are subdued but the light comes in
really strongly and illuminates these figures.
And we have dramatic powerful gestures,
and you're right, this is sacrifice and vitue
but simultaneously the terrible emotional cost of that
not just for Brutus' family, but for Brutus too.
And this is fascinating to me that
this painting was made in very year of Revolution
because it seems to speak to
the virtues that were requied for the Revolution.
The idea of sacrificing for the greater good,
the idea that the Revolution
brings in ideals of equality before the law.
So that even that Brutus is the leader,
he's not going to excuse his sons.
Tragically, the Revolution would
returned against his own sons.
And this becomes almost
the foreshadowing of what will happen.
In that case you have
the excesses of Rob Spear and others.
Where the virtues that are expressed
in this early painting by David are turned away from.
In some tragic way this painting does for shadow,
the collapse and failure of the Revolution.