if you havent tried already to write your own recursive fibonacci sequence function
i really encourage you to do so, or at least to try to do so
give it a serious debt before you watch this video
but if you have done that, or your feeling lazy
i guess you can watch this video
and so we're going to try to write a fibonnaci function
according to thespecs that i laid out when i first set up the challenge to write a fibonacci function
so ill call this fibonacci again fi-bo-nacci
fibonacci and it will take it
it has a parameter here, n, and it will pass an argument
to it to say which term do we want of the fibonacci sequece
but here we're going to do it recursively and what we're going to see
is that it's actually a very intuitive to write a fibonacci function
recursively, al-its like-almost-like
magic, and later we will see that it is not necessarily the
most efficient way to write the fibonacci function
so what im gonna do is, whenever you, whenever you write
any recursive program, you really need to think about
the base cases
really well, and the base cases of the fibonacci sequence
theres actually two base cases
theres the zeroeth term and the first term
and those are really given by definition
so lets just say,
if, if we want the zeroeth term
so if n is equal to zero,
if n is equal to zero,
well, that means you want the zeroeth term
and the zeroeth term is actually zero!
and you could say, else if,else if
n is equal to one, n is equal to one,
then you, then you can return
then you can return
you can return, one!
that is the zero term is zero, the first term in the fibonacci sequence
is one.
and now here is a little bit of where the magic happens.
otherwise, otherwise, return -and now this is really cool here-
return to the fibonacci, fib-o-nacci
of n minus one,so whenever the previous term in
the fibonacci sequence is, plus fibonacci, plus fibonacci,
of n minus 2.
and i think this should work. and that's why it seems magical.
cuz all we're saying is hey look, if you the zero term its zero
if you want the first term, its one
-lets give some spaces here-
if you want the first term, it is one!
if you want any other term, -if you want any other term-
so else, if you want- this is else if-
e-bu- else neither of these is true so neither
zero nor one if its some other number, its going to be
- and we're going to assume that your inputting some, some
non-negative integer over here-
right over here-
this would break down if you did something non-negative
integer over non-negative uh, negative, term
but if, assuming you have, uh, a non-negative integer,
then you say look!
if its not the zeroeth term or the first term
then just take
the fibonnaci of the, whatever term one term less than it is
plus two terms less than that, and you could try it
out, for example:
lets say you took the fibonacci of 2!
or,then, n is not zero
then you wont do this
n is not one so you wont do this
but you'll say return fibonacci of 2 minus 1
so thats fibonacci of 1
plus fibonacci of 2 minus 2 plus fibonacci of 0.
but we know fibonacci of one, evaluates to one
fibonacci of zero evaluates to zero
so it'll be one plus zero,
or,
just one!
And you can keep going!
try fibonacci of 3!
it'll work!
because we know fibonacci of 0,1,or 2 works
cuz fibonacci of 3 will boil down to fibonacci of 2 plus fibonacci of 1.
we know that fibonacci of 2 is 1, fibonacci of 1 is 1
1+1 is 2
so it'll just keep working.
now we could try it out
let's just save this
-actually didn't save the file name called recursive fibonacci-
-repeat twice-
and now let me actually run the program
and all this does is define the function
in-in my environment that i actually have to call the function.
so let me just run it
and let me ask for fibonacci offfff 4.
it gave me the right answer.
fi-bo-nacci of 10!
55, right answer.
fibonacci, -i could try simple things, fibonacci of zero
of the zero term is zero
so it all works out
so thats why recursion is kinda magical.
and if you wanted to simplify this any more, you might
recognize, hey! the zeroeth term of the fibonacci sequence
is zero, the first term of the fibonacci sequence is one,
so really, its-it-if your asking for the zeroeth or the first term
its really the same thing of as that number.
so you could actually maybe simplify this a little bit
if you assume that someone was going to input a non-negative integer
over here, you could say something like-
if n, if n is equal to zero or n is equal, or n is equal to 1,
- or n is equal to 1,-
return, return n!
Lets see if this works.
lets see if it simplified our code up a little bit
so lets try this- save this,
and now lets run it,
lets run it,
alright, and now lets try fi-bo-nacci, fibonacci of 10!
it still worked!
cuz really, the zeroeth term is zero, and the nth term is
or uh the first term is one,-so that works there-
or you can even simplify more
if n is less than 2! that should also work
becuz then if its zero or one your gonna return n, and otherwise
your gonnna return to this business
so lets try that out.
so we ran it, and lets try fibonacci fibonacci of, fibonacci of 10
now. it seems that the computer is able to do this
really quickly and all of that and all the rest of it
but if you really wanna see
all the work that's being done, all the calls to fibonacci
what you can do is
lets put a print in here
so that every time fibonacci gets called print, it prints
fibonacci it prints the text fibonacci COLON, and then,
pl- i'm going to add to that string, to that string of text
what, what the argument is.
so the argument of this is going to be n,
and i wanna make sure that its viewed as a string.
So i'll put, i'll put it, im casting it to a string
that's essentially just taking
an integer and making sure its a string, and when i add it
to this string, it'll make it one big string
but lets see what this does
i'm gonna try it out with lower values first
so let me,...., the function is defined
Fibonacci,-I can just-
let me do Fibonacci off 3
so notice,
when it called, it called Fibonacci of 3, then to do
Fibonacci of 3, it had to call Fibonacci of 2
and Fibonacci of 1, and then to do Fibonacci of 2 it
had to call Fibonacci, it had to call Fibonacci of zero
and Fibonacci of 1. So it had to do all of these calls to
Fibonacci, just to calculate the Fibonacci of 3.
and then eventually it gave me the answer.
If you did like Fibonacci of 10, its gonna go really
crazy, so I'm gonna do that
let me, let me just do Fibonacci of like 6,
and your gonna see how many calls to Fibonacci it had to do
so it had to do all of these calls, all of these calls, to fibonacci
so it was actually very computationally intensive
thing to do.
but it, you know, the computer's are super fast, so
you dont even notice it. But in the future we're going to talk about
a little bit more how do we think about how computationally-intensive
different ways of implementing a function,
can be.