We're on problem 76.
It says one bag contains
2 green
marbles and 4 white marbles.
So that's one bag, and we have
2 green and 4 white.
And a second bag contains
3 green
marbles and 1 white marble.
So here's a second bag.
It has 3 green and
1 white marble.
If Trent randomly draws 1 marble
from each bag, what is
the probability that
they're both green?
What's the probability that
he draws a green marble
from this first bag?
Let's see, there's
2 green marbles.
Out of a total how
many marbles?
2 plus 4 marbles.
There's a total of 6
marbles in here.
So there's a 2/6 or 1/3 chance
that he draws a green marble
out of this bag.
And then when he goes to this
bag, let's say, OK how many
green marbles are there?
Well there are 3 green marbles
out of a total
possibility of 4 marbles.
So there's a 3/4 chance
that he picks a green
marble out of this bag.
So the chance that he picks a
green marble out of both bags
is just the 2/6 times the 3/4.
That's 1/3 times 3/4.
Which is equal to a
1/4 probability.
Next question.
I've decided that it's
fast when I pre- cut
and paste the questions.
It took me, like, 18 videos to
think of that innovation.
Anyway.
A box contains 7 red
marbles, no.
7 large red marbles, 5-- let me
see, we have a box-- I have
7 large red marbles, 5 large
yellow marbles, 3 small red
marbles, and 5 small
yellow marbles.
If a marble is drawn at
random, what is the
probability that it is yellow?
So probability that it is
yellow, given that it is one
of the large marbles.
OK, so this might
seem difficult.
Conditional probability
and all of that.
But all you have to think about
is, OK, we've picked a
marble out of the box
and it's large.
So if I have a large marble
in my hand, what is the
probability that I picked
a yellow large marble?
So the easiest way to think
about it is just think about
the universe of large marbles.
We picked 1 of these
12 marbles here.
We picked 1 of the large ones.
So we definitely picked
1 of these 12 marbles.
And so what is the probability
that I picked a
yellow large marble?
So there's a total of 5
yellow large marbles.
That's what they want to know.
Given it was one of large,
probability of the yellow.
So there's 5 yellow
large marbles.
That's these right here.
And how many total large marbles
might I have picked?
Well 5 plus 7 is 12.
So there's a 5/12 chance that
I picked a yellow marble,
given that I picked 1 of
the large marbles.
Next question.
There's a trash truck outside
making a lot of noise.
Hope you don't hear it.
Anyway, this has
a big diagram.
Let's see.
Jamie will definitely try out--
this is problem 78-- let
me switch to a dark color
because I'm going to be
writing on white.
Jamie will definitely
try out for either
basketball or baseball.
Basketball or baseball.
But not both.
The probability that Jamie will
try out for baseball and
try out for catcher is 42%.
So this probability is 42%.
Baseball and catcher.
What is the probability that
Jamie will try out for
basketball?
OK, so what have they
provided us?
There's some probability that
Jamie tries out for
basketball, some probability
that Jamie
tries out for baseball.
Let's just assign some, let's
say that this is x.
Because that's what we
want to figure out.
And if that probability is x,
then the probability of trying
out for baseball is just
going to be 1 minus x.
And if that's 60%, it's
going to be 40%.
I don't know what it is yet.
But then they say, if Jamie is
trying out for basketball,
then there's an 80% chance that
he tries out for guard
and a 20% chance for forward.
But, if you said what's the
probability that he does
basketball and forward, it
would be x times 20%.
Maybe there's a 50% chance he
does basketball and then 20%
of those times he would
be a forward, so it
would be a 10% chance.
So we do the same logic here.
If he tries out for baseball,
there's a 70% chance he'll try
out for catcher.
And they already told us that
the combined probability, the
probability that he'll try out
for baseball and, given that
try out for catcher,
that that is 42%.
So we can write that 1 minus
x, that's this probability,
times 70%, times 0.7, is equal
to 42%, which is 0.42.
And then you get 1 minus
x is equal to what?
What's 0.42 divided by 7?
Let's see, it's 42 divided
by 7 would be 6.
0.7.
It would be 60%.
And you can do that division.
And it's always good to do a
reality check and say, OK, 70%
of something is 42%.
OK, 70% of 60%, yeah
that makes sense
that it would be 42%.
Just in case you don't make
a decimal mistake.
So 1 minus x is 60%.
This is a 60% probability
right here
going down this chain.
And so now maybe you can see it
a little more concretely,
we said, OK, whatever this is
times the probability that he
tries out for catcher, given
that he's trying out for the
baseball team, that's going
to be equal to 42%.
And we've figured this out.
Now if this is 60%, 1 minus x,
then x is-- if this is 60% x
is 1 minus that.
So x is 40%.
And we could have actually
solved for that.
We could have actually said,
1 minus x is equal to 60%.
And then you could have said,
minus x is equal to minus 40%.
Subtract 1 from both sides,
x is equal to 40%.
Anyway that's the question
they asked us.
And what choice was that?
What choice?
Oh, it doesn't matter.
That was choice A.
Two problems left.
I'm going to be nostalgic for
these California standards,
Algebra II exams. All right.
Let me copy and paste
this one in.
All right.
A small business owner must hire
seasonal workers as the
need arises.
The following list shows the
number of employees hired
monthly for a five-month
period.
If the mean of these data is
approximately 7, what is the
population standard deviation
for these data?
Round the answer to the
nearest decimal.
OK.
Standard deviation has all
sorts of definitions.
Well there is one definition
for it, but I just always
think about it is,
it's the average
distance from the average.
Or it's the average distance
from the mean.
And if you wanted a visual kind
of representation of it,
let's say that I were to draw--
this is some type of
y-axis there-- and on the x-axis
I were to draw each of
the data points.
So this is data point 1,
this is data point 2.
You wouldn't have to do this on
the problem, but I really
want to give you an intuition
for what the standard
deviation is so that you
don't forget it when
you're 32 years old.
All right.
So the data points go all
the way from 4 to 13.
So let's see, data
point one is 4.
Let's say that this is 4.
I just want to give you.
So that's 4.
Data point two is 13.
So maybe 13 will be up here.
Data point three is 5.
That's right around there.
Data point four is 6.
Maybe it's right there.
And data point five is 9.
So maybe nine is-- I don't know
I'm just eyeballing it--
maybe 9 is right there.
And they're telling us that if
we average these numbers, our
average is 7.
So 7 is our average.
So this is 7.
So the average is 7.
And they didn't have
to tell you that.
They're just trying to
save you some time.
You could have added all of
these numbers up, and you said
OK, I got 7.
I'm guessing that we get some
decimals or something.
That's why they said
approximately 7.
But anyway, that's
the average.
So the standard deviation is
just the average distance from
the average, or the average
distance from the mean.
So you say is, and you might
know it as the square root of
variance and all that.
And the variance is just
the square of the
distance from the mean.
And they just really square it
so that it stays positive.
But if you just say 4 and 7,
what's the difference, what's
the distance between 4 and 7?
Well I'll draw it
with my marker.
The distance between
4 and 7 is 3.
Remember we just want to figure
out the distance.
We don't want to know
which one's bigger.
4 is 3 away from 7.
That's why sometimes people will
say, oh OK, the variance
is equal to 4 minus
7, squared.
And then that'll give you 9.
And then they will say that
the standard deviation is
equal to the square root
of the variance.
Which is equal to 3.
But you could have just said
that the standard deviation is
equal to the absolute
value of 4 minus 7.
To me, this is more intuitive
because we're just saying, OK,
how far away is it from 7?
I don't care if it's
above or below.
I just want to know the
distance from it.
And then I just want to
average each of those.
Oh I'm sorry.
This isn't the standard
deviation itself.
This is each of the terms and
then we would average them.
Anyway, let me erase this
because I think
I'll need that space.
The standard deviation, you
figured this out, you take the
sum of these and then
you average them.
I'll show it to you
in a second.
Let me erase this.
I think the proper notation
would have been, you could
have written it as the standard
deviation is equal to
the sum of the differences
of the data points.
You know, there's
n data points.
The n data points.
And that we want to take the
absolute value between each of
the data points.
Data point i minus the mean.
They write mu for the
mean, or something.
It gets complicated.
So that's the sum of all of
them and then you want to
divide that by n.
So essentially you're
taking the average
distance from the mean.
All that might be really
complicated.
You could have written
variance-- well, anyway.
I just want to show you that
when you do the statistics
class, it'll introduce you to
a lot of things, but at the
end, all you care about
is the average
distance from the mean.
And I'll show you how easy
that is to calculate.
Everything I've done so far
this problem you would not
have had to do on a real exam.
I'm just trying to give a
little bit of intuition.
All right, so the distance
from 4 to 7 is 3.
So the distance from data
point one is 3.
The distance from 13 to 7,
what's that distance?
Well, that's 7.
We just care about the
absolute distance.
So then that distance is 7.
The distance from 5 to 7 is 2.
The distance from 6 to 7 is 1.
The distance from 9 to 7 is 2.
So we just want to take
the average of
all of these numbers.
Let's see, 3 plus 7 is 10.
10 plus 2 is 12.
12 plus 1 is 13.
Plus 2 is 15.
So the sum of these is 15.
And I have 5 data points.
So divided by 5 is equal to 3.
So the standard deviation is
equal to-- well, that's
strange because I got 3 and they
have an answer, 3.3, so I
feel like maybe I
made a mistake.
But, I mean, I'm going
to go with that.
I'm going to go with the 3.3.
Maybe, I guess the actual
mean is probably not 7.
So if you used the non-actual
mean you would have-- let's
see what the actual mean is.
And once again this is not
something that you
would have to do.
Well, anyway.
Actually, I just realized
I've run out of time.
So I'll continue this
in the next video.
See you soon.
The next video is going
to be one problem.