In the last video we first thought about the externalities.
The negative externalities of having plastic bags around.
It causes litter,
it might damage animals and the environment in some way.
And we assumed in that video
that we were able to calculate the actual external cost of a plastc bag.
These two cents a bag is the impact on litter and the environment.
And then we were able to figure out that if we factored this in,
instead of just having the regular marginal cost curve of the suppliers,
if we added that marginal cost curve to the external cost,
we would get a supplier plus external cost marginal cost curve.
And then we get what is actually the optimal price and quantity of plastic bags,
so that we actually do not eat into our surplus
by creating all of this negative surplus
where the total costs of the bags
are higher than the total benefit.
But one thing that we did not touch on in that video is how does this actually happen.
If we just let things be
and we just had the suppliers' marginal cost curve
and we have the consumers' demand curve,
and in this case the consumers were the supermarkets,
then the equilibrium price would be right over here
because this, although, theoretically saying that there is this cost over here,
the cost won't be factored in into the markets.
So if you are the benevolent emperor in this society,
what do you do?
What do you do to get the quantity closer to this point right over here
than what the equilibrium quantity will be when you don't factor in the external cost?
And there is a bunch of options here.
You could just ban plastic bags,
You could put a quota on plastic bags.
saying that more than a certain amount of bags cannot be produced.
Or you could tax plastic bags.
Now, let's think about which of these will result in the most surplus,
the most benefit to society in aggregate.
And one core assumption we are going to make
is that this is an accurate assessment of the external cost per bag.
So if you were to just ban plastic bags as this benevolent emperor,
maybe seemingly or hopefully benevolent emperor of this society right here.
If you just banned plastic bags, what would happen?
Well, then this market just won't exist
and all of this surplus that could have existed, won't exist anymore.
So you would actually be destroying surplus.
Now, you could say: "No, plastic bags are horrible. They should just be outright banned."
"There is no amount of benefit for which plastic bags are worth using."
But in that case you are actually arguing this point right over here.
You would be arguing that it's not two cents a bag, it's ten cents a bag of negative externality.
And because of that, then you would have this curve shift up even more.
And then, there is no positive quanity there.
And then, maybe a ban would be all right.
But if the two cents is the externality, the negative externality
and if you were to ban plastic bags
then you would actually be removing this surplus from society.
So that doesn't seem like a good option.
Now, what about the quota?
You kind of look at the study right over here and say:
"Look, the optimal amount of plastic bags is 1.9 mln bags per week,
so I will just say that's the most that the market can produce."
But when you say that, that's assuming that you really do understand
what does demand curve look like...
I just drew a straight line here, just to add simplicity.
...assuming you really do understand what this marginal cost curve looks like.
And throughout this play we've been assuming that we kind of do understand those things,
but in the real world it's actually very hard
to know exactly what the marginal cost curve looks like.
And it's also hard to know exactly what the marginal benefit curve,
rather than the demand curve looks like.
Especially, because they are always changing.
There is always more competitors, less competitors,
more substitute products, more R&D.
Things are getting more efficient, less efficient.
And so, it's very hard to know what the true equilibrium quantity should be.
So, a quota is difficult.
You don't have quite the right information.
A tax is interesting.
Because the tax says: "Look, regardless of what the marginal cost curve really is,
we are just going to shift it up by two cents."
We saw that when we first talked about taxes.
When we first talked about taxes,
we talked about: "Hey, they are introducing a deadweight loss,
because you are not producing as much quantity as you would have otherwise
or as much quantity isn't being consumed."
But here a tax could actually prevent a deadweight loss
because if you have a two-cent tax,
essentially adding the cost of the negative externality in the form of a tax,
on top of the suppliers' cost right over here,
you are going to cause the equilibrium quantity
to be the quantity where you are not generating all of this negative surplus.
And it's just the positive side effect.
Once again, this is all assuming that this is the right numer.
But it would be a positive side effect
that you would also generate some revenue for the government.
And what is good about the tax
in this circumstance right over here,
you are not assuming anything about what the marginal cost curve looks like
or what demand curve looks like.
As long as you are assuming that this is the right number
the tax will always shift,
whatever the marginal cost curve is,
it will always shift it to the right point to intersect,
wherever the demand curve is,
at this equilibrium point, that gives us an equilibrium price and an equilibrium quantity.
So if this is the right number
and you put a two-cent tax per bag
then this is probably going to be the best option
in terms of optimizing the total surplus.