Microwaves can pop
your popcorn. They can catch you speeding.
They carry thousands of phone channels to speed your calls.
But can microwaves help us learn about our world and our Universe?
Let's find out. With wavelengths ranging from 30 centimeters down
to one millimeter, microwaves fall between radio waves and infrared.
Microwaves are used in doppler radar which is
widely used for short term localized weather forecasting and what you
see on TV weather news. Satellites have revolutionized
weather forecasting by providing a global view of weather patterns
and surface temperatures. This unique perspective has greatly increased the accuracy
of tropical storm and climate forecasts.
Different wavelengths of microwaves, grouped into bands, provide different
information to scientists. Medium-length C-band microwaves
penetrate through clouds, dust, smoke, snow and rain
to reveal the Earth's surface. Satellite microwave measurements
reveal the full Arctic sea ice cover every day, even where clouds exist.
These measurements show great variability from year to year,
but also show an overall decrease in Arctic sea ice since the late 1970's,
illustrated here with maps and a time series of Arctic sea ice
in September, at the end of the summer melt. The Japanese
Earth Resources Satellite uses longer wavelength L-band microwaves
for forest mapping by measuring surface soil moisture -
such as this image of the Amazon basin - to identify areas of recent deforestation.
L-band microwaves are also used by Global Positioning Systems
such as the one in your car. Scientists routinely
combine microwave information with information from other parts of the EM spectrum
to study the composition of cosmic dust, or of a supernova
such as this supernova image that combines x-ray, radio and microwave data.
This recently known supernova in the Milky Way exploded
just over 140 years ago at the time of the American Civil War.
One important phenomenon is unique to microwaves.
In 1965, using long, L-band microwaves,
Arno Penzias and Robert Wilson made an incredible accidental discovery;
they detected what they thought was noise from their instrument,
but was actually a constant background signal coming from everywhere in space.
This radiation is called "Cosmic Microwave Background" and if our eyes
could see microwaves, the entire sky would glow with a nearly uniform
brightness in every direction. The existence of this background radiation
has served as important evidence supporting the Big Bang theory
for how our universe began. Microwaves have become both staples
and wonders of modern life. They are also the backbone
of communications and of Earth sensing systems, and they are
an excellent guide to the ancient history and origins of our Universe.