Use substitution to solve for x and y and we have a system of equations here.
The first equation is 2y=x+7 and the second equation here is x=y-4.
So what we want to do when we say substitution is we want to
substitute one of the variables with an expression so that we
have an equation in only one variable then we can solve for it.
So let me show you what I'm talking about. Let me write this first degree equation.
2y=x+7.
And we have the second equation over her, that x=y-4.
So if we are looking for an x and y that satisfy both constraints, what we can see is, well look,
if the x and the y's have to satisfy both restraints,
both of these restraints have to be true. So x must be equal to y-4.
So anywhere in this top equation where we see an x
we say, "Well look, that x by the second constraint has to be equal to y-4.
So everywhere we see an x, we can substitute it by a y-4.
So let's do that. So if we substitute y-4 for x in this top equation,
the top equation becomes 2y is equal to-- instead of an x,
the second constraint tells us that x needs to be equal to y-4. So instead of an x, we'll have a y-4.
And then we have a plus seven.
All I did here was I substituted y-4 for x.
The second constraint tells us that we need to do it.
y-4 needs to be equal to x, or x needs to be equal to y-4.
The value here is now we have an equation.
One equation with one variable; we can just solve for y.
So we get 2y=y, and then we have minus 4 plus 7 so y+3,
we can subtract y from both sides of this equation.
The left hand side -- 2y-y is just y.
y is equal to-- these cancel out; y is equal to three.
And then we can go back and substitute into either of these equations and solve for x.
This is easier right over here,
so let's substitute right over here.
x needs to be equal to y-4.
So we can say that x is equal to 3-4, which is equal to -1.
So the solution to this system is x=-1, and y=3.
And you can verify that this works in this top equation right over here.
2*3 is 6, which is indeed equal to -1+7.
Now I want to show you that over here we substituted.
We had an expression or we had an equation
that explicitly solved for x so we were able to substitute the x's.
What I want to show you is that we could have done it the other way around.
We could have solved for y and then substituted for the y's.
So let's do that. We could have substituted
from one constraint into the other constraint or vice-versa.
Either way, we would have gotten the same exact answer.
So instead of saying that x=y-4, in that second equation,
if we add 4 to both sides of this equation, we get x+4=y.
This and this is the exact same constraint.
I just added four to both sides to get this constraint over here.
And now since we've solved the equation explicitly for y,
we can use the first constraint-- the first equation--
and everywhere we see y, we can substitute it with x+4.
So it's 2 times--instead of 2 times y-- we can write
2(x+4).
2(x+4)=x+7.
We can distribute this two, so we get 2x+8=x+7.
We can subtract x from both sides of this equation,
and we can subtract 8 from both sides of this equation. Subtract 8.
The left hand side, that cancels out. We're just left with an x.
On the right hand side, that cancels out, and we are left with a -1.
Then, we can substitute back over here. We have y=x+4,
or so y=-1+4, which is equal to 3.
So once again we got the same answer,
even though this time we substituted for y
instead of substituting for x.
Hopefully you find that interesting.