SAL KHAN: So first of all,
I just want to thank Elon for coming – hungry.
ELON MUSK: Absolutely.
SAL: You didn't even have dinner,
and we didn't even feed you properly.
ELON: Sorry to be a bit late.
SAL: Oh, no.
ELON: I just came from the Tesla factory in Fremont.
SAL: Yeah? Was something wrong? [LAUGHTER]
ELON: There's always something wrong.
SAL: Did you have to like –
ELON: At any given point,
there is always something wrong –
SAL: Yes.
ELON: – because there are just too many things going on.
SAL: Yeah.
ELON: So, one of the trickest things about a car
is that there are thousands of individual components –
there are thousands of unique components.
And even if one of those things is missing,
you can't make cars.
SAL:Yes.
ELON: So – I mean today's fiasco was -- I kid you not –
we were missing three-dollar USB cables.
So we cannot complete cars because –
SAL: Basically, the whole line was stopped.
ELON: Yeah. Essentially –
because it's part of the wiring harness.
So you can't put the interior in without this cable.
And so we can either make a whole bunch of cars –
minus the interior –
which means that you got to stick them up in the yard –
SAL: The resale value would be no good.
ELON: It can be done, but --
the damned things go out of sequence –
SAL: Right. Right.
ELON: and it's way more inefficient.
You don't have a moving production line,
so then you have to send people out
to hundreds of cars that are sort of sitting in the storage yard.
And so we –
This happens to be a particularly pernicious cable
that's kind of routed under the carpet and in a difficult place.
And it's literally three dollars.
So, we basically had to send people
throughout the Bay Area to go and buy USB cables.
SAL: Like, literally, Radio Shack –
ELON: At Fry's.
SAL: Oh. Fry's. That's better.
ELON: You could have a hard time getting
a USB cable right now at Fry's.
SAL: Oh, really?
ELON: We just bought every one of them.
SAL: That's good.
ELON: And so we were able to continue production.
I don't want to belabor the anecdote.
But essentially, the supplier is in China.
And we had Plan A and Plan B.
And Plan A was like the normal supply chain process.
But what the supplier did was,
instead of sending our parts in their own package,
they grouped it together
with a bunch of other stuff for other companies,
and sent that all via
some extremely slow boat from China to LA.
And when it got to LA, the other stuff didn't pass customs.
SAL: Ohhh.
ELON: So they wouldn't let our stuff through, because –
SAL: They put in like a barrel of fruit or something,
ELON: I don't know what they put it in.
It's something that Customs didn't like.
The paperwork wasn't in order, or wWhatever.
So it got stuck there for, like, a couple of weeks.
And then we had Plan B.
So we call them and say,
"Look, you've got to airfreight some of these cables –
some of these little cables – to us."
And we talked to their US subsidiary,
and ordered them from the US subsidiary,
who then communicated with [the supplier in] China.
But then, because this was another batch of parts –
so it was kind of double the [usual] order –
it exceeded the credit limit that we had.
SAL: Oh! Yeah. You've gotta –
ELON: So it bounced off their credit limit.
So they didn't ship it.
SAL: Fascinating! So someone's losing their job now.
Nah, I'm kidding. [LAUGHTER]
You shouldn't fire anyone.
ELON: I mean, it's pretty farcical.
Anyway, so It's coming, like, tonight at 11PM or something.
SAL: Wow.
And these things are, happening, like, all the time?
– or this is an unusual circumstance?
ELON: That's like one example but there are many things like that.
SAL: I guess I mean that's a really good example because that kind of leads into
what I've always been fascinated by a lot of what you're doing
is well I guess I will start with
how did you get into this? I mean you know..
ELON: into cars?
SAL: Into cars, into taking over NASA?
into... well NOT taking over NASA...
of being a contractor for NASA...
ELON: Just for the record, we are not taking over NASA
SAL: Yes you are not taking over NASA.
They're an independent organization.
But you are becoming a major provider of services for NASA.
Obviously kind of internet payment and payments generally
I mean these are very... three completely different spaces
I think a lot of people would not take someone seriously
if they had a business plan in one of these.
ELON: Right.
SAL: Oh yeah, you can take your time
What was your...
I mean did you always think you're going to be doing this?
When did it dawn on you that
you would try to revolutionize three industries ?
ELON: Well, when I was in college
I didn't actually expect to do it.
So it was not like this is some long fulfilled expectation.
But when I was in college, I thought about
what were the areas that we most affect the future of humanity
and, in my opinion, and the three areas were
the internet, sustainable energy and space exploration.
Particularly if humanity would become multi planet species.
It's kind of like a pretty substantial bifurcation in our sort of future
if we are either out there among stars from local planets
or if we're confined to a...
until some obviously eventual extinction.
Not that I am pessimistic about life on earth...
Things are likely to be good ... even more likely to be good by far
SAL: Yellowstone's due for an explosion every 100s several 1000 years.
Someone knows about that ...
It's been 700,000 since ...
Right ...yeah...super volcano for those you don't know: it would envelope (the world).
ELON: Yeah exactly... I know exactly what you talked about...
SAL: We read the same books, I can tell.
ELON: Absolutely.
Something bad is bound to happen
if you give it enough time.
And civilization has been around
for such a very short period of time, that –
These time scales seem very long.
But on an evolutionary time scale
they're very short.
A million years on an evolutionary time scale
is really not much.
And the Earth's been around for 4 and 1/2 billion years.
So, that's a very tiny tiny amount of time, really.
But for us, that would be -
I mean, can you imagine if human civilization continued
at anything remotely [resembling] the current pace
of technological advance for a million years,
where would we be?
I think we're either extinct or on a lot of planets.
SAL: Yes. We should be.
ELON: These are our two options...
SAL: But given that. One: that's kind of as epic
as one can think about things – I mean, literally.
How did you make that concrete?
How does that turn into SpaceX, Tesla and PayPal?
ELON: Well, so I thought about these things
kind of in the abstract – not from the expectation
that I would actually have careers in those arenas.
But I wanted to be involved in at least one of them.
At first, I thought the best bet was going to be electric cars.
And so the area that I was studying
was advanced capacitors, right?
So essentially, those are capacitors that have
an energy density exceeding that of batteries –
because batteries have a very high-power density,
but low energy density.
SAL: Yeah.
[Maybe you should] have a lecture to that effect.
SAL: Oh yeah. We should do that – a little later –
ELON: [LAUGHS] Exactly.
So, obviously if you could make a capacitor
that had anywhere near the energy density of a battery –
with its incredibly high power density,
quasi-infinite cycle and calendar life,
then you'd have an awesome solution
for energy storage and mobile applications.
So, I was going to sort of work on that and try to
leverage the equipment that was developed
for advanced chip making and [??] –
to create ultra precise capacitors at the molecular level.
SAL: And this is when you were
going to go into grad school?
ELON: Yeah.
SAL: You had a brief stint at Stanford ...a PhD in Applied Physics
ELON: Applied Physics and Material Sciences... SAL: right this is what you were ...
even then you were thinking of kind of trying to do something in this space.
ELON: Well...actually this was
to work on energy storage solutions for electric cars.
SAL: Yeah.
ELON: And I actually worked at a company in Silicon Valley called Pinnacle Research
which did advanced capacitors.
There were electrolytic capacitors
and actually were pretty good. They had the energy density of a LED acid battery
which, for a capacitor, is a big deal.
But they used ruthenium titanium oxide.
And I think at the time
there was maybe one or two tons of ruthenium mined per year in the world.
So it's not a scalable solution.
But I thought there could be some solid state solution -
just like what I said - using chip-making equipment.
That was going to be the basic idea.
It was one of those things where
I wasn't sure if success was one of the possible outcomes.
You know... like you can't...
It's difficult to bound that problem exactly and say, "Okay..."
SAL: So you're saying, "I felt like this was a destined failure..."
It's another way to parse that sentence but anyway -
ELON: No I didn't think it would [necessarily] fail.
But I wasn't sure that success was a possibility.
SAL: OK yes.
ELON: You know, and generally,
[if] you want to embark on something, it's desirable to figure out
if success is at least one of the possibilities.
SAL: Right, exactly.
ELON: Because, for sure, failure is one of the possibilities.
SAL: Yes.
ELON: But ideally, you want to try to bracket it and say
success is in the envelope of outcomes.
SAL: Yeah
ELON: and I wasn't quite sure if that was the case.
I think success on an academic level would have been quite likely
because you can publish some useless paper.
And most papers are pretty useless.
SAL: We have a few: don't take offense.
ELON: I mean how many PhD papers are actually used
by someone ever?
SAL: That's a good point...
ELON: I mean, percentage wise it's not good
And so.... it could be one of those outcomes
where you add some leaves to the tree of knowledge.
And that leaf is: no it's not possible.
SAL: Right.
ELON: There goes 7 years of my life.
So that was sort of one path. I was prepared to do that.
But then the Internet was... the Internet came along it was like:
"Ok, the internet, I'm pretty sure success is one of the possible outcomes."
I could either do sort of a PhD and watch the Internet happen.
Or I could participate and help build it in some fashion, you know.
I just couldn't stand the idea of watching it happen.
Yeah,
So I decided to put things on hold
and start an Internet company.
And that was kind of...
We worked on Internet publishing software,
maps, directions, yellow pages kind of things.
We had as investors and customers
the media companies like New York Times company, Knight Ridder.
SAL: This was just the early stages. ELON: This was '95.
SAL: So its really early stages... so this [was] really out of the gate. ELON: Absolutely
So then we ...
The reason that we worked with the media companies is
because we didn't have money.
Like there was no advertising money in '95. SAL: Right
ELON: In fact, the idea of advertising on the Internet seemed like ridiculous to most people.
Obviously it's not ridiculous anymore. But
at the time it seemed like a very unlikely proposition.
A lot of the media companies weren't even sure that they should be online.
Like what's the point of that?
SAL: And did you all think that PayPal was going to be, you know, a simple little Internet way
Or did you think it was going to turn into
the major kind of transaction processing engine that it is right now?
ELON: I didn't expect PayPal's growth rate to be what it was.
That actually created major problems.
We started PayPal on University Avenue.
After the first month or so of the website being active,
we had 100,000 customers.
SAL: Really that ... well wow I didn't realize that.
And how did it start? How did people even know to use it?
And, I mean, both buyer and seller have to be involved.
ELON: Yeah
Well we started off first by offering people $20 if they opened an account,
and $20 if they referred anyone.
And then we dropped it to 10 dollars.
And the we dropped it to 5 dollars.
As the network got bigger and bigger,
the value of the network itself exceeded any sort of carrot that we could offer.
SAL: How much money did you spend with that kind of $5, $10, $20
incentive to get the critical mass going?
ELON: That was a fair amount ...I think it was probably
60 or 70 million dollars ... SAL: oh well so it was substantial.
So we're not talking peanuts here. This is ...
ELON: Yeah it depends on your relative scale.
It is a peanut to Google.
SAL: Yes well that's right, yes
ELON: I mean Google has got 50 billion.
Apple's got, I don't know, 150 billion some crazy amount of money.
That's cash... SAL: Yeah.
So that is not outlandish ... I didn't realize that was so core.
ELON: 1% of that would be 500 million dollars so it you know.
That's 0.1% of Google.
SAL: That's true. You are right. That's inexpensive.
ELON: Relative to that
proven pretty inexpensive.
SAL: That's right.
ELON: And then we did...we just did a bunch of things
to decrease the friction because -
and it's just like bacteria in a Petri dish -
what you want to do is try to have
one customer generate like two customers... SAL: yeah
ELON: Okay or something like that - or maybe 3 customers ideally.
And you want that to happen really fast,
and you can probably model it just like bacteria growth in a Petri dish.
It will just both expand very quickly until it hits the sides of the Petri dish.
And it slows down.
SAL: After PayPal then, I mean,
to some degree, especially in SiliconValley, you can understand the Internet.
We know people, I mean, PayPal is obviously onto the scale that is noteworthy.
But then Space X seems really, you know...
Well one, how did you decide, "I am definitely going to do that."
And then what's the first thing that you do?
Like how do you even like go out?
I don't even know how to start
trying to make a rocket company.
ELON: Neither did I really.
And in fact, the first 3 launches failed.
So it was[n't] like, you know, spot on -
did not hit the bull's eye.
SAL: But even getting to the point you're launching rockets. I don't even know how to
like how do you get there?
What did you do...like (1) what did you decide and what did you do on day one?
Like who would you call or did you write a plan, did you start...I don't even know.
ELON: Actually the urge of PayPal is ...oh Space X is that
I was trying to figure out why
that we have not sent any people to Mars
because the obvious next step after Apollo
was to send people to Mars.
But what in fact happened was that we sent a few people to the Moon
And then we didn't send anyone after that
to the Moon or Mars or anything.
But if you'd asked people in 1969
what would 2013 look like, they would have said
there'll be a base on the Moon.
There will be we would have at least sent some people to Mars
and maybe they'd even be a base on Mars offering space hotels
and there would be some stuff in space...Yeah.
And that's what people expected.
And if you said, well actually,
Unites States in 2013 will not be able to send anyone to orbit.
But I'll tell you what will exist is that there'll be this device in your pocket.
That's like the size of the...it's smaller than a deck of cards.
That has access to all the world's information.
You can talk to anyone on the planet Earth.
And even if you like in, you know,
some remote village somewhere, so long as...
something we called the Internet.
They wouldn't know what that means, of course.
Then you'd be able to communicate to anyone instantly
and have access to all of humanity's knowledge.
It's like bullshit. There is no way that's going to be.
SAL: Right right right
ELON: And yeah we already have that.
And space is not happening so
I was trying to figure out: what's the deal here?
This was 2001.
This friend of mine asked me what would I do after PayPal.
I said well you know I was always interested in space
but I don't think anything that an individual can do in space
because the province of government is usually large government.
But I'm curious as to when we're going to send someone to Mars.
so I went to NASA's website try to figure out
where is the place that tells you that.
I couldn't find that.
Either I'm bad at looking at the website or they have a terrible website.
Becasue surely ... SAL: that must be a big day
ELON: Yeah, this should be on the front page
And then I discovered actually that
NASA has no plans to send people to Mars
and or even really back to the Moon.
So this is really disappointing. I thought well maybe
this is a question of national will.
Do we need to
get people excited about space again?
And try to get NASA a bigger budget and
then we would send people to Mars?
And so I started researching the area
becoming more familiar with space
reading lots of books
I came with this idea to do something called 'Mars Oasis'
which was to send a small green house
It was seasoned dehydrated gel, upon landing, you hydrated the gel
You have green plants in a red background
and the public is
the public response to precedents and superlatives.
It's the ... it would be the first life on Mars...
The furtherest life has traveled
And you have this money shot green plants on the red background
That seem like
it would get people pretty excited
So that, I started getting into this
try to figure out okay
can I afford to build a spacecraft?
I had some money from PayPal
But it had to fit within that budget
I figure we have to do two missions because
if we only do one and fail
then it might have the opposite effect
SAL: You are willing to bet the farm so to speak on this...
ELON: yeah well
Yeah I figured like,
I was willing to spend half the money that I got from PayPal
with no expectation of return
SAL: Right
ELON: because i thought this was just something
that was pretty important and
I'm like
seem like I could spend half the money I made at PayPal on this
And if that got NASA a bigger budget...the result in us going to Mars
that would be a good...pretty good outcome
SAL: When your friends came and your family came up to you and said
look you know there're nations that can't do this you know,
You are a guy and you have some resources
What did you say or do or think
ELON: I had a lot of friends of mine trying to talk me out of
starting a rocket company because they thought it was crazy
One of my friends maybe watch a video of rockets blowing up
There are just lots of people thought it was a real crazy idea
Some people tring to start rocket companies had not succeeded
And that they tried to talk me out of it and
but the thing is that
the premise to talk me out of it was
"We think you're going to lose the money that you invest."
I was like yeah, well, that was my expectation anyway
So I don't really mind if I lose
I mind, but I mean it
It is not like I was trying to figure out
the rank or the best way to invest money right on that basis
So I chose space... thoughts like that
SAL: You weren't looking like the money market bonds
triple-A bonds, rocket company... ELON: real estate
invest in pew making or anything
Well the chase is just the highest ROI...that was not what I...what the fun is
I still thought that it was important that humanity expands beyond earth and
we weren't doing that. So maybe there are something I can do to
kinda spur...spur that on
I was able to compress the costs of the spacecraft and everything
down to a relatively manageable number
and I got stuck on the rocket
The US rockets were way too expensive
I ended up going to Russia and flew to Russia three times
to negotiate purchase of a ICBM
I tried to buy two of the biggest ICBMs in the Russian fleet
in 2001 and 2002
And actually the negotiator...
SAL: I just let those statements stand and I'm not even
ELON: That's...
SAL: Actually who did you call?
ELON: You open the yellow pages. Go to ICBMs
SAL: Like I mean how does this
And I don't get too much in the way..
And I am just curious about this one particular thing..you are...
You decided at some point you need to buy an ICBM
ELON: Yeah well actually at first I try to buy just the normal launch equipment
they use to launch satellites. Those were too expensive.
SAL: I see
ELON: The Boeing Delta II would have cost 65 million dollars each
and two would have been 130
and then I said well that breaks my budget right there
SAL: Yeah
ELON: And I tried to negotiate with them. I was not...
SAL: How much does an ICBM go for?
I am curious about market rate for one of those.
This is right after the fall. It might have gone up.
ELON: It's gone up a lot since then.
In 2001 it would've been about ten million dollars each.
Two would be twenty and then
And I thought I could get the rest of the mission
down to also around 10 per.. so we would have
a dual mission with like two identical launches, two identical spacecrafts
for like roughly forty million dollars
So I thought that ok I can do that and
SAL: But you must have had some like you know
rocket scientists advising you at this point
I mean this sounds like you were serious
ELON: yeah
I engaged a bunch of circuit consultants.
I kind of start to get familiar with the space industry.
But then after the third trip to Russia
I came to realize that I was actually wrong about
my first premise -- that there was a lack of will.
In fact, I think that there is a tremendous amount of will
in the United States for outer space exploration.
Because the United States is essentially
a nation of explorers.
It's a distillation of the human spirit of exploration.
So of course, it was quite so silly of me to think
that people lack motivation.
But what people don't want to think is that
sending people to Mars is going to be so expensive
that they'll have to give up healthcare or something
SAL: Right
ELON: They're not gonna do that.
So it's got to be [done in such a way] that
going to mars is not going to cause some
meaningful drop in their standard of living.
SAL: Right.
ELON: So it's like maybe
.25% to .5% of GDP – something like that is palatable.
Anyway so I thought ok it is not really gonna maybe matter that much
if I do this mission because
What really matters is having a way.
I was wrong, I thought I hope there was
there was enough will but actually there was plenty of will
if people thought there was a way.
So then I said, "Okay. I need to work on a way."
How hard is it really make a rocket?
"In history or historically all rockets have been expensive.
Therefore in the future, all rockets will be expensive."
But actuall, that's not true.
If you say, "What is a rocket made of?"
and say, "it's made of aluminum, titanium –
some copper –
carbon fibers, if you want to go that direction –
And you break it down and say,
"What is the raw material cost of all these components?"
And if you have them stacked on the floor,
and could wave a magic wand,
so that the cost of rearranging the atoms was zero,
then what would the cost of the rocket be?
As I was like, "Wow. It's really small.
It's like 2 percent of what a rocket costs."
SAL: Right.
ELON: So clearly, [most of the cost comes from how expensive
it is to arrange those] atoms.
You got to figure out – sort of – how can we [go about getting]
the atoms [assembled] in the right shape
much more efficiently.
SAL: Yeah.
ELON: So I had series of meetings
on Saturdays with people, some of whom were working
at the big aerospace companies,
just try to figure out if there is some catch here
that I am not appreciating.
SAL: Yeah.
ELON: I couldn't [find one].
It [didn't] seem that there [was] any catch, so ...
I started Space X.
SAL: And you ended up – you had some failures.
But obviously some huge successes.
What was the cost that you were able
to build this rocket for –
relative to what they were being built for before?
ELON: So, let's see.
For the Falcon One –
which was the first rocket we built –
the first three fights did not make it. in fact –
Yeah. I mean we got progressively further,
But, like, the first rocket came in and [crashed] –
– landed maybe a couple of hundred yards
away from the launch site – in tiny fragments.
So, anyway –
That rocket ended up costing around six million dollars –
SAL: Wow.
ELON: – compared to other rockets in that class –
which were about 25 million dollars.
SAL: Wow. That's [a] significant [saving].
ELON: Yeah. Like a quarter.
SAL: Wow. Wow.
ELON: But there is an even better step beyond that –
which is to make rockets reusable.
So ... right now ... that is around
what our
comparison prices is, excluding the refurbished ICBMs
If you say
building rocket from new
how does this Space X rocket compared to a rocket from Boeing or Lockheed?
It's about a quarter of the price
However if we make it reusable
then it can be two orders of magnitude cheaper
SAL: Two orders of magnitude cheaper...100th the price... ELON: that is right
SAL: So I mean... ELON: for you
SAL: Only today ... Memorial Day sale (laughter)
What ...
I have seen some ..you are doing those vertical landings
yeah...like literally out of the 1950s
like sci-fi movies ELON: yep
SAL: and that's what you're talking about.
ELON: Essentially the rockets need to come back and land in the launch site
and then reload propellant, take off again like an airplane.
SAL: How far do you think we are from that?
When do you think like you know your best guess is
when will we actually see that happening?
ELON: And I hope we can do it next year.
SAL: Okay yeah that's...
We've got some ambitious stuff at the Khan Academy for next year too (laughter)
Just we can compare.
We're redesigning the site you know.
Right
ELON: We have been working for a long time
Space X has been around for 11 years
And thus far we have not recovered any rockets.
We've recovered the spacecraft from orbit.
So, that was great.
But none of our attempts to recover the rocket stages have been successful
The rocket stages have always blown up basically on reentry
Now we think we've figured out why that was the case.
And it's a tricky thing because Earth's gravity is really quite strong
and with advanced rockets you can do maybe 2 to 3% of your lift off mass to orbit
typically
then reusability subtracts 2 to 3%
Then you go like nothing toward or negative
and
That's obviously not helpful
So the trick is to try to shift that from
say two-three percent
in and expendable configuration
put them to make the rocket
mass efficiency, engine efficiency and so forth
so much better that it moves to
around maybe 3.5 or 4% in an expendable configuration
And then try to be clever about the reusability elements
Try to drop that to around the 1.5 to 2% level
So you have a net payload to orbit of about 2%
SAL: But you're doing it one...two orders of magnitude cheaper
ELON: Yeah absolutely because ...
our Falcon line of rocket costs about 60 million dollars
But the propellant cost which is mostly oxygen
it's two thirds oxygen one third fuel
is only about 200 000 dollars.
SAL: Wow.
It's much like a –
I guess 747. It costs about as much to refuel our rocket as it does to refuel 747
You know within
We are pretty close essentially
SAL: What happens, assuming you are all successful
you all prove yourself to be successful on these audacious things in the past
I mean what happens and that seems likeit's
What happens in the next 5-10 years in this space industry
if you all are successful there?
I mean, do we get to Mars?
Do we have kind of market forces
commercialization of space starting to happen?
ELON: Yeah
Well the first step is that
we need to earn enough money to keep going as a company
So we have to make sure that we're launching satellites
commercial satellites so it's like
broadcast, communications, mapping
government satellites that do scientific missions –
earth-based or space-based missions, GPS satellites
that kind of thing.
And also service space station transfer cargo to and from space station
which we have done a few times.
Then taking people to and from the space station
So we've got to service the earth-based needs to launch satellites
and that pays the bills
but in doing that
keep improving the technology
to the point where we can make full reusability work
and we have sufficient scale and sophistication
to be able to take people to Mars.
SAL: Wow, so you think this is going to be a reality.
What's your best guess
when we're going to have someone on Mars?
ELON: I think probably about twelve years
SAL: twelve... and you think it'll be a round trip
It will be to have some type of permanent colony on Mars that
ELON: I think it's probably a roundtrip
SAL: Wow
So... ELON: it's not for sure.... SAL: I could talk about this for...I mean
People know I am... ELON: aspirational to be a round trip.
SAL: This is mind-blowing.
And I mean on Tesla,
Tesla is obviously from our, from my vantage
It's a huge success and it's...
What do you think is in that industry...
I want to be asking the same question what do you think, you know
This is something GM, Toyota
these massive multi-billion dollar organizations have been trying
you know, what gave you the confidence to kind of pursue it?
And now that it seems to be a huge success
where do you think this industry's going to be the next 5-10 years?
ELON: Yeah with Tesla
the goal is to try to accelerate
the advent of sustainable transport.
I think it would happen anyway
because it's just out of necessity
Because we have an unpriced externality
in the cost of gasoline
we weren't pricing in the environmental effects
of CO2 in the oceans [and] atmosphere,
that's causing the normal market forces
not to function properly.
So the goal of Tesla is to try
to act as a catalyst to accelerate
those normal forces, the normal sort of market reaction
that would occur.
We are trying to have catalytic effect on that
and try to make it happen – I don't know –
maybe 10 years sooner than it would otherwise occur.
Yeah that's the goal of Tesla.
So that's the reason I am making electric cars,
and not any other kind of car.
We also supply power trains to Toyota and to Mercedes
and maybe to other car companies in the future
to accelerate their production of electric vehicles.
So, that's the sort of goal there.
And so far it's working out pretty well.
SAL: I just saw in the news report the other day
that you sold more (Tesla) Model S-es than –
you're leading that segment of the industry –
that the Mercedes S class, the BMW 7 series,
the Lexus LS400 or whatever it is.
ELON: Yeah, actually, that seems to be the case.
And that's a
I didn't realize they sold so few cars in that segment.
SAL: That's
ELON: We are not selling that many cars.
We sold 5000 a quarter 12,000
SAL: Well out here they seem like you know every ...
ELON: Yeah but this is our home team you know
So it's...
We better sell a lot out of the Bay Area
SAL: Yeah...no but that ...and
What I mean it seems similar thing. I mean what would...
How did you start?
What gave you the confidence?
And do you see yourself, I mean, is
kind of major automotive mainstream brand in 5 or 10 years?
all the way down to kind of competing with the Honda Accords and Civics?
ELON: Yeah I mean the goal is not to...
it's not sort of to become a big brand
or to compete with Honda Civics.
We'd rather to advance the cause of electrical vehicles.
So, we're just gonna keep making
more and more electric cars
and driving the price point down.
So the industry is very firmly electric, you know.
Like maybe half of all cars made are electric –
or something like that.
Which is not to say we expect half of all cars.
We want to just have that catalytic effect
until at least that occurs.
I think the point which this
we're approaching half of all new cars made are electric,
then I think that's –
I'll consider that to be the kind of victory condition.
SAL: Wow.
ELON: And if so, the faster we can bring [about] that day,
the better.
SAL: When would be your guess when that happens?
ELON: I made a bet with someone about 3 years ago
that it would be sooner than 20 years.
So it's 17 years from now.
But that's – I think – that's conservative.
I think is probably maybe 13 or 14 years.
SAL: Wow, right about time – what happened
SAL: Right when we're going to Mars.
And it will be exciting times... yeah.
ELON: Absolutely true...it just could...
I also have been thinking about that:
it was like: those time frames are kind of a coincident
SAL: Yeah.
ELON: It's but yeah
I mean the nature of new technology adoption is it tends to follow an S curve
so what usually happens is people underpredict it in the beginning
because people tend extrapolate on a straight line.
And then they'll over predict that kind of midpoint
because there was late adopters and then
It'll actually take longer than people think
at the midpoint but
much shorter than people think at the beginning yeah
I am pretty excited about how things are going
It's...and in fact I think
that the pace of technology improvement is in energy storage
It is really
moving faster than anyone thinks ... SAL: wow
I got one or more ... what are we doing on time
9 o'clock how much time do you have?
ELON: I guess maybe another 15 minutes.
SAL: Okay
I'll finish with one last question before I open it up
What advice do you have for us at Khan Academy?
ELON: You guys are doing really great.
I was wondering if you had advice for me.
SAL: No
ELON: Yeah it seems like you are doing an amazing job of
really super leveraged, I mean, of this small team
you have a dramatic effect upon
SAL: Half the people don't even work here ... right it's right
ELON: So it's a very impressive thing you are doing
to spread knowledge and understanding throughout the world
SAL: The universe soon –
if you hold up your end of the bargain here
ELON: Yeah.
I mean it's actually kind of funny ...
You know, if you think what is education?
You're basically downloading data and algorithms
into your brain.
It's actually amazingly bad in conventional education.
It's like it shouldn't be this huge chore.
So you're making it way better.
But I think a lot of things I would say,
you've probably heard a hundred times.
And, in fact, if not doing.
The more you can gamify the process of learning, the better.
For my kids,
I do not have to encourage them to play video games.
I have to like pry them from their hands –
like crack (illegal drugs).
"Drop that crack needle."
SAL: You have that problem at your house, too.
The crack is addictive.
ELON: You know it's the degree to which you can
somehow make learning like a game.
Then that's better.
And I think unfortunately a lot of education
is very vaudevillian.
You've got someone standing up there
kind of lecturing at people.
And they've done the same lecture 20 years in a row.
And they're not very excited about it.
And that lack of enthusiasm is conveyed to the students.
Such that they're not very excited about it.
They don't know why they're there.
Like, "Why we are learning the stuff?
We don't even know why."
In fact, I think a lot of things people learn –
probably – there is no point learning them –
because they never use them in future.
SAL: Because who's going to launch a rocket into space?
That's just like – exactly – that never happens.
ELON: Well, you have to say, like, if you'll go, stand back,
and say, "Why are we teaching people these things?"
And – we should tell them, probably,
why we are teaching these things.
Because a lot of kids in school
kind of puzzled as to why they're there.
I think if you could explain the why of things
then that makes a huge difference to people's motivation.
They understand...
They understand purpose.
So that's pretty important.
Just make it entertaining.
But I think, just in general,
conventional education should be massively overhauled.
And I'm sure you very much agree with that.
The analogy I sometimes use is,
you've seen like Batman – like the Chris Nolan movie –
like the original one.
And it's pretty frickin awesome. Right?
You've got incredible special effects, great script
multiple takes, amazing actors, and great sound.
It's very... is very engaging
But if you would instead say okay that you have the same script
so at least the same script and you said ok now that script
instead of having movies, we're going to have
that script performed by the local town troupe.
Okay and so in every small town in America,
if movies didn't exist,
they'd have to, then, recreate the Dark Knight.
SAL: Right.
ELON: Like with home-sewn costumes, and, like
jumping across the stage –
not giving their lines quite right,
and not really looking like the people in the movie.
And no special effects – that would suck.
It would be terrible.
SAL: That's right. Very, very –
ELON: That's education.
SAL: So with that –
And I apologize to all of you guys for hogging up all the time.
Because obviously, I could talk for hours about this stuff.
But we do have time – I think 5 or 10 minutes – for a handful of questions.
If none of you all have any, I have about nine more. But yes –
QUESTION: So I noticed –
I picked up two kinds of themes from what you're discussing.
One was somewhat audacious goals.
And the other was
I don't think I heard you use the word 'profit'
in anything you spoke about.
You seemed to be – each thing is pointed at, like –
reinvigorating industry or
bringing back space missions –
How much of your success do you attribute to having really audacious goals
or versus just not being focused on the short term
you know money coming in or investors
ELON: Unfortunately, one does have to be focused on
short term money coming in when creating company
because otherwise company would die.
So, a lot of times people think
creating companies is going to be fun.
I would say it's not. It's really not that fun
There are periods of fun
and there are periods of where it's just awful.
Particularly if you're the CEO of the company
you actually have a distillation of all the worst problems
in the company
There is no point in spending time on things that are going right.
So you only spend your time on things that are going wrong.
And the things that are going wrong that
other people can't take care of... you're like the worst
You have a filter for the crappiest problems from the company
the most pernicious and painful problem.
So I wouldn't say .. I think you have to feel quite compelled to do it
and have a fairly high pain threshold and as a friend of mine
who says like starting companies is like
staring into the abyss and eating glass.
There is some truth to that.
The staring into the abyss part is that you're gonna be constantly facing
the extermination of the company
because most startups fail.
90% or 99% of startups fail.
So ...
That's the staring into the abyss part because you constantly say
if I don't get this right, the company will die.
Should be quite stressful
And then the eating glass part is
You've got you've got to do
You got to do the problems....
You got to work on the problems of the company needs to work on
not the problems you want to work on
So you end up working on problems
that you really wish you weren't working on
So, that's the eating glass part.
And that goes on for a long time
QUESTION: So how do you keep your focus on the big picture
when you constantly face with
you could be out of business in a month?
Well it's just a very small percentage of mental energy is on the big picture,
like you know where you are generally heading for
And the actual path is going to be some sort of zigzagy thing in that direction
You try not to deviate too far from the path that you want to be on,
but you're gonna have to do that to some degree
But I don't want to diminish, I mean
I think the profit motive is a good one
if the rules of an industry are properly set up
So there is nothing fundamentally wrong with profit.
Profit just means that people are paying you more
for whatever you're doing
than you're spending to create it.
That's a good thing.
If that's not the case
then you'll be out of business and rightfully so
Sure you're not adding enough value
But now there are cases of course
where people will do bad things
in order to achieve profit.
But that's actually quite unusual
because usually the rules are set up
mostly correctly like not completely, but mostly correctly.
SAL: Well we have time for one more question. Joe?
QUESTION: I have an important one... SAL: ok very good yes
QUESTION: So a few months ago you teased Hyperloop
and we haven't heard anything since.
So first of all, a few of us engineers are talking about
and I think we have a few ideas if you need help.
But if you feel comfortable
maybe you could tell us a little bit more.
ELON: I was reading about the California high-speed rail.
It was quite depressing
because California taxpayers
are going to be on the hook to build
the most expensive high-speed rail per mile in the world –
and the slowest.
Those are not the superlatives you want.
And it's like: Damn, like we're in California we make super high-tech stuff
Why are we gonna be spending 100 billion dollars
for something that will take two hours
to go from LA to San Francisco
Like okay why can't I get a plane to do that in 45 minutes
It doesn't make much sense.
Isn't there some better way to do it than that?
So if you just say ok, well, what would you ideally want
in a transportation system you take?
Well, you'd want something that –
relative to existing modes of transportation –
is faster, twice as fast, costs half as much per ticket
can't crash –
is immune to weather –
You can make the whole thing like self powered --
with solar panels, or something like that.
That would be great...a good outcome.
And so what would do that
and what's the fastest way,
short of inventing teleportation that you could do something like that.
Some of the limits to that solution are fairly obvious
and some are not so obvious.
And then the details...
the devil's in the details of actually making something like that work.
But I came into conclusion that there is something like that could work
and would be practical.
SAL: Is this around the vacuated tubes?
The vacuum tubes well the old bank....
ELON: It's something like that
SAL: We haven't been more public with what this is?
ELON: No. Although I did say that once Tesla was profitable,
that I would talk more about it.
But we haven't done our earning's call yet.
So I think I'll probably do it after the earning's call... SAL: yeah
ELON: The thing is,
I’m kind of strung out on the things that I am doing.
So adding another thing –
SAL: Yeah.
ELON: It's like -- It doesn't --
You know, that’s a lot.
SAL: Learning the guitar.
You could pick up all sorts of things.
ELON: Right. I tried learning the violin.
That’s, by the way, a hard thing to learn. LAUGHS.
SAL: Yes. Launching rockets – electric cars,
ELON: Yeah.
SAL: revolutionizing transportation. Yeah. That’s easy.
ELON: I cannot play the violin at all.
I'm very horrible.
If you think about the future,
you want a future that’s better than the past.
And so if we had something like the Hyperloop,
I think that would be, like, “Cool!”
You’d look forward to the day that was working.
And if something like that –
even if it were only in one place –
from LA to San Francisco, or New York to DC,
or something like that –
Then it would be cool enough
that it would be like a tourist attraction.
SAL: Yeah.
ELON: It would be like a ride or something.
So even if some of the initial assumptions didn’t work out –
the economics didn’t work out quite as one expected –
it would be cool enough that [people would say]
“I want to journey to that place just to ride on that thing.”
That would be pretty cool.
SAL: Wow.
ELON: And, so that’s, I think, how,
If you come up with a new technology,
it should feel like that.
You should really –
If you told it to an objective person,
would they look forward to the day
that thing became available?
It’d be pretty exciting to do something like that.
Or an aircraft.
like, I thought it was really disappointing
when the Concord was taken out of commission,
and there was no supersonic transport available.
SAL: Yeah.
ELON: And of course, the 787 has had some issues.
ELON: So. But the thing is, the 787,
even in the best case scenario,
is only a slightly better version of the triple seven (777).
SAL: Yeah.
ELON: And it’s like, OK. It’s not that exciting.
SAL: So this is something that you are working on.
ELON: I wouldn’t say “working on.”
SAL: And one day, in the not-too-far-[off] future --
or there are some plans or consultants involved or something.
ELON: LAUGHS.
SAL: You’ve made some phone calls to Russia?
ELON: Every now and then, it's sort of percolating away.
I’m not actively thinking about it.
But then there is some new element of that –
I’ll think, “Oh well, you know, this would make it better.”
SAL: Fascinating.
SAL: No. Well, thanks.
I think I’m speaking for everyone [when I say]
This is like the most epic possible conversation
one could have over about the course of an hour.
And I think all of us would love to chat with you
for hours on end.
But thank you so much.
I mean, I know you have a lot of free time,
and so, it probably wasn’t that big of a deal
for you to come here.
ELON: Yeah.
SAL: But yeah, it was a huge honor.
And I think that it inspired all of us to go out
and change the world and the universe.
ELON: Cool. All right.
SAL: Thank you very much.