Consider the following:
Imagine two rooms,
inside each room is a switch
In one room there is a man who flips his switch
according to a coin flip.
If it's heads, that signals that the switch is on --
And if it's tails, the switch is off.
In the other room, a woman switches her lights
based on a blind guess.
She tries to simulate randomness without a coin.
Then we start the clock
and they make their switches in unison.
Can you determine which light bulb
is being switched by a coin flip?
The answer is Yes.
But how?
And the trick is to think about properties of the sequence
rather than looking for any specific pattern.
For example, first we may try
to count the number of 1's and 0's
which occur in each sequence.
This is close, but not enough
since they were both seen fairly even.
The answer is to count sequences of numbers
such as runs of three consecutive switches
A true random sequence would be equally likely
to contain every sequence of any length
This is called the frequency stability property
and its demonstrated by this uniform graph.
The forgery is now obvious.
Humans favour certain sequences when they make guesses
resulting in uneven pattern, such as we see here.
One reason this happens
is that we make mistake thinking that
certain outcomes are less random than others.
But realize, there is no such thing as a lucky number.
There is no such thing as a lucky sequence.
If we flip a coin 10 times, it is equaly likely to come up
all heads, all tails, or any other sequence you can think of.