lets say we have two banks
bank a and bank b. and you might already know that banks, all banks, lend out the great majority of the
money that they get in as deposits, but they keep some of the money as reserves.
One just in case their depositors come and say "Hey can I have some of my money back?" and two, because
the central bank, the Federal Reserve, says you have to keep a certain amount of your deposits in reserve.
There is a reserve requirement. But you could imagine over the course of doing transactions
thousands of transactions a day, millions maybe, maybe bank b, more of its depositors come by
and say hey, "Give me some of my deposits back!"
Obviousl, he's lent out a lot of that money so he starts running low on reserves.
Maybe Bank A, the depositors haven't asked for the money, or for whatever reason,
maybe Bank A is sitting on a lot of cash
So in this situation, what you're going to have happen is Bank A is going to lend some reserves
is going to lend some cash to Bank B.
So this is lending some cash.
And they'll charge an interest rate for lending that cash.
Maybe it'll be 5% interest.
And that will be 5% per day (and usually these loans are on a per day basis),
and then the next day they will be renegotiated on a per day basis, but it's not 5% per day,
it'll be 5% per year, so it'll be some much smaller fraction.
But usually, as I mentioned, lending goes on a per day basis.
So we'll say "Hey this is your cash for tonight, if you need it for the next night, we'll talk again."
And maybe it'll be another 5% or maybe the interest rate can change again.
Now lets say that the Federal Reserve is sitting over here, and for whatever reason,
wants to stimulate the economy. So this is the Fed, and they want to stimulate the economy.
So they start printing some money. I should do money in green!
So the Federal Reserve here starts printing money. And they want to do two things:
they want to inject this money into the banking system, which essentially will, hopefully, find its way
into the economy, and they also want to lower the interest rate, especially the short
term interest rate, this overnight borrowing.
Remember, this is the annual interest rate but this is an overnight loan.
So when I talk about the short term interest rate I'm talking about the interest rate on loans that
are made over very short periods of time. So what the Federal Reserve will do is called
"Open Market Operations." They will go to the market, maybe directly to these banks,
or some other banks, and they will buy treasuries.
They will give this money to the market, and in exchange they will usually
buy treasury securities, sometimes something slightly different, but usually very safe securities.
And maybe its temporarily buy (I'll talk about repurchase agreements in the future).
And what happens is, this cash goes into the hands of the people who just sold
these Treasury securities, and they have to deposit it in banks,
and so they might deposit it in this bank over here,
the might deposit it in this bank over here,
or other banks. But the net effect is that there's more cash now in the banking system.
And if there's more cash in the banking system this guy right over here needs less
This guy needs less cash, so it lowers demand.
It lowers the demand for cash.
And then this guy has more to give. so it raises supply.
It raises supply because some people maybe just took some of this cash and deposited it.
So if it raises the supply of cash, and this guy needs it less,
then the rate to borrow this cash is going to go down.
So maybe instead of 5%, it goes down to 4%.
So what that would do is it would lower the short term of the yield curve.
So let me draw a yield curve right over here.
So this is maturity on this axis, and this is yield.
And lets say that the yield curve before looked like this.
Lets say it looked like this where this over here is 5%.
And this is overnight. This might the yield on 1 year debt, and this might be the yield on
maybe 5 year debt.
But by doing this open market operation the Fed was able to do both of its goals.
It was able to inject cash, printed cash, into the economy, and its also able to lower the interest rate.