Greek vases were made of terracota or baked clay.
Before the clay could be used for pottery,
pebbles and other impurities had to be removed.
First, the potter mixed the raw clay with water
in large outdoor pools, to make a thick silty liquid.
This liquid clay stood until the heavier impurities had settled to the bottom.
The refined liquid was then drained off into a second pool.
The potter repeated this settling process several times.
The pool was then left to evaporate in the sun,
leaving behind the refined clay.
The final step in preparing the clay for potting
was called "wedging".
The potter systematically compressed and folded the clay,
making it more malleable and mixing together
any parts that may have settled into layers.
The clay was now ready for use.
Most Greek vases were thrown or formed on the potter's wheel.
The complex shapes of Greek pottery often required
that the vase be thrown in pieces
and then assembled.
For example, to make a kylix or cup,
the potter first centered the clay on the wheel.
When it stopped wobbling,
the potter began a central hole.
Pressure from the potter's fingers inside the hole
gradually widened this opening
and formed the bowl of the cup.
Aside from the wheel,
the potter's main tools were his hands,
although a wet sponge was often used to smooth the surface.
To make the foot of the cup,
the potter again centered the clay,
drew it up and then hollowed out the stem.
The next day, when the formed pieces had dried slightly,
the bowl of the cup was trimmed with a metal shaver
and received a final smoothing.
The potter used wet clay
to bond the separately made bowl and foot
and then smoothed over the joint.