This is a video for the measuring angles model
because clearly at the time I am doing this video there
is no video for the measuring angles module.
This is a pretty neat module it was made by Omar Izwan
who is one of our amazing highschool interns
that we had this past summer the summer of 2011.
What it really is is it makes you measure angles. He made this cool
protractor tool here so that you actually use a protractor to measure the angles
and so the trick here is you actually measure it the way ypou would measure an angles using
any physical protractor. You would want to put the center
of the protractor right at the vertex of where the lines intersect
(The vertex of the angle). and then youd want to rotate
is at zero degrees is at one of these
sides so lets do it so this edge right here is right along this line
so let me rotate it. so then I'm gonna rotate a little bit further that looks... one more? That looks
about right and then if you look at it this way you can see
that the angle and I don't have my pen tool here I'm just using my
regular web browser so if you look at the angle here you see that the other line goes to 130 degrees
So this angle that we need to measure here is one hundred and 30 degrees let me check my answer
Very good I got it right it would be embarrassing if I didn't lets do the next question. I'll do a couple examples like this
so once again , let us put the center of protractor
right at the vertex right over there
and lets get this zero degree side to be on
one of the sides of the this angle kind of be within the protractor
so let me rotate it this way ,its really pretty cool.
so,let see lets do it one more time its too far.
its look about right,let the angle right over here it is ,
if you look at the other line points to in its 40 degrees
please check the answer very good lets do another one .
this is fun,alright so lets get our protractor we have already know how to do in a such a way
you can rotate if first so,that the zero degrees is,
wat you have to do rotate its zero degree to its one of the sides
so, that the angle is still within the protractor so,lets rotate it around
so,if we did like that you know how to do it in such a same way
we should rotate it when you have centre of the protractor at the vertex
of the angle so,it will rotate little bit more so,
this is zero degree is this line as we go further further opposite side i guess
since ,this is on side if it is a other line gets us to 150 degree.
lets do one more now i want to show you what not to do so,
what not to do is we could put the center right over there
let me put,let me make the zero above right over this side
right over here,if you did that notice,
your angle will not be within the protractor so you want to be measure
your tempting to do this measure these outer angle how we used it is an angle but does not the angle
with this question is asking is to measure
this is a arc over here telling us does the angle that we measures that arc has to be within the
protractor so,lets rotates this protractor little bit more
i have already did it,and so,
this looks like zero degrees and this right over here is 60 degrees.
we got the right answer