So in my "Sphereflakes" video,
I joked about folding and cutting space-time.
But then I thought, "Hey, why not?"
So, uh, how do you do that?
Well, when we wanted to fold and cut only space,
we chose a medium that takes place in space –
that is static paper cutouts, or a sphere sculpture.
But to fold and cut time,
we need a medium that happens over time.
I choose music.
Music has two easily recognizable dimensions.
One is 'time,'
and the other is 'pitch-space' –
not quite the same as space-space,
but it's one-dimensional –
which makes things easier.
But let's not get confused with the notation.
There are a few things to notice
about written music – firstly, that it's not music.
You can't listen to this.
Or, well, you can. But it'll be like –
[Sounds of paper being loudly rustled with fingers.]
It's not music. It's music notation.
And you can only interpret it
into the beautiful music it represents.
Kind of like how a book is squiggles on a page
that your brain interprets into a meaningful story.
And maybe don't understand it at all,
or you understand just a literal
surface meaning of the action.
Or maybe you can read deep and critically
into a story that simple on the surface,
and get more from it than even the author intended.
Math is like this too.
Secondly, written music represents
a two-dimensional space of pitch and time,
but only represents it.
Like there's the suggestion that this is the time axis.
But it's not.
This is exactly the same as this, even though
you're changing the values on the x-axis –
at least in standard music notation.
Some more modern composers do make use
of spatial notation – just like some poets
do intentionally stretch out words
or play with formatting.
But in standard notation, a stretched out word
only means your text editor
is terrible at justifying margins –
and has nothing to do with the word itself.
Pitch also doesn't entirely depend
on the notes placed on the y-axis.
So I'm going to use something
a little closer to reality.
I've got this music box that plays a paper tape.
As you put the strip through the box,
it plays the punched holes.
[Ascending notes play one after another.]
Hold on. It's too quiet.
This is why music boxes
usually come attached to wooden boxes.
I don't have a wooden box.
Maybe this nice wooden bowl.
Umm.
[Sound of a small drill going through thin wood.]
Ahh! There we go. Music bowl.
Anyway. Here, distance along the strip does translate
directly to time, assuming constant crank speed.
[Ascending tones being played.]
The box also has a set C-major scale on one staff.
So pitch space is represented pretty directly.
You don't have to worry about sharps and flats,
or the space between staves,
or the infinite possibilities
on the continuous logarithmic frequency scale.
The box magically ignores all notational elements
except for where and when the holes are.
Each hole, each note,
is a point on this strip of space-time.
So now let's fold it and cut it.
It's easy to fold time so that it goes
both forwards and backwards simultaneously.
Then we can punch in some notes and unfold it into
a symmetric melody that goes
first forwards and then backwards –
or first backwards and then forwards.
Point is it's reversible.
It sounds the same whether you play it like this –
[Ascending tones being played.]
[Descending tones being played.]
Or like this.
[Ascending tones being played.]
But maybe you'll want to fold time
into one finite chunk.
Then you could put two mirror lines
which reflect themselves – which means
folding time back and forth infinitely
to get a little time chunk to cut up.
And sometimes cutting through infinitely folded
space-time requires the use of power tools.
But then you can unfold a repeating
back and forth musicky thing.
[Many tones being played.]
Or you could leave time alone and fold space,
if that's what you're into.
And that sounds like this.
[Tones being played.]
Or you could do both.
Maybe you could try folding at other angles,
but now you're mixing up the space and time axes.
And mixing space with time is hazardous.
Though you could flip both space and time,
which is like rotating the music 180 degrees.
This one is especially fun,
because you can rotate any piece of sheet music
and try playing it upside down.
And it's not just upside down,
but backwards in time too.
[Music tones being played.]
Anyway, maybe you want patterns
that aren't all mirror lines.
Like what about a simple repeating melody?
Can we fold and cut that?
Yes. Loop up the paper cut then unfold.
Or if you're feeling snazzy, do the melody once,
then loop the paper through the box.
[Tones being played.]
This is probably the part where seasoned viewers
will be yelling something about Mobius strips.
In the first snowflakes video,
I did fold up a Mobius strip and cut it.
Okay. Here's what happens.
The strip unravels to give you your shapes
and then they repeat – but upside down.
And then they repeat, but flipped again.
It's a glide reflection –
and an example of how glide reflections really are
their own special sort symmetry –
different from just a combination of reflections –
which looks like this–
and translation which look like this.
and which, together, give you this.
So if you fold space time into a Mobius strip,
you get your melody, and then the inversion –
the melody played upside down.
And then right side up again.
And so on.
Or rather than folding and cutting all of space-time
just cut and tape a little loop of space-time,
into a Mobius strip to be played over ... and over ...