Find the slope of the line that goes through the ordered
pairs (4, 2) and (-3, 16).
So just as a reminder, slope is defined as rise over run
or you could view that as rise is just a change in y
and run is a change in x
The triangles here, there's the delta symbol
it literally means "change in"
Or another way, and you might see this formula and
it tends to be really complicated
but just remember it's just these two things over here
Sometimes slope will be specified with the variable m
and they'll say m is the same thing
(and this is really the same thing as change in y)
They'll write y2 minus y1 over x2 minus x1
And this notation tends to be kind of complicated
but all this means is you take the y value of your endpoint
and subtract from it the y value of your starting point
That'll essentially give you your change in y
and it says take the x value of your endpoint
and subtract it from the x value of your starting point
and that'll give you your change in x
So whichever of these work for you, let's actually
figure out the slope of the line that goes through these
two points.
So we're starting at
(actually we can do it both ways)
we can start at this point and go to that point and calculate the slope,
or we can start at this point and go to that point and calculate the slope.
So let's do it both ways.
So let's say our starting point is the point (4,2)
And let's say our endpoint is (-3, 16)
So what is the change in x over here
What is the change in x in this scenario
So we're going from 4 to -3
if something goes from 4 to -3, what was its change?
You have to go down 4 to get to zero
Then you have to go down another 3 to get to -3.
So our change in x here is -7
Actually, let me write it this way
Our change in x is equal to -3 - 4 which is equal to
-7
If I'm going from 4 to -3, I went down by 7
Our change in x is -7
Let's do the same thing for the change in y
And notice: I implicitly use this formula over here
our change in x was this value - our endpoint
our end x value minus our starting x value
let's do the same thing for our change in y
Our change in y
If we're starting at 2 and we go to 16 that means
we moved up 14
Or another way you could say it is:
You could take your ending y value
and subtract from the your starting y value
and you get 14
So what is the slope over here?
Well the slope is just change in y over change in x
So the slope over here is change in y over change in x
which is: our change in y is 14
and our change in x is -7
And if we want to simplify this 14 divided by -7 is -2
Now what I want to show you is we could have done it
the other way around
We could have made this the starting point and this the endpoint.
And what we would have gotten is the negative values
of each of these, but they would have cancelled out
and we would still get -2.
Let's try it out. So let's say that our start point
was (-3,16) and let's say that our endpoint is (4,2)
So in this situation, what is our change in x?
Our change in x.
If I start at -3 and I go to 4, that means I went up 7
Or if you want to just calculate that, you would do 4 - -3
but needless to say, we just went up 7
And what is our change in y
Our change in y over here
Or you could say our "rise"
If we start at 16 and we end at 2, that means we
went down 14.
Or you could just say 2 - 16 is -14.
We went down by 14 - this is our run.
So if we say rise over run, which is the same thing as change
in y over change in x.
Our rise is -14 and our run here is 7.
So notice these are just the negatives of these values from
when we swapped them.
So once again, this is equal to -2.
Let's just visualize this - let me do a quick graph here
just to show you what a downward slope would look like
So let me draw our two points
So this is my x axis
That is my y axis
So this point over here, (4,2), so let me graph it
So, we're going to go all the way up to 16, so let me save some space here
So we have 1, 2, 3, 4
it's 4 comma 1 ... 2
So (4,2) is right over here
Then we have the point (-3, 16)
So let me draw that over here
So we have -1 ... 2 ... 3
and we have to go up 16, so this is 2 ... 3 ... 4 ... 5 ... 6 ... 7 ... 8 ... 9 ... 10 ... 11 ... 12
13 ... 14 ... 15 ... 16
So it goes right over here
So this is (-3,16).
So the line that goes between them is going to look something like this
I'm going to try my best to draw a relatively straight line
That line will keep going.
So that's my best attempt.
And notice it's downward sloping - as you increase in x
value the line goes down.
It's going from the top left to the bottom right
As x gets bigger, y gets smaller
that's what a downward sloping line looks like
And just to visualize our change in x's and our change in y's
that we dealt with here,
when we started with (4,2) and ended at (-3,16)
That was analogous to starting here and ending over there
And we said our change in x was -7
We have to move back our run
We had to move in the left direction by 7
That's why it was -7
And then we had to move in the y direction positive 14
That's why our rise was positive
So it's 14 over -7, or -2.
When we did the other way, we started at this point, and ended at this point
Started at (-3,16) and ended at that point.
So in that situation our run was positive 7
And now we had to go down in the y direction since we
switched the starting and the end point.
And now we have to go down -14.
Our run is now positive 7, and our rise is now -14
Either way, we got the same slope.