Is the system of linear equations below
dependent or independent, and they gave us
two equations right here.
Before I tackle this specific problem,
let's just do a little bit of review of what
dependent or independent means.
And actually, I'll compare that to
consistent and inconsistent.
So, just to start off with, if we're dealing
with systems of linear equations in two dimensions,
there's only three possibilities
that the lines, or the equations,
can have relative to each other. So let me
draw the three possibilities. Let me draw
three coordinate axes. So that's my first x-axis
and y-axis, so x and y. Let me draw another
one. And that is x, and that is y. Let me draw
one more, because there's only three possibilities
in two dimensions, x and y, if we're dealing with
linear equations, x and y. So you can have
the situation where the lines just intersect in
one point, so you can have one line like that,
and maybe the other line does something
like that, and they intersect at one point.
You could have the situation where the two
lines are parallel. So you could have the situation
actually let me draw it over here, where
you have one line that goes like that, and
the other line has the same slope, but
it's shifted, it has a different y-intercept,
so maybe it looks like this, and you have no points
of intersection. And then you could have the
situation where they're actually the same line,
so that both lines have the same slope
and the same y-intercept. So really, they are
the same line, they intersect on infinite number
of points. Every point on either of those lines
is also a point on the other line. So just to give
you a little bit of the terminology here, and
we learned this in the last video, this type of
system, where they don't intersect,
where you have no solutions, this is an
inconsistent system.
And by definition, or I guess just taking the
opposite of inconsistent, both of these
would be considered consistent. Both of these
are consistent.
But then, within consistent, there's obviously
a difference, here we only have one
solution, these are two different lines
that intersect at one place. And here,
they're essentially the same exact line.
And so we differentiate between these two
scenarios by calling this one over here
independent, and this one over here dependent.
So independent, both lines are doing their own
thing, they're not dependent on each other,
they're not the same line. They will intersect
at one place. Dependent, they're
the exact same line, any point that satisfies
one line will satisfy the other.
Any point that satisfies one equation,
will satisfy the other. So with that said,
let's see if this system of linear equations
right here is dependent or independent.
So they're kinda having us assume that
it's going to be consistent. That we're either
going to intersect at one place, or we're
going to intersect at an infinite number
of places. And the easiest way to do this,
we already have this second equation here,
it's already in slope-intercept form,
we know the slope is -2, the y-intercept is 8.
Let's put this first equation up here in
slope-intercept form and see if it has
a different slope or a different intercept,
or maybe it's the same line. So we have
4x plus 2y is equal to 16.
We can subtract 4x from both sides,
what we want to do is isolate the y on the
left hand side. So let's subtract 4x from
both sides. The left hand side we are
just left with a 2y, and then the right hand side,
we have a -4x plus 16. I
just wrote the -4 in front of the 16
just so that we have it in the traditional
slope-intercept form. And now we can
divide both sides of this equation by 2,
so that we can isolate the y on the left-hand side.
Divide both sides by 2, we are left with
y is equal to -4 divided by 2 is -2x
plus 16 over 2, plus 8. So all I did is
algebraically manipulated this top equation
up here, and when I did that, when I solved
essentially for y, I got this right over here,
which is the exact same thing as the
second equation. We have the exact same
slope, -2, -2, and we have the exact
same y-intercept, 8 and 8. If I were
to graph these equations, that's my
x axis, and that is my y-axis,
both of them have a y-intercept at 8
and have a slope of -2.
So they look something, I'm just drawing
an approximation of it, but they would look
something like that. So maybe this is the graph of
this equation right here, this first equation.
And then the second equation will be
the exact same graph, it has the exact
same y-intercept and the exact same slope.
So clearly these two lines are dependent.
Dependent. They have an infinite number
of points that are common to both of them
because they're the same line.