as we've already talked about multiple
times world war one broke out in
nineteen forty in the beginning of it
was all about austria hungary
declaring war on serbia using the
assassination of archduke francis
ferdinand as the pretext for declaring
war on serbia this was in july july
twenty eighth nineteen fourteen to
declare war on serbia and if you are
military analyst at the time
you would have assumed that this would
have been kind of a quick actions and
this is why frankly are stronger was so
eager to declare war on serbia they
thought it would be very easy for them
to put the serbians out of commission
austria hungary
you're talking about this empire here
huge economy huge military industrial
complex
huge army
serbians much smaller country
much poorer country they'd also fought
several recent wars they were very
ill-equipped so any military analyst
with bob that this would be a short war
but nineteen fourteen did not prove that
way for the austro-hungarian to dissect
really who could be viewed as a huge
victory
a few surprise for the service of the
serbians were able to keep the
austro-hungarian spac
serbians
serbians hold
now this isn't to say that was an
incredibly incredibly incredibly block
bloody you've had several offensives
across the border into serbia
the austro-hungarian briefly captured
belgrade the serbian scattered back
in the meantime tens and hundreds of
thousands of folks
or dying
but at the end of nineteen fourteen
you to surprise a military analysts and
the serbians were able to hold despite
being less equipped
and and despite just being a uh... a
smaller country
the lock for the serbians did not hold
up dot well
as we go into nineteen fifteen
by nineteen fifteen other parties other
than the austro-hungarian ps
decide to get involved again get
involved against the serbians
in particular
you have the bulgarians that prior to
nineteen fifteen they're kind of trying
to figure out who woodside of the war
they want to fall in on
but they have had several battles or
several wars recently with serbia wanted
as recently as nineteen thirteen they
were here too
captor back some territory
so nineteen fifteen the bulgarians
joined at the war on the side of the
central powers
as we exit nineteen fifteen you have a
joint offensive between the bulgarians
the austro-hungarian sp and of the
germans
against this small country
against the small country of serbia and
the germans interest other than the fact
that they want to support their their
ally all stronger the austria
there are also either
to take control of the railways between
berlin in constantinople in that railway
what did went into
went into serbia
and so if they were able to capture this
take serbia out of the war than they
were able to they would be able to send
supplies much more easily to the to the
on him into their other allied
the autumn an empire
so on october of nineteen fifteen
october of nineteen fifteen you have a
joint offensive
between the german army this is what
this map right here's to depicting right
over here this is a third austrian army
this is the eleventh german army
this is the first a bulgarian army this
is the second bulgarian army and their
joint offensive it's usually successful
for the central powers there so she able
to roll into serb it's actually
and press it on the side of the serbians
that took this much force
for to be able to roll through serbia
but they were able to roll through
serbia essentially occupy all serbia
they put the serbian army on the run
and and the only redeeming thing is that
some
for the serbians is that some element of
the serbian army
was actually able to escape
through montenegro and albania and and
some of the civilians
and then they were transported by the
allies by the entire
to be over crew parade and then joined
as will see on the massive dhoni infront
sun nineteen fifteen
nineteen fifteen you have the central
powers
central powers
rolled through serbia
role
through
serbia so from from you know if any of
the right now serbia is essentially lost
now right wing that was happening the
the allies had recognized that serbia
was an adept very difficult situation
and as we will got to the end of
nineteen fifteen they did start the
french and british troops
did start to land
did start to land in salon aka right
over here
uh... in order to
one would think help
the serbian help of the serbian forces
now they were able to arrive enact in
enough time to prevent what happened and
october of
approver of nineteen fifteen
you have some french forces that were
able to essentially distracted the
bulgarian second army bed uh... aidid to
some degree the serbian retreat
but essentially they started to build
they start to build their own forces
right over here in salon ago
now this is interesting because we're
talking about this region right over
here and of massive dzone img greece
and at this point in the war greece had
st
neutral
the king was leaning towards king
constantine the first
he was a leaning towards the central
powers while the prime minister and i
wanna i'm sure i'm going to see this
incredibly
the needs of those
pretty he was leaning towards the allied
parties and so you had started have this
kind of disconnect between the two and
the prime minister resigns but he has
got active support especially especially
and kind of massive doni and especially
in massive increase in odyssey
he has support he has support amongst
the allies
so if you go into nineteen sixteen
as you go into nineteen sixteen you have
a coup for vin diesel os
in the mat and nasa do any increase
especially in and round salon aka
which is essentially being held by the
allies even though greece is essentially
as is officially neutral
so coup
crew for
the needs of
the needs of those
which leads to a very interesting
situation so after the coup for videos
alos
is actually have greece
kind of massive dorian grease is under
the control of supporters of unease alos
and supporters of the allies
while the rest of greece while the rest
of grease is still
is still loyal to the king and the king
is leaning towards the central powers
but it's not really clear what what what
he wants to do about it
then you get into nineteen seventeen
the allies start to get a little bit
forceful about it in nineteen seventeen
the have a blockade
they apply a blockade of southern greece
on c_ blockades are always inflict a lot
of hardship economic hardship human
hardship
uh... on civilians but this is socially
forces in june
june
of nineteen seventeen
constantine the first
constantine
constantine go
does into exile
and essentially at this point
all of greece is under is is kind of
uh... supporting the allies
and agrees
goes on the side of the allies so in
this map right over here that shows kind
of the allied powers
the beyond tog powers and the central
powers greece federated is depicted
as an allied power but it was a neutral
was officially neutral as we go to
nineteen seventy normally after the
overthrow
as only after constantine the first goes
into exile do we have greece formally
formally becoming an ally
and so that's that gives us the setup
into
nineteen eighteen
so you had to regroup serbian forces in
at this point because the massive dhoni
infront
serbia has been lost to the central
powers
you have regrouped serbian forces
epsilon after they've been transported
dislike a and and greek massive doing in
general
you now have the greek army
who is now on the side of the allies you
have the british and the french army and
so as we get into september
nineteen eighteen
they are ready to go on the offensive in
you to remember what's happening on in
the rest of europe at this point you
might remember august of nineteen
eighteen
this is the beginning of the hundred
days offensive that mark to be allied
victory on the western fronts unusual is
already getting in there
you had a great morale amongst the
allies you have not so great moa uh...
morale amongst the the central powers
and so in nineteen eighteen september
you have the allied offensive
allied
offensive
allied offensive coming out of greece
coming out of
i guess you call it massively increase
hugely successful they will to retake
they will to retake serbia
anarchy some of the british forces are
able to go east and retake
constantinople
and so this is or
part of this massive dhoni infront
is part of his overall it was on the
western front
kind of the and to the tent
through the end to the the central
powers ambitions in world war
in world war one and ends with a an
armistice on this front and as we know
as we continue member of nineteen
eighteen
you have a sense you armistice armistice
is for her
cease-fires on all the major fronts and
the allies have a sense you want