Barnett Newman's paintings
are those which, among the Abstract Expressionist themselves,
caused the greatest amount of skepticism and doubt.
Newman epitomizes the common sense of many Abstract Expressionist painters works
that anybody can do that.
I think Newman's paintings push that to its is for the sticks stream
not so much in that they look like
something a child could do –
because it's pretty hard to make those straight lines –
but something that a house painter could do.
And in fact,
one of the critics of one of his early shows at the Betty Parsons Gallery wrote
that when you went into the gallery you thought you were looking at the wall
but then you realize
don't know
you were looking at the paintings
so our question is what really does suck three these paintings?
Well for one thing the layers of color ana Newman painting
are not the one or two that house painter might make
but in fact countless layers
to achieve the saturation and the subtlety of tone
that Newman was looking for in the surface of his painting.
Also, he's not dealing with a predetermined area
if you have a Newman that's smaller than you as opposed to one that I keep house the whole length of the room communicate very different feelings
so of all the decisions that Newman is making
to get the effect that we see today
none of them is actually that simple
Instead, what Newman is doing
is trying to communicate a mood,
a profound feeling,
one might call it a spiritual feeling
at that time he would have
today that would be quite unfashionable to use
but there's no doubt in my mind that for Newman what he was expressing in a rather secular medium painting
was the kind of thing that in a previous times would have been called religious
The idea behind Newman painting
is not that you look at it and understand it or get it.
I think that's one of the things that's partly people about Newman ever since these paintings first was shown sixty years ago.
With a Newman,
you have to step aside all expectations of that
and surrender yourself to the physical experience
and the psychic experience
of being in the space of this picture
in fact, if you look through New Yorker Magazines of the nineteen fifties and nineteen sixties
you'll find many many cartoons filling its pages
of perplexed viewers standing in front of of Abstract Expressionist paintings
probably right here at the Museum of Modern Art.
But instead, really, what they were trying to convey
is that it wasn't easy for them is painters
to make the art that they were making
nor should it be easy for the viewers to experience what they made
For all of these artists,
it was essential that they form a signature style
and much as Pollock is somebody we associate with his drips
Newman is somebody we associate with what we now call his zips.
This is something new in modern art
and yet at the same time
as they were concerned with making rock goes or Newman's
with these very clearly identifiable styles,
at the same time they maintained
that these pictures were not about them –
that they were not about their mood
or their story they wanted to tell –
certainly not about any biographical detail.
And instead, they were about the much larger issues
of values and ideals of humankind
This is something that should take you
above your daily routine –
out of your ordinary work,
out of your ordinary family life.
When you're with these paintings,
you're going somewhere else
and you're bringing your soul
you're bringing your brain
you're bringing your physical body
into a different realm.