we are standing on a wooden walkware suspended over
water. the surface is fairly deep. well
this is a well afterall. we are looking at
beautiful monument by claus lutr, called the well of moses
we call that titel fairly recently. It was originally known as the great cross
but of course the claus is no longer here.
so let us give this a little bit of contacts
alot of things are no longer here. this monument stood
in the mirror of chryster surrounded bythe
self of confusion monks that rooms through they
established by philipthe four the dukeof
burgindy. so we are talking about the late fourteenth century
we are in burgindy in Djon, or rather i should say
just outside of the old walls of the city.
and this was the place where the duke had
commisioned in oral that the monks could
continuously say prayers over his soul. it also
was intended by philip and became his better place
of his family. it is important to remember that confusions are
close asidy. that is they dedicate themselves
into hirely into solitary prayer.that their environment to ensure the salvation of your self into eternity
it is interesting if i had to call the both the duke actually seems to have evolved the confusions
in fact he is pacified that he would be buried in a confuson robe
and of course he wanted to be buried here. so we are looking at
a very well funded monastery, the most brilliant odes of europe are working here
in kiting claus luter and we're looking up at
a heaxagonal structure on each side is a prophet
standing on each side of a nitch.but interestingly
and importantly this is breaking with the material
tradition of having these figures comkpletely embedded
within the architecture.each figure of a prophet is separated
by a lovely column and a capitol and standing on these capitols
are angels in positions of grieving and prayers with their wings outstretched
and above them we see a base and on that base
would have stood a tall and narrow cross
with christ on it and at the base of that cross
the single leaning figurre of mary maqualin.
all of this was painted you can see blue
there would have been gold and green.so wily
would have come alive and the monks would have
inspired in their prayer when they looked at this monument
slater is able to gear an individual life to each figure
it rerally does give us a sense of movement of the body
but maybe not so much of destruction of the body.but at least is
its engagement with the space around it.
and look up with the figureof king david
phersoah and then imporatant to the duke and david himself
of a king that he is so specific so individualised
is that there is sense of depth and wisdom t his personality
there is a recent suggestion that , that figure next to king david
who is a phophet emayor is also apotrait of philip the four
and in fact if we look into the potraits of philip, they look awesome though. thy do.
moses is looking out past us of power as a seer
that lacoraya looks down and almost offers us his prophecy
but it also challenges us. challenges the monks who have lived wit hit
sculpture do you see as i see do you understand
the importance of the tragedy of the spiritual miracle
that transpires above. we have these angels, all in different positions
some with their arms folded on their chest and some
with their arms raised, some clutching their drapery
or some touching their face. there is a depth of emotion in the figures of the prophets
and the angels are what i think would have
been inspiration to the monks.thsts important to
remember. here we are at the well the center of life
of the monastery. the monastery itself was meant to
continuously pray for the soul of the duke. but in some ways
this sculptural group wich we now call the world of moses
was the engine in the centre of the monastery
that was meant to power in sense and inspire the prayer of the monks
it is one of themost spectacular of le medieval sculptures
and truly of what i have seen