The graph of the line 2y+3x=7 is given right over here determine its x-intercept.
So the x-intercept is the x value when y is equal to 0 or is the x value where our graph actually intercepts the x axis.
Notice right over here our y value is exactly 0, where sitting on the x axis.
So let´s think about what this x value must be. Well just looking at it from, just trying to eyeball a little bit looks like it´s a little over 2.
It´s between 2 and 3, it looks like its less than 2 and a half, but we donpt know the exact value so lets got turn to the equation to figure out the exact value.
So we esentially have to figure out what x value when y is equal to 0 will have this equation be true.
So we could just say 2(0)+3x=7. Two times zero is just gonna be zero so we have 3x=7 and then we can divide both sides by three to solve for x and we get x=7/3
Now does that looks like 7/3, well we just have to remind ourselves that 7/3 is the same thing as 6/3 + 1/3.
And 6/3 is 2 so this is the same thing as 2 and 1/3.
Another way you could think about it is 3 goes into seven two times and then you have a reminder of 1 so you still got to divide that 1 by 3.
So it´s two full times and then a 1/3 so this looks like 2 1/3 and so thats its x-intercept.
7/3, if I was doing this on the exercise on Khan Academy its always a litte easier to tyoe in the inproper fractions so I would put in 7/3.