It's the longest side of the triangle; it's opposite the 90 degree side, it's oppisite the right angle.
And a, length a, this is the length of the adjacent side of this angle right over here.
So, what trig function deals with adjacent and the hypotenuse?
Well remember, let's rewrite soh cah toa.
soa cah toa.
Well cosine deals with adjacent and hypotenuse.
Cosine of an angle is equal to the adjacent over the hypotenuse.
So we can right that cosine of 60 degrees is equal to the adjacent side - the length of the adjacent side - which is a, over the hypotenouse, which is equal to 10.
If we want to solve for a, we can just multiply both sides by 10.
And we're left with a is equal to 10 time the cosine of 60 degrees.
Now if you were to type cosine of 60 degrees into your calculator, you would get this big decimal number,
but cosine of 60 degrees is one that comes up a lot.
It is actually good to know the sine and cosine of 60 degrees, 30 degrees, 90 degrees, 45 degrees because they come up so much
and often times you might want to express your answer, not as a decimal, but as some type of radical expression.
So it's good to know that the cosine of 60 degrees is one half.
And I guess, for the case of 60 degrees - cosine of 60 degrees - your calculator would have done the job.
and given you a vey exact answer. We can show that to you.
If we say cosine of 60 degrees, you get exactly one half.
Now this is one...I normally don't tell people to commit a lot of thigs to memory, but this is a useful one to commit to memory.
The cosine of 60 degrees is equal to one half.
So if the cosign of 60 degrees is one half, which is equal to 5.
So, a is equal to 5.