We're on problem 19.
If k, n, x,and y are positive numbers satisfying--
let's see, what did they write?
They wrote x to the minus 4/3 is equal to k to the minus 2.
y to the positive 4/3 is equal to n squared.
What is xy to the minus 2/3 in terms of n and k?
All right, so we just have to rewrite this in terms of n
and k, so let me write it big.
So xy to the minus 2/3, that equals x to the minus 2/3,
times y to the minus 2/3.
We know what x to the 4/3 is.
This is what I wrote here, it might not be that legible.
Sorry. So this is a 4, right?
We know what x to the minus 4/3 is.
So can we rewrite this as x to the minus 4/3 to something?
Well, sure.
We can rewrite this term, right here, we can write this as
let me write it right below it so you don't get too confused
as x to the minus 4/3, and then you raise that
to the 1/2 power.
This is the same thing as this.
How do I know that?
Well, if I multiply 4/3 times 1/2-- because I'm raising
something to an exponent, and then that to an exponent--
if I multiply minus 4/3 times 1/2,I get minus 2/3, right?
This 2 cancels out, this becomes a 2, and this is what I get.
You can try it out.
Similarly, I want to write this second term--
I'm going to do it in green-- this y to the minus 2/3.
I know what y to the 4/3 is, right?
So I want to write it as y to the 4/3 to some other power.
So 4/3 times what is equal to minus 2/3?
Well, 4/3 times minus 1/2.
And you can try it out.
4/3 times minus 1/2 is equal to minus 2/3, right?
A positive times a negative equals a negative.
And then the 4 and the 2 end up just the
2-- sorry, I'm burping.
So what does this become?
Well, we know what x to the minus 4/3 is, right?
x to the minus 4/3 is equal to k to the minus 2.
So that first term is equal to this, is equal to k-- that's
too dark-- k to the minus 2, and then we're raising that to
the 1/2-- right, that's the same 1/2 right there--
and then y to the 4/3.
What's y to the 4/3?
Well, that's n squared.
And then that's, of course,the minus 1/2.
And then we can multiply.
What's minus 2 times 1/2?
Well, it's just minus 1.
So it's k to the minus 1.
And then what's 2 times minus 1/2?
It's minus 1 again.
So k to the minus 1,n to the minus 1.
And that's the same thing as 1/kn, or 1/nk,
which is choice A.
And I just realized that there's actually an easier way
to do that.
We could've done it like this, we could have just said--
let me see, let me erase this stuff, because it's, I think,
good for you to know the easier way, instead of the way
I just showed you how to do it.
Let me erase all of this.
I think we would've saved some steps,
and been more intuitive.
Let me erase all of this, I just wanted to keep
what I had written before.
Erase, erase, erase.
OK, I think that's good enough.
You can just ignore the stuff on the right.
So we could've simplified these ahead of time.
We could have said, x to the minus 4/3 is equal to k
to the minus 2.
If we raised both of these to the 1/2 power,
we would get what?
Minus 4/3 times 1/2 is-- we would have gotten x to the minus
2/3 is equal to-- what's negative 2 times 1/2?
It's negative 1, right?
It would've equaled k to the negative 1.
And similarly, if we had raised y to the 4/3 equals n squared
if we'd raised both of those to the minus 1/2--
if you do something on one side of the equation, you just have
to do it on the other-- then you would have gotten
y to the minus 2/3 is equal to n to the minus 1.
And then this would have been really easy to solve.
xy to the minus 2/3 is the same thing as x to the minus 2/3,
times y to the minus 2/3.
x to the the minus 2/3 is k to the minus 1.
And y to the negative 2/3 is n to the minus 1.
So it would have been k to the minus 1, n to the minus 1.
That's 1/nk.
Well, I guess in hindsight I can say this was easier, but
the way we did it would've also worked, and you really
don't know sometimes which one will be the shortcut when you
do it the first time.
But either way could've worked.
You could've simplified ahead of time, if you had seen that
you wanted to get it into 2/3, not 4/3,
because they had a 2/3 here.
Or you could just go the way we did it the first time,
either way works.
Next problem, problem number 20.
OK, functions of f and g.
So I'm going to have to do some drawing here,
if we have enough time.
So I have to draw two of them.
That one's going to be for f,and this one's going to be for g
What points are there?
So f of x-- let's see, [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
f of x is 2 points back, and it intersects there.
And it intersects at the point minus 1 comma 1, 2, 3,
so it intersects here.
And then it goes through the origin.
And then it goes to 1, minus 3.
So that's 1, 2, 3, 1, so it goes here.
And then it goes at 2 comma 0, and it intersects here.
So let me try to draw that.
So the graph looks something like this.
It goes up, it intersects this point, comes down
through the origin, goes down here,and then goes up like that
That is y equals f of x.
Now what does g of x do?
g of x goes to 2 comma 1.
So 1, 2 comma 1.
Then it's to 4, minus 5.
So 2, 3, 4, 1, 2, 3,4, 5-- 4, minus 5.
And then it goes back up.
So it looks something like this.
It goes down, goes up like that, goes back up like that.
The figures above show the graph of the functions f and g.
The function f is defined by-- so this one-- f of x
is equal to x to the third minus 4x.
The function g of x is equal to f of x plus h, plus k,
where h and k are constants.
What is the value of k?
So essentially, what they're saying is, g of x is f of x
shifted up or down by some value, k, right?
Because when you add a constant to a function,
you're just moving it up or down by some value, k.
And when you add h, that means you're shifting it to--
let me make sure I get this right-- so if it was x minus h,
that means you're shifting it to the right by h.
So x plus h means you're shifting it to the left by h.
This point corresponds to this point.
So how much did we shift down?
This is the point negative 1 comma 3.
And this is the point 2 comma 1.
So we went from y equals 3 to y equals 1, right?
So we shifted down by 2.
So k is going to be minus 2.
And similarly you could do it with this point.
So k is equal to minus 2.
Now we have to figure out how much we shifted left to right.
So [? similarly, ?]
these are the corresponding points,
because you can look at them in the graph.
So we went from minus 1 to positive 2.
So we shifted to the right by 3.
And you could do the same thing with this point here
at the bottom.
We shifted to the right by 3.
So if I wanted to shift f of x to the right by 3,
I would write it like this,f of x minus 3.
That's how I would shift a function to the right by 3.
They're saying plus h, so h has to be minus 3.
h is minus 3.
And minus 3 times minus 2?
Well, that's positive 6,which is choice E.