I now want to re-figure out what this mystery mass is,
but we're going to start using a little bit more of mathematics.
And mathematics really are just a language of symbols for representing ideas --
for representing relationships between things.
And so the first thing I want you to do is think about if you can express a relationship mathematically
between this side of the scale and that side of the scale.
And I'll give you some hints:
we know that they have equal mass, so maybe you set some type of relationship using an equal sign --
somehow showing that this right over here is equal to that and I'll give you a few seconds to do that.
So let's think about it a little bit. What do we have on this side?
Well, we have our mystery mass,
and I'll represent that mystery mass by the question mark - right over here.
But that's not the only thing we have on the left hand side: we also have these other three kilograms.
So let me write over here, I'll just add, we'll assume that we're dealing with kilograms.
So we have the mystery mass in kg plus three more kg. That's what we have here on the left hand side.
Now what do we have here on the right hand side. Well just have 1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10 kg.
So we just have 10 on the right hand side.
And what else do we know?
Well, we know that the scale is balanced --
that the mass here is equal to the mass here, because the scale is balanced, the way it's been drawn.
We know that these two things are equal.
So we have just set up an equation. We're using question mark as our unknown.
We don't know what this mystery mass is.
If we add 3 kg to it, then we see that it has the exact same mass as 10 kg.
Now my question to you is, what can we do to this equation
so that we can essentially solve for the unknown,
so that we can figure out what the unknown is.
Well we saw in the last little problem that we had
that if we wanted to figure out this mystery mass
we had to remove, 3 of these, 3 kg from both sides.
If we just removed 3 kg from one side
then the scale wouldn't be balanced any more.
And we really wouldn't be able to say that the mystery mass
is equal to the thing on the right.
In order to say they're equal this stuff actually has to actually be balanced.
So in the last video, we removed three of these, we removed three kg from both sides
in order to keep the scale balanced.
So mathematically we'll do the exact same thing over here.
We will remove 3 not from side --
if we remove three from one side then it wouldn't be equal anymore --
we need to remove three from both sides.
So we need to remove three, we need subtract three,
from both sides of the equation in order to keep the scale balanced.
So on the left hand side, what are we left with?
Well, just like over here, we're left with just the question mark.
Three minus three is zero.
So on the left hand side we're left with just the question mark.
And on the right hand side, we're left with ten minus three which is seven.
10 - 3 which is 7.
And we get the exact same result: question mark is equal to seven.
And if we're doing it in kg then this is seven kg.