Let's now tackle a classic thought experiment in probability
called the Monty Hall problem.
And it's called the Monty Hall problem because
Monty Hall was the game show host
in Let's Make a Deal where
they would set up a situation very similar to
the Monty Hall problem
that we're about to say.
So let's say that on the show, you're presented with
three curtains.
So you're the contestant
this little character right over there
You're presented with three curtains:
curtain number one, curtain number two, and
curtain number three.
And you're told that behind one of these three curtains
there is a fabulous prize.
Something that you really want, a car, or a vacation
or some type of large amount of cash.
And then behind the other two,
and we don't know which they are,
there is something that you do not want,
say a new pet goat, an ostrich,
or something like that, or beachball,
something that is not as good as the cash prize.
And so your goal is to try to find
the cash prize.
And they say: "guess which one"
or "which one you would like to select".
And so let's say that you select
door number one,
or curtain number one,
then the Monty Hall and Let's Make a Deal crew
will make it a little more interesting.
They won't just show you whether or not you won,
They'll then show you one of the other two doors,
or one of the other two curtains.
And they'll show you one of the other two curtains that does not
have the prize.
And no matter which one you pick,
there will always be at least
one other curtain that does not have the prize.
There might be two if you pick right,
but there will always be
at least one other curtain
that does not have the prize.
And then they will show it to you.
And so let's say that they
show you curtain number three,
and that curtain number three has the goat.
And then they will ask you,
do you want to switch to curtain number two,
and the question here is,
does it make a difference?
Are you better off holding fast,
sticking to your guns, staying with your original guess,
or are you better off switching
to whatever curtain is left,
or does it not matter,
it's just random probability and
it's not going to make a difference
whether you switch or not.
So that is the brain teaser.
Start - pause the video now,
I encourage you to think about it.
In the next video,
we will start to analyze the solution
a little bit deeper.
Whether it makes any difference at all.
So now I've assumed that you've unpaused it,
that you've thought deeply about it,
perhaps you have an opinion about it,
now let's work it through a little bit.
And at any point,
I encourage you to pause it,
and kind of extrapolate beyond
what I've already talked about.
So let's think about the game show from
the show's point of view.
So the show knows
where there is a goat and
where there isn't a goat.
So that's door number one,
door number two, and door number three.
So let's say that our prize is
right over here.
So our prize is the car.
Our prize is the car and we have
a goat over here, goat over here and
over here we also have, we have two goats
in this situation.
So what are we going to do as a game show
remember, the contestants don't know this
we know this.
So the contestant picks door number one
right over here,
then we can't lift door number two
cause there's a car back there.
We're going to lift door number three
and we're going to expose
we're going to expose
this goat, in which case it probably
would be good for the person to switch.
If the person picks door number two,
then, we as the game show,
can show either door number one or
door number three,
and then it actually does not make sense
for the person to switch.
If they picked door number three,
then we have to show door number one
because we can't pick door number two
and in that case, it actually makes a lot of sense
for the person to switch.
Now, with that out of the way,
let's think of the probabilities
given the two strategies.
So if you don't switch,
Don't switch
Or another way to think about this strategy is
you always stick to your guns
you always stick to your first guess.
Well, in that situation,
what is your probability,
what is your probability of winning.
Well, there are three doors,
the prize is equally likely to be
behind any of them,
so there are three possibilities.
One has the outcome that you desire.
The probability of winning will be one third
if you don't switch.
Likewise, your probability of losing
well, there are two ways you can lose
out of three possibilities,
going to be two thirds.
And these are the only possibilities,
and these add up to one over here.
So don't switch, one third chance of winning.
Now let's think about the switching situation.
So let's say always, when you always switch
let's think about how this might play out.
What is your probability of winning;
and before we can think about that,
think about how you would win
if you always switched.
So if you picked wrong the first time,
if you picked wrong the first time,
they're going to show you this
so you should always switch.
So if you picked door number one,
they're going to show you door number three
you should switch!
If you picked wrong door number three,
they're going to show you door number one
you should switch!
If you picked wrong and switch,
you will always win!
Let me write this down.
And this insight actually came from
one of the middle school students
in the summer camp that
Khan Academy's running,
it's actually a fabulous way
to think about this.
So if you pick wrong,
so if it's step one: initial pick is wrong
Initial pick is wrong.
So you pick one of the two
wrong doors.
And then step two, you always switch
You always switch.
You will land on the car,
because if you pick one of the wrong doors,
they have to show the other wrong door,
and so if you switch you are going to end up
on the right answer.
So what is the probability of winning
if you always switch?
Well, it's going to be the probability
that you initially picked wrong.
Well, what's the probability that you
initially picked wrong?
Well, there are two out of three ways
to initially pick wrong.
So you actually have a two-thirds chance
of winning.
There's a two-thirds chance you
are going to pick wrong,
and are going to switch into the right one.
Likewise, what's your probability of losing?
What's your probability of losing, given
that you're always going to switch?
Well, the way that you would lose is
you pick right,
you pick correctly,
in step two they're going to show an empty,
they're going to show one of the two empty,
or non-prized doors,
and then in step three you are going to
switch into the other empty,
Switch into the other empty door.
But either way, you are definitely going to switch,
so the only way to lose if you're
always going to switch
is to pick right the first time.
Well what's the probability of you
picking right the first time?
Well that is only one-third.
So what you see here is sometimes
counterintuitive, but hopefully
this makes sense as to why it isn't.
You have a one-third chance of winning
if you stick to your guns,
and a two-thirds chance of winning
if you always switch.
Another way to think about it is,
when you first make your initial pick,
there's a one-third chance that it's there,
and there's a two-thirds chance
that it's in one of the other two doors.
And they're going to empty out
one of them, so when you switch,
you essentially are capturing that
two-third probability.
And we see that right there.
So hopefully you enjoyed that.