You have 8 coins in a bag
Three of them are unfair in that they have a 60% chance of coming up heads when flipped
The rest are fair coins
So 3 are unfair, the rest are 8 coins
When I say,
or when this problem says that they are fair coins,
It means that they have a 50/50 chance of coming up either heads or tails
You randomly choose one coin from the bag
and flip it two times
What is the percent probability of getting 2 heads?
This is an interesting question
but if we break it down essentially with the decision tree
it will help break it down a bit better
So let's say that
So we have a bag
three of them are unfair
So we can do is visualize the bag
You don't have to do this all the time
So we have
I'll do the fair coins in white
1, 2, 3, 4, 5 fair coins
And we have three unfair coins
1, 2, 3
This whole thing is my bag right over here
That is my bag of coins
If I were to
When I take my hand in,
if I were to take any of these white coins,
there's a 50% chance that it gets heads on any flip
The odds of getting two heads in a row would be 50% times 50%
for these white coins
But I don't know if I'm going to get a white coin
If I get one of these orange coins, I have a 60% chance
of coming up heads
And the odds of coming up 60% heads
if I have picked one of these orange coins
The probability of getting heads twice
would be 60% times 60%
So how do I factor in this idea
that I don't know if I've picked a
white fair coin or an orange unfair coin
Well we'll assume that the coins actually aren't white and orange
They all look like regular coins
So what I'll do is I'll draw
a little bit of a decision tree here
And maybe I'll call it a probability tree
So there's some probability that I pick a fair coin
And there's some probability that I pick an unfair coin
And so what is the probability that I pick a fair coin
Well; 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 out of the total 8 coins are fair
So there is a 5/8 probability
I'll write it here on the branch actually
So there's a 5/8 chance that I pick a fair coin
And then there is a 3
1, 2, 3 out of 8 chance that I pick an unfair coin
So if I were just to tell you what's the probablity
of picking a fair coin you'd say, oh 5/8!
So what's the probability of an unfair coin? 3/8
And you could convert that to a
decimal or a percentage or whatever you like
Now,
given that I have picked a fair coin
What is the probability that I,
that I will get heads twice
So, let me write it this way
This is just notation right here
So the probability of,
I'll call it heads heads
So I get two heads in a row
Given that I have a fair coin
It looks like very fancy notation
but it's just like look
If you knew for a fact that that coin
you had is absolutely fair
That it has a 50% chance of coming up heads,
what is the probability of getting two heads in a row?
Well then, we can just say,
well that's just going to be
50%
So 50% times 50%
Which is equal to 25%
Now, what is the probability that you
So if you want to know what is the probability
that you picked a fair coin
and you got two heads in a row
So given that you have a fair coin, with a 25% chance
that you have 2 heads in a row
For the probability of picking a fair coin
and then given the fair coin get two heads in a row
will be the 5 eighths times the 25%
So the probability,
So this whole branch,
I should be able to draw it this way
The probability of this whole series of events happening
So starting with you picking the fair coin
and then getting two heads in a row
Will be
I'll write it this way
It will be
5/8 times this right over here
times the 0.25
I want to make it very clear
the 0.25 is the probability of getting two heads in a row
given that you knew you got a fair coin
For the probability of this whole series of events happening,
you would have to multiply this
times the probability that you actually got a fair coin
So another way of thinking about it is
this is the probability that you got a fair coin
and you have two heads in a row
Now let's just do the same thing for the unfair coin
So the probability
I'll do that in the same color
The probability that I get heads heads
given that my coin is unfair
So if you were to somehow know that your coin is unfair,
what is the probability of getting two heads in a row?
Well this unfair coin has a 60% chance
of coming up heads
So it will be equal to
0.6 times 0.6
which is 0.36
So if you have an unfair coin
if you know for a fact you have an unfair coin
that is a given,
you have a 36% chance of getting two heads in a row
Now if you want to know the probability
of this whole series of events
The probability that you picked an unfair coin
and you get two heads in a row
So the probability of unfair
unfair and two heads in a row
given that you had an unfair coin
You would multiply this 3/8 times the 0.36
So this will be equal to
the 3/8 times 0.36
And so let's get a calculator out
to calculate these
So if I take 5 divided by 8 times 0.25,
I get fifteen point--
I'll just write it as a decimal
0.15625
So this is equal to 0.15625
And then if I do the other part
so if I have 3 divided by 8 times 0.36,
that gives me 0.135
So this is 0.135
So if someone were to ask you
what's the probability of picking a fair coin
and then getting two heads in a row with that fair coin,
you would get this number
If someone were to say what's the probability
you pick the unfair coin
and then get two heads in a row with that unfair coin
you would get this number
Now, if someone were to say
either way,
what's the probability of getting two heads in a row
because that's what they're asking us here
What is the probability of getting 2 heads?
So we could get it through this method
by chance picking the fair coin
Or through this method
by chance picking the unfair coin
So since we can do it either way,
we can sum up the probabilites
Either of these events meet our constraints
so we can just add these two things up
So let's do that
So we can add 0.135
plus 0.15625
gives us 0.29125
So 0.29125
That's when we add 0.15625 plus 0.135 will equal this
And if you want to write it as a percentage,
you essentially just multiply this times a 100
and add the percentage sign there
So this is equal to 29.125% or if we were to round
to the nearest hundredths then this would be,
well this would be the exact number
or we could say it's the approximately 29.13%
depending on how much we need to round it
So we have a little less than a third chance of this happening
And the reason why,
remember if it was a fair coin,
there would only be,
if everything in the bag was a fair coin,
there'd be a 25% chance of this happening
Because you would just say okay,
any of these
They're all the same,
flip it twice
25% chance
Our chances is a little bit higher
because there's some probability
There's a 3/8 chance that we pick a coin
that has a higher than even chance of coming up heads