- So, here we are at Dulwich Picture Gallery, in London and we are looking at
Rembrandt - A girl at the window, which is from about 1645
and this is just one of those pictures that... it hooks you. You know, when you're
at the cafe, and you're staring out, just gazing at the world go by.
That's what she seems to be doing in this picture.
And that rosy cheeks. But just like gazing off into the distance.
- Yeah, that's true. And being the viewer of this painting kinda puts you
into that imagined scenario that she's looking at.
If you'd kinda walk back and forth, it kinda is one of those portraits that
seems like her eyes follow you.
- The way we're gazing at her she's gazing back at us.
- And it's funny because there's very little background with us. I mean, we don't really know
where she is. And it's called "Girl at the window", but you don't see much of a window there.
- Definitely, leaning on the ledge.
- And yet she's so captivating, even without any background.
- Rosy cheeks... she makes you think what temperature it is, what she'd been doing
to have those cheeks. Is she always like that, you know, flashed in her face.
And her age, you know, when I first looked I thought: "A young girl."
And the more I look at her, the more I see some kind of...seems to be wisdom in there.
She's got gold chains on around her neck. She's holding them, so it makes you
question this states, 'cause her clothes, again...
Is that a night dress? Is she a servant girl?
- I mean, to Rembrandt's credit, of course, but he really does make you
kind of psychologically interested in her, without giving you...
I mean, he hasn't put house in the background
and he hasn't given her clothes that exactly tell you who she is or how old she is.
And he kind of made you interested in her simply by how he's painted her in this very basic way.
- And her parted lips...Is that a smile?
It's almost that Mona Lisa question, isn't it?
Is she smiling at us? Is she not?
Is she staring past us? Is she looking at us?
And I love the colour, the way he's used that kinda of texture of the paint,
the dry, rasping paint that he's put on her cheeks and the highlights in her hair really bring her to life.
- Kind of contrast in different areas of painting, as well how kind of dark and nondescript
to the background gets.
And even the ledge she is leaning on he's done with very quick brushstrokes.
And then the detail in the draping of her shirt, and again that both rosy cheeks...
Her skin looks like it would be soft to touch.
- Definitely. This is definitely not one of those ones...
You just want to fall into it. I find this interesting, 'cause it marries what i want to do -
I want to keep gazing, that's it, in that people watching way
which is what she's doing in the painting.
They say that, when Rembrandt painted this picture, he hang it outside
facing out to his apartment window, and people walking in the street shouted up
'cause they felt it was so realistic, like she was really there.
- Oh, a real girl in the window.
Maybe that was where the name came from, rather than window being actually painted.