The table below shows solar panel installations by state
during the last fiscal year.
How many total solar panels were installed
last year in Wyoming?
So we look at the state –
So this right over here is Wyoming.
And this whole table is about
solar installations by state during the last year.
So this is Wyoming during the last year.
This is the first quarter – so the first three months.
The second three months.
The third quarter.
The fourth quarter.
And then this right over here
is the total number of solar panels
that were installed in Wyoming last year –
which is what I think they're asking us for.
So let's just type that it in.
104.
We got it right.
Let's do another one.
The table below indicates
the points scored by four players
in a charity basketball game.
How many points did Ben have in total?
So here's Ben right over.
it's broken down by quarter –
but we care about his total number of points –
which is 31.
So Ben had a total of 31 points.
So this indicates the points scored
by four players in a charity basketball game again.
How many points did Vanessa score in the fourth quarter?
So let's look at –
This is Vanessa.
And we care about the fourth-quarter.
So she scored four points in the fourth quarter.
Put 4 right over there.
All right.
So once again we're talking about solar panel installations
by state during the last fiscal year.
How many solar panels were installed
in Alabama in the second quarter – in 'Q2?'
So Alabama [and] in the second quarter?
So that's this right over here.
28 solar panels were installed.
So 28.
So this is, once again, in a charity game.
How many points of Kevin scored third quarter.
So Kevin in the third quarters he scored nine points.
Maybe one more – just for fun.
So how many points did Gabriella score in the third quarter?
Well, same idea.
[Find] 'Gabriella.' [Find] 'third quarter.'
She scored five points.