What is BD?
So, when they're just saying BD,
they're saying literally the length of segment BD.
So they're saying the length from point B to point D.
And B is sitting here at negative two, D here is at five,
so you're looking at really the distance between negative two and five.
So you literally could just say,
Well, that's gonna be five (that's kind of our endpoint), minus negative two,
so five minus negative two is the same thing as five plus two, or seven.
Another way, you could literally just count it out.
Count out the distance: you go 1, 2, to get to zero; 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, to get all the way to five.
Or, you could say,
Look, I gotta go two to the right just to get to zero,
and I gotta go five more to the right to get to D,
so that's going to be seven.
Let's do a couple more.
What is BD, again?
Well, here we're going from one to four.
The distance between one and four is three.
And then, let's do one more.
What is AD?
So, A is at negative five, D is all the way at four.
So, we're going from negative five to zero, which is five, and then we're gonna go four more.
Five plus four is nine.
Or, you could say,
Look, we start at negative five, we end up at four.
Four minus negative five is the same thing as four plus five, which is nine.