PROBLEM: "Express the rational number 19/27
(or 19 27ths) as a terminating decimal
or a decimal that eventually repeats.
Include only the first six digits
of the decimal in your answer."
Let me give this a shot.
So we want to express 19/27 –
which is the same thing as 19 ÷ 27 – as a decimal.
So let's divide 27 into 19.
So 27 going into 19.
And we know it's going to involve some decimals
over here, because 27 is larger than 19,
and it doesn't divide perfectly.
So let's get into this.
So 27 doesn't go into 1.
It doesn't go into 19.
It does go into 190.
And it looks like 27 is roughly 30.
It's a little less than 30.
30 times 6 would be 180.
So let's go with it going 6 times.
Let's see if that works out.
Well, 6 × 7 is 42.
6 × 2 is 12, + 4 is 16.
And when we subtract, 190 - 162 is going to get us –
Actually, we could've had another 27 in there.
Because when we subtract –
So we get a 10 from the 10's place.
So that becomes 8 10's.
This became 28.
So we could have put one more 27 in there.
So let's do that.
So let's put one more 27 in there.
So 7 27's.
7 × 7 is 49.
7 × 2 is 14, + 4 is 18.
And now our remainder is 1.
We can bring down another 0.
27 goes into 10 0 times.
0 × 27 is 0. [Not "10," as Sal states by mistake.]
Subtract – we have a remainder of 10.
But now, we have to bring down another 0.
So let's bring down this 0 right over here.
So now, 27 goes into 100 3 times.
3 × 27 is 60 + 21, is 81.
And then we subtract: 100 - 81.
Well, we could take 100 from
the 100's place, and make it 10 10's.
And then we could take 1 of those 10's from
the 10's place and turn it into 10 1's.
And so 9 10's minus 8 10's is equal to 1 10.
And then 10 -1 is 9.
So it's equal to 19.
You probably –
You might have been able to do that in your head.
And then we have –
And I see something interesting here –
because when we bring down our next 0,
we see 190 again.
We saw 190 up here.
But let's just keep going.
So 27 goes into 190 –
And we already played this game.
It goes into it 7 times.
7 × 27 – we already figured out – was 189.
We subtracted.
We had a remainder of 1.
Then we brought down another 0.
We said 27 goes into 10 0 times.
0 × 27 is 0.
Subtract.
Then you have –
We still have the 10,
but we've got to bring down another 0.
So you have 27, which goes into 100 –
(We've already done this.)
–3 times.
So you see something happening here.
It's 0.703703.
And we're just going to keep repeating 703.
This is going to be equal to 0.703703703703 –
on and on and on forever.
So the notation for representing
a repeating decimal like this
is to write the numbers that repeat –
in this case 7, 0, and 3 –
and then you put a line over all of
the repeating decimal numbers
to indicate that they repeat.
So you put a line over the 7, the 0, and the 3,
which means that the 703 will keep
repeating on and on and on.
So let's actually input it into the answer box now.
So it's 0.703703.
And they tell us to include only
the first six digits of the decimal in your answer.
And they don't tell us to round or approximate –
because, obviously, if they said to round
that final sixth decimal place,
then you would round it up from 6 to 7,
because the next digit is a 7.
But they don't ask us to round.
They just say, "Include only the first six digits
of the decimal in your answer."
So that should do the trick.
And it did.
Exprese el numero racional 19/27
(o diecinueve veinticieteavos) en su forma decimal
o como un decimal que se repite indefinidamente
Incluyendo solamente los seis primeros digitos
del decimal en tu respuesta
Dejame dare una pista
Entonces queremos
lo cual es igual a 19 entre 27 en decimal
Asi que dividimos 27 entre 19
y Sabes que esto involucra algunos decimales
y no se divide perfectamente
Asi que veamos que pasa
El 27 no va a 1
tampoco va al 19
El se divide en 190
y vemos que el 27 en muy cercano al 30
Es un poco menor que 30
30 veces 6 seria 180
Asi que lo haremos 6 veces
Veamos si eso funciona
Bueno, 6 por 7 es 42
6 por 2 es 12
mas 4 es 16
y si restamos,
190-162 esto nos va a dar
de hecho no podemos tener 27 aqui
Porque cuando restamos
Asi que tenemos 10 del decimo lugar
Asi que se convierte en 8 decimos
Esto de convierte en 28
Asi que podemos tener un 27 mas aqui
Asi que lo haces
Asi que ponemos un 27 más aqui
Asi que 7 veinticieteavos
7 por 7 es 49
7 por 2 es 14, mas 4 es 18
Y ahora nuestro acarreo es 1
Podemos bajar otro 0
27 se divide entre 100 partes
0 por 27 es 0 (no "10", como Sal estado por error)
Restamos- podemos tener un acarreo de 10
Pero ahora tenemos que bajar otro cero
Asi que bajamos otro cero por aqui
Y ahora, 27 se vuelte 100, 3 veces
3 por 27 es 60
mas 21 es 81
y entonces restamos: cien menos ochenta y uno
Bien, podriamos tomar 100 de
del centecimo lugar
y tomamos 10 del decimo lugar
y entonces podriamos tomas uno de eso decimos de el decimo lugar
Asi que 9 decimos menos 8 decimas es igual a un decimo
y entonce diez menos uno es nueve
y eso es igual a 19
Probablemente seas capaza de hacerlo mentalmente
y entonces tenemos
Algo muy interesante
porque entonces bajamos el siguiente cero
y vemos el 190 otra vez
vemos el el 190 aqui arriba
Pero seguimos haciendolo
asi que el 27 cabe en el 190
y ya hemos jugado este juego
7 por 27 - que ya hemoss calculado, era 189
restamos
y nos sobra 1
Entonces bajamos otro cero
entonces decimos que el 27 se va a las decimas, cero veces
0 por 27 es cero
Restamos
Entonces tienes
Aun tenemos el 10
pero tenemos que bajar otro 0
Asi que si tienes 27 el cual se divide en 100
( ya hemos hecho esto=
3 veces
Y ves que algo esta pasando aqui
es 0.703703
Y solo estaremos repitiendo 703
y esto sera igual a 0.703703703703
y asi y asi y asi por siempre
Asi que la notacion para representar
yna repeticion decimal como esta
es escribier los numeros que se repiten
en este caso siente, cero y 3
y entonces pones una linea sobre toso ellos
los numero decimales que se repiten
para indicar que ellos que repiten
Entonce pones una line sobre el siete, el cero y el 3
lo cual indica que el 703 se estar
repitiendo una y otra vez
Asi que de hecho ahora los ponemos en una caja de respuesta.
Asi que es 0.703703.
y nos decicen que hay que incluir solamente
los primeros seis decimales en tu respuesta