So we have this line segment; JL here and we have point
K that also sits on that segment
and they tell us that JK is equal to 7x plus 9
So this distance right over here is equal to 7x
plus 9. Then they tell us that JL is equal to a 114
So JL is the entire length of the segment. So this entire thing
is equal to 114. Then they tell us that KL
is equal to 9x plus 9
So this right over here is equal to 9x plus 9.
And they say find KL
So they essentially want us to figure out
what does 9x plus 9 equal
And to figure that out we have to
figure out what x equals
And lucky for us, they have given us all the information we need.
They tell us that the entire segment is 114
long. And they don't give us any units, it's just 114
it has the length of 114. And we know that this segment
JK plus KL added together is going to be equal
to the length of the entire thing.
So we can say that 7x plus 9
We could say that 7x plus 9, actually let me write it this way,
we could write that JK,
that the length of segment JK
plus the length of segment KL
plus KL,
is going to be equal to 114.
114.
And we know that the length
of the segment JK is 7x plus 9.
7x plus 9.
We know that the length of segment KL is 9x plus 9.
So plus 9x plus 9,
And this is going to be equal to 114.
And now we just have to
work out a little bit of our algebraic skills.
So the first thing
we might wanna do is,
let's see we have, we have two terms
and x is in them.
So if I have 7 x's,
and I would add that to another 9 x's,
that means I'm going to have 16 x's.
And then if I have, so this is just plain ol' 9,
and I add it to another 9, that's going to give me 18
That's going to be equal to 114.
Now I just subtract 18 from both sides,
So I subtract 18 from both sides...
On the left-hand side, I have 16x
and on the right-hand side, I'm going to have
a 114 minus 18
Or if I were to subtract 14 I would get to a hundred,
so if I were to subtract 4 more from that
so that's going to get me to 96.
And now we just have to divide both sides by 16.
Divide both sides by 16.
And, let's see, this looks like,
96 divided by 16
it looks like it's going to be 6
6 times 10 is 60,
6 times 6 is 36,
60 plus 36 is 96.
So we get x is equal to 6.
But we're not done yet.
We're not just looking for x
we're looking for the length of KL.
KL is 9x plus 9, let me write that down.
So KL is equal to 9x plus 9.
They told us that, right over there.
it's equal to 9x plus 9.
We just figured out that x is equal to 6.
So this is equal to 9 times 6 plus 9
and this is equal to
9 times 6 is 54,
plus 9 is equal to 63.
So KL is equal to 63.