now know how to find the areas of rectangles.
What I want to do in this video, is think about how we can find the areas of triangles.
so we are starting here with a right triangle. It has 90 degree angle. Triangle A B C
so lets think about how we can find its area. Maybe we can construct a rectangle out of triangle ABC
and if we can construct a reactangle out of it, maybe we can somehow
find our area of part of that rectangle and the best way to construct our rectangle is to really duplicate
ABC
and then flip it over and put it right on top this. So just to verify that it will definitely be a rectangle
so we know that this is 90 degrees right over here. Let's say that this is x degrees right over there
we have x plus 90 plus this thing have to be equal to 180.
so this thing and this thing have to add up to 90 so let's just call this 90-x.
now lets flip this thing and rotate it around.
so that it will look like this.
so that you would have another triangle that would look just like this:
where now this right angle on the flip version, is that right angle right over there
this right angle right over here, this angle right over here, this x is now this angle right over there
and this 90-x is now this angle right over there. now you can see x+90 -x that will give you a right
angle
and that will gives you a right angle, and you have four sides and four right angles you are definitely
dealing with a rectangle.
and this rectangle has two of our original triangles in it.
So we can write that the area of triangle of ABC.
So the area of triangle ABC, thats what the brackets mean. Area of triangle ABC
is going to be equal to 1/2 times the area of our entire rectangle
let me add another point here, let me call this: D, its going to be 1/2 the are of the rectangle.
ABCD, and we know how to find the area of rectangle ABCD, its going to be equal to.
Its going to be equal to the base of the rectangle. So this is going to be equal to 1/2 times this par.
let me use this in a different color, the area of ABCD is equal to the base of the width of the rectangle
so thats just the length of BC, I'm just putting this in parenthessis.
BC is just the length of this length segment and I'm just putting it into parenthesis.
so that we don't get the letters jumbled up. So its going to be this width or this base right here
times the height of the rectangle. So times AD, sorry, times AB.
so this base times this height is gives us the area of our entire rectangle
And the area of our right triangle is half of that. So there we have it, 1/2 times times this base, times t
this height.
is the area of a right triangle. So in general if you ever have a right triangle and this is a right
angle right over there. You need one right angle in order for it be a right triangle and this
base has length B and this side over here has side h, so you know that the area
the area is going to be equal to 1/2 times the base times the base of the triangle
thats the base of the triangle bc.
times the height of the triangle. so you can view it this way if you look at the actual letter points
or just view these mesasures as the base times the height. 1/2 base times height
and we only know if this works for a right triangle. now let's think about it for other types of triangle that aren't
necessarily right triangles.
So here I have a kind of a arbritrary triangle bc. and to approach figure out its area
what I want to do is split this up into two right triangles. so what I'm going to do is drop
a perpendicular from b. so i'm just going to literally, and if this was an actual structure you would just literally drop something straight down from here, and that line is
going to be perpendicular to this base right over here. to ac let me call that point
let me call that point d, and whats useful here is that now that we have constructed we turned that one
triangle into two right triangles. So, we can say that the area
of triangle ABC thats what we want to figure out is equal to the area of this character
right here. So its equal to the area of triangle ABD.
ABD plus the area of triangle, plus the area of this magenta triangle, of BCD.
BCD
And this is useful becuase we know how to find the area of right triangles
and this is 90 degrees, this is also going to be 90 degrees.
the area of ABD is 1/2 Base times Height.
So its going to be 1/2 times AD times the height
which is going to be the length of BD right over here, assuming that we can figure this out
so this times that length. So BD, thats the area of the blue triangle.
and now if and now I can find the lengrth of the magenta triangle.
well once again its a right triangle its going to be 1/2, times the length of this base,
right over here which is DC
the length of segment DC times the length of BD again.
Times the length of segment bd. Now you can factor out a 1/2