We're in St. Peter's Basilica.
Standing right beside baldacchino.
In the crossing. Directly under Michelangelo's dome which is so high. It's breathtaking.
And we're looking past the baldacchino which is actually not easy to do.
Taking an extraordinary... I was about to call it sculpture but it's more than a sculpture.
It's architecture. It's sculpture. It's stained glass.
It's the cathedral's patron.
The chair is bronze and encases a older wooden chair.
Which is believed by tradition to have belonged to Saint Peter.
It appears to float effortlessly in the air and a kind of canopy held by four church fathers.
And it's not that they are lifting so much is they're restraing the chair.
Right. We seem to be honest being assumed to have it all around pouring from either side of the chair.
Pushing up from below are golden cloudes that raise up the throne and surrond it almost to push it forward in a way to.
It's true. And almost to see down on to our world.
Right. It's kind of pouring into our world. Such a boroque thing.
The spirituals are also clearly represented by this golden raise.
That move much more quiqly out into our space, out into cathedral.
Through the clouds.
Through the clouds and over and pass the plaster. They're actually architecture of the church.
And that frame themselves a cloud of angels.
The dance and spin and the intern frame the stained glass, this beautifull stained glass representation of the whole spirit.
The dove which is itself the centre-piece and it has the focal point of the entire cathedral.
And the Dove is represented within concentric oval shape. And you get this feeling of raising and moving towards the center of the world.
Well, that's right, it's a kind of almost visual multiplikation and a kind of intensifikation.
Untill we reach the Holly Spirit itself.
What always amazes me about Bernini and everything that we've seen in Rome,
is the sway that he is willing to think about architecture in a new way.
And sort of something that is heavy and incloses base.
If you think about the Pantheon
or just generally what architecture is suppose to do.
He makes architecture into this purest thing almost.
It becomes a playful stage.
It becomes something that can be in some ways overwhelmed by the kind of theatricality.
That he brings to his almost set pieces.
Its like painted centrally using stucco painted with gold on top of marble.
It is an extraordinary mix.
You've got the brilliant light of the stained glass window
which actually is illuminated by the sky beyond.
You have the gilded stucco you have the bronze which is in part gilded as well.
You have the marble which can be brilliantly white but also coloured.
And it becomes this kaleidoscope of form and colour and light.
And its dizzying and beautiful.
But when I say dizzying I dont want to suggest that it is unfocused.
But its tremendously unified.
And perfect in the scale of it.