In the last video, we took a look at what is
probably the simplest possible economy, and
it's not even clear that this economy is even
possible--this one person economy--but to make
it more analogous to the real world (where we have
households and we have firms). And in this one island,
this guy set up a firm and he essentially leased
out all the factors of production to that firm,
including his own labor (he leased it out,..the "rent" on his labour is essentially his wages), and then
he bought all of the goods and services he needed
from that same firm, so his payments would, his expenditures, would
be the revenue of that firm and then the revenue
of that firm would be turned into the expenses
and the profit of the firm. So, whatever wasn't
used in the expenses would end up being profit,
and then all of that went back to that one
household as income. And when we talked about
how would we measure the economic activity in
this island right over here--how would we measure its
gross domestic product (GDP)--we said, "well, look,
we could measure it in multiple different ways:
as it's leaving his hands, the dollars, and it's
going to the firm, you could view it as a
total expenditures, or as it's approaching the firm,
that's the same thing as the total revenue for this firm.Total revenue for this firm, simplified one firm-economy.
And that total revenue is the same thing as the
total expenses plus the profit for that firm and that's
the same as this one household's income.So let me write this down.The way we looked at the last thing,
In the very simple example,
GDP = Household expenditures which was = Firm revenues which was =
= Firm expenses + profit which is = household income (I'll just write Inc. for Income) =
and of course household income is then (or at least in this case it ended up being equal to) household expenses.
What I want to do in the video now, is think about
it in more general terms. Let's extend it to a more
complex economy--to the world we live in--and with
that I want to look at the more formal definition for
GDP. So this is the more formal definition of GDP: --Or I just say the defintion of GDP-- and it's
the market value of ALL FINAL goods and services
(and we're going to talk about what each of these things mean) of all, of ALL THE FINAL GOODS AND SERVICES..I'll underline all seperately..and in a different color...ALL FINAL goods and services...
produced within a country in a given period.
So, you could have a GDP for a month you could have a GDP for a quarter of a year or you can
be three months or you could have the GDP in a given year. And I guess you could even have a GDP over a ten-years period.
But it tends to be..we always think of GDP in terms of annual or quarterly GDP or sometimes even some estimates of a monthly GDP but it tends to be annually or quarterly. But let's parcel it a little bit more, cause these terms can be interesting.
So the first one I'd like to parce is the idea of market value.
What this is saying is..we need some way to measure what we've produced and the best way we can do it is to
say: "Well, how much benefit are people getting?", what they're willing to pay for in the market is the best way that we can measure how much benefit they're actually getting out of it.
So for example:
If someone, if in the year...I don't know..someone...an avocado was produced..If an avocado is produced in some farm and also an orange is produced..
We won't say that for each of these.."Oh GDP's increased by one fruit!" We look at the market-value for it.
So the market value of this avocado is
$1 and the market value of this orange is $0.5, then by producing this fruit the market-value, the GDP has increased by $0.50 by producing this avocado it's GDP has increased by $1.
Now in the next year maybe there's, whatever, demand for avocados goes down or whatever and people pay less for it.
And the market value of this incremental avocado is $0.50 then, in the next year, even though the actual number of fruits that were produced is the same as the previous year, now all of a sudden the contribution from avocados might be the same as the contribution from oranges.
So it really depends on the market value.
And then we can focus on this all...The market value of all the goods and services.All goods and services.
So we would do all the different avocados and oranges and but we would do computers, we would do cars, we would do tires and we're doing services.
So if you have a help at home, if you go to the doctor, the market value of all of those things are going to be put into GDP.
Now this won't include some thing, this does not include illegal things,
if someone sells someone else drugs, we're not keeping track of it, some would argue maybe it should be kept track of in some way but you have kind of this black market and things but you're not keeping track of illegal activities and
you're also not keeping track of goods and services that are produced within the household and consumed within the household. So for example:
If you hire an outside-person to babysit your children or your child they would be considered part of the GDP.That is a service that you are paying for but if you yourself are babysitting your children that is not going to be considered in GDP.
If I start a lawn-mowing business and I go mow other people's lawns,
or maybe before my wife I were dating, she used me to pay me to mow my lawns, then it would be included in GDP
but maybe once we get married I just mow her lawn out of..because it's my lawn..we're the same family now..then it will not be included in GDP.
But "all" does include pretty much anything that can be kept track of, anything where someone is ..there's exchange of money and some payment between two parties for that good or service.
Now the really interesting thing, this is something that I used to find confusing when I first got exposed to GDP,
is the whole notion of final goods and services.
And to understand it, let's think about
how jeans might be produced.
So you have a cotton farmer, and there's
some service used to be performed, whatever,
you know, some farming, some labout that used to be performed,
and let's say that that is
$5 of labour
and let's say that some land has to be rented,
so let's say that is $4 of land.
And there are other inputs, but we don't have to go into all the details.
And with that, there's gonna be some electricity and stuff, we won't count all of it..you can produce some cotton.
Just the plant cotton.
Some raw cotton.
And that raw cotton is worth the market value of the raw cotton,
is worth, let's say,
$10
So it's $10 worth of raw cotton.
And then you could take that raw cotton and you could combine in with some more labour
So let's say you combine that with another $6 of labor.
And it will probably also require some machines and electricity and things like that
but I won't factor in all those things right now, because we don't need them
to get the point across
and if I do that and combine the $10, this intermediate good,
with this $6 of labor
then all of a sudden
I can produce cotton thread
And that cotton thread, the worth of the market value of that cotton thread
let's say is now..
20$
...Is now $20..
And maybe there's another intermediate good there
maybe it's some dye.
Let's say..
Oh well.
Let's put in the dye later.
I have a $20 thread.
Now let's say I can take this $20 thread and
--I'll stay with white--
I can take this $20 thread and I could throw in some more labor
Maybe I could take $10 of labor
$10 of labour
and then
I can essentially create $30 worth of
cotton fabric
$30 worth of cotton fabric.
And then I could take this $30 worth of cotton fabric
plus some more labor
so let's say another $5 of labor and
let's say, we also are goint to put in $1 dye..
$1 of dye over here.
And in the process I can create the market value, let's say this is worth $50 of blue jeans..
And I do this all over the course of the year, so the period in question.
So as for the period in question, I'll assume it's a year.
So it's all happening over the course of
the periods in question.
So maybe it's happening..
We're talking about GDP in 2012,
this is all happening in 2012,
So what would be the contribution to GDP?
If we didn't have the word "final" here,
we just said that the market value of all
goods and services, then we would have
this $5, to this $4, to this $10, to this $6..
and we would because of the production of this jeans
we would get a very, very large number
a very, very large contribution to GDP.
But that would not even be double counting..
That'd be triple or 4-5 times the value that's actually created.
Because all of this value is essentially being accounted for in this end- $50.
So the actual contribution to GDP,
you would only put the final good,
so you wouldn't include all of these other intermediate goods and services
you would just say
this whole chain of events results in a $50 increase in GDP.
And in another video we'll talk about
what happens if you don't get to this point
during the course of the year,
if we just kind of stop when we're at the intermediate good.
But assuming we get to this point,
you just include the final good in GDP.
Now this last part of it is produced within a country.
And this is,you know,
you might have heard of GNP,
Gross National Product,
and that's the main difference.
GDP says: If, let's say we're talking about the USA,
so that's my best attempt to draw the US,
GDP says: look, if it was produced inside the country,
we don't care who it's been produced by.
It could have been produced by someone from Mexico.
It could have been produced by someone from Canada.
It could have been a factory that's owned by the Chinese but it was produced within the borders of the US
it gets counted as GDP
If an American who's an American national goes oversees and produces something over there,
that is not counted as GDP,
if an American owns a firm in another country and
that firm in the other country produces something, that is not GDP.
When you focus on people's nationality,
that is GNP.
So, not to confuse things,
but if you want to focus on GNP,
then you do care about the earnings of American nationals.
So you wouldn't count the Canadian.
But you would include the American who's making money overseas.
So GDP fairly simple idea:
You say, what's being produced within these boundaries.
We don't care who's doing the producing and what their actual nationalities are.
And we're going to ignore production by that nationality outside of these borders.