[music]
Dr. Steven Zucker: We wanted to look at a late Medieval Byzantine painting
Dr. Beth Harris: You just used a lot of words--Medieval and Byzantine
Dr. Zucker: I did! Sometimes it's even call the Italo-Byzantine
Dr. Harris: Ayy! We're in Italy--we see influence of Byzantine art here
--referring to the Byzantine Empire and the East
Dr. Zucker: And it's the end of the Middle Ages--right at the cusp when the Renaissance is going to begin
Dr. Harris: And so this is Berlinghieri's panel of Saint Francis
Dr. Zucker: St. Francis is really important--he had only just died--and already he is being commemorated
--with this very important altar painting
Dr. Harris: Yes--well he established the whole order of the Franciscans--right?
Dr. Zucker: But there was a whole controversy about whether or not he should be canonized
--and at one point I think the church was actually thinking about excommunicating him
--because he was really quite radical
Dr. Harris: He was a bit of a renegade--but this painting leaves not doubt that he should be canonized--right?
Dr. Zucker: Why I think that's right--I think some art historians have suggested
that this was actually produced in order to establish his importance--and to actually support his canonization
Dr. Harris: Yeah because we see Francis here
--and he is so clearly showing us the miracle of the stigmata--right?
Dr. Zucker: That's right--his direct affiliation with Christ
Dr. Harris: The idea is that he received the miracle of the wounds of Christ
---Christ's crucifixion directly on his own body--so the wounds from the nails in his hands and feet
Dr. Zucker: He's displaying it to us
Dr. Harris: And he is showing us very clearly--and we can also see it in his feet
Dr. Zucker: And in the apron scenes--those six small little scenes on either side
are scenes from Francis' life--but they're very much meant to parallel Christ's life
Dr. Harris: And Francis himself modeled his own life on Christ's poverty
Dr. Zucker: A little to directly for the church to actually feel a little uncomfortable
--you know there was that story of Francis when he was a young man
--growing up in a very prosperous household that he actually had this spiritual awakening
--and determined that he would live the life of poverty that Christ had
--and actually ripped the clothing off his own back and apparently--in a bit of a fit--threw them at his father
Dr. Harris: He's shown performing these miracles in the scenes on either side--preaching to the birds
--well in the top left we have St. Francis receiving the stigmata
Dr. Zucker: And who is he receiving it from though?
--because if you look very closely there are those little gold lines
--and there's that sort of curious little cruciform up at the top
Dr. Harris: I think that's the Holy Spirit
Dr. Zucker: But it's such an interesting--I mean so clearly coming out of the Medieval tradition
Dr. Harris: Yup--represented so symbolically
Dr. Zucker: Yeah--and so oddly--I mean there's no concern in this painting for scale
--you have the little Francis next to the gigantic Francis
Dr. Harris: Right--and little building next to big people
Dr. Zucker: It's actually beautiful and perfect here that Francis is represented this way
because even the way Francis is known to have dressed--with the shaved head which is symbolic
--the brown sack cloth which is symbolic--his barefoot-ness
--all of those things are symbols that refer to the way in which he lived his life
--to be closer to Christ in way that was humble--that was close to nature--that was without artifice
Dr. Harris: So it makes sense that in the visual imagery around Francis--and of representing Francis
--that we wouldn't have an embrace of the physical material world
Dr. Zucker: It really does--and in some sense it makes me think later representations
--which are much more polished--much more naturalistic--much more sort of traditionally beautiful
--are in some ways more at odds with what Francis actually represents--maybe this is a truer representation
[music]