Let's do some SAT problems. Let's see,
we're starting test 5 now
and it's problem number 1.
This is page 652.
According to a certain recipe,20-- I'm getting deja-vu,
this looks like a question I did in the last test,
but maybe this is different--
25 pounds of flour are needed to make 300 rolls.
So 25 pounds per 300 hundred rolls.
At this rate,
how many pounds of flour are needed to make 12 rolls?
Well, we can make a ratio here.
So I need 25 to do 300 rolls,right?
But they're asking us well,
how much do I need if I only need to do 12 rolls?
So 12 is what fraction of 300?
Whatever that fraction is,
the fraction of rolls of pounds of flour I need to use
will be the same fraction.
Let's say that this is x is the pounds of flour I need to use
So x is to 25 as twelve is to 300.
And I can tell you from inspection that
12 over 300 is the same thing as 1/25.
If you don't believe me,
divide 300 by 12 and I come up with that.
Well, you know 25 goes into 100 4 times
and then 4 times 3 is 12.
If you don't believe me,you can confirm this.
And they did it on purpose because this is the first problem,
which tends to be a quick one.
So x over 25 is equal to one over 25, so x equals 1.
So you need 1 pound of flour.
And you could have also set the ratio up like this:
you could have said 25 is to 300 as x is to 12.
This would have also worked.
Here we would have put the rolls all on one fraction
and we could've put the pounds of flour
all on the other fraction.
Next problem.
Switching colors.
Problem number 2.
If xy is equal to 10,
what is the value of 2 times x divided by y times y squared?
Well the trick here is you've got to simplify this expression
before you attempt to do anything.
And simplifying, what's x divided by y times y squared?
Well this right here,
this is the same thing as xy squared divided by y, right?
We could put the 2 out here.
And see, we have a 2 on top and the y on the bottom is
the same thing as y to the first,so this is the same thing.
What's y squared divided by y?
Well it's just y, right?
So we get 2x and y squared divided by y is just y, right?
The squared cancels out with this entire term.
This just gets 1.
I divide the top and the bottom by 1.
So all I'm left with is 2xy,
and we know that xy is equal to 10, so 2 times 10 is 20.
That's choice e.
Next problem.
Problem 3.
Let's see if I can fit it on this without having to--
x plus y is equal to 30.
I might be talking funny.
I just came from the dentist. And x is greater than 8.
Which of the following must be true?
Well, we know x is greater than 8,
and we also know that x is equal to 30 minus y, right?
I just subtracted y from both sides of that equation.
x is equal to 30 minus y.
Well we also know that x is greater than 8, so 30 minus y,
which is the same thing as x,
must also be greater than 8, right?
30 minus y is also going to be greater than 8.
And we could play with this a little bit.
We could add y to both sides
and get 30 is greater than 8 plus y.
We could subtract 8 from both sides
and then you get 22 is greater than y, or y is less than 22.
And that's choice b.
Next problem.
Problem 4.
I'm writing in toothpaste color
in honor of my recent visit to the dentist.
OK, what do they have here?
They have three points.
So point p, which is 3 comma 2.
Point q, which is 7 comma 2.
And point r, which is 7 comma 4.
The coordinates of points p, q, and r and the xy plane
are given above.
What is the perimeter of pqr?
Let's draw that real fast.
I think that'll make things make more sense,
especially if you missed it the first time around.
So p is 3 comma 2.
So 3 comma 2, approximately.
q is 7 comma 2, so this is 3.
So this is going to be a straight line.
And what's this length going to be?
Well, it's going to be 4 because it's going from 3 to 7
and we have no change in the y, they're both at 2.
Then we have r is 7 comma 4.
It's going to be roughly over here.
This is q, this is r.
And what's this distance?
Well we had no change it x,
so the distance is just going to be the change in y,
so this is just 2.
And now we have to-- and this is r--
and now the only thing we have to do to finish this problem
is figure out that distance.
And how do we figure out that distance?
Well this is a right triangle,
so we could use the Pythagorean theorem.
2 squared-- this is the hypotenuse, right?
The green side I drew, that's the longest side
and it's opposite the 90-degree angle,
so it's the hypotenuse.
So 2 squared plus 4 squared is equal to-- let's call this x--
is equal to x squared.
So this is 4 plus 16 is equal to x squared.
20 is equal to x squared.
So x is equal to the square root of 20.
So x is equal to-- let's try to simplify this,
that's the square root of 4 times 5, right?
And we know what the square root of 4 is,
so we can take that out.
So that's x is equal to 2 root 5.
I find that
this is actually where most people have a lot of trouble,
simplifying root 20 to 2 root 5.
All we did is we factor 20 as a product of a perfect square
and another number that's not a perfect square.
And then we took the perfect square out.
We said the square root of 4 is 2, so we can take it out.
So x is 2 root 5.
So what's the perimeter?
It's 4 plus 2 plus 2 root 5.
So 4 plus 2 is 6 plus 2 root 5.
Now let me see what the choices are.
Oh, I didn't even have to do 2 root 5.
They actually have choice c says
6 plus the square root of 20.
So I didn't even have to do this but that's good to know.
This, what I did here,is good to learn.
But they made it so we didn't have to do that.
So it never hurts to glance at your choices
before you move forward like I just did.
Invert colors. I'm getting tired of this color,
so I will switch.
Problem number 5.
They give us a sequence: 8, 17, 26, 35, 44, and so on.
The first five terms in a sequence are shown above.
Each term after the first is found
by adding 9 to the term immediately preceding it.
Which term in the sequence
is equal to 8 plus 26 minus 1 times 9?
Fascinating.
So each term is equal to 9 plus the previous term, right?
So the first term, let's say term one,
let's call this the term.
Term one is 8.
Term two, let's call this t for term.
Term two is 17.
And an equation we could have gotten that is we could've
gotten 8 plus 2 times-- oh sorry, 8 plus 9 times what?
The term minus 1, right?
Because that's just 8 plus 9 so if the term is 2,
2 minus 1 is 1.
So we multiply it times 9 and we add it to 8.
Similarly, the third term, which is 26.
That's essentially 8 plus 16, right?
So that's 8 plus-- I'm sorry, 8 plus 18.
So it's 8 plus 9 times-- once again,
t minus 1, or 3 minus 1.
Right here it's 2 minus 1, here it's 3 minus 1.
So in general, this is the t-th term.
This is the equation of the t-th term,
which looks oddly familiar
to what they give us in the beginning.
And if we do a little pattern matching,
we see that t is equal to 26.