We're at Musee d'oRsay and we're looking at Manet portait of Emile Zola who is as very important 19th century novelist
And art critic Zola behind is an image of Manet Olympia and Olympia seems to look down at Zola and Zola was also a friend of Cezannes. So Zola is an important figure in this circle and this is a really new kind of portrait, a very different
then we would have had expected it doesn't give us very much
information in the way that portrait usually gives us information
as through the face
He's actually turned away from us, you've got a sense
that he is at his desk, at his study while he's turned towards us
just for a moment as for a pause of reflection not to look at us as through the camera
for instance, but we have sort of caught him in his odd recordist view
that's really almost a profile.
There's something that almost registers emotion there. It's not like he's been absorbed in some odd and looked up from his reading
There is some eligibility in his face. And I think that quality of / being a narrative, something we see frequently in Manet