We're told that the measure of angle QPR..
So QPR, so that's this angle right over here,
is 2x + 122 and I'll assume that these are in degrees.
So its 2 x + 122 degrees.
And the measure of the angle RPS (that's this angle right over here)
is 2 x + 22 degrees.
And they ask us to find the measure of angle RPS.
So we need to figure out this right over here.
So we would be able to figure that out
if we just knew what x is.
And lucky for us, we can use the information
given to solve for x.
And then figure out what 2 times x plus 22 is.
The main big idea here, the thing that pops out here,
is that the outside rays for both of these angles
form a line. These 2 angles form line.
You could say that they are supplementary
Both of these angles are supplementary.
2x+22 plus another 2x+122 is going to add up to 180.
We know that this entire angle right over here is 180 degrees.
So we can say that the measure of angle QPR (2x+122)
PLUS the green angle RPS (2x+22)
is going to be equal to 180 degrees.
And now we can add - we can start simplifying this.
We have 2 x's and another 2 x's so those are going to add up to 4 x.
And then we have 122 + 22, so that's going to be 144.
The sum of those two are going to be equal to 180 degrees.
We can subtract 144 from both sides.
On the left hand side, we are just going to be left with a 4x.
This 4x right here.
And on the right hand side, we're going to have...
Let's see, if we were subtracting 140, we would have 40 left.
And then we have to subtract another 4, its going to be 36.
Divide both sides by 4, and we get x is equal to 9.
Now, remember, we're not done yet.
They didn't say: "solve for x",
they said: "find the measure of angle RPS."
Which is 2x+22, which is 2 times 9 plus 22.
which is 18 + 22 = 40.
So the measure of the angle RPS is equal to 40 degrees.