So I have got a rocket here.
And this rocket is going to launch a projectile maybe its a rock of some kind.
With a velocity of 10 meters per second.
And the direction of that velocity is going to be 30 degrees.
30 degrees upwards from the horizontal
or the angle between direction of the launch
and the horizontal is 30 degrees.
And what we wanna figure out
in this video is how far does the rock travel?
We wanna figure out how..how far does it travel?
Does it travel?
And to simplify this problem what we are going to do
is to break down this velocity vector into its vertical and horizontal components.
We are going to use the vertical components.
So let me just draw it visually.
So this velocity vector can be broken down into its vertical
and its horizontal components.
And its horizontal components.
So we are going to get some vertical component..
some amount of velocity in the upwards direction.
And we can use that to figure out how long
will this rock stay in the air.
Because it doesn't matter what its horizontal component is.
Its vertical component is going to determine
how quickly it decelerates due to gravity
and then reaccelerates and essentially how long it is going to be in air.
And once we figure out how long its in the air
we can multiply it by...
we can multiply by the horizontal component of the velocity
and that will tell us how far it travels.
And once again the assumption we are making in these video is
that air resistance is negligible.
Obviously if there was significant air resistance this horizontal velocity
would not stay constant while its travelling through the air.
But we are going to assume that it does.
That it does not change.
That it is negligible.
We can assume that we are doing this experiment on the moon.
If we wanted to have a...
If we wanted it in purer terms.
But lets solve the problem.
So the first thing we wanna do is to
breakdown this velocity vector
we wanna breakdown this velocity vector
that has a magnitude of 10 meters per second
and has an angle of 30 degrees with the horizontal.
We wanna break it down into its x and y components.
So its horizontal and vertical components.
So that its horizontal
draw a liitle bit better.
That its horizontal component amd its vertical components look like this.