Before we talk about the debt ceiling,
it is important to realize the difference between
the deficit and the debt,
because these words are thrown around
and it‘s clear that they're related,
but sometimes people might confuse one for the other.
The deficit is how much you overspend in a given year,
while the debt is the total amount, the cumulative
amount of the debt you've gotten over many, many years.
So, lets take a look at a simplified example.
Let's say you have some type of a country,
and that country spends in a given year $10,
that country spends $10.
but it’s only bringing in $6 in tax revenue.
So it's only bringing in $6
So this country, in this year where it spends $10
Even though it only has $6 to spend,
it has a $4 deficit.
$4, d-e-f is short for deficit
Well let me just write it out,
you might think it stands for defense, or something,
it has a $4 deficit
and you might say
how does it spend more money than it brings in?
how can it actually continue to spend this much?
where will it actually get the $4 from?
the answer is it will borrow that $4.
Our little country will borrow it.
Maybe coming into this year,
the country had some debt,
maybe it already had $100 of debt;
In this situation,
it would have to borrow another $4 of debt
So, exiting this year,
it would have $104 in debt.
It would have $104 in debt.
If the country runs the same $4 deficit
the year after this,
then the debt will increase to $108.
If it runs another $4,
then the deficit will increase to $112.
Now that we have that out of the way,
lets think about what the "debt ceiling" is.
So you can imagine the United States
is continuing to run a deficit-
it‘s continuing to spend more than it brings in-
and actually for the United States
these ratios are appropriate,
for every dollar that the United States spends
40% is borrowed,
it only has 60% of every dollar it needs
to spend right now,
so it needs to go out into the debt market
and borrow 40% to keep spending at its current rate
so if it’s continuing to borrow,
you can imagine that
the debt keeps on increasing.
So let me draw a little graph here
So that axis is time
this axis right over here is
the total cumulative amount of debt that we have.
We continue to have to borrow every 40%
of every dollar that we're spending.
So our debt is continuing to increase
So our debt is continuing to increase.
And Congress has the power,
Congress has the authority
to essentially limit how much debt we have.
So right now, we have a current debt limit
of 14.3 trillion
and even though Congress has this authority,
the way that it‘s worked in the past
is its kind of just a rubber stamp;
Congress has just always allowed the debt ceiling
to go up and up to fund our borrowing costs;
and if you think about it,
that kind of makes sense,
because right now Congress is the one that decides
where to spend the money
what are the obligations?
So the debt ceiling is like, okay so, we've already agreed
what you spend your money on
Congress has to determine
Congress figures out
what we spend our money on and what our taxes are
we've already determined how much you have to borrow,
it would seem kind of ridiculous for us
after we've decided what you need to borrow,
to say that you cannot borrow it
you cannot actually do what we've told you to do
and so, historically,
Congress has just kind of gone on with the flow
Okay, yeah, we've told you
you need to borrow more money
to execute, the executive branch
has to run the government
based on the budget we've told you
so they just keep upping it
so last time the debt ceiling was raised
which was actually very recently,
February 12, 2010,
it was raised from 12.3 trillion to
actually 12.4 trillion to,
to the 14.3 trillion
this actually happens pretty regularly
it’s happened ten times since 2001
seventy-four times since 1962
it‘s just a regular operating thing
Right now, the Obama administration says
look we've actually already come up
against our debt ceiling
and we want to raise it,
and ideally the
Obama administration wants to raise it
by about 2.4 trillion
so they want to raise it to 16.7 trillion
which will kind of put it off the table a little bit
until after the elections,
so we don't have to debate this anymore.
The Republicans on the other hand
want to essentially
use this, this is a little bit unusual, use this
as leverage to essentially, reduce the deficit
and not only to reduce the deficit
but reduce the deficit through spending cuts
and so thats why it’s become
this big game of chicken and why we're
going up against this limit
and one thing you might not have realized
we already hit that debt limit
on May 16, 2011,
I'm making this video at the end of July 2011
and the only reason this country
is continuing to operate
has been able to continue
to pay interest to its obligations
to issue social security checks,
to support Medicare
and buy fuel for aircraft carriers,
and all the rest is because
Geithner, the security treasurer
has been able to find cash in other places
cash normally set aside
for employee pensions and
all the rest and
has essentially done a little bookkeeping
taking money from one place to
feed another, but what he's said,
what he's publicly said,
is that he won't be able to do that anymore
as of August 2, 2011;
so this right here is the date that everyone is paying attention to,
August 2, 2011, according to Geithner
at that point, he won't be able to find
random pockets of cash and shuffle around and
what he calls extraordinary measures
and at that point the United States
will not be able to fulfill
all of its obligations
and so if you think about all of the
obligations of the United States-
This is a huge oversimplification here.
So this bar is all of the obligations
Some of those obligations are things like
things like
interest on the debt it already owes
a huge amount of debt 14.3 trillion dollars
things like Social Security,
Medicare,
defense,
and then all of the other stuff
that the country has to support,
all of the obligations
so as of August 2, 2011,
we cannot issue any more debt
and Geithner cannot,
doesn't have any more cash around
doing these extraordinary measures.
The only option is to somehow
reduce some of these things by 40%
because 40% of every dollar we used to spend
are borrowed so something
over here is going to give
we're not going to fulfill our obligations
to one or more of these things.
All of these things which we are legally obligated
to fulfill that Congress has said,
all these things that Congress
has said we should be spending this money on
and so at that point it is perceived
that we would have to default
and a default would be on any of these obligations,
but in particular,
we could, especially if we have to
cut everything by 40% and we don't
want to see retirees, you know
not being able to pay interest on their houses
or you know, aircraft carriers being able to have fuel
or whatever else
we might defer, or restructure
or do something weird with our debt
in which case we would be defaulting
and i want to be clear
a default is usually referred to as
not fully paying interest on debt that you owe
but it would be any of these obligations
the United States has this AAA rating
If the United States says
it‘s going to give you a Social Security check-
you trust that.
If the United States says
it’s going to pay that Medicare payment-
you trust that.
If it says it‘s going to give you an interest payment-
If it doesn't fulfill any of these obligations,
then all of the obligations become suspect
and the reason why this is a big deal
is you can imagine
if you borrow money,
and you've always been good
at paying back that money,
you're going to have to
pay lower interest
than other people would have to pay
but if for whatever reason,
one day you default
you either delay your payments,
or you say you don't
have the cash to pay your payments
Then, people are like, wow
you're a much riskier person to lend money to
so now I'm going to increase
the interest rates on you.
The perception is that if the United States
were to default on its debt,
or any of its obligations,
that interest rates would go up
and the reason why
(this would really kind of not be great)
is because it would make the debt
and the deficit even worse
and then this chunk is going to have to grow
and as new debt gets issued,
we're going to have to pay
more and more interest and
thats going to make matters worse.
It’s going to make the deficit worse,
and on top of that,
it‘s not just that the government
debt will go up,
but interest on all debts will
probably go up,
because government debt is perceived to be
the safest,
it’s the benchmark,
a lot of other contracts are
actually tied to government debt
so you'll have interest rates
throughout the economy go up
which is exactly what we do not want
to happen when you are in a recession
or when you are recovering from a recession.