we've been discussing this amazing second paragraph of the declaration of independence
where we've gotten through what past is for the first two sentences and we've also used some punctuation here
and then they're going on to say that when any form of government becomes destructive of these ends
its the right of the people to alter or abolish it and to institute new government
laying its foundations on principles as organizing
its powers in such forms as to them shall seem most likely to affect their
safety and happiness
and just to make sure that I.. cuz they've been writing.. uh, they get a bit ornated.. and its not very clear but this sentence
is a little bit ornate but when they write that when any form of government becomes destructive of these ends
they're talking again of the life, liberty and persuit of happiness
right.. in other words if you have a king whose taken away people's lives, liberty and the persuit of happiness
so they;re talking about the English government not just
the parliament but the king nail has become destructive
of these inalienable rights that they were supposed to protect
and therefore form a new government to affect their safety and happiness
Right.. but most importantly its the right of the people to alter or abolish
it.. in other words they're saying something thats not yet been accepted by history which is you're people and if you dont like your government
you can overthrow it. We hadnt had so many revolutions in on the past 200 years leading up to that and this is the beginning of an age of revolution
where people say "oh yeah.. we have the right to abolish our government".. woah thats holy cow people doing it
not another king not another ruler.. right
exactly most of history I mean for 100 years leading up to this document