The fading light of the sun is being
replaced by the lanterns being held by these children
it's that moment at twilight when artificial light
just begins to assert itself against the light of the day
It is a wonderful and haunting part of the day, and Sargent
captured it in his painting, Carnation Lily, Lily, Rose
from 1885-6. You know that title
was pretty poetic, and the repetition in the title really gives us a
sense of the idea of repetition of form and light throughout this
painting. Look at the way the Japanese lanterns move from left to
right across the middle of this canvas. Forming a
curving arabesque across the center. They're almost like the notes that you would find
in a musical score, and we do read across but of course our eye
also stops because there's so much that's beautiful to look at here.
All we have is this really lush, rich surface.
There's nobody that moves paint across the surface of the canvas like Sargent,
and look how he's just moved that brush across the surface
in rendering those roses, or the carnations down towards the bottom
or even the ridges of the lanterns themselves, and the way in which those blue
shadows play against the beautiful warm illumination from within.
It's interesting because the parts of a painting that you would expect
to be illuminated are not. Everything is
drenched in dusk. You look to the faces of the children
for where they would be illuminated, where you might see the expression
on a child's face, but he hasn't concentrated his attention there.
His attention is dispersed across this decorative surface. The parts that are illuminated are these
lanterns against this graying, green forms of
dusk. Look at the way the canvas is really flat; clearly, the influence
of Japanese prints. The way in which, for instance, the flowers are smallest
at the feet of the children, and then as we move up to those large lilies
they rise, and that's directly in opposition to the way
paintings would normally be constructed. It has the effect of
making the background come forward. So there is a conflation of
nature, and childhood, and innocence
and all of those things coming together, it's just lovely. And so nineteenth century.
So we have a painting that lacks any kind of a real subject
except for the quality of light
and color harmonies, these greens, and peaches, and pinks and whites.
We see this in British painting the last half of the nineteenth century
with artists like Albert Moore, where the subject of the painting is the color harmony
art for art's sake. This is well into this movement that we know as
aestheticism, which removes all of the literary, all of the weighty
subjects of history, and really make the painting and the beauty of the painting
its main focus. And the formal qualities of the painting, like shapes, patterns, colors
those are the things that become most
important. We could think about artists also like Whistler.
And it's easy to see how this becomes important for the beginnings of Abstraction. Looking at
art not for what it's representing, not for the objects
it's copying from the world, but for the things that art is made up of itself.
Sargent actually painted this plein air,
that is he painted it in a garden. So he was also very interested
in a tonal accuracy, an accuracy of form, even if in fact
ultimately the painting is about painting.
Apparently, this was a bit of a frustration, you know painting outside with models is not an easy thing,
especially when you've got children, and dusk is such a fleeting moment.
One can imagine him, in England, in this garden, really trying to keep everybody's
attention, making sure that the weather is right, making sure that the light is just
right, and trying to get all of this down.
The children are really concentrating on the lighting of their lanterns.
Their thoughtfulness draws us in, and allows us to linger
over all of the beautiful, visual lushness
that the artist has given us.