We’re here in MoMA storage with Pablo Picasso’s
“Glass, Guitar, and Bottle” of 1913.
He, along with other Cubist painters –
notably Georges Braque and Juan Gris –
had begun to introduce non-art materials
into their fine-art pictures –
things like wallpaper or newspaper –
a few snippets of which you see here.
By contrast, what Picasso sets the task of doing
is trying to build a collage of paint.
The result is really one of Picasso’s most
complex paintings of the Cubist period, in terms of
its facture and the variety of its surface effects.
So he used all of these different tools
and devices to manipulate his paint.
Stencils, bits of cardboard to push up
against the edges of paintings.
These very sharp, distinct lines.
Sometimes he would use,
with a stencil that was cut,
the jagged edges of his scissors, (Right?)
would be translated over into the paint.
Our conservators suspect that in some areas
creating skins of paint – skins of white lead paint –
and then literally applying those in these
shaped contours to the surface of this work –
so, actually, taking the material of paint
and making it a collage element literally. [LAUGHTER.]
The Paris Surrealists,
some people like Louis Aragon and André Breton,
always insisted, in fact, that paste and paper
were not essential to the making of collage.
They really described collage as an operation
that set out to produce a work of art,
that wasn't a seamless unity –
that wasn't a coherent whole.
That made you so forcefully cognizant
of the constructed nature.
Picasso’s always engaged with this game
of the true and the false, the vrai and the faux,
reality and illusion.
And this picture sort of ups the ante of that game
in this way that is absolutely remarkable.
Sub-titling done by the 9th-graders of ISJA middle school, Saint-Maximin, France