PROBLEM: Choose the right number of each
place value to make 8129.123.
So for the .123 part, we could say it is 123 thousandths.
Or we could say it is
1 tenth, 2 hundredths, and 3 thousandths.
So let's just go place by place.
So first, we have 8.
This 8 right over here is in the thousands place.
It represents 8 thousands.
So we're going to have 8,000.
So let's select (1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7) 8 thousands.
Then we have 1 hundred.
So we literally just have
only 1 hundred right over there.
Then we have 2 tens.
This 20 is 2 tens.
So we're going to need 2 tens.
Then this 9, well that's just 9 ones.
So it's (1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8 ) 9.
And now we're going into the tenths place.
This is only 1 tenth. So 1 tenth.
We'll write it like that.
Now this is 2 hundredths.
So we're going to put 2 hundredths there.
Then finally, 3 thousandths.
(1, 2) 3 thousandths.
And we check our answer.
And we got it right.