[music playing]
We've walked into the Academia in Florence,
which is an old art school
and is now #1 tourist destination in Florence, I think,
There's a lot of people here.
And there's a long line of people waiting outside to
get in, and it's hard to blame them
because inside is Michelangelo's David, and it's
unspeakably beautiful.
So this is a sculpture that's often seen as a perfect
exemplar of high Renaissance art.
And I suppose it's important to get the story
out of the way first.
It's an Old Testament story, and it speaks to a young man whose name is David.
He's brave enough to take on this terrible giant,
this terrible enemy, Goliath,
that all of the older men are too fearful of to confront.
He does so without any armor. He goes to battle against Goliath on behalf of the Israelites
and defeats Goliath with the help of God,
specifically with a sling shot and a single rock,
but clearly with the help of God.
You can see the sling shot in his left hand and the rock in his right, and although the
Bible says that David fought Goliath without armor
it doesn't say completely nude.
If you look at the body, of course it's in a kind
of classical contrapposto,
the weight is clearly on the right leg, the left leg is free
but the body is engaged in something
even more complex and more specific.
Much of the body is still relaxed.
His right hand is just beginning to tense and you can
see his eyes have darted to his left.
His body, it seems to me, is about to swivel and follow the head's movement
and so you have this sense that David has just
caught sight of his enemy and his body is just
beginning to tense. He's just preparing to meet Goliath.
It's impossible not to notice the remarkable
knowledge that Michelangelo brings of the human
body, of how it works and the muscles and the skeletal
structure and he created this ideally beautiful figure.
Michelangelo had dissected the human body, understood
it's internal structure, and this is a fascinating thought:
it was not long before this age that in the west
we had no idea how the human body functioned.
We take for granted in the 21st century
that we understand the mechanics of the body.
And so that kind of analysis of the structure
of the body is really an extraordinary achievement.
This is a sculpture that is about potential.
It is showing this idealized body, but in a sense
we can begin to see ourselves
in this kind of heroic stance as well.
This is nearly three times the size of a human being.
You can see why Michelangelo later got the name
Il Divino, "the divine one".
It's important to remember that Michelangelo
is a relatively unknown sculptor at this point. (He's young.)
He's really young, he had had one major commission
which is the Pieta, and then he comes out with this
tour de force, which will bring him
an enormous amount of attention.
He was commissioned by the city government
of Florence in 1501.
He was originally going to be placed on one of the
tribunes high atop the roof line of the Duomo in Florence
that is, of the main cathedral of Florence.
So it was meant to be seen from very far below.
When Michelangelo showed
what he had completed three years later
to his patrons, the city government of Florence,
they were astounded at how unbelievably beautiful it
was and thought, there's no way we want to put this
high up. We're going to put it in the piazza,
in the square, in front of the Signoria.
In front of the government building of Florence.
And that's because not only was the sculpture so
extraordinarily beautiful, but because the story of
David had come to be aligned with the story of
Florence. It was a symbol of the republic of Florence
in opposition to the notion of tyranny.
This was a very particular moment in Florentine history.
The Medici had by that time actually assumed
a great amount of power and had really subverted
the republican ideals of the city and so this
was a brief moment of the flourishing again of
these democratic ideals. There were ways in which
the pose referred specifically back to classical
images of Hercules. Hercules was a long standing
symbol of Florence as well. So there's a
whole set of symbols that surround this figure.
By making a colossal male nude, and by that we
mean way over life size, Michelangelo is taking on
a type of sculpture that the ancient Greeks and
Romans had made and in a way surpassing what the
ancient Greeks and Romans had done
showing that Florence itself has surpassed ancient
Greece and Rome too. We know that Florence saw itself
as sometimes the New Athens or the New Rome.
In fact, an important part of the mythology of
Florence was that it had been founded by the
ancient Romans. It was an inherent part of their identity.
So this all makes sense. It makes total sense that
the government in Florence, the signoria, would see
this sculpture and bring it to the Piazza Vecchia,
bring it to the seat of government (as this potent
symbol). A special conveyance was built to bring it
to the Signoria. There were 14 greased logs that
rolled it with the power of 40 men over several days
from the studio to the piazza. And thy didn't want
it to go up in the cathedral. They wanted it close.
they celebrated it. The city fell in love with this
sculpture and saw it as the most powerful symbol
they could imagine of their renewed republic.