Welcome back. I almost ran out of time in that last video,
so let's just start from the beginning for
problem number fourteen. So I drew the figure,
and they told us that this line is perpendicular to that line
and they drew it here.And that this is perpendicular to that,
and they drew it there.
They told us this was 125 degrees,this is x.
And then the one piece of information they tell us,
is that LN,this line,is equal to LM. And I marked it here.
What we said at the end of the last video was,
well if these two sides are equal,
we also know from geometry class,
that the base angles are also going to be equal.
And then let's see what we can do with that,
whether we can figure out x.
Well the first step we can do, is we can say,
well if this is 125 degrees, what is this angle right here?
Well they're going to have to add up to 180,
because they're supplementary.
So this is going to be,what's 180 minus 125?
Well what's 80 minus 25? It's 55 degrees.
So if that's 55,then this is also going to be 55.
And then if these are both 55,what is this angle up here?
Well they're all in a triangle,so they have to add up to 180.
So 55 plus 55 is 110,so this one has to be 70 degrees.
Or 180 minus 110. You have to add up to 180 degrees.
So this is 70 degrees right here.
And now can we figure out what this angle is here?
This is what I call the angle game.
You just have to keep figuring out of angles.
Well if this is 70 degrees,this angle plus this angle,
they're going to be complementary.
They're going to come out to 90,because this is 90.
So all we have left is 90 degrees here.
So if these two have to add up to 90 degrees,
then this is 20 degrees. That says 20.
I know I wrote it really small,you probably can't read it.
We know that this whole thing is a right angle
because this is a right angle.
So if this is 90,we know that this whole thing is 90.
So this is 20. And now finally,I think we're ready for x.
Because x plus 90 plus 20 has to be equal to 180
because it's in the same triangle.
So x plus 90 plus 20 is equal to 180.
x plus 110 is equal to 180. x is equal to 70 degrees.
And we are done. Next problem.
Problem number fifteen.
A measuring cup contains 1/5 a cup of orange juice.
It is then filled to the 1 cup mark that is a mixture
containing equal amounts of orange,
grapefruit and pineapple juices.
What fraction of the final mixture is orange juice?
This is interesting. You have 1/5 already orange juice,
and then the next 4/5 is going to be equal parts--
because we're going to fill to the 1 cup mark.
It's going to be equal parts orange,grapefruit--
I'll just write grape--and pineapple.
So the next 4/5 is going to be split amongst these three,
and it's equally.
So how much more orange juice are we putting in?
We took 4/5,and 1/3 of this 4/5 is going to be orange juice.
So the amount of orange juice we're putting in now
is 1/3 times the 4/5. So we're putting in 4/15 orange juice.
And we already had 1/5 orange juice. So 1/5 plus 4/15.
That equals 3/15 plus 4/15,which equals 7/15.
That is the final mixture of orange juice.
And doesn't that make sense intuitively?
That makes sense because there's 20% orange juice,
and then we're adding maybe a little bit less than a 1/4.
So we'll have a little bit less than 1/2 in the glass.
All right. Next problem.
I don't know,my cousin's answer seems a little suspicious.
She had marked up this book.All right.Problem number sixteen.
If a plus 2b is equal to 125% of 4b. So that equals 125%.
If you want to write 125% as a decimal,
which I like to do,it's 1.25.
125% of 4b,what is the value of a over b?
So we want to figure out a over b.
Let's just solve this thing.
So a plus 2b is equal to,what's 1.25 times 4?
If you have $1.25 and you have that 4 times,it's $5.00,right?
4 times 1 and then 4 times a quarter,
that's another dollar,so that's 5b.
And then subtract 2b from both sides.
You get a is equal to 3b. Divide both sides by b,
and you get a over b is equal to 3.
And you are done the problem. Problem number seventeen.
They have a number line.
This number line,let me see how much
I have to draw of this number line,to minimize my drawing.
They say 0 is here,1 is here. How many hash marks are there?
1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8 hash marks. Oh it says there.
On the number line above,
there are 9 equal intervals between 0 and 1.
What is the value of x? So there's 1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9.
I have 9 equal intervals,and then x is right--
I'm just going to make sure I draw it correctly.
We have 2 marks,and then we have x.
And actually we have the square root of x.
So they're 9 equal intervals,right?
So we could just do this is 1/9,this is 2/9,this is 3/9,
4/9,this is 8/9,this is 9/9.
This is 8/9,this is 7/9,this is 6/9,this is 5/9,
because 9 equal intervals.
So we know that the square root of x is equal to 6/9.
Square both sides. What's 6/9? That's the same thing as 2/3.
So you square both sides. You get x is equal to 4/9.
2 squared,3 squared. We are done. Next problem.
Problem eighteen.
In the xy-coordinate plane,the distance between point B--
so B is the point 10 comma 18.
The distance between the point B and the point A--
A is point x comma 3.
So the distance is 17 between these points.
What is one possible value of x?
So this is the distance formula,and the distance formula
is really just the Pythagorean theorem. What we do is we say,
well the distance squared is equal to the change in x squared
plus the change in y squared.
And this is really just the Pythagorean theorem.
If you haven't learned that yet,
actually I don't think I've done a distance formula video,
that's on my to-do list.But I'll do that.
It's just the Pythagorean theorem.
The distance squared,so 17 squared,is equal to--
what's the change in x?
So let's just call that 10 minus x squared plus--
and then we know that change in y--so 18 minus 3.
So it's 15 squared. I know 15 squared is 225.
This is going to be equal to x squared minus 20x.
It could be plus 100. What's 17 squared? 17 times 17?
7 times 7 is 49. 1 times 7 is 7,plus 4 is 11. 0 17.
It is 289. And so then we can subtract 289 from both sides.
So you get 0 is equal to x squared minus 20x plus--
add these two together--325 minus 289.
I only have 10 seconds left,
so I'll do it in the next video.