You go for a job interview.
And the first thing your interviewer says is,
"Look you have great work experience, you seem like a nice young person,
but what I really care about is your logical reasoning capabilities."
So what she says is, "Just sit down, I'm going to ask you a question about some math expressions."
And you say, "Sure shot away, give me some questions about math expressions."
And she says, "Alright so you have two integers, integer 'a' and integer 'b.'"
And she tells you that integer 'a' is greater than zero and integer 'b' is less than zero.
Then, she says that we also know that 'a' over 'b' is greater than 'a' times 'b.'
So then she says tell me some interesting things about 'a' and 'b' and 'a' over 'b' and 'a' times 'b.'
And you say, "Okay, I'll give my best shot"
And I encourage you to actually pause now and try to think about how these things might relate
or how 'b' might be constrained or 'a' might be constrained and then unpause it.
So, I've assumed you've unpaused it so let's think about this a little bit.
So the first thing, we know 'a' is positive and 'b' is negative.
So if I take a positive divided by a negative what am I going to get?
Well this right over here, a positive divided by a negative is going to be a negative.
What happens if I take a positive times a negative?
Well 'ab' is also going to be a negative.
A postive times a negative is also a negative.
So really what we're saying is that we have two negative quantities and
this one over here is greater than that one.
So let's visualize that on a number line.
Let's visualize that on a number line.
So let's say that this right over here is zero
this right over here is the positive direction, this is the negative direction.
We know both of these are negative, but 'a' over 'b' is larger.
So 'a' over 'b' is going to be to the right of 'a' times 'b.'
So, we know that 'a' over 'b'
'a' over 'b,' it has to be negative.
It has to be to the left of zero.
'a' over 'b' is going to be to the right of 'a' times 'b.'
To the right of 'a' times 'b.'
So one way to think about it is that they're both negative, but
'a' over 'b' is going to be less negative
or another way of thinking about it,
it's going to have a smaller absolute value.
it's distance from zero, which is another way of thinking about absolute value,
it's distance to the left of zero
is less than 'a' times 'b's distance to the left of zero
but because they're both negative
and we'll talking about distances from the left of zero
the one that has the smaller distance to the left of zero is less negative
and therefore is a greater number.
So, so far your interviewer seems impressed
so that was pretty good,
you were able to get a lot of clues just out of this little bit of information that I gave you.
But tell me more about what 'b' has to be and
whether we can constrain it in some way.
And you say, well okay, well we got some clues here
the fact that this absolute value right over here
is going to be less than this absolute value
we know that the absolute value of 'a' over 'b' is going to be less than 'a' times 'b,'
the absolute value of 'a' times 'b,'
Once again, it's going to be not as far left of zero as 'a' times 'b.'
So that is how we can make that statement, but
let's manipulate, algebraically manipulate this inequality here.
We could multiply both sides times 'b.'
So let's do that, let's multiply both sides by 'b',
'b' is less than zero, 'b' is less than zero.
So if your multiplying both sides of an inequality by something less than zero, it swaps the inequality.
So let me, that's why I got rid of it, I'm going to rewrite it.
So 'b' times 'a' over 'b' is going to be negative.
We know it's going to be negative, so its going to be less than 'ab' times 'b.'
If we just multiply it out, these cancel out.
We get 'a' is less than 'a' times 'b' squared.
Well now if we want to simplify, we can divide both sides by 'a'
and since 'a' is greater than zero it does not change the inequality
so we divide both sides by 'a.'
This becomes one and this becomes 'b' squared.
So we're left with one is less than 'b' squared
or another way we can think about this is,
well we can say if one is less than 'b' squared that means that 'b,'
let's be careful here, that means that the ABSOLUTE VALUE of 'b'
is going to be greater than one.
This means that the absolute value of 'b' is greater than one.
So you say, "Wait Sal, how did you get from that to that right there?"
Well just think about this a little bit,
if I square something and if its greater than one,
so that means that either 'b' is less than negative one because if it was negative one and
you squared it you would get one
and if it was greater than negative one
or just directly greater than negative one.
If it was negative 0.99 than when you squared it,
it would also be something less than one.
So that doesn't work.
So 'b' has to be less than negative one or 'b' has to be greater than one
and because for the same exact logic if it was exactly equal to one
if you squared it, this would be equal.
If it was 0.5 then 'b' squared would be 0.25 which wouldn't be greater than.
So you know both of these are true
This is another way of saying the absolute value of 'b' is greater than one.
Now we have our other constraint that 'b' is less than zero.
So since we know that 'b' is less than zero we can take this out of the picture
and if the absolute value of 'b' is greater than one
and 'b' is less than zero, then we know that 'b' has to be less than
'b' has to be less than negative one.
So, wherever negative one is 'b' is going to be less than that.
And the interviewer's very impressed,
and she says "Look you've done very good reasoning here
I think you deserve the job."