David Drogin: This a small painting by the Sienese artist--Duccio
active at the end of the 13th and very beginning of the 14th centuries
--and Duccio was one of the artists who helps establish
a Sienese gothic style--and this well rather well
preserved painting is an excellent example of that
Beth Harris: We're lucky because this painting is at
the Metropolitan Museum of Art
--and there's not a lot of the great paintings
of the 1200s and early 1300s that are here
in New York City
David Drogin: That's right--and in fact there are
very very few Duccio paintings that survive
anywhere in the world
--there's only thirteen of them total in the world
Beth Harris: And the Met actually just purchased
this one a few years ago
for a very very large sum of money
David Drogin: That's right because there are only
thirteen of them--and all of the other paintings
besides this one--at the time--were already in
museum collections and museums don't sell
or get rid of works of art
--and so when this painting came up to sale
it was the only opportunity the Met
was ever going to have to buy a painting by Duccio
Beth Harris: So we should all go and look at this one
because we are really fortunate that it's here
--but it's hard not to look at it and think about
how much money it cost
David Drogin: That's right--the Met--the Metropolitan Museum
won't officially confirm how much money they spent
but people estimate that they probably paid
$45 million for this painting
which is less than one foot tall
Beth Harris: Oh my gosh
David Drogin: It's quite a lot
Beth Harris: So let's talk about what makes
it so special--so we're looking at just a typical
Madonna and child painting
--and its got that Sienese interest
in all that gold that we were talking about
David Drogin: It's very other worldly looking in some sense
because of the intense gold in the background
that has patterns incised into it
that also made it more reflective
when candles were burning in front of it
--and the halo makes it very other worldly
the disparity and the unevenness in scale
between the infant Christ and the Virgin Mary
--the flowing undulous liquid-like weightless fabric
that covers her body
--all of these thing help us understand
that these figures are other-worldly figures
not a scene that you would glimpse
through a window as you were walking down the street
Beth Harris: And why does he look like
a little man and not like a child?
David Drogin: Well that's a good question
--it's not that Duccio didn't know how to represent
an infant if he wanted to
--but by choosing to represent the infant Christ
looking mature--looking like a little man
--Duccio and viewers would have understood
this as acknowledging his maturity
--in other words that Christ had the wisdom
of man--the wisdom of God--even though he
was a small child
--and not only that these paintings--and even sculptures
of the Virgin Mary with the infant Christ
are supposed to remind you of the scene
at the end of Christ's life
when the dead adult Christ is lying
across his mother's lap
--so by painting the figure in this way
--looking as a mature sort of older man
Duccio is doing all of things
suggesting maturing and also referencing Christ's death
Beth Harris: And we can see Mary looking down at Christ
and there's a kind of connection between them
as mother and son
--and he lifts up her headdress here
and gazes back at her
--she looks sad--and maybe there's a sense
of foreboding of his future
and how she will hold him on her lap
after the crucifiction
David Drogin: Even though the painting
is generally other-worldly
there are some things that help us understand
exactly what's going on--there are some things here
are descriptive and naturalistic
such as the child-like gesture of him pulling her vail
--the way she looks at him--and also the fact
that they stand behind a painted parapet or balcony
Beth Harris: I didn't realize that was painted
David Drogin: This is painted here
--and it serves to--in a way--separate them from us
that's a boundary between them and us
--but at the same time is also connects
there space with our space
because it's as if we glimpse them
across that wall--over that balcony
and that also is something that was rather
unusual and innovative for the time
Beth Harris: Now it looks like Mary is dressed in very dark clothing
but it would have been a very vivid blue--right?
David Drogin: Originally it would have been a brighter
stronger blue that would also have been
a very decorative effect
Beth Harris: What happened down here--to the frame?
David Drogin: Well--as I said before
this painting is very well preserved
but you notice these areas down in the bottom
this is actually where this small painting
was burnt by candles
that were burning in front of it
--this was not an altar piece
--but it was a devotional image
Beth Harris: So it wasn't in a church?
David Drogin: It might have been in a church
but it wouldn't have been over an altar
--it could have been hanging on the sidewall
of a chapel or even on a column or pier
and there would have been candles
burning in front of it as people prayed
in front of it and those candles
have left their mark
Beth Harris: So its smallness helps it to be
a very person image
David Drogin: Absolutely
it has a kind of intimacy because of its scale