It always helps me to see a lot of examples of something so I
figured it wouldn't hurt to do more scientific
notation examples.
So I'm just going to write a bunch of numbers and then write
them in scientific notation.
And hopefully this'll cover almost every case you'll ever
see and then at the end of this video, we'll actually do some
computation with them to just make sure that we can
do computation with scientific notation.
Let me just write down a bunch of numbers.
0.00852.
That's my first number.
My second number is seven trillion, twelve billion.
I'm just arbitrarily stopping the zeroes.
The next number is 0.0000000 I'll just draw a couple more.
If I keep saying zero, you might find that annoying.
five hundred The next number -- right here, there's a
decimal right there.
The next number I'm going to do is the number seven hundred and twenty-three.
The next number I'll do -- I'm having a lot of seven's here.
Let's do 0.6.
And then let's just do one more just for, just to make sure
we've covered all of our bases.
Let's say we do eight hundred and twenty-three and then let's throw some -- an
arbitrary number of zero's there.
So this first one, right here, what we do if we want to write
in scientific notation, we want to figure out the largest
exponent of ten that fits into it.
So we go to its first non-zero term, which
is that right there.
We count how many positions to the right of the decimal point
So it's going to be equal to this.
So it's going to be equal to eight -- that's that guy
right there -- 0.52.
So everything after that first term is going to
be behind the decimal.
So 0.52 times 10 to the number of terms we have.
One, two, three.
ten to the minus three.
Another way to think of it: this is a little bit more.
This is like eight one / two thousands, right?
Each of these is thousands.
We have eight one / two of them.
Let's do this one.
Let's see how many zero's we have.
We have three, six, nine, twelve.
So we want to do -- again, we start with our largest
term that we have.
Our largest non-zero term.
In this case, it's going to be the term all
the way to the left.
That's our seven.
So it's going to be 7.012.
It's going to be equal to 7.012 times 10 to the what?
Well it's going to be times ten to the one with this many zero's.
So how many things?
We had a one here.
Then we had one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten, eleven, twelve zero's.
I want to be very clear.
You're not just counting the zero's.
You're counting everything after this first
term right there.
So it would be equivalent to a one followed by twelve zero's.
So it's times ten to the twelfth.
Just like that.
Not too difficult.
Let's do this one right here.
So we go behind our decimal point.
We find the first non-zero number.
That's our five.
It's going to be equal to five.
There's nothing to the right of it, so it's 5.00 if we wanted
to add some precision to it.
But it's five times and then how many numbers to the right, or
behind to the right of the decimal will do we have?
We have one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten, eleven, twelve, thirteen, and we
have to include this one, fourteen.
five times ten to the minus fourteenth power.
Now this number, it might be a little overkill to write this
in scientific notation, but it never hurts to get
the practice.
So what's the largest ten that goes into this?
Well, one hundred will go into this.
And you could figure out one hundred or ten squared by saying, "OK, this
is our largest term." And then we have two zero's behind it
because we can say one hundred will go into seven hundred and twenty-three.
So this is going to be equal to 7.23 times, we could say times
one hundred, but we want to stay in scientific notation, so I'll
write times ten squared.
Now we have this character right here.
What's our first non-zero term?
It's that one right there, so it's going to be six times and
then how many terms do we have to the right of the decimal?
We have only one.
So times ten to the minus one.
That makes a lot of sense because that's essentially
equal to six divided by ten because ten to the minus
1 is 1/10 which is 0.6.
One more.
Let me throw some commas here just to make this a
little easier to look at.
So let's take our largest value right there.
We have our eight.
This is going to be 8.23 -- we don't have to add the other
stuff because everything else is a zero -- times ten to the --
we just count how many terms are after the eight.
So we have one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten.
8.23 times 10 to the 10.
I think you get the idea now.
It's pretty straightforward.
And more than just being able to calculate this, which is a
good skill by itself, I want you to understand why
this is the case.
Hopefully that last video explained it.
And if it doesn't, just multiply this out.
Literally multiply 8.23 times 10 to the 10 and
you will get this number.
Maybe you could try it with something smaller
than ten to the ten.
Maybe ten to the fifth.
And well, you'll get a different number but
you'll end up with five digits after the eight.
But anyway, let me do a couple more computation examples.
Let's say we had the numbers -- let me just make something
really small -- 0.0000064.
Let me make a large number.
Let's say I have that number and I want to multiply it.
I want to multiply it by -- let's say I have a really large
number -- three two -- I'm just going to throw a bunch of zero's here.
I don't know when I'm going to stop.
Let's say I stop there.
So this one, you can multiply out.
But it's a little difficult.
But let's put it into scientific notation.
One, it'll be easier to represent these numbers and
then hopefully you'll see that the multiplication actually
gets simplified as well.
So this top guy right here, how can we write him in
scientific notation?
It would be 6.4 times 10 to the what?
one, two, three, four, five, six.
I have to include the six.
So times ten to the minus six.
And what can this one be written as?
This one is going to be 3.2.
And then you count how many digits are after the three.
one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten, eleven.
So 3.2 times 10 to the 11th.
So if we multiply these two things, this is equivalent to six
-- let me do it in a different color -- 6.4 times 10 to
the minus 6 times 3.2 times 10 to the 11th.
Which we saw in the last video is equivalent to 6.4 times 3.2.
I'm just changing the order of our multiplication.
Times ten to the minus six times ten to the eleventh power.
And now what will this be equal to?
Well, to do this, I don't want to use a calculator.
So let's just calculate it.
So 6.4 times 3.2.
Let's ignore the decimals for a second.
We'll worry about that at the end.
So two times four is eight, two times six is twelve.
Nowhere to carry the one, so it's just one hundred and twenty-eight.
Put a zero down there.
three times four is twelve, carry the one.
three times six is eighteen.
You've got a one there, so it's one hundred and ninety-two.
Right?
Yeah.
one hundred and ninety-two.
You had them up and you get eight, four, one plus nine is ten.
Carry the one.
You get two.
Now, we just have to count the numbers behind
the decimal point.
We have one number there, we have another number there.
We have two numbers behind the decimal point,
so you count one, two.
So 6.4 times 3.2 is equal to 20.48 times 10 to the -- we
have the same base here, so we can just add the exponents.
So what's minus six plus eleven?
So that's ten to the fifth power, right?
Right.
Minus six and eleven.
ten to the fifth power.
And so the next question, you might say, "I'm done.
I've done the computation." And you have.
And this is a valid answer.
But the next question is is this in scientific notation?
And if you wanted to be a real stickler about it, it's not in
scientific notation because we have something here that could
maybe be simplified a little bit.
We could write this -- let me do it this way.
Let me divide this by ten.
So any number we can multiply and divide by ten.
So we could rewrite it this way.
We could write one / ten on this side and then we can multiply
times ten on that side, right?
That shouldn't change the number.
You divide by ten and multiply it by ten.
That's just like multiplying by one or dividing by one.
So if you divide this side by 10, you get 2.048.
You multiply that side by ten and you get times ten to
the -- times ten is just times ten to the first.
You can just add the exponents.
Times ten to the sixth.
And now, if you're a stickler about it, this is good
scientific notation right there.
Now, I've done a lot of multiplication.
Let's do some division.
Let's divide this guy by that guy.
So if we have 3.2 times 10 to the eleventh power divided by
6.4 times 10 to the minus six, what is this equal to?
Well, this is equal to 3.2 over 6.4.
We can just separate them out because it's associative.
So, it's this times ten to the eleventh over ten to
the minus six, right?
If you multiply these two things, you'll
get that right there.
So 3.2 over 6.4.
This is just equal to 0.5, right?
32 is half of 64 or 3.2 is half of 6.4, so this
is 0.5 right there.
And what is this?
This is ten to the eleventh over ten to the minus six.
So when you have something in the denominator, you
could write it this way.
This is equivalent to ten to the eleventh over ten to the minus six.
It's equal to ten to the eleventh times ten to the
minus six to the minus one.
Or this is equal to ten to the eleventh times ten to the sixth.
And what did I do just there?
This is one over ten to the minus six.
So one over something is just that something to the
negative one power.
And then I multiplied the exponents.
You can think of it that way and so this would be equal
the same bases, ten in this case, and you're dividing them,
you just take the one the numerator and you subtract the
exponent in the denominator.
So it's eleven minus minus six, which is eleven plus six,
which is equal to seventeen.
So this division problem ended up being equal to
0.5 times 10 to the 17th.
Which is the correct answer, but if you wanted to be a
stickler and put it into scientific notation, we want
something maybe greater than one right here.
So the way we can do that, let's multiply
it by ten on this side.
And divide by ten on this side or multiply by one / ten.
Remember, we're not changing the number if you multiply
by ten and divide by ten.
We're just doing it to different parts of the product.
So this side is going to become five -- I'll do it in pink -- ten
times 0.5 is 5, times 10 to the 17th divided by 10.
That's the same thing as ten to the seventeenth times ten
to the minus one, right?
That's ten to the minus one.
So it's equal to ten to the sixteenth power.
Which is the answer when you divide these two
guys right there.
So hopefully these examples have filled in all of the
gaps or the uncertain scenarios dealing with
scientific notation.
If I haven't covered something, feel free to write a comment on
this video or pop me an e-mail.