now that we have a visual sense of what this common tangent with a positive slope would look like
let's see if we can get some constraints on it, especially constraints on it's slope and y intercept
so this line that I drew in the last video here in pink it will have the form y is equal to mx + b
it's a line where m is the slope and b is the y intercept.
now let's think about what constraints there would have to be on m and b
if this is tangent to the circle.
you might be tempted to break out some calculus and figure out the slope at any point
along side a circle but there's an easier way to do it
you just have to realize that if a line is tangent to a circle it will only
intersect that circle at one point. Let me show you what I'm talking about