Problem 17.
The three dimensional figure above
has 2 parallel bases and 18 edges.
I could try to draw it, but, well let me draw that.
So their bases are both hexagons, essentially.
So I have one base that looks like this.
I have time so let me draw it properly.
So the base in front looks something like this.
And then the top base is just a small version,
or smaller version, that looks like that. Whoops.
And then they draw-- these are the front edges--
look something like this.
Under the rear edges in a darker color, so you know,
that they're in the back.
Rear edge.
I should have drawn that later,
because that's going to switch back to this.
And just paint over this,just so you know,these are in front.
OK, good enough.
And they tell us that this point up here is v.
I don't know if that even fit on the video,
but hopefully you can see that point up there.
The three dimensional figure above has two parallel bases,
right,this is one base, that's the other base.
Two parallel bases and 18 edges.
Line segments are to be drawn connecting vertex v
with each of the other 11 vertices.
Each of the 11 vertices in the figure.
How many of these segments
will not lie on an edge of the figure?
So an edge of the figure is essentially,
well let's see what they're saying.
Line segments should be drawn connecting vertex v
with each of the other 11 vertices.
So what are the other 11 vertices?
Let me draw them. Let me do it in a brighter color.
There's 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11.
And they want to know, how many of these segments
will not lie on an edge of the figure.
And actually I think this is a little ambiguous,
because if something is on the face of the figure,on a base.
OK, well they're saying the edges.
They're defining the edges as the lines.
So there's 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14,
15, 16, 17, 18 edges.
So it can lie on a face and still count.
So how many of these line segments can I draw?
Well, if I want to draw a line segment with every point
on this base that is not on an edge.
So this one won't count,
because that is on an edge right there. But I can draw 1.
Oh, I should use a different color,
because this is going to get messy.
I can draw 1, 2, 3,
because I'm connected to the other 2 with an edge.
So I have three there.
And then how many can I draw a line segment to in the other
that I'm not connected already with an edge?
Well the way to think about it is,
this point is connected to this only here.
So we can't use this as one of the line segments.
But then there's 5 other points that it can connect to,
where you're not going through an edge.
So you're going 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. So there's 5 more.
3 plus 5 is equal to 8.
And if you wanted to do that even without drawing it
you could have said, well, there's two types of vertices.
There's the ones that are on the top base,
and the ones that are on the bottom base.
On the top base, which was the hexagon,
this was our point right here.
On the top base with the hexagon
there are 5 other vertices, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
But you're connected directly to 2 of them.
So there's only going to be 3
that you can go where you're not already connected to them.
And likewise, on the bottom base,
if this was the bottom base,
vertex v was only directly connected to this one,right?
It had an edge directly to that one.
But the other 5, it didn't have a direct edge to.
So all of those would have been fair game for the problem.
So 5 on the bottom it can connect to, and 3 on the top.
And that's where we got our 8 from.
Next problem.
Alright. This looks like something that I need to draw.
That's my x-axis, that's my y-axis.
Let me label them, x, y.
And then they drew a rectangle
that I'll do in a different color.
It looked something like this.
It looks like that. And then how do they label it?
They said that this point, c, is the point 1/2 comma c.
This point b is the point minus 1/2 comma b.
My microphone is hitting my sweatshirt.
And then, let's see, this point here, a, is minus 1/2 a.
And then finally, this point here, d, is 1/2 comma d.
And then they drew a graph
in between this whole thing that intersects.
It goes from here, then it starts to flatten out.
It's already looking kind like an x cubed graph,
if you're familiar with what an x cubed graph looks like.
And it goes through that point.
Of course there's a point here.OK.
Note, figure not drawn to scale.
In the figure above, abcd is a rectangle.
Points a and c lie on the graph of y equals px cubed.
This is y, it looks like,y equals px cubed. Fair enough.
Where p is a constant, if the area of abcd is 4,
what is the value of p?
So area is base times height,right?
Can we figure out what the base is? Well sure.
We know that this is 1/2,right?
because the coordinates of these two,
the x coordinate is 1/2.
We know that this is minus 1/2,
because the coordinates of these two are,
the x coordinate's minus 1/2.
So if this length is 1/2, and this length is 1/2,
we know this entire base is 1,right?
So if we know the area is 4 of this entire rectangle,
what is this height?
This distance is going to have to equal 4.
Because 4 times 1 is the area,and 4 times 1 equals 4.
So this has to have height 4.
And this is symmetric, right?
Well, do we know that it's a symmetric?
It's a rectangle, points lie on the graph.
Do you know how we know it's symetric?
Because this is y equals px cubed.
And anything that is px cubed would be symmetric like this.
At 1/2, whatever pointed it is at c,
it would be at a similar point down here.
But it would just be on the other side
and in the third quadrant.
So it's kind of like you're flipping it over the origin.
But anyway, so if we assume that that's symetric,
then we know that this distance is 2,this distance is minus 2
If this distance is 2,then now we know a point on this graph.
We know that c must be equal to 2, right?
because that's the y coordinate.
Now we have a point on the graph,
so we can substitute it back in.
y equals px cubed.
So let's put 2 for our y,
because we know that that's a point of the graph,right?
We know that point 1/2, 2 is on the graph.
So if we put 2 for y,
we get 2 is equal to p times the x value.
p times 1/2 cubed.
So 2 is equal to p over 8.
1/3 cubed, oh sorry I can't do math.
I did 1/2 over cubed. 1/3 cubed is 27. 3 squared, 9, 27.
So p, multiply both sides by 27, is equal to 54.
And all we did here is we just said, well,
let's figure out what this side is.
We know that this side is 1,
because we can look at the minus 1/2 and the 1/2.
So this side has to be 4.
If this side is 4, and it's symmetric,
it goes just as much as above the x-axis as below,
and we know that
because this is an x third,x cubed function.
We know that this side must be 2,
or that the y coordinate is 2.
And then we just substitute into y
is equal to px cubed to solve for p.
I'll see you soon.