Use elimination to solve for x and y,
and they give us two equations here.
x + 2y is equal to 6
and
4x - 2y is equal to 14
so to solve, to solve by elimination
what we do is we are going to add these two equations together
so that one of the two variable essintially gets
eliminated, gets cancelled out.
what we can do right here
we see we have a +2y here we see we have a -2y
right over here. So clearly if we added these two
together the y's would cancel out.
So that's exactly what were going to do.
were going to add the left side of this equation
to the left side of this equation,
and the right-hand side of that equation
to the right hand side of the bottom equation.
So to make it clear that this should make sense is
were just using both of these constraints.
Whenever you learn about any type of equation