Evaluate the expression 5y to the 4th minus y squared when y is equal to 3
so every place you see a y here we can just replace it with a three
to evaluate it so it becomes 5 times three to the fourth power minus
three squared, all I did is every time we saw a y here, I put a three there
so what does this evaluate to, we have to remember our order of operations
remember parenthesis comes first, sometimes it's referred to as PEMDAS
P is for Parenthesis, E is for Exponents, M and D are for multiplication and
division and they are really at the same level of priority and then addition
and subtraction are at the same level. If you really
want to do it properly should be P-E and then multiplication and division
are at the same level and addition and subtraction are at the same level
What this tells us is that we do parenthesis first and expeonentiation takes
priority over everything else here, so we have to evaluate these exponents
before we multiply anything or before we subtract anything.
So the one exponent we have to evaluate is three squared
so just remember three to the first is three, it's just three times itself once
so it's just 3. Three squared is equal to three times three, three multiplied
by itself twice, thats equal to nine, three to the third power
is equal to three times three time three, or it can be viewed as
as three squared times three, so it would be nine, three times three
is nine, nine times three is equal to twenty seven, three to the fourth is
equal to three times three times three times three, three times three is nine
three times three is nine, so it's going to be the same thing as nine times nine
so it's going to be equal to eighty one. So we now know what
three to the fourth is, we know what three squared is
lets just put it in the expression, so this is going to be equal to
five times three to the fourth, three to the fourth is
eighty one, so five times eighty one, minus three squared, and we have three squared right over here it is
equal to nine. Five times eighty one minus nine, let's figure out what five times eighty one is,
so eighty one times five, one times five is five, eight times five is forty,
so this right over here is four hundred and five, so it becomes
four hundred and five minus nine, so that is going to be equal to
if we are subtracting ten it would be 395, but we're subtracting one less than that
so it's 396, and we're done.