cryptographic hash functions are basically fundamental building blocks
that are used within many cryptographic algorithms &amp; protocols
we have a number of very important applications
in the context of information security as a whole
now, some of the more common algorithms in this category, that are known as cryptographic hash functions, include
things like MD5, &amp; also
it has some predecessors like MD4 &amp; others
as well as algorithms like
like SHA-256, and actually SHA-256 is
preceded by others algorithms like SHA-1 and so on
and also there are some algorithms that maybe you
heard of, maybe they're a bit lesser known, but things like RIPEMD, and BLAKE, and Skein, and others
now cryptographic hash functions are basically
used as critical building blocks in many applications
and really, the first motivating application, the first
historical application of these type of hash functions, was in the context of
was known as a digital signature. And digital signature is used in so many different
cryptographic applications such as
the cornerstone of many e-commerce protocols
they're used in doing things like Bitcoin generation &amp; so on
cryptographic hash functions are also used in things like message authentication protocols
in pseudo random number generation &amp; password security
even encryption to some degree
and in fact
aside from their use in digital signatures
these hash functions are also used in other places in the Bitcoin protocol as well
so 1st of all, let me talk about what a cryptographic hash function is, &amp; of course
as the implies, the 1st thing is, it's a hash function
and by hash function, I basically mean that it will
take input. It's a mathematical function, a transformation if you will
that takes a particular input, &amp; we call these inputs "messages"
and message can be of arbitrary length
and the hash function basically applies a mathematical
transformation, maybe a set of mathematical transformations to this input
to produce a single output. We typically call this output a digest, although
sometimes you will see the output referred to as a tag,
or as a hash, or
as a fingerprint, but digest is one of the most
common norm &amp; in fact MD5
which was one of the
one of the earlier hash functions stands for "Message Digest 5"
and MD4 is "Message Digest 4" &amp; so on &amp; so forth
now, the message, just as I mentioned briefly, can be of arbitrary size, they can be
as long as you want, or as short as you want
but the output, the
the size of the digest / tag, is going to be fixed in length, for example
in the context of a hash function like
let's say SHA-256, the digest will actually be exactly
the 256 bits in length
so it's gonna have a fixed length output
but an arbitrary length input
and the other thing I wanna point out about
these cryptographic hash functions, is that the function is a deterministic function, &amp; by that I mean that the
output will always be the same for a given input. So if you have
a given input, you're gonna see the exact same output. You won't have a situation in which a given input will have
two different possible outputs. It's going to be consistent.
now, traditional
traditional hash functions have been used in computer science
for quite some time, and they're used in many
computing applications. For example, you may have heard of something like a hash function used to form a hash table
but the kind of hash functions that are used in hash tables
and I wanna stress this,
they aren't necessarily the same as cryptographic hash functions
the qualifier cryptographic here is very, very important. And usually,
means / implies that: that hash function
has to have a certain set of
critical design goals &amp; maybe some
particular properties in mind
that make it suitable for use
in applications that use cryptography / cryptographic application areas, where
perhaps security / privacy
or confidentiality / authentication is a serious concern
so first &amp; foremost in describing somebody's property is that
and maybe this almost goes without saying
one of the first properties you want in a cryptographic hash function is that it should be
computationally
computationally efficient. By that I mean that it shouldn't take a lot of time
the compute the output from a given input. If you're
If you're given a message &amp; you wanna apply this set of transformations to that message to get a digest
that set of transformations should not take a long time to implement. On a computer it should be very fast / relatively fast
and it almost goes without saying but I think it's important to stress &amp; point it out, because I've seen
people come up with grossly inefficient hash functions sometimes &amp; those would not be considered
suitable in the context of typical
cryptographic hash functions that are used for cryptographic applications.
and the second property you typically need, especially in the context of digital signing
is that you want it to be the case that
it's hard to find 2 inputs that actually map to the same input. I mean 2 distinct inputs
whose corresponding digest is identical
and this property is typically referred to as
collision
collision resistance
That means it's hard to find a colliding pair of inputs
In another words, if we have 2 inputs, let's say you have some message M1 &amp; M2
their output under the application of the hash function
should not be the same. You will never have the same
you won't ever have the case that the output of M1 &amp; M2
under an application of the hash function is the same. It should never be the same. It should always be different.
Now, I should take a step back &amp; point out that
of course, in practice
given that messages can be of arbitrary size, and
given that the output is a fixed size
it's not mathematically possible to guarantee that the
output will always be different for 2 distinct messages
But what you typically want is not that the output are neccessarily different, but that it's hard to find
2 distinct messages that produce the same output
We know that they exist, by the virtue of the fact that messages can be hashed in only a finite
small number (or relatively a small number compared to the number of messages)
a small number of possible digest values
but aside from that consideration
it should be hard, it should take a long time, &amp; by long I mean
an astronomically long time to find 2 distinct messages that would result in the same output
under the application of the hash function
Now, the 3rd thing I wanna point out, is that in many cases
you might want also, in the context of hash functions, for the hash function to be able to hide
information about the inputs. In other word,
given the output
it should be hard to glean anything useful about the input
anything, any relevant detail &amp; I don't just mean the whole input
but maybe even something as simple as "was the input an even number / odd number"?
That should be the kind of thing that should be hard to infer when you see the output
even something as simple as the
the evenness or the oddness of the input
Now, 4th property I wanna point out
is that you typically want the output to be
well distributed. In other words, the
the output should look
should look random. In other words, it should look like a set of coin flips took place, not in a
a predictable way
in which, the output was created
And really, what that means is that (&amp; you can think about it, maybe more conceptually, as) it's almost as if you flipped a bunch of coins to get the output. It should look that random.
So what you can really think cryptographic hash functions as, is perhaps maybe the mathematical equivalent / analog
of a meat grinder. So it can take inputs &amp; apply these
these mathematical transformations to them
such that the output looks
for all intents &amp; purposes, completely random &amp; unrelated to the original input
Now, I do wanna make a few quick remarks about these
particular properties. And first of all, they are interrelated
for example, if you have
a situation where the outputs
let's say really appear to bear no relationship to the input
&amp; the output also
looks random, then that'll in fact give you
to a large degree, a lot of the collision resistance properties
because just the fact that you can't predict the output &amp; the fact that it hides all this information
implies it's gonna be hard to find
two inputs that are distinct that map to the same output
And so, sometimes you get one property in exchange for the others,
Now the 2nd thing I wanna point out, is that, typically these properties
in practice, or maybe even in the underlying mathematics
are things that you hope for
but you can't always guarantee that they'll always hold. Maybe it's entirely possible that
you could design a hash function that you think is completely collision resistant
but someone might come along, a year from now, &amp; come up with a more clever way of refining
a collision. Maybe they'll find a clever shortcut that doesn't involve
doing a brute force search of any sort
And it turns out that cryptographers
for better or worse, currently do not have
any mathematical techniques, they haven't developed techniques for being able to work around
some of these limitations
And so we often do take it, on face value
that these schemes are secure, based on how long they've been around
Now I also wanna point out, the last thing I wanna point out, is that this treatment that I've given is not meant to be mathematically rigorous
by any stretch of the imagination. There are
far more precise ways to describe
these underlying properties
But my hope is that
this video gives you, maybe a bit of flavor
for what is required of a cryptographic hash function, without getting bogged down in some of the mathematical minutiae &amp; formalism.