I want to add one super fast addendum
to the video on Friedel-Crafts acylation.
In the last step of the mechanism,
I had this chlorine swipe the electron,
or essentially that electron that was with the aluminum.
It was given to the hydrogen proton.
So the hydrogen was nabbed away.
Its electron was allowed to go back into the benzene ring.
So the aluminum lost a chlorine.
This benzene ring lost a proton.
It was able to take back that electron.
And I forgot to draw the hydrogen and the chlorine.
So then that results in hydrogen chloride.
So you have the hydrogen proton bonded.
It took this electron from the aluminum.
And it is bonded to the chlorine.
I didn't want to forget that in that last step
of the Friedel-Crafts acylation.
We also get some hydrogen chloride.