We were on problem 227 when I got a phone call
It was actually from Jonathan who helps me
with the Khan Academy
so I thought it was worth taking
He works at LinkedIn and he wanted let me know about all
this news that was occurring there
Anyway, I'm getting distracted
Let's go back to the GMAT problems
So problem 227
In the coordinate system above
which of the following is an equation of line l?
And they didn't put this 2 here and this 3 here
but from the drawing you can assume that
this is the point x is equal to 3
and this is the point y is equal to 2
And then frankly, you need that information to figure out
the equation of this line
So, first of all, what's the slope of the line?
Make sure my tool is right
The slope is equal to change in y over change in x
See, when you go from this point to this point
what's the change in y?
It's 0 minus 2, which makes sense
because we went down by 2
and the change in x is 3 minus 0
Whenever you do slope, it's important remember
if I'm taking this as the first point on the y side
so 0 minus 2
I have to do the same on the bottom, 3 minus 0
Otherwise, we'll get the negative of the slope
Anyway, this is equal to minus 2/3
and what's the y-intercept?
Well, it's pretty obvious
When x is equal to 0, y is equal to 2
So we could say, y of 0 is equal to 2
So the equation of this line
at least the mx plus b form that you learned in school
is y is equal to minus 2/3 of the
slope times x plus the y-intercept
And that's not one of the choices
They've written it in a different form
They call it the ax plus by equals c form
so let's see if we can get there
Let's get rid of this 3 in the denominator
so let's multiply both sides of this equation by 3
I'll switch colors
You get 3y minus 2x-- no, 3y is equal to--
sorry-- minus 2x plus 6, right?
I just multiplied everything by 3
3y is equal to minus 2x plus 6
Now let's add 2x to both sides
and you get 2x plus 3y is equal to 6, which is choice B
Next problem
Problem 200
No, what is this?
Problem 228
If a two-digit positive integer has its digits reversed
the resulting integer differs from the original by 27
So let's say I had AB
That's a two-digit number
And I'm going to subtract BA from it
and so the difference is 27
Since I'm assuming a positive difference
AB has got to be a bigger number than BA
So at least the way I've written it
what do we know about it?
Well A has to be greater than B, right?
If AB is greater than BA, A has got to be-- well, right
A has got to be greater than B
I was going to say A could be greater than or equal to B
but if A was equal to B
then this thing right here would be 0
So if we assume that AB minus B is a positive 27
then that tells us that A is greater than B
or B is less than A
So if B is less than A
when we're doing the subtraction problem
we're going to have to-- when we do this part
when we do the ones place, if B is less than A
we're going to have to borrow, right?
So if we borrow
this A becomes A minus 1 and the B becomes B plus 10
and then we'd be ready to subtract
So what could we say?
We could say that B plus 10 minus A is equal to 7
which tells us that B minus A is equal to minus 3
And that's essentially what they're asking for
They want to know by how much to do the two digits differ
Well, B minus A is equal to minus 3
that's saying that A minus B is equal to positive 3, right?
You just multiply both sides by negative 1
Or you could say that the absolute value of B minus A
or A minus B, or how much they differ is equal to 3, right?
The absolute value of B minus A is plus 3
And just to make sure that this all works out
if we do it with the tens place
A minus 1 minus B is equal to 2
Let's add 1 to both sides
You get A minus B is equal to 3, so it works out
A and B differ from each other by exactly 3
and that's choice A
Problem 229 The circle-- OK, let me see if I can draw this
So I have one line, I have another line
and then I have a circle
It starts right there, so it looks something like that
There's a tangent
It has center c right there
And it says the circle with center c shown above is
tangent to both axes
If the distance from o to c is equal to k--
I'll get a different color
So this is from the origin to c
So they label the origin as o
But if that is equal to k
what is the radius of the circle in terms of k?
Let's think about this
So this is-- this is going to deal with triangles
and how can we use the radius
and relate it to this right here?
Well, the first thing that might come to mind is
if I just drop a line straight down from here
that's equal to the radius, right?
That's equal to the radius
because it is a 90-degree angle right here, right?
It touches that line
So if we could figure out this distance right here
then we could use the Pythagorean theorem to maybe figure out
what the radius is
And luckily enough, this distance is also the radius
And if that's not obvious to you, think about it
The distance from here to here is exactly the same thing as
the distance from here to there, right?
And from here to here is the radius of the circle
So this is also r
So now we can use the Pythagorean theorem
r squared plus r squared is equal to k squared
Or 2r squared is equal to k squared
They wanted radius in terms of k, right
So you get r squared is equal to k squared over 2
Take the square root of both sides
r is equal to k over the square root of 2
Do they want us to rational-- nope
that's one of the choices
Sometimes they want you to get the square
root of 2 in the numerator
At least when I used to take Algebra
they used to harp on that little bit
But anyway, this is choice B
Next question, problem 230
In an electric circuit, two resistors with the resistances
x and y are connected in parallel
This is reminding me of the Physics videos
So they're connected in parallel
And this resistance is x and resistance y
In this case
if r is the combined resistance of these two resistors
then the reciprocal of r is equal to
the sum of the reciprocals of x and y
and that's what they teach you
So if you want to know the combined resistance of this
and let's say that's r, they say 1 over the combined
resistance is equal to 1/x x plus 1/y
And if you took basic circuits
this is one of the fundamental things
about parallel resistances
And then they want to know what is r in terms of x and y?
So let's see if we can solve for r
So 1/r will be equal to-- let's get a common denominator, xy
1/x x is y/xy
1/y is x/xy, right?
And then we can take the reciprocal of both sides
So then r/1, or r, is equal to xy over x plus y
I just switched those two around
And that is -- xy over x plus y-- that is choice D
Problem 231
Let me do it in this brown color
Xavier, Yvonne and Zelda, who happen to go by X, Y and Z
at least in my world
each try independently to solve a problem
If their individual probabilities for success are
1/4, 1/2, and 5/8, respectively
what is the probability that Xavier and Yvonne
but not Zelda will solve the problem?
So Xavier and Yvonne, but not Zelda
So that's the case we're looking for
So we're looking for that case
So there's a 1/4 probability that Xavier solves it
and then there's a 1/2 probability that Yvonne does
but the probability that both of them do is 1/4 times 1/2
That's the problem that they both solve it
And then we want that case and-- not or--
and Zelda can't solve it
So what's the probability that Zelda doesn't solve it?
5/8 is the probability that she does solve it
so what's 1 minus this?
So there's a 3/8 probability that
Zelda does not solve the problem, right?
And what does this come out to?
This is equal to 3 over-- 4 times 2 is 8
8 times 8 is 64, which is choice E
And I'm out of time
I'll see you in the next video. video