So now we're going to take the derivative of the sine of
the natural log of x squared, so now we have a function
thats the composite of a function thats a composite of another function
So one way you could think of it: if you set f(x)
equal to sine of x and g of x
g of x being the natural log of x
the natural log of x, and lets say
h of x equaling x squared
then this thing right here is the exact same thing as
take the derivative with respect to x
f of g of h of x
and what I want to do is kind of think of how I want to do it in my head
not having to write all of the chain rule notation, so the way I would think
about this if I were doing this in my head is the derivative of this outer function of f with respect to the level of composition directly below it
so the derivative of sine of x is consine of x
but instead of it being cosine of x it's going to be cosine of whatever was inside of here, so it's going to be cosine of
natural log, cosine of natural log of x sqaured
and so you could really view this, this part that I just
wrote right over here as f prime of g of h of x
if you want to keep track of things
Just took the derivative of the outer with respect to whatever was inside of it
have to take the derivative of the inside with respect to x, but now we have
another composite function, so we're going to multiply this times-we're going to do the chain rule
again, the derivative of, we're going to take the derivative of
ln with respect to x squared
so the derivative of ln x is 1 over x, but now we have