Use the discriminant to state the number
and type of solutions for the equation
-3x²
-3x² + 5x
-3x² + 5x - 4
-3x² + 5x - 4 = 0.
And so just as a reminder
you're probably wondering
what is the discriminant?
And we can just review it by
looking at the quadratic formula.
So if I have a quadratic equation in standard form
ax²
ax² + bx
ax² + bx + c
ax² + bx + c = 0
We know that the quadratic formula,
which is really just derived from
completing the square right over here,
tells us that the roots of this,
or the solutions of this quadratic equation are
going to be
x =
x = (-b)
x = (-b ± √())
x = (-b ± √(b²))
x = (-b ± √(b² - 4ac))
all of that over (2a).
Now, you might know from experience
applying this a little bit,
we're going to get different types of solutions
depending on what happens
under the radical sign over here.
As you can imagine, if what's
under the radical sign over here is positive,
then we're going to get an actual, real number
as its principal square root.
And when we take the positive and negative
version of it, we're going to get two real solutions.
So if b² - 4ac, and this is
what the discriminant really is,
it's just this expression under the radical sign
of the quadratic formula.
If this is greater than zero,
then we're going to have two real roots,
or two real solutions to this equation right here.
If b² - 4ac = 0,
then this whole thing is
just going to be equal to zero,
so plus or minus the square root of zero,
(which is just zero)
so this is plus or minus zero.
Well, when you add or subtract 0,
that doesn't change the solution,
so the only solution is going to be
-b / 2a
So you're only going to have one real solution.
So this is going to be one--
--I'll just write the number "1"--
--one real solution,
or you could kind of say,
you have a repeated root here.
You're kind of having it twice.
Or you could say one real solution or one real root.
Now if b² - 4ac were negative –
you might already imagine what will happen.
If this expression right over here is negative,
we're taking the square root of a negative number.
So we would then get an imaginary number
right over here.
So we would add or subtract
the same imaginary number.
So we'll have two complex solutions;
not only will we have two complex solutions,
but they will be the conjugates of each other.
So if you have one complex solution
for a quadratic equation, the other solution
will also be a complex solution
and will be its complex conjugate.
So here we would have two complex solutions.
So, numbers that have a real part
and an imaginary part.
And not only are they just complex, but
they are the conjugates of each other.
The imaginary parts have different signs.
So let's look at b² - 4ac over here.
This is our a,
this is our b,
and this is our c.
Let me label them
Let me label them – a
Let me label them – a, b
Let me label them – a, b, c.
I can do that because we've
written it in standard form.
Everything is on one side,
in particular the left-hand side,
we have a zero on the right-hand side,
we've written it in descending power form,
or descending degree,
where we have our 2nd degree term first,
then our 1st degree term,
then our constant term.
And so, we can evaluate the discriminant!
b = 5
b = 5, so b² = 5²
5² - 4
5² - 4 • a
5² - 4 • (-3)
5² - 4 • (-3) • c
5² - 4 • (-3) • (-4)
c is this whole thing, I have to be careful.
c is negative 4, we have to make sure
we take the sign into consideration,
so times c, which is negative 4 over here.
So this is
25 - 4 • (-3) • (-4)
25 - 4 • 12
25 - 48
We don't even have to do the math –
we can just say that this is definitely going to
be less than zero.
You can actually figure it out –
this is equal to negative 23,
negative 23...
which is clearly less than zero.
So our discriminant in this situation is
less than zero, so we are going to have
two complex roots here,
and they are going to be each other's conjugates.