Calculate the sum of all positive divisors of 27 000
The easiest thing that i can think of doing
is first take the prime factorization of 27000
and that will help us kind of structure our thought
of what all the different divisors of 27000
would have to look like
so 27000 is the same thing as 27 times 1000
which is the same thing as
3 to the 3rd times 10 to the 3rd
and 10 is of course the same thing as 2 times 5
so this is the same thing as 2 times 5 to the third
or the same thing as 2^3 times 5^3
So 27000 is equal to 2^3 times 3^3 times 5^3.
So any divisor of 27000
is going to have to be made up of
the product of
up to three 2, up to three 3, and up to three 5.
So let's try and look at all the combinations
and think of a fast way of solving it.
Lets say that it has no 5's in the divisor.
So if it has no 5's, then it can have up to three 2's.
So if it has zero 2's
So I am going to take the powers of 2's
So lets say it has zero 2's
then I'll put a 1 here
if it has two 2's then it has to be divisible by 4
and if it has three 2's it is going to be divisible by 8
when I say three 2, I mean 2 x 2 x 2
Now let's do the same thing with 3's
Oh wait I forgot a power
If it had zero 2's
it means it is just divisible by 1.
for we're looking at the 2
If it has one 2, then it has to be divisible by just 2
If you have two 2's it is divisible by 4
and if you have three 2's
and what i mean by that is 2x2x2 it is divisible by 8.
Lets do the same thing with 3.
From the point of view of 3
if you have no 3
then that means at least you you're deivisable by 1.
if you have one 3, that means you're divisible by 3
Two 3's, or 3 times 3, means you are divisible by 9
if you have three 3's
that means you are divisible by 27.
So let's look at all the possible combinations
in this grid that I am going to generate right here
We assume that you are not divisible by 5
or you are only divisible by 5 to the zero power
So what are all the possible numbers here.
You have 1x1 = 1 ; 1x3 = 3 ; 1x9 = 9 ; 1x27 = 27
So these are all the numbers
that have up to three 3's in them
from 0 to three 3 in them
and they have no 2's in them
If you have another 2 in here
you essentially multiply all these numbers by 2.
you are going to multiply all these numbers by two.
Now before I do this
because I want to do this as fast as possible
I could figure out what these numbers are
I could multiply them
But instead lets just take the sum
let's just take the sum of this row
the first row we just did.
We have 1 + 3 + 9 + 27
3 + 27 = 30; 1 + 9 = 10,
so this is going to be 40.
Now whatever these numbers are
they are just going to be 2 times these numbers.
So the sum is going to be 80.
And the sum over here is going to be
2 times the previous row
because here we were multiplying by 2
here we are multiplying by 4
So it is going to be 160.
And over here we just multiply by 2 again.
It is going to be 320.
Or another way of thinking about it is
whatever the sum is here
it is going to be 8 times the sum of the first row
and I could, just so you know what I am doing
I could actually put numbers here.
This number will be 8, 24, 72 and whatever 8x27 is
Now what is that 160 + 56 = 216
But we don't want to do that
we just have to think about the sums.
If you think about all the divisors of 2700
that are not devisable by 5
so they're only divisible by 5 to the zero power
I guess you could say it
we have just now figured out their sum.
It is going to be the sum of all of these rows.
So if you take 40 + 80
you have 120 + 160 + 320 = 600
So this is the situation.
this is the sum of all of the combinations
of the 2's and the 3's
that don't have 5's in them.
Now if you took the same combination of 2's and 3's.
These added up to 600.
Let me write it over here.
So no 5's.
Now if you did the same exact thing we did here
but we just multiplied everything by 5.
so we then would be looking at the combinations
that have this many 2's and this many 3's and one 5
what would have this sum
we would just multiply it by 5.
So we multiply 600 by 5
You get 30 with two zeros
So this is one 5
in the prime factorisation of the divisors
One 5. Just like that.
Now if I want two 5 I can just multiply by 5 again.
So if I multiply by 5 again I get 15 000
This is two 5's
Another way of thinking about this
if I just multiply every term here by 25
which is essentially just 5 times 5
this sum is going to be 600 x 25 which is 15000
Now if I have three 5
then I can just multiply this by 5 again.
5 times 15 is 75, so I get 75000
So now I know all the sums.
If I had no 5 the sum of all the divisors is 600
If we have one 5, 3000, and so on and so forth.
So if I want the sum of everything
I just take the sum of these numbers.
Let me just scroll down a bit.
So I have zero, zero,
then in the hundreds place I only have a 6.
And them 3 + 5 + 5 is 13, is that right?
yep, thats 13. and then carry the one.
and then I have a 9.
So I have 93600
So the sum of all posible divisors of 27000 is 93600.
Hope you found that entertaining.