oxidation state-indicate the general distribution of electrons
another name for oxidation states is oxidation numbers and
of course,this concept is covered in general chemstry
a lot,I'm gonna start,I would the general chemistry way of assigning oxidation states,and then i'm gonna go into a more organic way of assigning oxidation states
and the way that's most useful when you are dealing with organic molecules,and the thing that a lot of people
mess about oxidation states,is that electronegti-
vity is involved ,so I'll show you some examples of that
other difinitions from general chemistry,the concept of oxidation
is an increase in the oxidation state of
an element,and the other definition that's covered
a lot in general chemistry is loss of electrons
is oxidation,so LEO is an acronym for that
another definition is reduction,which is a decrease
or reduction in the oxidation state of sth,and
GER stands for"gain of electrons" is reduction,so
LEO the Lion goes GER is one of those things that all general chemistry students
have heard before.Here we have,um,a reaction
where methane is being combusted,and the products
are CO2 and water.Let's assign oxidation states
using the general chemistry way,and we'll see what is oxidized
and what is reduced,and then we will use the organic way
to assign oxidation states using the concept of electronegativity
and dot structures.So,first we'll do it the way that you memorize
you have all these rules for assigning oxidation states
and one of those rules is hydrogen is usually
plus1,so go ahead and put a plus one oxidation state
here for hydrogen.I have four of them so I am gonna put a total of plus 4
down here.Another rule for assigning oxidation states is that
for a neutral molecule,they total has to add up to equal zero
so,this would be-4 over here on the carbon side
and I have only one carbon,so carbon's oxidation state is -4
I move over here to oxygen.I ignore the coefficient and
I'm only focused in the fact of this is O2 here,and one of your rules
for assigning oxidation states is for an element in its elemental state
it has an oxidation state of zero,so oxygen
has an oxidation state of zero which we just memorize.Move over here
now we have oxygen in a molecule with carbon
and in this case,oxygen is going to have an oxidation state
of -2.Again,just one of those rules that we memorize,so I have
two oxygens ,so I get a total of -4 over here,which must mean
that this carbon's oxidation state is +4
I go over here to water
I always start on the right here ,so once again oxygen is going to have
an oxidation state of -2,only have one of them
and so,again,I'm ignoring the coefficient,so my total has to be plus
2 over here,and this time I actually have 2hydrogens,so 2 hydrogens have to add
up to +2,so each hydrogen is+1 like that.Now when we take
a look at what happen to these elements,um.I look
at carbon,and I see that carbon went from an oxidation state of -4
to an oxidation state of +4,so obviously
that's an increase in the oxidation state of carbon
so we say that carbon was oxidized
what was reduced,well,reduction is a decrease or a reduction in the oxidation state
so all I have to do is look at my numbers and see which one went down
oxygen went from an oxidation state of zero to an
oxidation state of -2,so oxygen was reduced in this reaction
so that's the general chemistry way of doing it.Let's look at
the more organic way of doing it using dot structures and
electronegativity,so let's go ahead and draw some dot structures for these molecules
so we start off with methane over here,so methane has a
very simple dot structure and
let's go ahead and indicate the electrons in methane,so
we have each one of our bonds consist of two electrons like that
OK,so
let's think about which atom is more electronegative
so we have carbon vs hydrogen,and if you remember your trends for electro-
negativity,carbon is going to be more electronegative than hydrogen
so what we are going to do is treat this like its an ionic bond
even though its technically a covalent bond,so if this were an ionic
bond,carbon being much more electronegative is going to steal all those electrons
so let's draw another picture showing carbon stealing all those electrons,so now carbon
is going to have a total of eight electrons around it,because it is going to steal
all electrons in those bonds with hydrogen,and hydrogen is gonna sit all alone over here
with no electrons around,since it's not as electronegative as carbon,so if we were to
assign an oxidation state
to this carbon,the formula we would use is we would say
to figure out the oxidation state,we would say what is the number of valence electrons
that are normally,um,around
an atom,and from that number,we are going to subtract the number of
electrons around the atom
after we've accounted for
electronegativity after we thought about the electr-
onegativity of the atoms,so that would be our second picture down here
that would be the one with carbon with eight electrons around it.Well,carbon
normally has four valence electrons so we spend a lot of time talking
about that earlier,so carbon has 4 valence electrons
let's go ahead and write her oxidation state,so number of electrons minus
electrons around the atom,so carbon normally has 4,from that
number we're going to subtract the number of electrons around
the atom after we count for the electronegativity,well,that would be these 8 electrons
right here,so 4-8is going to give us an oxidation state
of -4 for carbon.What about for hydrogen,well,hydrogen normally has
1 valence electron around it,and how many electrons around each one
of our hydrogens here
0 of course,so 1-0,and this is going to be
+1,so we have an oxidation state of -4 for carbon and oxidation state of +1 for hydrogen