What I want to do in this video is think about
the two different ways of interpreting lowercase g
as we talked about before. Many textbooks would give you either 9.81 m/s^2
downward or towards the Earth's center
or sometimes give you a negative quantity that signifies the direction
essentially downward, -9.81 m/s^2
And probably the most typical way to interpret this value
as the acceleration due to gravity near Earth's surface
for an object in freefall--this is what we're gonna focus on in this video
For an object freefall
and the reason why I am stressing this last part
is because we know many objects that are near the surface of the Earth
that are not in freefall
For example, I'm near the surface of the Earth right now and I am not in freefall
What's happening to me right now is I'm sitting in the chair
And so this is my chair
and this is me
Let's say the chair is supporting all my weight
My legs are flying in the air
So this is me and so what's happening right now?
If I were in freefall, I would be accelerating towards the center of the Earth
at 9.81 m/s squared
But what's happening is is all the force due to gravity
is being completely offset by the normal force from the surface of the chair onto my pants
And so this is normal force. I'll make them both as vectors
So the net force in my situation is equal to zero, especially in this vertical direction
Because the net force is equal to zero
I am not accelerating towards the center of the Earth. I am not in freefall
And because this 9.81 m/s^2 still seems relevant to my situation
I'll talk about that in a second, but I'm not an object in freefall
Another way to interpret this
it's not as the acceleration due to gravity near Earth's surface
for an object in freefall. Although it is that
A maybe more general way to interpret this, is the Earth's gravitational field--
or it's really the average acceleration
because it actually changes slightly throughout the surface of the Earth
But another way to view this as the average gravitational field at Earth's surface
I'll talk about what a field means in the physics context in a second
Field. The average gravitational field at Earth's surface
This is a little bit more of a abstract thing. We'll talk about that in a second
But it does help us think about how g is related this scenario where I'm not an object in freefall
A field when you think of it in the physics context--
slightly more abstract a notion in the mathematics context
But in the physics context
a field is something that associates a quantity with every point in space
So this is just a quantity is with every point in space
And it can actually be a scalar quantity, in which case we call this a scalar field
There's just value
Or it could be a vector quantity with the magnitude and the direction
associated with every point in space
in which case we're dealing with a vector field
And the reason why this is called a field is because it's near Earth's surface
if you give me a mass--so for example, maybe my mass is in kilograms
If you're near Earth's surface, you give me a mass. Let's say that mass is 10 kg
You can use g to figure out the actual force on that--of gravity on that object
at that point in space
So for example, if this has a mass of 10 kg
This is the surface of the Earth
That's the center of the Earth
So it actually associates a vector quantity whose direction is towards the center of the Earth
and the magnitude of this vector quantity is going to be the mass times g
This already specified the direction. You can say 9.81 m/s^2 towards the center of the Earth
And so in the situation it would be 10 kg times 9.81 m/s^2
which is approximately 98.1 kg m / s^2
which is the unit of force, or 98.1 N
And this thing might not be in freefall. So this is why it becomes
why g is relevant even in a situation where the object isn't in freefall
g has given us the force per unit mass of gravity on an object near the surface of the Earth
So let me think about it. So this is the average gravitational field
What it's giving is force per mass
So if you give me a mass near Earth's surface, whether it's an object in freefall or not
you multiply that mass times g because it's giving you force per mass
And it would give you the force of gravity acting on that object
near the surface of the Earth whether or not it's in freefall
So I just want to make this little distinction
because although g tends to be referred to this way right over here
sometime you might encounter this and say, no no no no no
but g is relevant even when it's not in freefall
You obviously can't say that my acceleration when I'm sitting in my chair is 9.81 m/s^2
towards the center of the Earth. I'm not accelerating towards the center of the Earth
And so they'll say, no no no no. You can't just call this acceleration
It is the acceleration when an object is in freefall near the surface of the Earth
If you don't have air resistance, if the net force is the force of gravity
then this really would be the object's acceleration
But it becomes relevant--we know a lot of objects are not in freefall
And the object in freefall doesn't stay in freefall for long because it'll hit something
But we know that now g is actually relevant to all objects
It tells us the force per mass
It's tempting to call it always acceleration because of the units of an acceleration
But even when you talk about in terms of the gravitational field, it's still the same quantity
It still has the exact same unit, the same magnitude
and the same direction. It's just a different way of viewing it
Here acceleration for an object in freefall
Here, something to multiply by mass to figure out the force due to gravity