In the last several videos we learned how we can approximate an arbitrary function
but a function that is differentiable and twice and thrice differentiable and all off the rest
how we can approximate a function around x is equal to zero using a polynomial. If we have a zeroth degree poynomial
which is a constant, you can approximate it with a horizontal line that just goes through that point. Not a great approximation.
If you have a first degree polynomial, you can at least get the slope right at that point.
If you get to a second degree polynomial, you get something that hugs the function a little longer
If you go a third degree polynomial, something that hugs the function even a little bit longer than that
But all of that was focused on approximating the function around x = 0
and that is why we call it the McCloran series or the Taylor series at x is equal to zero
What I want to do now is expand it a little bit -- generalize it a little bit and focus on the Taylor
expansion at x equals anything
So let's say we want to approximate this functiono
when x--this is our x-axis-- is equal to c
So we could do it the exact same thing.
We could say "Look out first approximation at c should be equal to a function. Whatever the function
equals at c