What I have attempted to draw here is
a unit circle
and the fact I'm calling it a
"unit circle" means it has a radius of one
so this length here from the center, and I've centered it at the origin,
this length, from the center to any point on the circle is of length one.
so what would this co-ordinate be right over there? Right where it intersects along the x axis?
well X would be one, Y would be zero (1,0)
what would this co-ordinate be up here?
well we've gone one above the origin, but we haven't moved to the left or the right...
so our X value is zero, our Y value is one.
what about back here?
well here our X value is negative-one, we've moved one to the left
and we haven't moved up or down so our Y value is zero
and what about down here?
well, we've gone one unit down (one below the origin)
but we haven't moved in the X direction... so our X is zero, and our Y is negative-one.
now with that out of the way, I'm going to draw an angle...
and the way I'm going to draws this angle- I'm going to define a convention for positive angles.
I'm going to say a positive angle, well the initial side of the angle, we're always going to draw along the positive X axis.
so this is the... you can kind of view it as the starting side of the angle (the initial side of an angle)
and then to draw a positive angle the terminal side we going to move in a counter-clockwise direction
so a positive angle- means we're going counter clockwise
...counter clockwise...
this is just the convention I'm going to use, and it's also the convention that is typically used,
and so you can imagine that a negative would move in a clockwise
...clockwise... direction.
so let me draw a positive angle
a positive angle might look, something like this. (this is the initial side)
and then from that I go in a counter-clockwise direction until I measure out the angle...
and this is the terminal side.
so this is a positive angele- "theta"
and what I want to do is think about this point of intersection,
between the terminal side of this angle and my unit circle.
and let's just say it has the co-ordinates (a,b)
the X value (where it intersects) is "a", the Y value (where it intersects) is "b"
and I'm also, the whole point of what I'm doing here is,
I want to see how this unit circle might be able to help us extend our traditional definitions of trig-functions
and so what I want to do is... I want to make this "theta" part of a "right-triangle" (right-angled triangle)
so to make it part of a "right-triangle" let me draw up an altitude...
right over here, and let me make it clear that-
this is a 90 degree agle
so this "theta" is part of this right triangle
so! let's see what we can figure out about the sides of this "right-triangle"
so the first question I have to ask you is-
What is the length of the hypotenuse? (of this "right-triangle" that I have just constructed)
well this hypotenuse is just a radius of a unit circle!
the unit circle has a radius of one
so the the hypotenuse has length one!
now what is the length of this blue side right over here?
this blue side which you could view as the opposite side to the angle...
well this height is the exact same thing as the Y co-ordinate of this point of intersection.
so this height right over here is going to be equal to "b"
(the Y co-ordinate over here is "b"; this height is equal to "b")
now, exact same logic: what is the length of this base going to be?
the base just of the "right-triangle"?
well this is going to be the X co-ordinate of this point of intersection
and if you were to drop this down... this is the point: X equals "a"
or this whole length between the origin and that, is of length "a".
now that we have set that up-
What is the co-sine of my angle going to be? (in terms of a's and b's and any other number that might show up)
well to think about that we just need our "SOH CAH TOA" definition
that's the only one we have now (we're actually in the process of extending it)
..."SOH CAH TOA" definition of trig-functions...
and the "CAH" part is what helps us with co-sine; it tells us...
that the co-sine of an angle is equal to the length of the adjacent side, over the hypotenuse
so what's this going to be?
the length of the adjacent side, for this angle... the adjacent side has length "a"
so it's going to be equal to "a", over...
what's the length of the hypotenuse?
well that's just one...
so the co-sine of "theta" is just equal to "a"
...let me write this down again...
so the co-sine of "theta"... is just equal to "a"...
it's equal to the X co-ordinate of where the terminal side of this angel intersected the unit circle.
now let's think about the sine of "theta"!
... and I'm going to do it in (let me see)... I'll do it in orange!
so what's the sine of "theta" going to be?
well, we just have to look at the "SOH" part of our "SOH CAH TOA" definition
it tells us that sine is: opposite, over hypotenuse.
well the opposite side here has length "b", and the hypotenuse has length one...
so our sine of "theta" is equal to "b"
so an interesting thing! This point where our terminal side of our angle intersected the unit circle at point (a,b)
we can also view this, as...
"a" is the same thing as co-sine of "theta"
and "b" is the same thing as sine of "theta"
well that's interesting, we just used our "SOH CAH TOA" definition.
now, can we in some way use this to extend "SOH CAH TOA" ?
because "SOH CAH TOA" has a problem...
it works out fine if our angle is greater than zero degree's (if we're dealing with degrees)
and if it's less than 90 degrees we can always make it part of a "right-triangle"
but "SOH CAH TOA" starts to break down as our angle is either zero, or even becomes negative
or as our angle is 90 degrees or more.
you can't have a "right-triangle" with two 90 degree angles in it!
it starts to break down... let me just make this clear...
so sure! this is a "right-triangle", so the angle is pretty large-
I can make the angle even larger and still have a "right-triangle"
or even larger- but I can never quite get to 90 degrees!
at 90 degrees it's not clear that I have a "right-triangle" anymore, it all seems to break down...
and especially the case- what happens when I go beyond 90 degrees...
so let's see if we can use what we said up here,
let's set up a new definition of our trig-functions,
which is really an extension of "SOH CAH TOA" and is consistant with "SOH CAH TOA"
instead of defining co-sine as "oh if I have a right-triangle, which is the adjacent over the hypotenuse"
and saying "sine is the opposite over the hypotenuse, tangent is the opposite over the adjacent"
why don't I just say: for any angle, I can draw it in the unit circle using this convention I've just set up.
and say that: the co-sine of our angle is equal to the X co-ordinate where we intersect.
or where the terminal side of our angle intersects the unit-circle.
I'll write... Where the terminal side of the angle intersects the unit-circle...
and why don't we define sine of "theta" to be equal to the Y co-ordinate
where the terminal side intersects the unit circle.
so essentially for any angle- this point is going to define co-sine of theta and sine of theta
and so what would be a reasonable definition for tangent of theta?
well, tangent of theta (even with SOH CAH TOA) could be defined as "sine of theta, over co-sine of theta"
which in this case is just going to be the Y co-ordinate, where we intersect the unit circle, over the X co-ordinate.
in the next few video's I'll show some examples where we use the unit circle definition to start evaluating some trig-ratios...