In which quadrant is the point -7, 7 located?
So let's just review what a quadrant is
A quadrant is each of the four sections of the coordinate plane.
and when we talk about the sections we're talking about the sections
as divided by the coordinate axis.
So this right here is the x-axis, and this up down axis is the y-axis,
and you can see it divides the coordinate plane into four sections.
We call each of these sections quadrants
This one over here where both the x values and y values are positive
we call the first quadrant, and we use the roman numeral 1.
Then if we move counterclockwise around the coordinate plane
This quadrant, where the x values are negative and the y values are positive
we call the second quadrant.
We call this the second quadrant.
Then we go down here, where both the x values are negative and the y values are negative,
we call this the third quadrant.
Once again using roman numerals.
Then finally the quadrant where the x values are positive but the y values are
negative, we call this the fourth quadrant.
So let's see which quadrant the point -7, 7 is located.
So there's two ways to think about it, you could just say look: We have a negative
x value, our x value is negative, so we're gonna move to the left, we're gonna be on this side.
We're going to be on this of the coordinate plane.
So just by the fact that the x value is negative, we're gonna be in either
the second or the third quadrant.
Now we know that the y value is positive, we know that the y value is positive.
So if the x value is negative, and the y value is positive, we're gonna land
some place right overe here in the second quadrant.
The other way to think about it is that you can literally just plot this point
and see that it falls in the second quadrant, so let's do that.
If x is negative 7, so it's negative 1. Negative 2. Negative 3. Negative 4,
Negative 5. Negative 6. Negative 7.
Did I do that right?
One. Two. Three. Four. Five. Six. Seven.
So x is negative 7, and then we have to go up 7, because y is positive 7.
So one. Two. Three. Four. Five. Six. Seven.
So the point -7, 7 is right over here.
Clearly lies in the second quadrant.