Lets think a little bit about how margin works for futures contract.
So lets say that the terms of the contract are a 1,000 pounds of apples for delivery on November 15th.
And we're assuming that this is some date in the future.
And right now on the futures exchange the market delivery price,
so the price in which the apples will change hand in the future is 200 dollars.
And I've written here what the exchange specifies for the initial and maintenance margin
and we'll talk about that more in a second
but this essencially means that both the buyer and the seller for, the initial margin,
have to put up 20 dollars, sometimes it will be specified as an absolute dollar amount, like
I've just done, sometimes it might just be a percentage of the actual
delivery price. So they both have to put up $20, and this guy has agreed to buy a thousand pounds of apples
from this guy on
november 15th for 200 dollars.
So its essencially 20 cents a pound.
Now lets say that a day goes by and the next day - these guys have this contract - this price right here
is fixed in their minds.
But lets say the next day the same contract between 2 other parties, between
2 other parties, the same contract, trades with the delivery price of
$190. Now all of a sudden this
guy over here feels silly! He's like: "man im agreeing to buy something for $200 dollars in the future,
which some other dude, all of a sudden, has agreen to buy for $190 dollars".
This guy over here feels really smart, he agreed
to sell something for $200 the day before, and now people are selling it
for a $190, so hes kind of $10 better than the people
participating in the futures market today.
The way mark to market works with futures contracts
is that the exchange says "well, you know what? I'm afraid that this guy,
if things keep moving against him, he's not even going to want
to put up the money to buy at $200 dollars
if he can buy at the market for $190 dollars
or something lower, so I'm going to reset their futures contract
to a delivery price of $190".
But, to make things fair, this guy is gonna be $10 in the hole.
He's getting a $10 deal, if I take the delivery price from $200 to $190 dollars
I need to take $10 from this guy, because he's getting a $10 dollars better deal.
So from his margin account I take it from 20 dollars to $10 dollars
and then I place the $10 in this guy's margin account.
If he's going to get a $10 less of a good price on the delivery date
then let me give him the $10 dollars right now, so his margin account will go
to $30 dollars, now if this number was
$18, $17, $16 or $15
this guy wouldn't have to do anything.
But right here he has triggered his maintenance
margin, and actually, he's right at our maintenance margin.
So lets say that he goes, that the next
day this happens a little bit more, he goes down to
$185 and we have to do the process again:
This guy losses $5, he goes down to $5.
This guy will be given $5,
so he goes to $35 dollars
in order for him to essentially reset the futures price, he's been given another $5.
Now this guy has only $5 in his margin account
and the maintenance margin is $10,
so it triggers a margin call, and this guy is got to
find some place to put another $15 dollars in his margin call.
Every time you get below the maintenance margin, it triggers
a margin call and you have to refill your margin account to the initial margin. So he has to add
$15
so he gets back to $20.