Over many videos now, we've been talking about
how every interstellar object is moving away from Earth.
We've also been talking about how the further something is
away from Earth, the faster it's moving.
What I want to do in this video
is to put a few numbers behind it,
or even better conceptualize what we've been talking about.
So, one way to think about it
is that, if at an early stage in the Universe,
I were to pick some points,
so that's one point,
another point, another point
another point,
let me just pick 9 points so that I have a proper grid.
So this is an early stage in the Universe
if we fast-forward a few billion years,
and I'm clearly not drawing it to scale.
All of these points
have all moved away from each other.
So this point is over here,
and actually let me draw another row,
actually another column,
just to make it clear.
So if you fast-forward a few billion years
the Universe has expanded,
and so everything has moved away from everything
and let me color code a little bit,
let me make this point magenta.
So this point, the magenta point is now here.
This green point
has now moved away from the magenta point.
And now this blue point
has now moved away from the magenta point
in that direction,
and we can keep going,
this yellow point is maybe
over here now.
I think you get the general idea.
And I'll just draw the other yellow points,
so they've all moved away from each other.
So there's no center here
everything is just expanding away
from things next to it.
And what you can see here,
is not only did this thing expand away from this,
but this thing expanded away from this
even further,
because it had this expansion plus this expansion.
Or another way to think about it is
the velocity with which,
the apparent velocity with which something is expanding
is going to proportional to how far it is.
Because every point in between is also expanding away.
And just to review a little bit of the visualiztion of this,
one way to think of this, if you think of the Universe
as an infinite flat sheet.
You could imagine that we are just taking a sheet of
I don't know
some type of sheet of stretchy material and just stretching it out
we're just stretching it out,
that's if we kind of imagine a more infinite Universe,
that just goes off in every direction.
We're just stretching that infinite sheet out,
so it has no boundaries, but we're still stretching it out.
Another way to visualize it, and this is what we did earlier on,
is you could imagine that this --, that the Universe is the
three-dimensional surface of a four-dimensional sphere,
or the three-dimensional surface of a hyper-sphere.
Sort of an early stage in the Universe,
the sphere looked like this, and these points here
the magenta point is right over here
the green point is right over there,
then we had the blue point up here,
and then let me just draw the rest of the yellow points.
And the yellow points are here, they're all on the surface of this sphere.
They're all on the surface of the sphere.
Obviously, I'm only dealing with two-dimensions right now,
and it's nearly impossible, or maybe impossible to imagine
a three-dimensional surface of a four-dimensional sphere,
but then the analogy holds.
If is the surface of a balloon, or the surface of a bubble,
if the bubble were to expand,
so if the bubble were to expand over a few billion years,
and once again - not drawn to scale.
So now we have a bigger bubble here
This part of the surface is all going to expand,
so once again, you have your magenta
you have your blue dot,
you have your green dot,
and then let me just draw the rest in yellow.
So they will have all expanded away from each other on the surface of this sphere.
Just to make it clear that this is a sphere, let me draw some contour lines.
So this is a contour line,
just to make it clear that we are on the surface,
we are on the surface of an actual sphere.
Now with that out of the way, let's think about
how fast or what is the apparent velocity with which things are moving away.
remember, we're going to say not only how far things are moving away,
but we're going to say, how far they are moving away from, if the observer is us
depending on how far they already are
we're going to do, we could say, let me write this down
all objects
all objects moving away from each other
and the velocity and the apparent velocity
apparent relative velocity
relative velocity
is proprotional to distance
proportional to distance
And what I've written down, this is why I wrote it down
this is a rephrasing of essentially Hobble's law.
Hubble's law
And he came up with this by just observing, that when he looks especially the further
out he looks, the more red shifted objects are and not only,
they were moving faster and faster away from earth, but they seem
to be moving faster and faster away from each other.
So this is just a restating the Hubble's law or another way to say it is
from anypoint, let say from the Earth,
the velocity something appears to be moving is going to be
some constant times the distance
times the distance it is away from the observer.
In this case we're the observer. And we put this little zero,
so this is H here is called Hubble's constant.
Hubbles's constant.
And it's a very non-constant constant, this constant will change depending on
where we are of the evolution of the Universe.
So we put this little zero here, this little sub-zero,
right over here to show, this is Hubble's constant right now.
And when we talk about distance, we talk about proper distance
right now. Propper distance
now. And this has to be very important, because that proper distance
is contantly changing as the Universe expands.
The now will actually change slightly from the beginning of this video to the end of this video.
But we can roughly say in kind of our current
period of time. And when we say proper distance, we're talking about
if you actually had rulers and you would just lay them down instantaniously.
Obviously, we can't do something like that, but we can imagine
doing something like that, so that's what we're talking about.
Just to give a sense of how fast thing are acually moving apart.
The current Hubble's constant
is, let me accualy write it where someplace i have more space,
the current Hubble's constant is 70.6 +/-
3.1, so we have observed
some varriation here, there is I guess some error to
our actual measurement, kilometers
per second per megaparsec.
And remember parsec is roughly 3.2
3.2 to 3.3 light years
so another way to thing about it is, if this is
where we are in the Universe right now and if this is
and if this object right over here, if this distance right over here,
is one megaparsec, so one
million parsens or 3.2
million light years from Earth.
So this is roughly, so just so we have a sense, this is 3.2
6 roughly, 3.26 million
light years from Earth, than this object will
appear to be moving away, althought it's not moving in space, just the space
that it is in is stratching in such a way, that it looks to be moving
at 70, it looks like it's moving
70, based on it's redshift, 70.6
kilometers per second away from us
So this is huuuge velocity, 70.6
kilometers per second, per second! So this is
a pretty fast velocity
But we have to remember, this is over one megaparsec
the Andromeda galaxy is not even a megaparsec
away, it's about 2.5 million light years, it's about
0.7 or 0.8 of a megaparsec. So if you look
at the points in space little bit further, than the Andromeda galaxy,
it will look to be right now receiving 70.6
kilometers per hour
If you would look at something, that is almost 7 light years away,
2 megaparsecs away, so if you look at
this object over here,
how fast would that be receding
It's two megaparsecs away, so it's gonna be twice
this. You just gonna multiply it's distance two megaparsecs times
this, the megaparsecs cancels out, so 70.6
times 2 is, so it's going to be moving
or it's going to look to be moving, it's not mooving in space, remember,
the space is stratching. It's velocity, it's apparent velocity
will be 70.6. times 2, so that's 141.2
141.2 kilometers per second
And this is, one question, how did Hubble know
You know, it's easy to observe the red shift of objects moving away from us,
but did he know, that they are moving away from each other?
Look at the red shift of this object, wow that's moving away moving away at 70.6
kilometers per second and than you'd look at the red shift of this and say: wow,
that's moving away from us at 141.2 kilometers per second
then you also know, that these two objects
are moving away from each other at 70.6
kilometers per second
and we can keep doing this over different distances. But hopefully this gives you a little bit more
a little big bigger sense of thing. And just remember, even thought I said this is
a huge distance, a mega parsec, further than it is to
the Andromeda galaxy. The Andromeda galaxy is the nearest large galaxy
to us, there are some smaller galaxies to us , that are kind of satelites
galaxies around the Milky way, but the Andromeda is the largest galaxz
nearest large galaxy to us, but we also know
that, we are talking about hundreds of billions of galaxies in
just the observable universe
So very quickly as you go near the edge of the observable universe
these velocities
aparent distance start to become
prety significant.