Let's say that I have a huge frozen over lake, or maybe it is a big pond.
So I have a huge surface of ice over here.
This is my best attempt at drawing a flat surface of ice.
And I am going to put two blocks of ice here.
So I'm going to put one block of ice just like this,
one block of ice right over here
and then I'm going to put another block of ice right here.
And these blocks of ice are identical.
They are both 5 kilograms. Let me write this down
or both of their masses, I should say, are are 5 kilograms.
And the only difference between the two
is that relative to the pond
this one is stationary, and this one is moving with a constant velocity.
A constant velocity in the rightwards direction.
And lets say that its constant velocity is at 5 meters per second.
And the whole reason that I made blocks of ice on top of ice,
is because we are going to assume, at least for the sake of this video,
that friction is negligible.
Now what does Newtons first law of motion tell us
about something that is either not in motion,
or you can view this as having a constant velocity of zero,
or something that has a constant velocity.
Well, Newton's first law says,
they are going to either keep their constant velocity or stay stationary,
which
is a constant velocity of zero
unless there is some unbalance,
unless there is some net force acting on an object.
So lets just think about it here.
In either of these situations there must not be any unbalanced force acting on them
or there must not be any net force.
But think about it, if we are assuming that these things are on earth,
there is a net force acting on both of them.
Both of them are on the surface of the Earth,
and they both have mass. So there will be the force of gravity acting down on them
There is going to be the downward force of gravity on both of these blocks of ice.
And that downward force of gravity is going to be equal to
the gravitational field near the surface of the Earth
Times, which is a vector, times the mass of the object. So time 5 kilograms.
This right over here is 9.8 meters per second squared
So you multiply that times 5, you get 49 kilogram meters per second squared
which is the same thing as 49 Newtons.
So this is a little bit of a conundrum here!
Newton's first law says,
an object at rest will stay at rest, or an object in motion will stay in motion,
unless there is some unbalanced or net force
but based on what we have drawn right here, it looks like there is some sort of net force.
It looks like I have 49 Newtons of force pulling this thing downwards,
but you say, "No no Sal, obviously this thing won't start accelerating downwards
because there is ice here. It is resting on a big pool of frozen water."
So my answer to you is, well,
if that's your answer, then what is the resulting force that cancels out with gravity
to keep these blocks of ice from plummeting down to the core of the Earth?
From essentially free falling or accelerating down to the center of the Earth?
And you say, "Well, I guess these things would be falling if not for the ice,
the ice must be providing the counter acting force."
And you are absolutely correct.
The ice is providing the counter acting force in the opposite direction.
So the exact magnitude of force, and it is in the opposite direction.
And so if the force of gravity on each of these blocks are 49 Newtons downward,
it is completely netted off by the force of the ice on the block upwards,
and that will be a force of 49 Newtons upwards, in either case.
And now hopefully it make sense that Newtons first law still holds.
We have no net force on this in the vertical direction.
Actually, no net force on this in either direction.
That is why they have a constant velocity.
This guy has a zero velocity in the horizontal direction,
this guy has a contant velocity in the horizontal direction.
and neither of them are accelerating in the vertical direction,
because you have force of ice on the block.
the ice supporting the block, that is completely contracting gravity.
And this force, in this example is called the normal force.
It is 49 Newtons upwards.
This right here is the normal force
and we will talk more about normal force in future videos
the normal force is the force when anything is resting on any surface, that is perpendicular to the surface.
and it will start to matter a lot when we start talking about friction.
We will see in future videos that when you have something on an incline,
lets say I have a block on an incline like this.
The normal force from the wedge on this block is going to be perpendicular to the surface.
And if you really think about what is happening here it is fundamentally in electromagnetic force
because if you really zoom in on the molecules of the ice, or even better, the atoms of the ice.
What is keeping this top block of ice from falling down,
is that in order for it to go through, it's molecule would have to compress against
or get closer to the water molecules or individual atoms in this ice down here.
And the atoms, let me draw it on an atomic level right here.
Let me draw one of this guys molecules
So you have an oxygen with two hydrogens,
and it forms this big lattice structure. And we can talk more of that in the chemistry play list
and lets talk about one of this ice's molecules
So maybe it looks something like this and it has it's two hydrogens
and so what is keeping these two guys from getting compressed,
what is keeping this block of ice from going down further
is the repulsion between the electrons in this molecule and the electrons in that molecule.
So on a macro level, we view this as kind of a contact force
but on a microscopic level or an atomic level, it is really just electromagnetic repulsion at work.