We're asked to graph the function f(x)=5x-4
and we'll do it by really just sampling some points from the domain
and seeing what value our function takes
and then we'll just graph those points
and then we'll just connect the dots and see what forms,
and there's other ways to do this
but this is kind of the most simple, or the most basic way.
So if you look at this function over here,
it's actually defined for any real number that you stick there for x
so, when we talk about sampling the domain,
we can actually pick any real number for x
I'm actually going to pick real numbers that are fairly small in magnitude
so that they're easy to graph,
so you don't have to plot, you know, 8 billion on a number line over here.
So let's draw ourselves some simple graph paper,
let's call that the x-axis
let's call that the y-axis
or actually I should call it the y=f(x)
so whatever my x is, I input it into this function definition,
it'll tell me what the function value is there, it'll tell me f(x),
and we're going to say that y is equal to that.
Let's draw a little table here to try out some values.
So, let's say that this is x values and this is f(x)
and I can even say that these are my y values which are going to be equal to f(x).
So let's start with, I'm going to try,
-2, -1, 0, 1, and 2.
So let's try -2 first.
If x is equal to -2, what is f(x)?
Well f(x) is going to 5 times -2 minus 4,
so it's 5 times -2 minus 4
which is equal to -10 minus 4, which is -14
So let me plot that over here,
I'm going to have a slightly more scrunched up scale
on the y-axis, and actually, let me give myself some space
so I can go further down
let me clear this, give myself a little bit of space
'cause I'm feeling I'll be using a lot of
negative values since I just got all the way down to -14
so let me go further down here and then let me mark off some increments over here.
So let's say that this is -5,
this is -10,
and this is -15,
and then this would be +5,
and this would be +10.
So, when x is -2,
f(x) is equal to -14
which is right about there, so that is -14
so that right over there is the point (-2, -14)
which we got right from that
Now let's try another point. Let's try -1.
When x is -1, f(x) is
5 times -1 minus 4
5 times -1 is -5,
minus 4 is -9.
So when x is -1,
f(x) is -9.
So -9 is right about here.
So this is -9, so this is the point (-1, -9).
That is on the graph of f(x).
And now let's try zero. When x is 0, f(x) is going to be
5 times 0 minus 4
Well that's just 0 minus 4 which is equal to -4,
So when x is 0, f(x) is equal to -4.
That's -4 right over there
and actually, our point is going to be sitting right over there, that is 0, -4,
we're to the left of the point.
Let's keep going! Let's see what happens when x is equal to 1.
When x is equal to 1, f(x) is equal to 5 times 1 minus 4.
5 times 1 is 5, minus 4 is equal to 1.
So we get to the point (1,1), which is right about there
so this is point (1,1).
and then let's just try one more. Let's see what happens when x is equal to 2.
Then f(x) is 5 times 2 minus 4,
which is 10 minus 4, which is equal to 6.
So, we have when x is equal to 2, f(x) is equal to 6.
So that's right about there.
That's 6 right there, so this is the point (2, 6).
So once again, these are just sample points from the domain,
this isn't the entire domain, but it gives us enough points
to see the general structure of the graph.
If we connect the dots, we see a line forming.
If we connect the dots, it looks something like this,
and my shaky hand makes it look a little bit curvy, but
it should be an absolute straight line.
If I had this on really good graph paper,
and if I had a ruler, you'd see that this is a straight line
and it would keep going on and on and on
And I want to make it clear that we just sampled points from the domain,
but we can take any point
in the domain, which we already said
is all real numbers,
so if we took right over here,
we said 1.5,
you could see,
and if you graph 1.5,
f(1.5) should sit
on that line right over there.
If you graph f(-.5),
so this is -.5,
if you graphed f(-.5),
it should sit on the line right over there.
But we're done!
We have graphed the function
f(x)=5x-4.