Welcome back. We're on problem number six, on page 670.
If the average of 6, 6, 12,16,
and x-- the average is equal to x, what is the value of x?
So if I were to average all these numbers, I get x.
How do I average? I add them up, I add up the numbers,
and I divide by the number of numbers there are.
So there's 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 numbers, so I divide by that.
And they're saying that this average is going to equal x.
So let's multiply both sides by 5.
And I get 6 plus 6 plus 12 plus 16 plus x is equal to 20
my brain is malfunctioning,the average is equal to x, right?
So I have to multiply both sides by 5.
So I multiply both sides by 5, I get 5x. Right?
This is the average, and they say the average is equal to x.
Multiply both sides by 5, you get rid of the 5 in the
denominator here, you get 5x on the right-hand side.
And what's the sum?
6 plus 6 is 12, 12 plus 12 is 24, 24 plus 16 is 40.
So we get 40 plus x is equal to 5x.
Subtract x from both sides,40 is equal to 4x.
Divide both sides by 4, you get x is equal to 10.
And that is choice D. Next problem. Let me draw this triangle.
Let me try my best to draw the triangle.
Looks something like that.
And then there's an altitude right here,
just drop straight down.
And then they tell us that this is a 90-- or do they tell us?
My cousin who used my book drew over it, so I'm not sure.
But I'm pretty sure they tell us that
this is a 90 degree angle.
For the figure above, what is the value of z?
So they say this is z, this is y, this is 2y,
and this is 40 degrees. So what is z?
So we know this is a 90 degree angle, and we know that z plus
y plus 90 is equal to 180.
So if we know what y is,we could figure out z.
And how can we figure out y? Well we know that 2y
if we look at this right-hand triangle
we know that 2y plus 40 plus 90 is equal to 180. Right?
So 2y plus 130 is equal to 180. 2y is equal to 50 degrees.
y is equal to 25 degrees. So this is 25 degrees.
I really wish I could read this problem, I'm pretty sure
they drew in a little perpendicular but anyway,
we might have been able to address it even if they didn't.
But if y is 25, then we know that z plus 25 plus 90 is
equal to 180. z plus 115 is equal to 180.
z is equal to-- subtract 115 from both sides,
what's 80 minus 15? 65. The choice is C.
Next problem, problem number eight.
A computer program randomly selects a positive 2 digit integer
If the integer selected is odd, twice that integer is printed
So odd, it prints 2 times integer.
If the integer is even, the integer itself is printed.
So if it's even, it just prints the integer.
So if it's an odd and you multiply it by 2,
it's actually going to print an even integer no matter what.
If the integer printed is 26,
which of the following could have been the integer selected?
So all we see is 26. We just see 26.
So 26 could've been generated one of two ways.
It could have been generated by an even number that was
just kept the same.
Well, if it was an even number that was kept the same and
you got 26, then we know that the number is 26.
The number that generated was 26.
The other possibility is it could've been an odd number
that was doubled, right?
If it was an odd number that was doubled,
that means 2 times the odd number is equal to 26.
So that means that the number would have to be 13, right?
13 times odd-- sorry-- 2 times odd-- these are the two
situations-- 2 times odd is going to be equal to 26,
in which case odd is equal to 13.
Or 1 times even is going to be equal to 26,
it which case even equals 26.
So the number generated could've been 26
or it could have been 13.
And those are choices 1 and 2, and that's C.
Next problem, problem number nine.
They give you choice 52 in that last problem just to
confuse you, to actually end up doubling the 26,
but we know that the odd number was doubled to get 26,
so the number generated would have been 13.
Problem number nine.
How many seconds are there in m minutes and s seconds?
Well, how many seconds are there per minute?
Let's write this expression as m minutes plus s seconds,
right? Well, what does m equal in terms of seconds?
Or how many seconds are there per minute?
Well, we know that there are 60 seconds per m, right?
Or we could say that 60 seconds is equal to 1m, right?
So if there's 60 seconds in 1m,how many-- actually,
I'm confusing the issue, let me write it this way.
m minutes, right? There's m minutes.
How many seconds are there per minute?
Let me start over,because I think I confused you a little bit
So I'm going to write--actually, let me write it
without m and s, that's what confusing me as well.
Let's say I have x minutes plus y seconds,
and I want to convert it all into seconds.
Well, we know that there are 60 seconds per minute, right?
So if we want to convert a minute to seconds, we write
x minutes times 60 seconds per minute plus y seconds.
And so the minutes will cancel out, and so you're left with
60 times x-- and this is something that you'll learn in
physics class, that you can treat units just like you
would treat variables, and they'll cancel out similarly.
So you'd get 60x-- right, the minutes have canceled out--
let me switch colors--you'll get 60 times x seconds,
plus y seconds.
So your total number of seconds is 60x plus y.
And in the problem though, in minutes they didn't say x,
they said m, so x is m, and then y is s.
So 60m plus s, so that's choice A.
And this might have been a little confusing, let me do it
a simpler way, or maybe a more intuitive way for you.
There's m minutes, how many seconds are in m minutes?
Think about it. If there is
if I'm talking about 2 minutes,there's 60 seconds per minute,
so if I said 2 minutes, I would multiply 2 times 60,
and I would get to 120 seconds. If it was 5 minutes,
I would multiply 5 times 60, and get to 300 seconds.
So if I have m minutes,
I'll multiply 60 times m to get 60m seconds.
And of course, they said m minutes plus s seconds.
So now I have 60m seconds,plus these s seconds.
So my total number of seconds is 60m plus s.
This is a more intuitive way, maybe.
You should always try out numbers,
and hopefully it'll make a little bit more sense.
The way I did it previously is how you would do it in physics
class, where you would actually cancel out the units
and make sure you're doing it the right way.
See you in the next video.