What we're now going to think about is
finding the differences between sets.
The first way that we will denote this is we'll start with set A
I've already defined set A here
and in both cases I have defined the sets with numbers.
Instead of having numbers as being the objects in the sets I could have had farm animals or famous presidents
but numbers will hopefully keep things fairly simple
so I'm going to start with set A
and from set A I'm going to subtract set B.
This is one way of thinking about the
difference between set A and set B.
When I've written it this way, this essentially says,
"Give me the set of all of the objects that are in A with the things that are in B taken out of that set."
So let's think about what that means.
So what's in set A with the things that are in B taken out?
That means, let's take set A and take out the 17, 19, and 6
so we're going to be left with the 5, 3,
we're not going to have the 17 because we subtracted out set B, so take out anything that is in set B.
You get the 5, 3, 12 (12 is not in set B so we can keep that in there)
and then the 19 is in set B so we're going to take out the 19 as well.
So this right over here, you could view it as set B subtracted from set A.
One way of thinking about it, as we just said
these are all of the elements that
are in set A that are not in set B.
Another way you could think about it is
these are all of the elements that are
not in set B but also in set A.
Let me make this clear.
You could view this as B subtracted from A
or you could view this as the
"relative complement of set B in A".
We're going to talk a lot more
about complements in the future
but the complement is the things that are not in B.
This is saying, "What are all of the things
not in B but are in A?"
If you said all of the things that aren't in B
then you're thinking about all of the numbers in the whole universe that aren't 17, 19, or 6
and actually you can even think broader, not even just thinking about numbers.
The colour orange is not in set B so that would
be in the absolute complement of B.
I don't see a zebra here in set B
so that would be its complement.
But we're saying, what are all of the things
that are not in B but are in A?
That would be the numbers 5, 3, and 12.
When we visualize this as B subtracted
from A you might be saying
"I can imagine you took the 17 and 19 out, but what about taking the 6 out? Shouldn't you have taken the six out?"
In traditional subtraction maybe we might have ended up with a negative number or something.
When you subtract a set, if the set you're subtracting from does not have that element
then taking that element out of it doesn't change it.
If I start with set A and take all the 6's out of set A, it doesn't change it since there was no 6 to begin with.
I can take all the zebras out of set A - it will not change it.
Another way to denote the relative complement of set B in A
or B subtracted from A
is the notation I'm about to write.
We could have written it this way:
A, and this little figure right here that
looks eerily like a division sign
but this also means "the difference between set A and B".
When we write it this way, we're talking about all of the things in set A that are not in set B
or the things in set B taken out of set A
or the relative complement of B in A.
Let's think about things the other way around.
What would B slash A, or B minus A be?
We could also write it as B - A.
What would this be equal to?
We could view this as all of the things in B with
all of the things in A taken out of it
or the complement of A that happens to be in B.
Let's think of it as the set B with all
the things in A taken out of it.
If we start with set B, we have a 17.
But a 17 is in set A, so we have to take the 17 out.
Then we have a 19, but there's a 19 in set A
so we have to take the 19 out.
Then we have a 6 but we don't have to take
a 6 out of B because a 6 is not in set A
so we're left with just the 6.
So this would the set with the single element in it, set 6.
Let me ask another question.
What would the relative complement of A in A be?
This is the same thing as A minus A
and this is literally saying
let's take set A and take all of the things in set A out of it.
I start with a 5 but there's a 5 in set A so I take the 5 out.
There's a 3 but there's a 3 in set A
so I have to take the 3 out.
I'm going to take all of these things out, so I'm
just going to be left with the empty set.
The empty set, often called the null set.
Sometimes the notation for that will look like this.
The null set, the empty set.
There's a set that has absolutely no objects in it.