We are in a Louvre and we are looking at painting by one of the David followers one of his students.
An artists whos name is quite long but is usually just shortened to Giordet
And the title of the paiting is "Sleep of Endymion" .
So this is an ancient myth and it speaks of a sheepard who was an ideal beauty.
And he got into an disagreement with godness Juno
Who as punishment put him into the 30 years long sleep.
But rather kindly and to futher the story I guess doesn't have him age.
So he mantains his ideal beauty durning this 30 years sleep.
And in this sceen he is visited by the chase godness Diana.
She is the godness of the hunt and apparently was so in love with him
that she visited every night.
She takes the form of the moonbeam.
Well she is associated with the moon
and so that is how she is personified here and she baths him in light .
The beam is coming down from the moon light sky
but it got to get through all of that underbrush, and you notice that there is another figure.
That is a Zephyr who is personification of the west wind.
Who helps Diana by pulling the branches back
so the light could bathe him in that extraordinary glow.
So we see this intres in the ideal male nude.
We kow that David's followers in this time were looking back
at ancient greek sculptures of nude athletes and gods.
And there is a real interes here in nudity.
But the form is soften to we don't really have a lot of anotomical
details and terms of masculature and we will see a little bit at the abdomen.
But as we look at the arms and legs they look rather soft and in a way a litte bit feminine.
There is no question in fact the
entire painting glows so that all the clarity of lines has been removed.
And I think, it is quite clear
that Giordet has been looking at some of the earlier Italian masters I am thnking about
Leonardo's use of sfumato, and I am thinking about of some of the later manners, painters.
And I think we have in some ways the begginings of romanticism.
In the figure that is really languid and sensual.
And we have emotionalism here that is very different
from the severity and rationalism of Davide in neoclassicism.
I think that it is right in some ways at least in terms of temperament.
It is a return to the more lascivious
or actually you can't say lascivious because of course Diana was chased.
But to the emocionalism and the intres of a heart that has been so much apart of the rococo.