We are in the museum of the cathedral of Siena, and we are looking at
probably , the singlemost famous work of art
from Siena, and certainly one of the most important
works of art from the 14th century. This is Duccio's Maesta.
The title means the Virgin Mary in majesty
and we see her very large in the centre of the main
panel. She is by far the largest figure anywhere in this painting.
This is a polyptych. It is made of many many panels,
not all of which are here in the museum unfortunately.
Maestas peter on both the front and the back.
The Mary is on the front and the stories of Marys life are on the front
but the story of Christ is on the back. so in a sense this is
a free standing painting. It is a large sculptural object
that has all this imagery all over. And the figures
of the saints and angels are almost life size.
Its true, and there are three rows of them and they are lined up
almost as if you worked for a class picture.
There are four local saints in front, and then angels and saints in the second row
and I think an unbroken row of angels in the back
Now we would have originally seen a predella below, that is a stab of small paintings,
and then above the large panel, there would have been
the series of saints as well. We think that the predella,
would have held the scenes of the early life of virgin Mary
and above her death and ascend to heaven
and then there would have been in the elaborate frame.
In the previous century,
Siena had won a significant battle against
its arch rival
Florence. Now Siena and Florence were wealthy city states.
That is they were independant nations
and were often at war with each other. Siena
believes that they won because of the grace of Mary. Many years later
the town of Siena commissioned their most famous painter
Duccio , to create a very large painting, which
was dedicated to Virgin Mary. It would have stood exactly
on the altar of the cathedral in the crosslink just under the dome
As you cross the higher altar you would be able to make out, just at the bottom
an inscription that read, 'Holy Mother of God, be the cause of peace to Siena, and to the life of Duccio, because he has painted thee thus.'
Now Siena was very much a competitor of Florence. and
the great florentine painter of the day was
Giotto. He had painted a major cycle, telling the story
of the Virgin Mary. of the Christ's parents, of Christ himself
and in some ways the Maesta was a kind of answer to that. We can do this too.
We can be as comprehensive and have a masterpiece
too. And I think they proved that they did something that their rival Giotto did
in the arena chapel. But Giotto's
painting was a fresco. Fresco did not make sense for the cahtedral
of Siena because the cathedral of Siena is made of
alternating blocks of black and white marble.
It has a very decorative interior, that would'nt have worked with fresco
and so it made sense to do a panel painting for the altar piece.
And you have to remember that at the end of the medieval,
Mary had taken on an enormously important role.
she was the bridge that normal people could access Christ through.
You would speak and pray to the virgin Mary and she
would perhaps speak to her son on your behalf. She had the role of an intercessor, or someone who intercedes
between god and mankind. As is traditional, she is garbed in an intensely
billoed, that must have been fabulously
expensive, given of the lapezzawould have been required to produce that artillery in paint.
There is this beautifully embedded gold
in the strait behind her. There are lot of decorative surfaces,
representing that this is particular to the siena style.
There is a sense of delicacy, and christ has modelled him
there is a kind of transparency and around his leg there is a beautiful
amatilation of light and shadow
that is being used here not only strylation of gold
this is not the earlier work of Chimabue. this
is a work of Duccio who is moving steadily and consciously
it is creating a sense of real mass and real volume.
the drapery about the Christ is softly and beautifully modelled. look at the christ
in her hands pearls in her drapery
and dthe modelling that we see under chrissts chin and neck
it really is three dimensional and the way we begin to see its life charter also
in the early thirten hundreds, creating forms that were three dimensional
and lok at the face of christ. there is a look of awaremess
and wisdom that is peircing. he seems to look dirrectly at us
and it is the stare of a fully conscious adult.
the angels are remarkably animated. some
look at mary,, some look away, some look at us
there is a kind of informality. its true
that informality is so unexpected. you would expect something more rigid
this is the court of heaven after all. this is quite wonderful
and gives it a sense of complexity and lso notincing
the lovely curls that make up the wings of the angel
somehow actually make to feel like feathers
it gives us a sense of voleume and the wings are not flat
and now in the ground we see the throne opening out moving
into our space
now remember that in the medieval era
the cathedrals and churches in general were not open for people to walk
through as they are now. and the lay people as they are
known would have gone to the front of the church only
the area at the back of the church, the altar would have been reserved
for those who had worked directly with the church. it is intersting to note
the relation that the men who had the power to access
to this side of the painting that focussed on virgin Mary
the intercessor between man and the divine
a more privileged reach was available to the monks and the priests
to those who were closely associated with the church.
let us take a walk at the back and take a look at that panels