We're now on problem number 4
from the Normal Distribution
chapter from ck12.org's
FlexBook on AP Statistics.
You can go to their
site to download it.
It's all for free.
So problem number 4, and
it's, at least in my mind,
pretty good practice.
For normal or a standard normal
distribution, for a standard
normal distribution, place
the following in order from
the smallest to largest.
So let's see, percentage of
data below 1, negative 1.
OK, let's draw our standard
normal distribution.
So a standard normal
distribution is one where the
mean is-- sorry, I drew the
standard deviation-- is one
where the mean, mu for mean,
is where the mean is equal
to 0, and the standard
deviation is equal to 1.
So let me draw that standard
normal distribution.
So let me draw the
axis right like that.
Let me see if I can draw a
nice-looking bell curve.
There's a bell
curve right there.
You get the idea.
And this is a standard normal
distribution, so the mean,
or you can kind of do the
center point right here.
It's not skewed.
The mean is going to be
0 right there, and the
standard deviation is 1.
So if we go one standard
deviation to the right,
that is going to be 1.
If you go two standard
deviations, it's going to be
2, three standard deviations
3, just like that.
One standard deviation to the
left is going to be minus 1.
Two standard deviations to
the left will be minus 2,
and so on and so forth.
Minus 3 will be three standard
deviations to the left because
the standard deviation is 1.
So let's see if we can
answer this question.
So what's the percentage
of data below 1?
So the percentage-- Part a,
that's this stuff right here,
so everything below 1.
So it's all of-- well, not just
that little center portion.
It keeps going.
Everything below 1, right?
Percentage data below 1.
So this is another situation
where we should use
the empirical rule.
It never hurts to
get more practice.
Empirical rule.
Or maybe the better way to
remember the empirical rule is
just the 68, 95, 99.7 rule.
And I call that a better
way because it essentially
gives you the rule.
These are just the
numbers that you have to
essentially memorize.
If you have a calculator or a
normal distribution table,
you don't have to do this.
But sometimes in class,
people want you to estimate
percentages, and so
it's good to do.
You know, you can impress
people if you can do
this in your head.
So let's see if we can use
the empirical rule to
answer this question.
The area under the bell curve
all the way up to 1, or
everything to the left of 1.
So the empirical rule tells us
that this middle area between
one standard deviation to
the left and one standard
deviation to the right,
that right there is 68%.
We saw that in the
previous video as well.
That's what the empirical
rule tells us.
Now of that 68%, we saw in the
last video that everything else
combined, it all has that up to
1 or to 100%, that this
left-hand tail-- let me draw it
a little bit-- this part right
here, plus this part right
here, has to add up-- when
you add it to 68-- has to
add up to 1 or to 100%.
So those two combined are 32%.
32 plus 68 is 100.
Now, this is symmetrical.
These two things are the exact
same, so if they add up to 32,
this right here is 16% and
this right here is 16%.
Now the question, they want us
to know the area of
everything-- let me do it in a
new color-- everything
less than 1, right?
The percentage of data below
1, so everything to the
left of this point.
So it's the 68%, it's right
there, so it's 68%, which is
this middle area within one
standard deviation, plus this
left branch right there.
So it's 68 plus 16%,
which is what?
That's equal to 84%.
So this Part a is 84%.
They're going to want us to
put this in order eventually,
but it's good to just solve
essentially the hard part.
Once we know the numbers,
ordering is pretty easy.
Part b.
The percentage of
data below minus 1.
So minus 1 is right there.
So they really just want us to
figure out this area right
here, the percentage of
data below minus 1.
Well, that's going to be 16%.
We just figured that out.
And you could have already
known, just without even
knowing the empirical, just
looking at a normal
distribution, that this entire
area, that Part b is a subset
of Part a, so it's going to
be a smaller number.
So if you just have to order
things, you could have made
that intuition, but it's good
to do practice with
the empirical rule.
Now, Part c, they want to
know what's the mean?
Well, that's the easiest thing.
The mean of a standard normal
distribution, by definition,
is 0, so number c is 0.
d, the standard deviation.
Well, by definition, the
standard deviation for
the standard normal
distribution is 1.
So this is 1 right here.
This is easier than I
thought it would be.
Part e.
The percentage of data above 2.
So they want the percentage
of data above 2.
So we know from the 68, 95,
99.7 rule that if we want to
know how much data is within
two standard deviations-- so
let me do it in and new color.
So if we're looking from
this-- let me do it in
a more vibrant color.
Oh, green.
If we're looking from this
point to this point, so
it's within two standard
deviations, right?
The standard
deviation here is 1.
If we're looking within two
standard deviations, that whole
area right there by the
empirical rule is 95% within
two standard deviations.
This is 95%, which tells us
that everything else combined--
so if you take this yellow
portion right here and this
yellow portion right here, so
everything beyond two standard
deviations in either direction,
that has to be the remainder.
So, you know, everything in
the middle is 95 within two
standard deviations, so that
has to be 5% If you add that
tail and that tail together,
everything to the left and
right of two standard
deviations.
Well, I've made the
argument before.
Everything is symmetrical.
This and this are equal, so
this right here is 2 and a half
percent, and this right here
is also 2 and a half percent.
So they're asking us the
percentage of data above 2.
That's this tail, just
this tail right here.
The percentage of data more
than two standard deviations
away from the mean, so that's
2 and a half percent.
I'll do it in a darker colors
Now, they're asking us, place
the following in order
from smallest to largest.
So there's a little bit of
ambiguity here, because if
they're saying the percentage
of data below 1, do they want
us to say, well, it's 84%.
So should we consider the
answer to Part a 84, or should
we consider-- if they said the
fraction of data below
1, I would say 0.84.
So it depends on how they
want to interpret it.
Same way here.
The percentage of data
below minus 1, I could
say the answer is 16.
16 is the percentage below
minus 1, but the actual number,
if I said the fraction of data
below minus 1, I would say
0.16, so this actually would be
very different in
how we order it.
Similarly, if someone asked me
the percentage, I would say,
oh, that's 2.5, but the
actual number is 0.025.
That's the actual fraction
or the actual decimal.
So, I mean, this is just
ordering numbers so I shouldn't
fixate on this too much.
But let's just say that they're
going with the decimal.
So if we wanted to do it that
way, if they wanted to do it
from smallest to largest, the
smallest number we have
here is c, right?
That's 0.
And then the next smallest
is e, which is 0.025.
Then the next smallest
is b, which is 0.16.
And then the next one after
that is a, which is 0.84, and
then the largest would be
the standard deviation d.
So the answers is cbad.
And obviously, the order would
be different if the answer to
this, instead of saying it is
0.084, you said it was 84,
because they're asking
for the percentage.
So a little bit of ambiguity.
If you had a question like this
on the exam, I would clarify
that with the teacher.
But hopefully, you
found this useful.