We're still on the fourth floor in the Museum of Modern Art,
and we're standing in front of one of Jackson Pollock's great, seminal, signature works of painting called "One: Number 31, 1950."
That's a lot of numbers.
You know, he made a real decision.
Is it like Chopin, you know - "Nocturne No. 22?"
It's exactly what it is. He had titles and, actually, he would occasionally title again,
or sometimes accept the title that his friends developed for a painting after it was finished.
But scholars have thought that Pollock numbered because he wanted not to close down meaning.
He wanted the meaning to remain open and the system that was used by composers did that.
That makes sense.
So he didn't want any text associated with this image and wanted instead something very open-ended.
The same year he produced this, in fact, at the same time that he produced this,
he produced "Autumn Rhythm," which hangs up at the Met.
Which does have a name.
It does have a name and people look for, you know, the colors of fall. They look for...
The rhythm.
Yeah, exactly.
And they wonder what that is. It's a series of associations.
A minute ago, when we walked into the room, you said that you could tell when it was upside down,
which I don't think many people could do.
So that would mean that there is something very intentional about the drips and their direction
and the form that this image takes that I think is probably lost on most viewers.
See, that is a really interesting and, I think, complicated set of issues.
When we think of Pollock's drip paintings, we, I think quite rightfully, think of a kind of improvisation.
And these paintings are kind of improvisation.
Like jazz musicians going off on a riff.
Right, exactly. But that same jazz musician probably knows how to control a saxophone brilliantly.
And Pollock, I think, really understood how to control the paint in his incredibly unique way.
It's interesting that we don't want to allow him that control.
We love the idea of the artists as the idiots of art, we want it with Van Gogh, we want it with everybody.
These people who are somehow brilliant in this very narrow way.
But Pollock was very sophisticated visually and really understood, I think, what he was up to.
So how does top and bottom work here?
Well, if you look at the canvas, this is a huge canvas, first of all, and it's one he painted in the spring.
He painted it horizontally, unstretched and unprimed on a piece of rock and [...]
And he walked around the canvas quite famously and certainly.
There've been many photographic documentations of him painting.
But if you look at the painting, you'll see that he really ordered the canvas in these really particular ways.
First of all, the density of the paint is towards the center and there really is a frame around the edge...
The edge of the architecture.
So he knew exactly where he was going and where he was ending.
But at the same time, the density becomes most extreme a little bit more than a third of the way up the canvas and, in fact,
there's a sort of a loose horizontal that's about one third of the way up the canvas...
I see.
...which in some ways functions to, I think, anchor the canvas and give it a kind of center of gravity
that's low rather than high, so it doesn't feel unwieldy.
But in the classroom, if you take a slide of this painting and flip it over, the painting falls apart.
Really?
Yeah.
I wish we could do that here.
Your mention of the horizontal reminded me of a horizon line.
Which is a funny thing to think about, because he's got the canvas flat on the floor, there is no horizon line.
I was consciously avoiding the word "horizon line."
It's a pretty inevitable association here, though.
Yeah, it is. We really do see a kind of space, it's the way in which those schemes of paint, those lines,
really fold into each other and become this incredible sort of dense, spacial...
It's quite powerful to stand in front of it, it feels very enveloping and around one, even though one is standing separate from it.
It's true. I want to go back to the idea of his intent, though,
because there's been a lot of discussion. These two sort of great critical framers, early on.
Greenberg?
Greenberg and Rosenberg had very different views on what Pollock was doing
and Rosenberg very famously says that what we're seeing in the museum is, in some sense,
just a fossil of the original work of art, which was the act of making.
The performance.
The performance, the performative element itself.
Whereas Greenberg said that it only became a work of art when it was lifted off the floor,
into the realm of the vertical and sort of entered into this continuum of the history of art.
It's an interesting thing, because we're not looking at it the way the artist himself looked at it and created it,
which is probably something that had never happened before.
And because of that sometimes I find myself going to the edge of the canvas and cuffing my head to the side,
so that I can see across the canvas, the way that Pollock would have.
It's a very different exterior.
I wonder how he kept both of those things in his head.
He was very conscious of what [...]. He was very conscious of what his painting would look like when it did reach the vertical.
Well, he must have. I mean, he was speaking to a tradition of painting, to the history of painting.
There is one case, though, when he asked Tony Smith, who put together some of his most important exhibitions,
to hang a painting horizontally, on the ceiling, in the gallery.
Really? That's interesting.
So there was one case when you actually would have looked across the canvas - or at least up at it.
I'm looking now and there are some people standing in front of it and pretending that they're dripping.
They've figured out that dense network of drips and lines, it looks so strange.
There are a very famous photographs of Vogue models actually,
it's in front of one of these canvases, and they look incredibly striking.
You know, there are so many ways to approach this painting,
but I think that one of the most important things to take away from Pollock
is that this is not a canvas that's about representing a bouquet of flowers or a human body.
It's really a painting that represents the action and the activity of painting itself.
The gesture. This is about the painterly gesture.
And the act of making. But yes, gesture, absolutely.
But there's no paintbrush, which is the thing we think abotu when we think about gesture.
Think about it this way. Would you look at any of those individual lines of paint?
They get thicker and thinner and sometimes they pull.
And when they pull, you get the sense that Pollock stopped and the paint continued to drip.
When his arm moves slowly, you have a thicker line, and when you have this thinning line, you know that he sped up.
So this becomes almost a kind of choreographic notation
where you can almost begin to reconstruct how he moved around this.
And so in some places it's a broader gesture.
It's not the gesture of the brush, it's not the gesture even of the hand, it's the gesture of the entire body.
I can feel that, but at the same time I can feel the tension.
There's some way that in its multifariousness and in its density it seems like a natural thing and not something that was made.
And that's maybe tying back into the point you made earlier about us not wanting Pollock to have been overly conscious.
We want this to somehow be an act of nature and that ties in beautifully with this whole myth.
There's a very famous moment early in Pollock's career,
when Lee Krasner, an extraordinary artist in her own right, and, off course, Pollock's wife,
would introduce him to Hans Hofmann, the great German abstractionist.
And Hofmann would say to Pollock that he needs to look more closely at nature,
when Hofmann was reviewing Pollock's early work.
And Pollock is said to have responded: "I am Nature."
Oh. Interesting.