Use substitution to solve for x and y they give us a system of equations here y is equal to negative
five x plus 8 and ten x plus two y is equal to negative two so they've set it up for us pretty well they
already have y specifically solved for up here so they tell us this first constraint tells us that y
must be equal to negative five x plus eight so when we go to the second constraint here everytime we
see a y we say well the first constraint tells us that y must be equal to negative five x plus eight
so everywhere we see a y we can substitute it with negative five x plus 8 cuz thats what the first
constraint tells us y is equal to that i dont want to be repetitive but i really want you to internalize
thats all its saying y is that so everytime we see a y in the second constraint we can substitute it
with that so lets do it so the second equation over here is ten x plus two and instead of writing a y
there and ive said it multiple times already we can write a negative five x plus eight the first constraint
tells us thats what y is so negative five x plus eight is equal to negative two now we have one equation
with one unknown we can just solve for x we have ten x plus so we can multiply it we can distribute this
two into both of these terms so we have two times negative five x is negative ten x and then two
times eight is sixteen so plus sixteen is equal to negative two now we have ten x minus ten x those
guys cancel out ten x minus ten x is equal to zero so these guys cancel out and we're just left with
sixteen equals negative two which is crazy we know that sixteen does not equal negative two this is an
inconsistent result and thats because these two lines actually dont intersect and we could see that
by actually graphing these lines whenever you get something like some number equaling some other number
that they're clearly not equal to that means its an inconsistent result its an inconsistent system and
that these lines actually dont intersect so let me just graph these just to make it clear this first
equation is already in slope y intercept form so it looks something like this thats our x axis this is
our y axis and its negative five x plus eight so one two three four five six seven eight and then it
has a very steep mega downward slope every time you move forward one you have to go down five so it
looks something like that thats this first equation right over there the second equation let me re write
it in slope y intercept form so its ten x plus two y is equal to negative two lets subract ten x from
both sides you get two y is equal to negative ten x minus two lets divide both sides by two you get y
is equal to negative five x negative five x minus one so its y intercept is negative one its right over
there and it has the same slope as this first line so it looks like this its parallel its just shifted
down a bit so it just looks like that so they're parallel lines they have the same slope different y
intercept we get an inconsistent result they dont intersect and the tell tale sign of that when you're
doing it algebraically is you get something wacky like this that is why its called inconsistent its not
consistent for sixteen to be equal to negative two these dont intersect there's no solution to both of
these constraints there's no x and y that satisfies both of them.