An investment firm creates a graph showing the performance of a specific stock over 12 months. Over
the course of the year, is the prices of the stock rising, falling or staying the same? So over on this axis here, the horizontal axis, they have month by month
and we move forward in time; July, August, September, October...And on this axis, the vertical axis, we have the price. So for example, In July
the price of this stock was a little over 10 dollars, then in August it moved up to around 11 dollars
I could keep going month by month. This type of graph is called a line graph because you have the data points for each month and
we connected them with a line. And the reason we connected them with a line is to really see if there
is a trend here. To really show that you have something that's moving
from one price to another. So line graphs tend to be used when you something that is changing over time
With that out of the way, lets answer their questions. Over the course of the year is the price of the
stock rising, falling or staying the same?
So on a month to month basis you have, for example from July to August the price went up
Then from August to September it went down, then it went up for two months, then it went down for a month,
then went for a couple more months, then it went REALLY up from February to March, it went all the way
up to almost 17 dollars then it went down again. And then it started going up again.
They are asking us not-did it go up EVERY month?- but over the course of the year, is the price of the
stock rising falling or staying the same? If you go from July, where our data starts, right over here.
Our price was around 10 dollars. And even though there was a few months where it went down. The overall
trend is that the price is going up. You can even see that. In July it was 10 dollars.
Then by June of the next year, it was approaching a little over 16 dollars, maybe almost 17 dollars.
So it actually had gone up a lot. They don't give us July of the next year, but the trend is in the upwards
direction. You can see it just visually by just looking at the graph. There are a few bumps that go down,
but the overall direction is upward.