Let's see if we can write 1.501 as a percentage.
Now, we really just want to write this quantity, as something over 100.
So, what we can do is, we can say that this is the same thing as 1.501 over 1.
We haven't changed it's value, now let's multiply it times 100 over 100.
When we do this product, and I haven't changed the value,
this just multiplying something times one.
But, when we do it we're going to change the way that we're representing it.
The denominator now, is going to be 1 times 100, so that's pretty straightforward.
That's just going to be 100.
And then the numerator, we're going to want to multiply 1.501 times 100.
And so, this is going
If we multiply this times 10,
we would move the decimal one over,
we want to be multiplied by hundreds,
we want to multiply by 10 again.
So we going to more the decimal over to the right twice.
We're multiplying it by 10, twice.
Or you're multiplying it by 100.
This is multiplying by 10,
this is multiplying it by 100.
So this is where the decimals are going to sit now.
So we're going to get 150.1
And so we've rewritten 1.501 as 150.1 over 100,
or 150.1 per 100.
Let me write that, 150.1 per... per 100
Which is the same thing as 150.1 per cent
Which is the same thing as 150.1%
And we're done.
And essentially what we are doing
- if you really want to simplify the process -
we're multiplying this by 100 to get 150.1
and then we're saying that is the percentage.
So you wanna make sure that you write % there or the % symbol.