I've written some example relationships
between the two variables,
in this case between 'm' and 'n',
between 'a' and 'b', between 'x' and 'y',
and what I want to do in this video is
[to] see if we can identify whether the relationships
are a direct relationship,
whether they vary directlly,
or maybe they vary inversely,
or maybe it is neither.
So let's explore it a little bit.
So over here we have m/n = 1/7.
So let's see how we can manipulate this.
If we multiply both sides by 'n',
what are we going to get?
And in general, you want to separate them
so that the two variables are on different
sides of the equation,
so you can see-- is going to be the pattern--
Let me write it this way:
is m=kn, this would be direction variation,
or is it going to be the pattern
m = k * 1/n -- this is inverse variation.
And you see in either one of these,
they are on different sides of the equal sign.
So let's take this first relationship right now,
let's multiply both sides by 'n',
and you get m -- these cancel out--
is equal to 1/7 * n.
So this actually meets
the direct variation pattern.
It's some constant times 'n'.
m = some constant * n
So this right over here is direct variation.
Let's see ab = -3.
So if we want to separate them,
and we could do it with either variable,
let's divide both sides by 'a'.
We could've done it by 'b'.
If we divide both sides by 'a',
we get b = -3/a,
or, you could also write this as
b = -3 * 1/a.
And once again,
this is this pattern right here.
One variable is equal to
a constant times 1 over the other variable.
In this case, our constant is -3.
So over here, they vary inversely.
They vary inversely.
Let's try this one over here.
xy = 1/10
Once again, let's try to separate the variables,
isolate them on either sides of the equation,
and let's divide both sides by 'x'.
You could divide by 'y',
because you're really trying to find
an inverse or direct relationship.
So divide both sides by 'x',
you get y = 1/10 over x,
which is the same thing as 1/10x,
which is the same thing as 1/10 * 1/x.
So y = some constant * 1/x.
Once again, 'y' and 'x' vary inversely.
Let's do this one over here:
9 * (1/m) = n
So this one's actually already done for us.
And it might be a little bit clearer
if we just flip this around.
If we just flip the left and the right-hand side,
we get n = 9 * 1/m.
n = some constant * 1/m.
So n varies inversely with m.
And, remember, if I say that n varies that m,
that also means that m varies inversely with n.
Those two things imply each other.
Now let's try it with this expression over here.
This one's a little bit of a trickier one.
Because we've already separated
the variables on both hands
and we have this kind of--
if this [were] b = 1/3 * a,
then we would direct variation,
and b would vary directly with a.
But in this case, we have 1/3 - a.
And you say, "Hey, maybe they're opposites,
or whatever."
And it actually turns out
that this is neither.
And to make that point 100% clear,
let's look at 2 of these examples.
In direct variation,
if you scale up one variable in one direction,
you would scale up the other variable
by the same amount.
So if x doubles from one to two,
when x is one, actually I should do this
with 'm' and 'n',
so m and n.
And the way I've written it here,
although you could algebraically manipulate it
so that one looks more dependent that the other,
but in this situation
where n is 1, m is 1/7.
And when n is 7, m is going to be 1.
So you have the situation
that if n is scaled up by 7,
then m is also scaled up by 7.
Or vice versa.
This is more of a relationship.
I could've expressed n in terms of m.
But when you scale one variable up by 7,
you also have to scale up the other variable by 7.
Or if you scale it up
by some amount,
you have to scale up the other variable
by the same amount.
This is direct variation.
Let's take the inverse,
or when two variables vary inversely:
this situation right over here.
Let's take a and b.
When a = 1, b = -3.
Or we could do it explicitly right over here,
we could even go to the original one.
When a = 1, we have 1b = -3, b=-3.
If I were to take 'a', and I were to triple it,
so if I were to multiply it by 3,
so now a = 3, we have 1/3 * -3.
So now b = -1
Notice! We didn't multiply b times 3 here!
Now we divided by 3.
Or another way is
[that] we multiplied by 1/3.
So if you scale up 'a' by 3,
you're scaling down 'b' by 3.
So they're varying inversely.
What you're going to see in this 'neither'
is that neither of these
are going to be the case.
So let's try it out.
I'll do it in that same green color.
That same green.
So we have 'a' and 'b'.
So when 'a' is, I don't know,
when 'a' is 1, what is b?
1/3 - 1, that's 1/3 -3/3,
that's -2/3.
And then let's divide,
just for fun,
'a' by 3.
So 'a' goes to 1/3.
So we're dividing by 3,
or you could say that we're multiplying by 1/3.
So if 'a' is 1/3,
then 'b' is equal to 0.
If a = 1/3, b = 0.
So notice: if this [were] direction variation,
we would be multiplying this by 1/3 as well,
which clearly we didn't!
And if this [were] inverse variation,
if they varied inversely,
we would be multiplying by 3,
which clearly we didn't,
we just got some other number!
The scaling actually didn't matter;
what happened is that things
really just got shifted by some amount.
They got shifted by 2/3.
So these vary neither directly nor inversely--
--this last one right over here.