Let's think about what might
happen if we had a solution of
this molecule and water and
how they might react.
And just as a bit of review
on naming, let's
just name this molecule.
The longest chain, let's see,
we have one, two, three
carbons, so it is going
to be a prop-.
It's an alkane, All
single bonds, so
it's going to be propane.
And then this is our
longest chain right
here, one, two, three.
We have this methyl group off of
the number two carbon, and
we also have the bromo group off
of the number two carbon.
So it's going to be 2-bromo.
let me write this here.
It's going to be
2-bromo-2-methyl.
let me write that a
little bit neater.
I'll need more space
to the left.
This is going to be
2-bromo-2-methyl-- for this
methyl group off the number
two carbon-- propane.
So let's think about how it
might react with just water.
Now, in this example, water is
going to be our nucleophile.
It has some electrons already
over there, but even more,
it's very electronegative,
which we've
seen multiple times.
So it's hogging electrons
from the hydrogen.
It's not as strong of a
nucleophile as the hydroxide
anion that we saw in the Sn2
reaction, but it is a
nucleophile.
This is actually a
weak nucleophile.
This right here is a
It wouldn't mind maybe being
attracted to a nucleus because
it has extra negative charge.
It has a partial negative charge
on this side of the
oxygen, because it's hogging
hydrogen's electrons.
You have partial positive
charges on these sides.
But it's not as strong as a
hydroxide, which has an actual
negative charge, not just a
partial negative charge, and
really wants to offload
electrons, or is
attracted to a nucleus.
So this is a weak nucleophile.
And we're going to talk more
about-- we're going to see one
type of reaction in this video,
and we're going to talk
more in several videos about
when this type of reaction
versus an Sn2 type of reaction
might occur.
So let's look at this
right here.
We have a bromine
right over here.
We know that bromine is very
electronegative, and that it
is somewhat stable when it
has a negative charge.
At least it'll have eight
valence electrons, which makes
it feel relatively good,
although charge is never a
super stable situation.
So maybe, and I'm not going to
say that the reaction will go
super fast in this direction,
but maybe bromine will take
away the electron that
it has from carbon.
It was already hogging
it a little bit.
It is already more
electronegative.
Let me draw all of bromine's
valence electrons.
So it has that one that's on
that side with the carbon.
Let me draw the carbon
electron on the other
side of that bond.
And then it has six other
valence electrons.
So one, two, three, four,
five, six, seven
total valence electrons.
So maybe we can imagine a
situation where bromine takes
this carbon's electron
altogether.
So let's draw that out.
So it literally will take this
electron altogether.
And once again, I said this
isn't going to be the super
fast direction, but
it could happen.
And so this reaction won't
necessarily go super fast.
It'll kind of be
in equilibrium.
So if that were to happen, we'd
be in equilibrium with
this situation.
So let me draw my original.
So I have my carbon.
I have that CH3 group
behind it.
I have the CH3 group
in front of it.
I have the CH3 above it.
But now the bromine has left.
It's no longer bonded.
And it has its original seven
valence electrons: one, two,
three, four, five, six, seven.
This one right here was
originally bonded with the
electron from carbon, but now
bromine has taken that orange
electron altogether.
It has a negative charge.
The carbon has lost that orange
electron and so it has
a positive charge.
Now, it could be interesting if
oxygen comes into the mix.
Sorry, if water comes
into the mix.
So let me draw the water
molecule right here.
It is a weak nucleophile,
but this guy
really wants an electron.
He has a positive charge.
It is a tertiary carbocation,
so it's reasonably stable.
That's actually one
of the reasons why
this can even happen.
If this was a primary or if it
was connected to no other
carbons, then it would be very
hard for this thing to just
turn into a carbocation.
But because it's tertiary, it's
somewhat stable, but it
doesn't like to have that
positive charge.
It really wants an electron.
So you could now imagine that
this oxygen-- oh, sorry, this
water-- let me be careful.
This water will give one
of its electrons.
So maybe that electron
right there will be
given to the carbon.
You could view it that this is
the nucleophile and it's being
attracted to carbon's
positive nucleus.
So then what will happen?
And once you're in this state,
this reaction actually will
occur much faster than
this one right here.
This is actually a reasonably
stable situation.
That's why I drew
the equilibrium.
But now this will actually
be a faster reaction.
So I'll just draw
an arrow here.
And then it will
look like this.
So we have our original carbon,
the original molecule.
That's the thing that's
behind it, CH3.
We have another CH3
in front of it.
And now, this water
is attached to it.
So let me draw the oxygen
and the two hydrogens.
Oxygen had these
two electrons.
It had another electron here.
That's that one right
over there.
Let me do it in this color.
So this has this
electron here.
But its pair, the thing that it
was in a pair with, is now
given to the carbon.
And they will be bonded.
These two guys are
still paired up.
Now, since oxygen-- this water
had a neutral charge.
But now it has given away one
of its electrons, so now the
water itself will have a
positive charge, or I guess
this water group, or you
can say it's kind of an
oxonium group now.
It has a positive charge.
And so the last thing that might
happen is maybe another
water molecule, or actually it
could even be the bromine,
comes along and grabs one of the
hydrogen protons so that
this electron can be taken
back by this oxygen.
Let me show you what
I'm talking about.
So maybe you could imagine
another water molecule.
There's gazillions of them.
Let me draw another water
molecule here.
We have another water
molecule right here.
And this would happen
simultaneously.
This might give one of his
electrons to, say, that
hydrogen right there.
And if that happens
simultaneously, this electron
that this hydrogen had could be
given back to this original
oxygen right here.
So that oxygen will take
back that electron.
And when that reaction happens,
we will be left
with-- let me draw our
original structure.
So we have the CH3 behind us.
We have the CH3 in
front of us.
We have the CH3 above this
carbon that's doing all the
reacting, and then it is bonded
to an oxygen, which is
bonded to a hydrogen, to only
this hydrogen, because it took
back the electron from
that hydrogen right
there, just like that.
You also have the bromine with
its negative charge, and it
has eight valence
electrons now.
And then, of course, you
have an extra oxonium.
So this oxygen right
here gave this
electron to this hydrogen.
So now it will be bonded
to that hydrogen.
And if you wanted to draw all
of the valence electrons on
this oxygen right here, it
would look like this.
So you have these two,
so one, two.
You have the one with
that three that's
bonded with that carbon.
Let me do that in a
different color.
So you have this one is
the same thing as
that valence electron.
It has the one bonded
with the hydrogen.
Let me make the bond clear.
It has a bond here with
the hydrogen.
So that's this hydrogen
bond right here, this
bond with the hydrogen.
I don't want to call
it a hydrogen bond.
You get the idea.
It has that valence electron
right there on
that end of the bond.
And then it had this
valence electron.
It had this one right
here at this end of
this bond with hydrogen.
That was just like that.
And then it took the other
electron from the hydrogen,
and so it's right there.
So once again, it still has
six valence electrons.
It is now a neutral
oxygen: one, two,
three, four, five, six.
So we were able to react this
2-bromo-2-methylpropane with
water, which is a weak
nucleophile.
We'll talk more about strong
and weak nucleophiles.
And we got to-- what is this
thing right over here?
Our longest chain is
one, two, three.
It's still prop-.
We're going to have
prop- as a prefix.
And I actually haven't
taught you this.
But since we have an OH group,
this is an alcohol.
And the way you name alcohols
is the suffix is -anol.
So we would call this, this is
prop-, and sometimes they'll
just say propanol, but since
we want to specify which
carbon we're on, this is the
one, two, three carbon.
This is propan-2-ol.
And, of course, we also
have a methyl
group on the two carbon.
So it's 2-methylpropan-2-ol.
Now, this whole reaction that I
just showed you is called an
Sn1 reaction.
And you might have a gut
sense of why it's
Sn1 instead of Sn2.
So let me write it down.
It's Sn1 reaction.
The S still stands
for substitution.
The n still stands for
nucleophilic, right?
We had a weak nucleophile in
the water molecule, so it
substituted.
Now, the 1 stands for the fact
that the slowest-- the
rate-determining step in this
mechanism, the one that is
going to happen the
slowest. That only
involves one of the reactants.
This right here was the
rate-determining step, the
bromine taking the electron
away from the carbon.
It did not involve this
water at all.
It did not involve both the
reactants like we saw in the
Sn2 reaction.
Since it only involves
this one reactant,
it is an Sn1 reaction.