Now what are the signs of sine of negative 210 degrees and cosecante of -210 degrees and I encourage you to pause this and try this on your own.
So let's draw ourselves a unit circle because we're going to have to use the unit circle defnition of trig functions to come up with what the sine and cosecante of -210 degree are .
So let's draw a unit circle
There's my unit circle, a circle of radius one, so for example this right here is point (1,0)
and you've seen this many many times
Now let's draw our angle, this angle of negative 210 degrees,
well as always the convention is draw the initial side of the angle along the postive x-axis
so just like that and now to think about which direction we rotate in to place our terminal side we look at the sign,
if this was a positive sign we'd go counter clock-wise , so this is a negative sign ,
the convention is we're going to go clock-wise
and we have to ask ourselves how far are we are going to rotate clockwise
so we rotate this far,
that would be negative 90 degrees, and if we do that much again , that's negative 180 degrees.
so to get to negative 210, we'll have to another negative 30 degrees,
so we have to go about that far into, what is this ,
this is the second quadrant, and so we end up with our angle looking something like this
now how do we figure out the value of sine of an angle using the unit-cricle definition
well the unit circle definition of trig funtctions tells us that
where the terminal side of our angle intersects the unit circle,
the coordonate of this point gives us both the cosine of that angle and
the sine of that angle
So the coordonates of this point is cosine -210, that's the x-coordinate and
sine of negative -210 degrees
the sine of this angle is just the y-coordinate of where the terminal side intersects the unit-circle
well is that going to be a positive or a negative y-coordinate
well you see that point is above the x-axis, this is a positive value of y.
So that tells us that that the sine of negative 210 degrees is going to be positive
Now given that, can we think about what the sign of the cosecante of negative 210 degrees is going to be?
well by defnition , by definition ,
cosecante of negative 210 degrees, is just the reciprocal of sine of negative 210 degrees,
and if I take the reciprocal of a positive number,
If I take one and I divide that by a positive number what am I going to get?
Well I'm going to get another positive number.
So the signs of both sine of negative 210 degrees and cosecant of negative 210 degrees are both positive.