Quadrilateral ABCD they're telling us it is a rhombus
To prove that the area of this rhombus is equal to one half times x AC x BD,
essentially proving that the area of a rhombus is one half
times the product of the lengths of its diagonals
Let' s see what we can do over here
There's a bunch of things we know about rhombi
All rhombi are parallelograms and there's tons of things that
we know about parallelograms
First of all, if it's a rhombus, we know that
all of the sides are congruent
That side length is equal to that side length, is equal to
that side length, is equal to that side length
Because it's a parallelogram, we know that
the diagonals bisect each other
Let's call this point over here E
We know that BE is going to be equal to ED and
we know that AE is equal to EC
We also know because this is a rhombus and we proved this
in the last video: that the diagonals,
not only do they bisect each other, but they're also perpendicular
So we know that this is a right angle
This is a right angle
That is a right angle and then this is a right angle
The easiest way to think about it is, if we can show that
this triangle ADC is congruent to triangle ABC and
if we can figure out the area of one of them, we can just double it
The first part is pretty straightforward
We know that triangle ADC is going to be congruent to triangle ABC
and we know that by side-side-side congruency
This side is congruent to that side
This side is congruent to that side and
they both share AC right over here
So, this is by side-side-side
Because of that, we know that the area of ABCD is just going to be
equal to 2 times the area of, we can pick either one of these, ABC
Let me write it this way
The area of ABCD is equal to the area of ADC plus the area of ABC
but since they're congruent, these 2 are going to be the same thing
so it's just going to be 2 times the area of ABC
Now what is the area of ABC
The area of a triangle is just one half of base times height
The area of ABC is just equal to times the base of that triangle
times its height
What is the length of the base
The length of the base is AC
I'll color code it
The base is AC and then what is the height here
We know that this diagonal line over here is a perpendicular bisector
so the height is just the distance from BE
So, it's AC times BE, that is the height
This is an altitude
It intersects this base at a 90 degree angle
Or we can say BE is the same thing as times BD
This is equal to times AC, that's our base
Our height is BE, which is times BD
So that's the area of just ABC, that broader,
larger triangle right up there
That half of the rhombus
We just said that the area of the whole thing is 2 times that
If we go back, if we use both this information and
this information right over here
We have the area of ABCD is going to be equal to
2 times the area of ABC, this thing right over here
It is 2 times the area of ABC, right over there
So times is , times AC times BD
Then you see where this is going
2 times is , times AC times BD
Fairly straightforward, there's a neat result
Actually, I haven't done this in a video
I'll do it in the next video
There are other ways of finding the areas of parallelograms
Generally, it's essentially, base times height
But for rhombus, we could do that because it is a parallelogram,
but we also have this other neat little result
that we proved in this video
And if we know that lengths of the diagonals,
the area of the rhombus is times the products of the lengths
of the diagonals, which is kind of a neat result