After the farmer and the pie chain
get involved in this forward contract
a few questions start to pop up in each of their minds
the main one is
what if the other party isnt able to uphold their end of the contract
and this is called counter party risk
COUNTER PARTY RISK
which is essentially the counterparty to the farmer is the pie store
and the counter party to the pie chain is the farmer
and the risk that the other party wont be able to uphold
their end of the contract
The other thing that starts to worry either one of these is
what if they have second thoughts
about this forward contract they entered into
will they be able to may be sell their obligation to some one else?
So is their anyway to trade the contract?
and then there is another issue
that even if you were to trade the contract, How will you know
that the other party whoever you want to trade with,
will be cool with a million pounds for 200,000 dollars
may be they want to deal with a smaller quantity
may be they would want only a thousand pounds or
hundered thousand dollars worth of apple
So the Local... The local brain comes up
with an idea
he is like... Why dont we standardise these forward contracts?
Why dont I just create a bunch of contracts,
whenever someone wants to enter to one of these forward contracts
but I standardize them and I say there is a thousand
instead of having a million apples, I do a small enough increment
so I say, thousand pounds of apples for delivery
for delivery on lets say November... On November 15th
and everyone of these contracts say the samething, a thousand pounds
of apples for delivery on 11/15
and this guy, he is also the richest guy in the town,
he is already been running a stock exchange,
and so to, to help alleviate counter party risk fear,
he also says that I am going to guarantee,
i will guarantee any of these contracts
so essentially he is taking on all of the counter party risks
to make people more comfortable with trading
so all of a sudden, what happens is, is that
now these guys dont have to do a one off contract
they dont have to do this one off forward contract,
there are these standardized contracts, that this exchange can trade
and what happens is, is that smaller farmers,
so small... We ll do this in a different colour
You have farmers, Farmer A, Farmer B
Farmer B... Can now... Can now transact with...
Um i should say i guess we can call it Customer ... Customer...
C and Customer... Customer D
where they could agree to have a fixed price
where they could do smaller increments, more granular increments
and if any of them wants to get out of it, they can by selling their
contract to another person on the exchange.
And these more standardized forward contracts, there is still essentially
the same thing... they are just standardized... The agreements to transact
at a future date
Give a certain amount of money, for certain amount of something else
It could be a security, it could be apples
these things, these standardised forward contracts,
these are called futures,
where they are standardized and they are traded on in exchange