What i wanna do with this video is to give an overview og how money is created in most market based economies
an even a bit of a discussion of what really is money, and we can go to much more depth in future videos
in most market based economies right now there is a central bank, which is essentially the actor,
they do many things, they often will be the regulatory agency as well
but their main role is to have the right to print money, and to put that money into circulation
i'll rely heavily on the model of the US and the Central Bank
The central bank in some countries is formally part of the governement
in other countries, its pseudo-independant. In the US its more pseudo independant
Although obviously, closely connected with the government, the UD federal reserve
a lot of the leaders are appointed by the government, its excess profits go back to the government, so obviously
it have very close ties to the goverment. But when the central government decides to print money
it literally can just create physical money, or it can create electronic money, which has the same effect
So let's say the central bank goes out there, and prints 3 physical dollar bills
now it has to figure out, how does it get it into circulation, how does it get it into the economy?
It does not just put it into a helicopter and drop it out!
Sometimes, in certain circumstances, is can lend this directly to bank, certain types of banks
but the typical way that this enter circulaiton, is that the central bank will use this newly created money
to go out into the open market and buy securities and they typically buy safe securities like government debt.
So they will go out there and put this into circulation, and in exchange they are buying securities form the open market
So these securities will go to the central bank. so there are securities, or bonds
And once they do that, then whoever had these before, whoever was the owner of these securities before
Now they have these dollarbills, and they can either directly spend these dollars
or they can deposit these dollarbills in the bank. If they spend the dollars, then whoever they gave those bills to at some point would want a deposit in a bank
So someway, by buying these securities, someone now has these dollarbills, and they will deposit them in a private bank.
So let's draw that. So right over here is a private bank. And now it has the dollarbills.
It has the reserves. Now, that's not the end of the story
This money can now be lend and this is key because this is typical in most market economies
where they have fractional reserve lending.
franctional reserve lending
which is a bit strange, because you are telling the people who just deposited these money here
that you can go at any time and you can take this money out.
We've got this money for you, you can trust us, you don't have to be paranoid about what's gonne happen with this money
But the reality is that this bank i allowed to keep only a fraction of these reserves and lend the rest out.
In order for the system to not be super fragile, the central bank then also insures these banks
I just want to show you how this money is created in the fractional reserve lending system
So this bank over here says, we'll have to keep a little bit of these reserves in case these guys come the probability of all of my
customers come on the same day and ask for all of my money is low. I just have to keep a little bit for whoever does come, and the rest i can lend out
Eventhough i promised everyone that all of they money is always available. So they lend it out to whoever needs that money
who looks like a decent risk. And those people might not spend it emediately, they would deposit it into a bank
Or they might spend it immediately, they buy a factory or car or something.
and whoever they bought those things from will now have this money and they will deposit it into a bank
So this newly lend money will now end up in a bank
Also end up in a bank
Now this can it can also only keep a fraction of the reserve and lend out the rest
And for simplicity in most banking systems, they only have to keep about 10 percent of the reserves in house and lend out the rest
But overhere i'm keeping much larger reserves just for the sake of making it easy to draw this diagram
So this bank overhere may decide to keep this dollarbill and could lend this one over here out
And once again, when it lends that dollarbill, it will end somehow and the person they lend it to may keep it in a bank temporarily or they might immediately buy
something, and when they buy something it will eventually end up in a bank because the person they
bought something from will deposit that money, and so it could end up in another bank.
This is interesting and in future videos we will go into more of the math of exactly how much money is being created
Its an interesting mathematical problem - actually its the sum of an infinite series and you can look it up if your'e interested.
But the basic idea here is that even though the central bank printed 3 units of base dollars, there a lot more money in the system
You have this guy who made this deposit thinks he has 3 dollars, this person thinks he has 2 dollars and this person thinks they have on
So in this example we have 1,2,3,4,5,6 - 6 dollars
So we have 6 dollars in this system
6 dollars
And you might say "is this really money"?
This guy thinks he has it but he's not using it if he had to use it he would have to withdraw it and then the bank would be able to do this
And this is where checking accounts is really important
I'm assuming that these are on-demand checking accounts
So this guy, the reason why he's not going to withdraw this money is that he can still use it as money by writing checks
So this guy says ok this is all the money i have, and he decides that he really needs to buy and apple and that apple costs 1 dollar
He does not have to withdraw this dollar out of the bank, he can write a check
So right now he has claims to all 3 of these dollars. He can write a check to the apple vendor, so 1 dollar
he writes a check, gives it to the applevendor, and will get the apple so his check is acting as money
and now the applevendor will have the rights to one of these apple's overhere
and how the applevendor can write a check so this dollar never has to leave the banking system
But because of checks it is essentially enabling these transactions to occur, so its still an
enabling, it is still acting in some forms of money because the rights to it can change
even though it is sitting out here and has been lend
or you can say it is enabling the writing of checks that are acting as some form of money
And the whole reason i wanna do this is to show you that the amount of money in circulation
is not essentially in the central banks control
They can definitely decise, hey i'm gonna print money, buy securities, put in into circulation
or if they wanna take money out of circulation, they can decise to sell these securities
and when they sell the securities, them maybe this guy will buy them
and those dollars will go back to the central bank and they will go out of commission
But you have this whole effect over here. If you have more lending occuring and the banks are feeling very confident
then more of this will happen. You'll get a larger multiplier effect of this lending.
And if less lending is happening, then you could potentially see all of this contract