So we're told that quadrilateral ABCD is a square
which tells us that the 4 sides have equal length,
and that they are all the interior angles are 90 degrees
We also know that FG,FG is a perpendicular bisector of BC
so we've already shown that it's perpendicular,
that this a 90-degree angle, but it also bisects BC
So this length is equal to that length right over there
Then they tell us that arc AC, it's a curve on top,
arc AC is part of circle B
So this is a circle centered at B
So this is the center of the circle,
this is part of part of that circle
It's really kind of the bottom left corner of that circle
and then given that information, they want us
to find what the measure of angle BED is
So what is BED?
So it's BED
So we need to figure out the measure
of this angle right over here
And I encourage you to pause it and try it out
And you might imagine, well I you could pause it
and try it without any hints
and now I would give you a hint if you if you try it the first time,
and you weren't able to do it,
and you should pause it again after this hint, is,
try to draw some triangles that maybe split up this angle
into a couple of different angles
and that might be a little bit easier
You might be able to use some of what we know about triangles
Now that said, I will try to solve it
and you should pause at any point
where you think that you know exactly how to do this
and try to do this yourself
So the trick is to realize that this is a circle
and so any any line that goes between B
and any point on this arc
is going to be equal to the radius of the circle
So AB is equal to the radius of the circle
BE is equal to the radius of the circle
And we can keep drawing other things
that are equal to the radius of the circle
BC is equal to the radius of the circle
So let's think about it a little bit
If we were to draw, and a lot of trickier geometry problems
really all revolve around drawing the right lines
or or visualizing the right triangles, and I'll do one right here
that might open up a lot for you in terms of thinking
about how to do this problem
So let me draw segment EC
and draw that as straight as possible
I can draw a better job of that
So the segment EC
Now something becomes interesting
because what is what is the relationship
between EBG and triangle ECG?
Well they both definitely share, they both share
this side right over here
They both share side EG
And then BG is equal to GC
And they both have 90 degree angles
They have 90 degree angle here
and they have 90 degree angle there
So you see by side angle side
Side angle side, these 2 triangles are going to be congruent
So we know that triangle EBG is congruent to triangle ECG
ECG, I should emphasize the C not the E
ECG by side angle side congruency,
by side angel side congruency
And that also tells that all of the corresponding angles
and sides are going to be the same
So, that tells us, that tells us right there
that EC that EC is equal to EB,
EC is equal to EB
So we know that EB, EB is equal to EC,
and what is what also is equal to that length?
Once again, this is the radius of the circle
BE, is one radius of the circle going from the center to the arc
But so is BC
It is also a radius of the circle going from the center to the arc
So this is also equal to, this is also equal to BC
So I could draw this other other 3 things right here
I'm I'm referring to the entire thing
not just one of the segments
All of BC
So what is, what kind of a triangle is this right over here?
Triangle BEC
Triangle BEC is equilateral
Equilateral
And we know that because all 3 sides are equal
So that tells us that all of its angles are equal
So that tells us that the measure of angle BEC, BEC,
we're not done yet, but it gets us close, is 60 degrees
So the measure of angle BEC right over there is 60 degrees
So that gives us part of the problem
BEC is part of the angle BED
If we can just figure out the measure of angle CED now,
if we can figure out this angle right over here,
we just add that to 60 degrees and we're done
We figured out the entire the entire BED
Let's think about how we can do this right over here
So there's a couple of interesting things
that we already do know
We know that this right over here
is equal to the radius of the circle
And we also know that this length down here,
this is a square
We know that this length down here
is the same as this length up here
That these are the exact same length,
and this is equal to the radius of the circle
We already put these 3 slashes here
BC is the same as that length, is the same as that length,
so all 4 sides are gonna be the same as that length
because this is a square
So let me write, let me write this down
Because because it's a square, I'll just write it this way
Because it's a square, we know that CD, we know that cd
is equal to BC which is equal to,
and we already established this as equal to CEC
which is equal to EB, which is equal to EC
What's important here is to realize that this and this
are the same length
And the reason why that is interesting
is it let's us know that this is an isosceles triangle
It's an isosceles triangle
So whatever isosceles triangle, if you have your 2 legs of it,
the 2 base angles are going to be congruent
So whatever angle this green angle is,
this angle is going to be as well
So somehow, somehow,
we can figure out this angle right over here
We can subtract that from 180
and then divide by 2 to figure out these 2
because we know that they are the same
So how can we figure out this angle?
Well we know all the angles of these things off up,
we can figure out all the angles of the larger ones up here
We know that this is an equilateral triangle
So this over here has to be 60 degrees as well
That's 60 degrees, and that is also 60 degrees
In fact, I can write it over here,
which is equal to the angle of BCE
The measure of angle BCE, BCE
So this is 60 degrees, we know we are dealing with a square
So this whole angle over here is a right angle
What is the measure of angle ECD?
What is this angle right over here?
I'm using a new color
This angle over here is gonna have to be 30 degrees
So that is going to be 30 degrees
And now, we are ready to solve
If you know, now we are ready to solve for these 2 base angles
If we call this x, if you call this x,
and we know they have to be the same,
we have x + x + 30 degrees,
x + x + 30 degrees is going to be equal to 180 degrees
That is the sum of all the interior angles of a triangle
So you get 2x,
2x + 30, + 30 is equal to 180 degrees
Now you can subtract 30 from both sides,
and we are left with 2x is equal to 150
Divide both sides by 2, you get x = 75
So we figured that x = 75, and now we are at the home stretch
We have to figure out angle BED
Well, that's going to be angle C,
so x is equal to the measure of angle CED,
so BED is CED + CED + BEC
So the 60 degrees + 75 degrees
So it's going to be,
ready for the drum roll?
This is going to be equal to 75 degrees + 60 degrees
which is equal to 135 degrees
And we are done