Well, we've spent many videostalking about electrostatic
fields and the potential on acharge or the potential energy
of a charge when it'sin one place.
But let's see what happenswhere, given a potential, what
happens when we actually allowthe charge to move?
And this will probably be a lotmore interesting to you,
because you'll learn how muchof the modern world works.
So let's say that I havea source of voltage.
Let me see how I wantto draw that.
I'm going to drawthat like that.
So this is my sourceof voltage,
often known as a battery.
This is the positive terminal.
This is the negative terminal.
It's a whole other subject, awhole other video, and I'll
make one eventually, ofhow a battery works.
But let's just say that nomatter how much current--
well, actually, let me explainin a second, but no matter how
much charge flows out of oneside of a battery to the other
side of the battery,that somehow the
voltages remain constant.
So that's kind of anon-intuitive thing, because
we learned about capacitors, andwe will learn more about
capacitors in the context ofcircuits, but what we learned
about a capacitor is that if wegot rid of some charge on
one end, the total voltageacross the
capacitor will decrease.
But a battery is thismagical thing.
I think it was invented byVolta, and that's why we call
everything volts and voltageand all of that.
But it's this magical thingthat, even as one side loses
charge to the other side, thatthe actual voltage, or the
potential betweenthe two sides,
actually remains constant.
That's the magic of a battery.
So let's just assume that wehave one of these magic
instruments.
You probably have one in yourcalculator or your cellphone.
And let's see what happens whenwe allow the charge to
actually travel from oneside to the other.
So let's say that I have anultra-good conductor.
Let's say it's a perfectconductor.
It's normally drawn straighterthan what
I'm capable of doing.
And no, I haven't hadanything to drink
before making this video.
So what did I do here?
So in the process of kind ofconnecting this positive
terminal to the negativeterminal of the battery, I'm
also exposing you to commonschematic notation for
electrical engineersand electricians,
et cetera, et cetera.
So what this is, these lineshere essentially are wires.
There's no reason why I drewit at a right angle here.
I just did that to be neat,those right angles.
And it's assumed that this wireis an ideal conductor,
that charge can flow freelywithout being impeded.
This thing right here, thisscratchy line, this is a
resistor, and this is somethingthat will actually
impede the charge.
It'll keep the charge from goingas fast as possible.
And then, of course,out here, this is a
perfect conductor again.
Now, which way willthe charge flow?
Well, I think I've mentionedthis before, but in electric
circuits, it's actually theelectrons that are flowing.
The electrons are those smallparticles that are going
really, really fast aroundthe nucleus of an atom.
And it's actually the electronsthat have this
fluidity that allow it to flowthrough a conductor.
So the actual movement ofobjects, if you call an
electron an object, some wouldargue that they're almost just
notional objects, but the actualflow is the electrons
from the negative terminalto the positive terminal.
But the people and all whooriginally created circuit
schematics and were thepioneers of electrical
engineering and electricians andwhoever, I don't know who
came up with it, they decided tosay-- and I think the point
here was to confuse people--that the current flows from
the positive to the negative.
So the direction of the currentis normally given in
this direction, and currentis specified by I.
And what is current?
Well, current-- so wait.
Actually, before I tell youwhat is current, just
remember, even though peoplesay that the current-- and
most textbooks do this, and ifyou become an electrical
engineer, people will oftensay that the current is
flowing from the positiveterminal to the negative
terminal, the actual flowing ofthings actually occurs from
the negative terminal tothe positive terminal.
It's not like somehow these bigheavy protons and nuclei
are somehow travelingthis way.
Once you compare the size of anelectron to a proton, you
would realize howcrazy that is.
It's the electrons, these littlesuper-fast particles
that are moving through theconductor from the negative
terminal this way.
So you could almost view thiscurrent as, the lack of
electrons are flowingthis way.
I don't want to confuse you.
But anyway, just remember thatthis is the convention, but
the reality is to some degreethe opposite of the
convention.
So what is this resistor?
Well, as the current isflowing-- and I want to stay
as close as possible to realityso you have a good
visualization of what'sgoing on.
As the electrons are flowing,you have these little
electrons, and they'reflowing in this wire.
And we assume for some reasonthis wire is just so amazing
that they don't in any way bumpinto any of the atoms of
the wire or anything.
But when they get to thisresistor, that's when these
electrons start bumpinginto things.
They start bumpinginto the other
electrons in this material.
So this is the resistorright here.
They start bumpinginto the other
electrons in this material.
They bump into the atoms andmolecules in this material.
And in the process, theelectrons essentially slow
down, right?
They're bumping into things.
So essentially, the more thingsthat there are to bump
into, or the less space thereare for the electrons to flow
through, the more that thismaterial is going to slow down
the electrons.
And as we'll see later, thelonger it is, that only
increases the chance thatelectrons bump into things.
And this is called a resistorand it provides resistance,
and it dictates how fastthe current flows.
So current, even though theconvention is it flows from
positive to negative, currentis actually just the flow of
charge per second.
So we could write that down.
I know I'm saying this in kindof a disjointed way, but I
think you get what I say.
Current is flow of charge, sochange in charge per second,
or per change in time, right?
So the way you could think aboutit is, what is voltage?
Voltage is how badly doescurrent want to flow?
So if there's a high voltagedifference between these two
terminals, then the electronsthat are sitting here, these
electrons want to reallybadly get here, right?
And if the voltage is evenhigher, these electrons want
to get there even more badly.
So before people understoodthat voltage was just a
potential difference, theywould actually call this
desire of the electrons toget from here to here the
electromotive force.
But what we've learned now,it's not actually a force.
It's just this potentialdifference that makes the-- we
could almost view it as anelectrical pressure, and
that's what people used toactually call voltage,
electrical pressure.
How badly do the electrons wantto get from here to here?
As soon as we give the electronsa path through this
circuit, the electronswill start traveling.
They'll start traveling, andwe assume that this wire
provides no resistance, thatthey can travel as
fast as they want.
But when they get to thisresistor, they start bumping
into things, and thislimits how fast the
electrons can travel.
So you can imagine that ifthis object right here is
somehow the rate-determiningfactor in how fast the
electrons travel, no matterhow fast the electrons can
travel after that, thiswas the bottleneck.
So even though electrons cantravel really fast here, they
have to slow down here, thenthey could travel really fast
here, the electrons here can'ttravel any faster than the
electrons through this.
Well, why is that?
Because if these electrons aretraveling slower, so the
current here is lower-- currentis really just the
rate at which the chargeis traveling, right?
So if the current is lowerhere and the current was
higher here, we wouldessentially end up having a
buildup of charge someplace herewhile all of the current
were waiting to travelthrough this.
And we know that that's notthe case, that all of the
electrons actually travel atthe exact same rate through
the entire circuit.
I'm going in the opposite ofthe convention right now,
because the convention is thatsomehow we have the positive
things traveling this way.
But I want to give you a reallyintuitive sense of
what's going on in a circuit,because I think once you
understand that, once problemsget a lot more complicated,
they won't be so daunting.
So what we know, and this iscalled Ohm's law, we know that
the current is actuallyproportional to the voltage
across the circuit.
So we know that voltage-- orwe could view it the other
way, that the voltage isproportional to the current
through a circuit.
So the voltage is equal to thecurrent times the resistance,
or you could say that thevoltage divided by the
resistance is equalto the current.
This is called Ohm's law, andthis is true whenever we're at
a constant temperature.
We'll go into more depth later,and we'll learn that if
a resistor actually hastemperature increases, then
its particles and its moleculesare moving around
more, they have higherkinetic energy.
And then it's even more likelythat electrons will bump into
them, so actually, theresistance increases with
temperature.
But if we assume at a constanttemperature for a given
material-- and we'll also learnlater that different
materials have differentresistivities.
But for a given material at aconstant temperature in a
given configuration, the voltageacross a resistor
divided by the resistor isequal to the current that
flows through it.
An object's resistance isactually measured as ohms, and
it's given by the Greekletter Omega.
So let's do a simple example.
Let's say that this is a16-volt battery, so the
potential difference here is 16volts between the positive
and the negative terminal.
So it's a 16-volt battery.
Let's say that this resistor is8 ohms. What is the current
flowing through-- and I keepdoing it in the opposite of
the convention, but let's goback to the convention.
What is the current flowingthrough this circuit?
Well, it's fairlystraightforward.
It's just Ohm's law,V equals IR.
The voltage is 16 volts, andit equals the current times
the resistance, times 8 ohms. Sothe current is equal to 16
volts divided by 8 ohms,which is equal to 2,
and this is 2 amperes.
Or sometimes they're calledamps, and that's
the units for current.
But as we know, all current is,is the amount of charge
per amount of time, so an ampereis just 2 coulombs per
second, right?
Oh, I'm already at11 1/2 minutes.
So I will leave you there.
You now know the basics of Ohm'slaw and maybe a little
bit of intuition on actuallywhat's going on in a circuit,
and I will see you inthe next video.