Now Shannon had just finished developing
his theories related to cryptography,
and, therefore, was well aware that human
communication was a mix of randomness
and statistical dependencies.
Letters in our messages were obviously
dependent on previous letters, to some extent.
And in 1949, he published
a groundbreaking paper,
"A Mathematical Theory of Communication."
And in it, he uses Markov models as the basis
for how we can think about communication.
And he starts with a toy example.
Imagine you encounter a bunch of text written
in an alphabet of 'A', 'B' and 'C'.
Perhaps you know nothing
about this language.
But you notice A's seem to clump
together, while B's and C's do not.
He then shows that you could design
a machine to generate similar looking text,
using a 'Markov chain'.
And he starts off with
a zeroth order approximation
which means we just independently
select each symbol -
A, B, or B - at random,
and form a sequence.
However, notice that this sequence
doesn't look like the original.
He shows then you could do a bit
better with a first order approximation,
where the letters are
chosen independently,
but according to the probability of each
letter occurring in the original sequence.
So this is slightly better,
as A's are now more likely,
But it still doesn't capture
much structure.
The next step is key.
A second-order approximation takes into
account each pair of letters which can occur.
And in this case,
we need three states.
The first state represents
all pairs which begin with 'A',
the second, all pairs that begin with 'B',
and the third state,
all pairs that begin with 'C'.
And notice now that
the 'A' cup has many 'AA' pairs,
which makes sense,
since the conditional probability
of an 'A' after an 'A' is higher
in our original message.
Now we can generate a sequence using
this second-order model easily, as follows:
We start anywhere and pick a tile
and we write down or output the first letter
and move to the cup defined
by the second letter.
Then we pick a new tile
and repeat this process indefinitely.
Notice that this sequence is starting
to look very similar to the original message,
because this model is capturing
the conditional dependencies between letters.
And if we want to do even better,
we could move to a third-order approximation,
which takes into account groups
of three letters - or 'trigrams'.
And in this case,
we would need 9 states.
But next, Shannon applies this exact
same logic to actual English text
using statistics that were known
for letters, pairs, trigrams, etc.
And he shows the same progression from
0th order random letters, to 1st-order,
2nd-order, and 3rd-order sequences.
He then goes on and tries the same thing
using words instead of letters.
And he writes,
"The resemblance to ordinary English text
increases quite noticeably at each depth."
Indeed, these machines were
producing meaningless text,
though they contained approximately
the same statistical structure
you'd seen in actual English.
Shannon then proceeds to define
a quantitative measure of information
as he realizes that the amount
of information in some message
must be tied up
in the design of the machine
which could be used to generate
similar-looking sequences.
Which brings us to his concept of entropy.