Imagine we listed all integers in a growing spiral,
and colored the prime numbers blue,
and left the composite numbers black.
One interesting question we may ask is,
"How many primes are there
compared to composites?"
First, let's zoom out to see the big picture.
Notice the prime color is dense in the center,
and slowly drops off in the distance 
but never seems to end.
One way I like to think about this is as follows:
Imagine there is a tree at the center
which is infinitely high.
The leaves which drop from this tree
represent prime numbers
which are scattered unpredictably below 
dense near the base of the tree 
and as we walk away from the tree,
we find fewer leaves 
though we always find them.
This is exactly what happens
when we look at larger and larger integers.
We always find more primes 
though the number of primes we find gradually drops
the further [away from the tree] we look.
So let's return to our question.
How many primes are there less than some integer 'x?'
If we make a table,
we see the number of primes is always increasing.
Though as we search further,
we find fewer and fewer.
Let's graph the number of primes
found on the vertical axis,
and the search size, x, on the horizontal.
As we zoom out to include billions of numbers,
notice the curve never flat lines.
It's always rising, albeit gradually.
First, let's think about the density of primes
less than some integer x.
We can find the density by dividing
the number of primes found by the search size.
For the first 100 integers, we find 25 primes 
therefore, 25% are prime.
Of the first 1000 integers, we find 1229 primes 
12.29% are prime.
Of the first 1 million integers, 7.84% are prime.
And the first 100 million integers contain 5.76% prime.
As we search further, this density continues to drop 
though the speed at which it drops slows down.
Here is a graph of the search size on the horizontal axis,
and the prime density on the vertical.
Notice that as we zoom out,
the primes are a vanishing proportion of all integers.
Amazingly, we find this formula in nature.
We see it in galaxies, storms, flowers 
and even inside our bodies 
as the design of least resistance 
known as the 'logarithmic spiral.'
Notice that as the spiral rotates,
it gets further and further away from the center.
Incredibly, the rotation rate of a logarithmic spiral
is related to the density of primes – as follows:
We have the number of rotations  – call this 'phi' 
and the distance from the center  – call this 'r'.
If we graph phi against r, and zoom out,
we see they are related
according to the natural logarithm.
This means the natural logarithm of the distance
is related to the number of rotations.
The graph of the natural logarithm is commonly written 
using the variable names 'y' and 'x' 
as y equals the natural logarithm of x [or y = ln(x)].
Notice the graph tapers off in the same way
the density of primes gradually decreases.
The final step is to invert this
by changing the y axis to 1/ln(x).
And when we zoom out,
we find the exact same curve generated
when we plot the density of primes.
Let's confirm this by overlapping the two plots.
In green is a graph of the line y = 1/ln(x).
And in red is the plot of prime number density 
up to x.
As we zoom out, they approach each other.
The further we zoom out,
the more accurate the green estimate becomes.
This is known as
the 'asymptotic law of distribution of prime numbers.'
We now have a formula to accurately tell us
the density of primes  – without counting.
The density of primes up to some integer x
is approximately 1/(ln(x).
So let's say you need to know the density of primes
between 1 and 100 trillion. Simple.
1/ln(100,000,000,000,000) = 3.1%.
Compare this to the actual result
from counting all primes –
which is 3.2 percent.
This is off by 0.1 percent.
And as we check larger and larger numbers,
the difference approaches zero.
Realize now that we can use
this formula for prime density
to estimate the number of primes up to x.
The number of primes is the area under
the density curve 
for which we can simplify
by assuming density is constant.
So the number of primes equals size times density –
or x/ln(x).
This is the prime number theorem.
Here is a graph of y = x/ln(x), in blue,
and [the line] in yellow is a plot
of an actual count of primes.
Notice as we zoom out,
these lines eventually overlap as we look to infinity.
And that is it.
We have a formula which tells us approximately
how many primes there are up to any value –
 no counting needed.
For example, let's say we need to know
the number of primes less than 100 trillion.
100 trillion divided by
the natural log of 100 trillion = 3.1 trillion.
Compare this to the actual count,
which is 3.2 trillion.
This is over 99.99 percent accurate –
even at this relatively small scale.
So to recap:
Given a search size up to some integer x,
the prime density is about 1/(ln(x).
And the number of primes is about x/ln(x).
This is the prime number theorem.