We're in the Uffizzi and we're looking at Verrocchio's painting of
the Baptism of Christ. So we see St. John on the right
baptizing Christ. This is simultaneously the moment that
Christ's divine nature is revealed and we see that in the Holy Spirit and the hands of
God above. What is especially fun about this painting is that
Leonardo was one of his students and Leonardo painted some parts
of this painting. OK, so that is a wild idea right there. Because we think of Leonardo
as the master of the High Renaissance, and the notion of him as a student
and to actually have some of his student work available is really fabulous.
Well, it is pretty wild, just the notion, that other people would paint part of your
paintings - that is true. It is not something we could imagine a modern artist doing. But this was
a standard idea, that a master would have students, would have apprentices, and
they would work in his work shop and often do some of the less critical elements.
So we know that Leonardo was responsible for one of the
angels, Right, so one day Verrocchio said: "Today, Leonardo, could you paint one of the
angels for me?" And so Verrocchio painted one of the angels and Leonardo painted
the other. And I think what is fun about this is to think about
one of the angels as an Early Renaissance angel and the other
angel as a High Renaissance angel. Leonardo's angel as the High
Renaissance angel, because it is really Leonardo who invents the style of the High
Renaissance. To me I think it is pretty obvious. So we have two angels,
they are very close. Think about how one angel, Verrocchio's
angel looks rather typical, like a boy. He does
look like a boy. Yeah, like maybe Verrocchio went out and got a boy to model for
him. Leonardo's angel looks like it has no earthly model. It's
just ideally beautiful. And it's that ideal
beauty that will become so important in the High Renaissance.
If you think about figures like Michaelangelo's David, it's the ideal
beauty of the High Renaissance figures that suggests their divine
nature. So that's so interesting. Because when we think about the Trecento, like we have a
kind of painting that created a representation of the other
worldly, of the divine, that had nothing to do with the earthly. But then
in the 15th century we had artists that were studying nature, studying
our reality. In a sense you are saying that
Leonardo is surpassing even that, that he took the lessons of the 15th century and
reworked them in order to be able to create an even more
transcendent representation of the divine. Well, in the 1300s
artists would represent spirituality or in the heavenly by using
a lot of gold, halos, figures that were very
flat and so they suggested transcendence, a kind of other worldliness.
So what Leonardo is doing is, he is keeping all of those lessons of the early
Renaissance of how to make the human figure look real, right. Using
modeling, giving the figure a sense of weight and gravity, giving
the figure a sense of three-dimensionality. Understanding its
anatomy. Exactly. All of those lessons of the Early Renaissance and
yet is able to imbue the figure with a sense
of transcendence and divinity. So much so
that the halo now almost seems redundant. Exactly. And
it is Leonardo who will do away with the halo but it is not just the ideal
beauty of the figure that suggests that kind of transcendence
and spirituality. It is also, I think for me, in the movements of the
figure. If you look at Leonardo's angel holding Christ's
clothing, he kneals facing to the right, his
shoulders twist slightly to the left, his head leans
back and up and it is an incredibly complex
pose. If you think back to the Early Renaissance, the artists
like Masaccio and Donatello were just really discovering
how to create figures standing in contrapposto, who could
move realistically. But Leonardo is taking a giant
step beyond that. So the figures really move in a very
elegant and graceful way that suggests that divine nature
So Leonardo is really offering us a glimpse into the future, a
promise of what the High Renaissance will hold in store for us.