We know the US is running a relatively large deficit relative to China in 2009
We imported 260 billion more than we exported to China
and we know from the last two videos that the way,
the way the China is keeping their currency from appreciating
because of this trade imbalance
is that they are going out there printing money
and using that Yuan to buy Dollar assets
And we see over here in (2006), (2007), (2008) major increase in US assets.
But what's little bit more interesting is 2009
we didn't have a huge increase. Its pretty large by any standard
but not large enough to offset the actual trade imbalance
So how did China keep its currency pegged.
Even better, lets actually look at ... because this isn't just the Chinese government.
These are just ownership of US assets by Chinese nationals.
We can actually look at the major foreign holders of treasury securities.
this actually comes from the Treasury's own website
and it tells us how much different Central Banks are,
how many treasury securities they are actually holding
You can see China is the biggest holder. It is the biggest holder
If you go to November of 2009 it has 929 billion dollars
This is the Peoples Bank of China has 929 billion dollars worth of US treasuries.
But whats interesting here it is the largest holder
but as we go from November of 2009 to November of 2010,
their holdings actually went down not by a ton.
they are still right around 900 billion but they went down.
So given the fact that we have this trade deficit,
given the fact they want to peg their currency
and they want to print money and go buy other people's assets,
how did this happen. How did the number of treasuries actually go down.
And actually how did they were able to reduce the amount of all US assets that they bought
Now the treasury answer is they don't have to just buy treasuries.
they could buy other US assets. But you go over here
we saw they didn‘t buy a ton of other US assets and a clue to what's happening here
and this isn't exactly what necessarily happening,
it is far more complicated than I can explain in one video.
But we do see other countries whose
US treasury holdings are increasing dramatically over the course of 2010.
In particular you see the United Kingdom.
You see the United Kingdom. Their holdings have grown
from 155 billion to 500 billion over the course of 2010 and this is relative.
United Kingdom does not have a significant trade imbalance
one way or the other with the United States
and we actually see, we actually see that
its currency really didn't change much over the course of 2010.
It‘s been about, it’s been about the same and
this looks more dramatic than it really is.
So the answer and it could be much more complicated,
and this is that China has decided to somewhat diversify
from buying US treasuries, and in particular US assets
and maybe they are diversifying to the pound sterling
maybe they are diversifying to the Euro and so they'll start buying,
they'll start buying, say, British assets.
But the British don't want their currency
to appreciate too much because then they will suffer a trade consequences.
Their goods will be too expensive
and so the British Central Bank will then want to, maybe,
-- so that their currency does not appreciate relative to the dollar --
they'll want to go and buy american assets.
And that's what it looks like its actually happening.
And maybe one other small point is that
the Chinese government has slowly allowed its currency to appreciate
but the appreciation isn't as dramatic as this chart makes it look.
This is 6.8 Yuan to the dollar at the beginning of 2010 to about 6.6.
We are not getting close to zero here. This is just from 6.8 to 6.6.
But over the last several years
they have slowly been allowing their currency to appreciate
but what's really happening is that they are diversifying away from dollar assets.
When they buy those other currencies
those people are going to wanna buy dollar assets to keep their currencies from moving too much.