Let's multiply 4 times 2012.
Actually, let's make it a little bit simpler, let's multiply 4 times 201.
Just to simplify things a little bit.
So 4 times 201.
So as we've seen in previous videos I'd like to write the larger number on top.
This is just one of many ways of tackling a calculation like this.
I'll write the 201 and then I'll write the 4 right below it, right below the ones place.
And so I have 201 times 4.
Now just like we did when we were multiplying a one digit times a two digit,
we do essentially the same process.
We first multiply 4 times the 1. Well, 4 times 1, we know, is equal to 4.
So we put a 4 right over there in the ones place.
Then we could multiply our four times the digit that we have in the tens place.
In this case we have a 0 in the tens place.
So 4 times 0, well that's just 0. 4 times 0 is 0, we put that 0 in the tens place right over here.
And then last, we have 4 times this 2 right over here.
And so 4 times 2 is equal to 8. And we put the 8 right over here.
And we got our answer! 804.
Now why did this work?
Well, remember when we multiplied 4 times 1, there was literally just 4.
(We've got that 4 right over here.)
Then we multiplied 4 times 0, that's 0 tens so we've got 0 tens right over here.
And then we multiplied 4 times 2, this was actually a 200, it's in the hundreds place.
So 4 times 200 is 800.
So, what we were essentially doing by writing in the right places,
we were saying: 4 times 201, that's the same thing as 4 times 200, which is 800,
plus 4 times 0 tens, which is 0 tens,
plus 4 times 1, whis is 4.
So 800 plus 0 plus 4 is 804.