Find the domain of f(x) is equal to the principal
square root of 2x - 8
So the domain of a function is just a set of all the possible
valid inputs into the function
or all of the possible values for which the function is defined
And when we look at how the function is defined right over here
It is a square root. The principal square root of 2x-8
It's only going to be defined when its taking the principal square root of a non-negative number
and so 2x-8 is only going to be defined when 2x-8 is greater than or equal to zero
It can be zero because the square root of zero is zero
It can be positive. But if this was negative then all of a sudden this principal
square root function which we are just assuming is just the "plain vanilla" one
for real numbers would not be defined
So this function definition is only defined when 2x-8 is greater than or equal to zero
and then we can say if 2x-8 has to be greater than or equal to zero we can solve this
inequality to see what it is saying about what x has to be
So if we add 8 to both sides of this inequality you get
(these eights cancel out) you get 2x is greater than or equal to 8
0 plus 8 is 8. And then you divide both sides by 2 since 2 is a positive number
you don't have to swap the inequality. So you divide both sides by two
and you get x needs to be greater than or equal to 4.
So the domain here is the set of all real numbers that are greater than or equal to 4
X has to be greater than or equal to 4
and we are done!