For the past year a travel agency has collected data
about the number of individual tickets that
it sells for its signature product - a Mediterranean cruise.
The monthly data on ticket sales is shown below.
What are the best and worst months for cruise sales?
So what they have given us
This diagram --
This is usually called a pie chart or pie graph
because it looks like a pie that is sliced up in pieces.
Sometimes this is called a circle graph,
but pie graph is much more common
And then they say its monthly ticket sales
So each of these slices represent the sales in a given month.
So for example, this blue slice over here represents the sales in January.
And they way that a pie chart is set up
each slice is bigger or smaller
depending on what fraction of the whole it represents.
So, for example, they're telling us in January they sold
18% of the total years' ticket sales, in January.
So if you add up all these percentages
it should add up to 100%
And not only do they tell us they sold 18%,
but the slice of this pie should be
18% of the area of the entire pie.
It is literally 18% of the pie.
If you were to eat this slice,
you would have eaten 18% of the pie.
Now with that out of the way,
let's think about their questions:
What are the best and worst months for cruise sales?
So the best month is obviously the month
where they sell, where they have the largest
percentage of their tickets were sold.
And actually, I started with January
and if you just ...
and this is what's neat about pie graphs.
You wouldn't even have to look at numbers.
January just jumps out as the biggest slice of pie
If you didn't even see the numbers,
if you couldn't even read,
and you just looked at this, and someone said
"what is the largest slice of pie?"
you would immediately say,
"Hey, this is the largest slice of pie right over there."
And so, that is actually the best month for cruise sales
cuz they sold 18%.
You see this 18% is larger than
all of the other percentages over here.
But it's clear, just by looking at the graph
this is the largest slice.
Now, what is the worst month
for cruise ticket sales?
Well, then we just have to find
the thinnest slice of pie.
And, if we look over here the slices of pie
get very thin out down here.
This is the summer, in June and July,
and in May.
But the smallest are actually July and June
And this is where the numbers become useful.
Because when you just look at it,
when you just eyeball it,
you're not sure, are these exactly the same,
or do they just look exactly the same?
This is where these numbers are valuable.
And based on the data they've given us,
it looks like these are tied for the worst in ticket sales.
In both of these months they sell
only 3% in each month.
So the worst months for cruise sales are
July and June.
July and June are tied for the worst.
The best is clearly January.
And then after January, the next best ...
they're not really asking us that,
but since we have the pie chart in front of us
might as well ask ourselves that.
What's the next best?
It looks like November is slightly better than December,
but in general, it's pretty clear that the winter months,
the winter months do much better in terms of cruise sales
than these over here.
I guess people are looking
to get away from the cold.