These are just perhaps just my favorite figures in the entire metropolitain museum of arts islamic collection.
I dont think I have ever seen anything quite like these.
No, well there really isnt anything else in the world like them. They are two really exceptional pieces carved and molded sculptural figures made out of stone they are extraordinary.
Stuco its the soft cement like material, its not stone, so its easy to carve.
Oh, its fantastic to carve you can mold it then carve it, and the wonderful thing is its light its easy to affix to walls.
Well even though its pretty soft stuff its survived beautifully these are in great condition.
They really are, probably one of the reasons they are in such good condition is they were from the desert.
I love them because they are so alive they are so dynamic, beautiful, bright, gorgeous and they also throw one of the great misconceptions about islamic art out the window.
Which is that Islamic art is anionic.
Right i had been taught that in Islamic cultures like in judan culture you dont represent the human body. You dont represent animals.
Well thats true. The conception comes from one of the heideds that says you basically shouldnt be making graven images. Not to different from the prohibitons in the new testament.
But what seems to happen is that very early on in Islamic art that prohibition seems to up held in masque and religious spaces, but in the secular all bets are off.