What I want to do now is figure out what's the minimum speed
that the car has to be at the top of this loop de loop in order to
stay on the track, in order stay in a circular motion, in order to not fall down like this
I think we can all appreciate that that is the most difficult part of the loop de loop
At least at the bottom half right over here
the track itself is actually providing the centripetal force to keep it going in a circle
But when you get to the top
you now have gravity that is pulling down on the car almost completely
and the car will have to maintain some minimum speed in order to stay in its circular path
Let's figure out what that minimum speed is
To help figure that out, we have to figure out what the radius of this loop de loop is
Actually it's not a perfect circle based on this little screen shot that I got here
it looks a little bit elliptical
but it looks like the radius of curvature right over here is actually
smaller than the radius of the curvature of the entire loop de loop
So if you made this into a circle, it would actually be even a smaller circle
But let's just assume for the sake of our argument right over here
this thing is a perfect circle, and if it was a perfect circle, let's think about
what that minimum velocity would have to be up here at the top of the loop de loop
So we know that the magnitude of your centripetal acceleration is going to be equal to
your speed squared divided by the radius of the circle that you are going around
Now at this point right over here at the top, which is going to be the hardest point
the magnitude of our acceleration, this is going to be 9.81 meters per second squared
And the radius we can estimate. I copied and pasted the car and it looks like
I can get it to stack on itself 4 times to get the radius of this circle right over here
I looked it up on the web and a car size is going to be about 1.5 m high
from the bottom of the tires to the top of the car
And so it looks like just eyeballing it based on these copying and pasting of the cars
the radius of this loop de loop here is 6 m
So this right over here is 6 m
Actually we could just in the variables
just to manipulate so we can solve v
We have v squared over r is equal to a
and then you multiply both sides by r, you get v squared is equal to a times r
And you take the principal square root of both sides
You get v = the principal square root of a times r
And then if we plug in these numbers
this velocity that we have to have in order to stay in the circle
is going to be the square root of 9.81 m/s squared times 6 m
and you can verify that. These units work out. Meters times meters is meter squared
per second squared
You take the sqrt of that. You get meters per second
Let's get our calculator out to actually calculate this
So we are going to get the principal square root of 9.81 times 6 m
It gives us--and here's our drumroll
7.67. I'll just round it three significant digits, 7.67 meters per second
Significant digits in our conversation
This is just a very very rough approximation, I am unable to measure this accurately at all
but I get a roughly 7.67 meters per second. Approximately 7.7 m/s
And just to give you a sense of how that translates into units that we're used to
when we're driving cars
I'll take 7.7 m/s. If you want to say how many meters you go in an hour
well, there's 3600 seconds in an hour
and if you want to convert that into kilometers
this will be in meters, you divide by 1000. 1 km is equal to 1000 m
These units will cancel out. You have meters, meters; seconds, seconds
You're left with km/h
Let's actually calculate this
And so we get our previous answer and we want
multiply it times 3600 to figure out how many meters in an hour
and then you divide by 1000 to convert to kilometers per hour
So you divide by a thousand
And we get 27.6 km / h
which is surprisingly slow. I would've thought that it would be much much much faster
but it turns out it doesn't have to be much much faster. Only 27.6 km/h
Now the important thing to keep in mind is
this is just fast enough at this point to maintain the circular motion
But if this were a perfect circle right over here, and you're going in exactly 27.6 km/h
you would not have much traction with the road. If so
the car might slip and might not be able to actually maintain its speed
So you definitely want your speed to be a good bit larger than this
in order to keep a nice margin of safety
in order to especially have traction with the actual loop de loop to maintain your speed
What I want to do in the next video is actually time the car
to figure out how long it takes to do this loop de loop
We're gonna assume that it's a circle
and we're gonna figure out how fast its actual average velocity was
over the course of this loop de loop