We are asked to plot (8,10). So the first number in this ordered pair, this is our x coordinate.
This tells us how far we move into the x direction.
It's a positive 8, so we move 8 in the x direction.
And then the second point or the second number in our ordered pair is 10.
That is our y coordinate; that tells us how far we move in the y direction.
Since it's positive we move up 10. So we move up 10 all the way over here.
And you could have thought about it either way. You could have said:
'Hey, look, this is our y coordinate, this is 10, so I could move up 10 and then my x coordinate is positive 8,
so I'll move 8 along the positive x axis or I'll move 8 to the right.
You see right over here, I have moved 8 to the right, 1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8
and I have moved 10 up: 1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10.
You might be tempted to move 8 up and then 10 to the right which would put you there,
but then you would've had the 2 numbers mixed up.
You would've had the x and y coordinates mixed up.
The 8 tells you how far to move in the horizontal direction, the 10 tells you how far to move in the vertical direction.
Let's do a couple more of these.
Plot (6,10). Well, once again, the first number in the ordered pair is the x coordinate,
how far we move in the x direction, so we move 6 to the right
and then the second number, the 10 tells us our vertical coordinate, our y coordinate.
So it's positive 10, so we move 10 up.
Let's do one more.
(5, 7)
So, my horizontal coordinate is 5, so I move 5 to the right
and then my vertical one is 7, or my y coordinate is 7. So I move 7 up: 1,2,3,4,5,6,7.
And as long as you remember which one is horizontal and which one is vertical,
or which one is the x coordinate and which one is the y, you should be fine!
You could say: 'Look, this is my y coordinate, 7.
So I'm going to move 7 up, and my x coordinate is 5, so I'm going to move 5 to the right
and we'll get you to that exact same point.
This specifies exactly one point in the coordinate plane.