Alright, so I'm Vi Hart and I'm here with Sal Khan
Sal: Hello
Vi: Yeah were talking about how we think about numbers
And what is the most natural way to think about them in our everyday lives
Sal: And Vi said that she was going to test me right now
Vi: I - Yeah, right, can I borrow the pen?
Sal: Yes, yes
Vi: I get to use the official pen!
Sal: No that's off screen
You need training Vi
Looks like a pizza
Vi: It's a triangle
Sal: Where's your test Vi?
You're diverging
Vi: I'm sorry
Alright, so here's the number line
Regular old number line
I'm going to start at one and go all the way up to a million
I'm giving you the pen now
And I'm going to ask: Where is 1,000?
Sal: Where is 1,000? Where is 1,000?
I see
I see what you're doing
Vi: So you can think of it logically
Yes, yes, So I'll tell you what went through my brain
My first reaction was to put 1,000 like, right over here
That's what I was tempted to do
And then my brain kicked in
My highly analytical mind