In the last video, we talked about the idea that
If I dug up a bone someplace and if I were to measure its
carbon 14 I found that it had half the carbon 14 that I would
expect to find in a living animal or plant. Then I would say hey, maybe 1 half life is gone by
or roughly for Carbon 14 one half life is 5,730 years. So I'd say maybe
its 5,730 years since this bone was part of a living animal, or it is roughly that old.
Now when I did that I made a pretty big assumption
Some of y'all have touched on this on you tube in the last video
is how do I know that, this this estimate I made is based on the
assumption that the amount of carbon 14 in the atmosphere
is roughly constant from when this bone was living to now
so the question is the amount of carbon 14 in the atmosphere
and in the water and in living plants and animals is it
constant and if it isn't constant how do you calibrate
your measurement so you can actually figure out how
much carbon 14 there is relative to living plants and
animals at that time.
The way that you can make that calibration, because it turns
out that it isn't perfectly constant, the way that you can
make that calibration, there are two ways, and I have
pictures here of both of them. One is to look at tree rings
and I am told that this will work up to about 10 thousand
years, up to ten thousand years old, I don't know of any
ten thousand year old trees, I don't think anyone does
but maybe there are some remains of old trees and you can
look at there tree rings. And I think most of us are
familiar with this idea that every year that a tree
grows it forms another layer of bark. And so you can look back
to that layer of bark, adjust for the half life
of carbon 14, and then figure out how much carbon 14
was there in the atmosphere at that period in time
and so it is kind of a record of the atmosphere up to
ten thousand years. If you want to go even further
back you can look at cave deposits. And the fancy word
for these cave deposits are speleothems, speleothems,
speleothems, you might be familiar with stalagmites,
those are the speleothems that are kind of coming out
of the bottom of the cave, or stalactites, those are the
speleothems, that are coming from the top of the cave
but the reason why these are useful is
these are formed by calcium carbonate, so they have carbon
in them and slowly over really ten thousand years
the water in the cave deposits that calcium carbonate
so it is a record of the fraction of carbon 14 in
some of those years. And you can go down to resolutions
of up to as small as ten years.
So this will give us pretty good estimates of over tens
of thousands of years (up to 50 thousand years) and
frankly carbon 14 isn't even useful beyond really 50
or 60 thousand years. So this gives us a pretty good,
pretty good, this gives us a good record of carbon 14
in the atmosphere. Assuming that it is fairly uniform
throughout the atmosphere
and all evidence suggests that and that uniformity
through the atmosphere goes into the water supply
and into living plants and animals. Now the other thing
and I looked into this a little bit, it actually turns
out that because we are spewing so much fossil fuel
right now, we are changing the amount or proportion
of carbon 14 much much faster than has happened
in other time periods. So just to answer the question
in probably really the last 50 years when the fossil
fuel use has really exploded we've really been changing
the proportion of carbon 14 relative to the other
isotopes of carbon. But anyway, hopefully that
rests some of your worries about the assumptions I
made in the last video about carbon 14 being relatively
constant. There are ways to look back at specific years
and figure out the relative amounts of carbon 14 so
it is a pretty good way of estimating how old living things
are especially things that are less than 50,000 years old