in baseball, in soccer,
sometimes sports announcers will look for
the turning point of the game
and the scene that we are looking
at is battle, not sport,in fact one of the most
important battles in ancient history
is at that particular turning point,
the moment when the great ruler of persia turns and flees
under the onslaught of the great Greek general Alexander.
Darius, the king of the Persians, has just ordered his troops to retreat.
So this tremendous tension of this moment, because we have this reversal of momentum,
we can feel the momentum moving in from the right, because
we can still see the Persian guard's spears facing towards the Greeks.
But just at that moment, the largest object in this mosaic, the chariot,
is being spun around, and the tension and the torsion that is required
for that is creating this is creating this tremendous sense of dynamism.
On the ground we see the wounded and the dying.
One of my favorite details is the reflection of one
of the Persian soldiers in his own shield. He
is looking at himself, fallen in battle, perhaps about to die.
I think another favorite is the horse that
is part of the team leading Darius' chariot.
Almost all four hooves are off the ground!
As it is being pulled to the left, its head turns to the right.
There is this almost frenetic quality to this image.
And you have a sense of confidence as you look at Alexander's face
as he heads towards Darius. Darius looks fearful as he gestures towards Alexander.
It looks to me as though Darius is almost pleading for the lives of his soldiers.
Well there is a look both of surprise and worry
and seeking compassion, I think that's exactly right.
Alexander is known, ultimately, for his compassion, at least towards Darius's family.
And Alexander is the great Greek general, the founder of an enormous empire.
Well, that's right, he not only unifies Greece,
but he will then move south into Egypt, he moves east into Persia, and he
gets actually Indus Valley itself. So he puts under Greece's control
an enormous area of the known world.
And all of these details are rendered in tiny pieces of stone and glass.
So we're looking at a mosaic that we think is based on
an ancient Greek painting. We hope
it's based on an ancient Greek painting,
because almost nothing of ancient Greek paintings survives, as it was talked about
how amazing Greek painting was.
It's true, when we think of Greek art, we think of Greek art, we think of Greek sculpture,
we mayhap think of Greek architecture, perhaps we
think of Greek vase painting, but it is right, in the ancient world, literature tells us
that the what the Greeks did better than anything was wall painting.
We just dont have any.
So mayhap this gives us some idea.
I do find it really interesting that the mosaic is almost
empty at the top, and is almost weighted down towards the bottom.
Especially when we remember that this is based on a painting that would have been on a wall.
And so this was intended to be seen vertically, at least initially, at least that's our best guess.
Our historians link this mosaic to a literary description of an ancient Greek painting by an artist
named Philoxanes. And in this literary source,
by Plinea Philoxanes, is said to have created a painting of the battle of Alexander and Darius.
But here's the problem, there were probably lots of paintings of that subject.
And we know for certain that there was a female artist who painted this subject.
And ancient Greece as well.
This is an incredibly important confrontation between these to generals,
between these two civilizations. I'm sure there were many more.
But this is what we have. This is what was found, and we have it because of
the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in 79 which preserved
under a layer of volcanic ash, the city of Pompeii.
Including this mosaic. This was found on the floor between to paristiles, that is
between two open courtyards that were surrounded by columns in the largest and most elaborately decorated
mansion in Pompeii, often called the House of the Fawn, after a bronze sculpture of a fawn that was found there.
And the mosaic itself is of extraordinary quality and so it's not surpriseing that we find it in such a lavish
environment as the House of the Fawn. There are apparently a million and a half pieces of
stone and glass that make up this mosaic. And the quality is not just in the fineness of the
material, but in the incredible naturalism of what we see here,
which is what the ancient Greeks were known for.
We have forms that even with these tiny pieces of stone we have a sense of
modeling, of the use of light and dark, to create a sense of 3d forms.
If we look at the horses, or the faces of the figures, we see the turn of the face
the anatomy of the body. And look at the foreshortening of the animals, for instance, of the horses.
That ancient Greek knowledge of the human body of how it moves through space, is so clear here.
And of course all this speaks to the Roman's regard for the achievement
of ancient Greek art. Sometimes seems as though everyone in Pompeii
wanted to imitate the ancient Greeks, to to own copies
of ancient Greek sculptures, ancient Greek paintings.
There was a real mania as in Rome itself for ancient Greek culture.