So, two words often get thrown around
and confused for one another,
and I thought we would take a few minutes
to clarify the differences between
salts and sodium.
And we know they're related,
but I want to get at exactly what the differences are
and how to, kind of, make sense of all the
numbers I hear about how much
I'm supposed to get every day.
So, I always think of, for salts,
of my salt shaker at home
that sits right next to my pepper shaker,
and whenever I have dinner,
I often reach for it,
and sometimes I think that I'm eating too much of it;
am I putting on more than I should?
I was thinking about this in terms of a spoon,
so if you have a spoon, let's say a teaspoon,
of salt.
And, let's say I took this teaspoon
of salt - here it is - and I weighed it
on a scale.
I would find that one teaspoon of salt
weighs about 6 grams.
Let me write that here.
So it's about 6 grams,
and 6g is the same as 6,000mg,
so that's the weight of one teaspoon of salt.
Now, the question comes up:
how much of that is from sodium?
So, to answer that, we know that
sodium chloride (NaCl) is [table] salt.
That is what salt is made of,
and if I imagine that there's nothing
in my salt shaker except for Sodium Chloride,
no ants have gotten in there, you know,
no other stuff besides the NaCl,
then I can assume that all 6,000mg of salt
is going to be either from the Sodium or the Chloride.
Now the 'Na', let me be totally clear,
is the Sodium part,
and the 'Cl' is the Chloride part,
that's what that means.
And actually all atoms have an atomic mass unit.
You can actually weigh the atoms
and line them up by size
by which is the smallest or largest in weight,
and sodium weighs out at about 23 units.
Chloride is about 35 units.
So, this is chloride right here and this is sodium.
If I [were] to sum it up, I would get 58 units.
Units is atomic mass units.
So, now that I have the total atomic mass units,
I can try to figure out what proportion
is from the sodium and what is from the chloride.
So, for the first part, which is sodium,
I can take the 23 units over the 58 unit total,
and the units cancel out,
and that works out to about 40%.
So about 40% of the weight of salt
is actually coming from the sodium part
The chloride part is the rest of it,
so I've got 35 units over 58 units,
and that is about 60%,
and again the units cancel out.
So, I know that, in salt,
40% of the weight is coming from sodium;
60% [is] from chloride.
Now, I have to go back to my teaspoon,
and in my teaspoon, I had 6g or 6,000mg.
So in that teaspoon, I can just multiply it
by these numbers to figure out
how much of the weight comes from sodium
and how much comes from the chloride.
So the sodium gives me 40% of 6,000,
which when you multiply those two numbers
you get 2,400mg of Sodium.
60% x 6,000mg = 3,600mg of chloride.
So now I know, in each teaspoon
I have 2,400mg of Sodium.
And now I've actually looked and I've seen
that there are recommendations on how much
sodium you should get in your diet
if you're not having any medical problems
in general,
so I'll call that a 'normal amount'.
This is a regular amount,
and this would be a low-salt diet.
If you're on a low-salt amount diet,
we'll figure out how much salt
you're supposed to take in,
or how much sodium you're supposed to take in.
And same for regular.
How much you should be taking if you're on a regular diet.
I'm going to do it both from a salt perspective
and from a sodium perspective.
So let's do the sodium perspective first.
So the normal amount that you should get,
actually let me write 'per day'.
Sodium, and over here we'll do salt.
So, the regular amount of sodium
that you should get per day,
is about 2,300mg
And on a low-salt diet,
you should get about 1,500mg.
Now, we know that one teaspoon has 2,400mg,
and 2,400 and 2,300 are pretty close,
so in my conversion, I'm going to assume that that
means I can have about 1 teaspoon per day of salt.
And on a low salt diet,
you're recommended to have no more than
about 1,500mg of sodium,
and if one teaspoon equals 2,400mg
then 1,500mg is about 2/3 of a teaspoon of salt.
So, when I look at a teaspoon of salt,
I just remember that if this is my teaspoon,
that if I'm on a regular,
I can basically eat one of them each day,
not each meal, but each day,
and if I'm on a low-salt diet,
I can only fill it up about 2/3 of the way,
and I'd have to stop there,
because that's the limit of sodium
that I'm recommended.