In the last series of examples we go into month 2 with $100 of cash
and the way we set up the example we spend $200 in month 2
and what we've been doing so far is saying
"Oh! That gets us to a cash balance of negative $100 at the end of month 2"
It's a little unrealistic, I kept it simple here and allowed us to have a negative cash balance
just for simplicity, but usually you will not see a negative cash balance.
The fact that you have a negative cash balance and you're allowed to operate
essentially means that someone is lending you money,
so to make this example a little more realistic,
let's imagine a situation where in month 2 you only have $100.
The person you are catering for, that you're buying those $200 of supply for,
they're not going to pay you until next month, so you tell the people that you need to buy stuff from
"Look,I only have $100 dollars, I have this customer, I'm doing thec atering for him this month.
Can I pay $100 for it to you this month, and then maybe pay another $100 to you next month?"
And let's say that they agree to that. So on month 2, on a cash basis,
instead of spending $200, you're actually spending $100.
and then in month 3, you'll also spend $100.
Now this will change your cash accounting numbers, this will now be -$100, and this would now be $500.
but the more important thing is how this can be accounted for in Accounts Payable.
The fact that you essentially told your vendors, "even though you gave me $200 worth of stuff,
I'm only going to pay you $100 now and I'm going to give you $100 later"
That means that you've increased your Accounts Payable by $100.
You've increased this liability that you owe things to other people.
So let me add Accounts Payable over here.
I'll just write A period, so I don't have to write the whole thing.
Accounts Payable
And going into the period, you didn't have any Accounts Payable,
and then now that you're essentially borrowing $100 from your vendors,
you're allowing to push back when you pay them,
you now have an Accounts Payable of $100.
and I'm not going to work it through on all of this stuff over here.
But let's see how that would have affected the income statesments and the balance sheet.
So over here you had another liability.
Accounts Payable is a liability
So you have an Accounts Payable liability of $100
sorry, at this point we had no Accounts Payable liability
and then after the end of the month
we have an Accounts Payable liability of $100.
We owe $100 to our vendors.
And our cash is now at $0
So notice, it still does not change our Equity.
We essentially added $100 cash, and we added a $100 liability
They cancel out
Now if you take this part over here all of the assets are $400,
$400-$100 in Liabilities still gets you to $300 in Equity.
But now the reconciliation is to go from $100 in cash to $0 in cash.
We're not allowing ourselves to go negative.
And the reason that we can do that is that we actually have a source of cash.
So let me erase that and then let's add a line right over here
so we can say Accounts Payable increase
and now this is a source of cash.
And it might not be obvious. We're increasing a liability.
But it's a source of cash because we don't have to use our own cash.
Increasing the Accounts Payable is allowing us to not use all of our cash
So we have an Accounts Payable increase of $100.
So this is a source of cash, so now the cash from operations:
$200 net income-$400+$100
This whole thing is now -$100 cash from operations
so you start with $100, you use $100
Our ending cash is now 0, and it all works out.