Plot the ordered pair (6, -8) into the coordinate plane.
So this is the coordinate plane over here:
This is the horizontal axis over here is the x axis
The vertical axis here is the y axis
and the convention when we get an ordered pair like this
is the first coordinate is the x coordinate
and the second coordinate is the y coordinate
So they're telling us we have an x coordinate of 6
x coordinate of 6.
that means we count up 6 on the x axis
So let's count up 1, I can even write down 1
then we have 2, that's right there
then we have 3, then we have 4, then we have 5
and then we have moved up 6 along the x axis
we started at the origin
at (0,0), that's the origin
then we moved 6 to the right
that's this part right over here [indicating 6 in (6,8)]
Now our y coordinate is -8
that means we move down 8 in the vertical direction
so we can see it right over here
I'll just do every 2.
So this is down 1, this right here is -2
-3, this right here is -4
-5, -6, -7, -8
So we move to the right 6 and down 8
we move to the right 6
then we move down 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, and 8
and we are right over there
so that is the point (6, -8)
you can also move at it this way
so you move 6 there
so we will be along this line here
and then you can go and then the y coordinate is -8
and you say we will be along this line over here
and the place they intersect is this coordinate
the way i like to think of it move 6 to the right
move along the x axis
and then move along in the y axis
so you go down 8