I want to write this expression here as a decimal
and the first question that might pop into your head is,
Do I multiply four times a thousand, then add three,
then multiply a thousand, then add sixty-seven,
then multiply by one over a thousand?
Or, do I do the multiplication first?
To answer that question, we just have to remind ourselves
about order of operations.
Order of operations, if you have a bunch of multiplication and addition in a row like this,
you will do the multiplication first.
So you will do the multiplication first.
Let me put some parentheses here to remind us of that.
So let's figure out what each of these expressions in the parentheses actually represent.
What's four times one million? Well, that's four million.
What's three times one thousand? Well, that's three thousand. Three thousand.
What is sixty-seven times one-thousandth?
There's a bunch of ways of thinking about this.
Actually, let me, let me write them all over here.
Well, I'll do the most obvious one right over here:
sixty-seven times one-thousandth is sixty-seven thousandths.
And we can represent this literally as sixty-seven thousandths,
or we could represent this as sixty over a thousand plus seven over one thousand,
and what's sixty over a thousand?
Well, sixty over a thousand is six hundredths.
Six hundredths. And let me put that in a different color.
Six hundredths, seven thousandths.
So you can view this as sixty-seven thousandths,
or you could view this as six hundredths, and seven thousandths.
Either way, let's add all of these things together.
So, we have four million. So the four in the millions place
literally represents four million.
Then we have no hundred-thousands, we have no ten-thousands,
but then we have three thousand. So the three is in the thousands place.
Put a comma here so we can keep track of things.
And then we have no hundreds, we have no tens,
we have no ones, we don't even have any tenths,
but we do have some hundredths. We have six hundredths. We have six hundredths.
And then we have some thousandths. We have seven thousandths.
So let me put that seven in the thousandths, in the thousandths place.
So we could read this as:
four million, three thousand, six hundredths, and seven thousandths.
Or, we could read it as:
four million, three thousand, and sixty-seven thousandths.
Sixty-seven thousandths.