Let's review our intuition of what a limit even is.
So, let me draw some axes here.
Let's say this is my y axis, so try to draw my vertical line
That right over there is my y axis
and let's say this is my x axis.
I'll focus on the first quadrant, although I don't have to...
Let's say this right over here is my x axis and let me draw a function.
So let's say my function looks something like that.
It could look like anything suitable, so this is y is equal to f of x
and just for the sake of conceptual understanding
I'm going to say it's not defined at a point.
I didn't have to do this, you could find the limit as X approaches a point
where the function actually is defined,
but it becomes that much more interesting, at least for me
where you start to understand where a limit might be relevant
when a function is not defined at some point.
So, the way I've drawn it this function is not defined
when x is equal to c
Now, the way that we've though about a limit is,
what does f(x) approach as x approaches c?
So, let's think about that a little bit.
When x is a reasonable bit lower than c,
f(x) for our function that we just drew is right over here
y is equal to f(x)
when x gets a little bit closer, then our f(x) is right over there
when x gets even closer; It's really almost at c but not quite c
then our f(x) is right over here
and the way we see it,
we see that our f(x) seems to be that as x gets closer to c it looks like our f(x) is getting closer to some value.
right over there, I'll even draw it with a more solid line.
and that was only the case
when x was getting closer to c from the left,
from values less than c.
But what happens when we get closer and closer to c
from values of x that are larger than c,
well when x is over here, f(x) is over here.
That's what f(x) is
when x is over there, x gets a little bit closer to c
our f(x) is right over there,
when x is just very slightly larger than c,
then our f(x) is right over there
and you see once again it seems to be approaching
that same value
and we call that value, the value f(x) seems to be approaching as x approaches c,
we call that value L, or the limit
and we'd call the limit, we don't have to call it L all the time.
and the way that we would write that mathematically is,
the limit of f(x) as x approaches c is equal to L
and this is a fine conceptual understanding of limits
and it really will take you very far,
and you are ready to progress and start taking a lot of limits.
But this isn't a very mathematically rigourous definition of limits.
This sets us up for the intuition,
in the next few videos we will introduce
a mathematically rigourous definition of limits.
That will allow us to do things.
Like prove that the limit as x approaches c
truly,
is equal to L.