In the last video we talked about how humans over time
have been getting better and better, getting more Calories out of a given unit of land.
And one thing I want to emphasize, in the last video
these numbers that I came up with, I picked these numbers
to make the map fairly simple and to give you a general idea,
I don't want you to think that what a square kilometre
can support today is exactly 1,000 people.
It depends hugely on what the land is like,
how much of the land you're actually using for agriculture,
what crops you're planting etc. etc. ..
how the people are living, how many Calories they need ...
the whole point of the last video was just to give you a framework
that, wow, there is this upper bound based on how much productivity you actually get from the land.
Now, what we want to think about in this video
that was kind of the last video with this axes right here
gettin more and more out of the land,
but what I want to think about in this video,
is how did humans through different technologies,
how do we get by doing less and less of the labout for getting those Calories out of the land.
Obviously, you just don't have land and things spontaneously grow
like I guess would happen in the wild,
but if you're doing agriculture, you need to put some energy into the land,
you've got to work the land.
And so what we have over here in this chart,
and this chart is derived from inforamtion from this book right over here,
this is Energy And Society, and what we want to think about here
is the different ways that humans have gone about to till soil.
So not if you're going to think about the total process
or the total energy required to grow a certain crop,
what we're just going to focus is one step of the agricultureal process
and that is tilling the soil.
And, in case you're like me, and you have never worked on a farm,
that's one thing that I would like to change one day, actually go through that process,
but tilling the soil is kind of turnig it up
so you get the nutrients from the bottom layers to the surface,
you dig, you bury all of the remains from the last harvest,
you bury all of the weeds so that they die
and you also kind of get air in the soil
what is does is it essentially prepares the soil for the next agricultural cycle.
So it's a process that humans have been doing since antiquity.
And what I want to do in this video is to think about the different ways to do it
and how much energy is required to do it.
And we're going to think about the enrgy in two ways,
how much of that energy comes from humans,
and how much of that energy comes from things other than humans.
So just as an example. When we talk about human power,
we're talking about someone literally hand-ploughing the field.
So this woman right over here is literally, she has a sort of cart
that's digging up the soil behind her.
When we talk about the oxen power, we're talking about the oxen doing most of the work.
They're the ones dragging this plough which is digging up all of the soil
and this gentleman has to kind of be there to supervise.
But this still is fairly an intense labour that this gentleman is doing right over here.
And when we talk about the tractors, we're talking about a scenario like this,
where the tractor is doing most of the work of actually digging up,
dragging this plough behind it and digging up all of the soil.
And from this book right over here, that's where we've got these numbers from,
I'll tell you which numbers I've got from them
and which numbers I kind of reason through
because I wasn't fully comfortable with the numbers they had.
But these are their numbers. That if your human power
to till 1 hectar of soil will take 400 hours.
Oxen power, this should be a pair, not pari, a pair of oxen, 65 hours.
6-HP tractor 25 hours.
50-HP tractor 4 hours.
And in case you are wondering what is a hectare of soil,
it is literally a plot of land, a hectare of soil,
a hectare of land I should say,
is a plot of land that is 100 m by 100 m
and it's roughly equal to 2.5 acres, not exactly 2.5 acres,
it's like 2.47... something, but roughly 2.5 acres.
When you think about how many hours to essentially dig up all of the soil
for a plot of land 100 by 100 metres.
So what we have over here, so clearly human takes a lot longer,
oxen make it a little bit faster,
6-HP tractor even faster, 50-HP tractor, very powerful tractor, even faster than that.
Now, this column right over here is the amount of energy
required to actually produce and maintain the machinery used.
So this is a very unintuitive thing. For example, whenever you think about
the amount of energy to plough this land over here,
you tend to think: ok, this individual is going to expend a lot of her energy,
you don't think about the amount of energy required to actually maintain the tool,
to build the tool that she is using, in this case a hand plough,
and then to maintain that as she does it.
And so this estimate, I've got these two from these fellows right over here,
they're actually more and there might be a gal?,
but it's about 6,000 kilocalories, and this is kilocalories for lower case c.
And one thing I wanna emphasize here,
1 kcal is equal to 1 Calorie with a capital C
which is the same thing as 1,000 calories with a lower case c.
We talked about this in the last video,
but when people talk about food calories
they are really talking about the Calorie with the capital C
or you can say they talk about kilocalories.
So your candy bar, 200 Calories, they are talking about this right over here,
in Chemistry class you talk abou the amount of energy to rise a gramme of water 1°C,
you're talking about these calories here.
So all of these numbers in this chart right over here,
you can either use them with this unit, kcal, kilocalories,
or Calories with the capital C, they're essentialy the same units that we used in the last video,
and these are the same numbers that you are used to from a kind of a dietary calorie point of view.
So for example, 6,000 Calories, that's about how much a typical male would expand in 3 days,
so this is to maintain it over the course of these 400 hours in the case of the hand plough,
and the total amount of Calories that were needed to make the plough,
devided by the total number of hours.
So whatever fraction of the plough's live is being used here,
you used that fraction right over here to put this 6,000 Calories.
But needless to say, for at least the plough, for the kind of the ...
either the human or the oxen scenario, this isn't a significant amount of the total Calories.
So obviously, if you are doing either with human power or oxen power,
you are not usin any gasoline, you are not using any petroleum,
in all of these scenarios we're going to assume,
that someone has 10 working hours in the day.
And that right over here this is kind of a measure of how hard that person's work is.
I kind of estimated these numbers here,
they are slightly different than what the original numbers were in this book right over here.
But they are saying: look, if you are actually walking along using this hand plough,
that is actually very vigorous activity.
It is going to require about 400 Calories per hour to do this type of activity,
you do it over 10 hours, it's going to require 4,000 Calories
just to do it over 10 hours, and then we are assuming that the rest of the day
you are going to walk around, maybe you cook dinner, eath breakfast, sleep some of it,
we are assuming the other 14 hours of the day are going to be about 100 Calories per hour,
and so this is the total if someone were to using this techique
work for a total of 10 hours, this is how many Calories they would consume in the day.
You can see this is the most labour-intensive,
so it looks like that they would consume the most Calories per day,
these two are the least labour-intensive, you are sitting on the tractor,
although that still requires more Calories than sleeping or watching TV,
and so that is the number of Calories they would consume.
Now this right over here, this is the interesting number, or one of the really interesting numbers,
based on all of these assumptions, this is the total human input in Calories to do this task,
to till this 1 hectare of soil.
So over here, you are using 5,400 Calories a day,
it you are working 10 hours per day and it requires 400 working hours,
you are going to be working 40 days, right, 400 divided by 10,
40 days times 5,400 Calories per day, it is going to take a human,
just the human part, not even thinking about the 6,000 Calories necessary to maintain and make that plough,
the human is going to expend 216,000 Calories to till, to plough that 1 hectare of land.
And if you add the other 6,000 into for the actual plough,
and you can debate what this number should be,
because it is not a significant number compared to this,
you get about 222,000 total Calories.
When you go to the oxen situation requiring fewer hours
and each hour requires fewer ... a little less Calories,
this is still labour-intensive, but not as labour-intensive as what this women right over here is doing.
So at daily base is she using a little bit fewer Calories,
but since you are only doing 6.5 days of this, 65 hours divided by 10,
you have significantly reduced the number of Calories, the total number of Calories
that the human need to put into this task.
Now, there still is other energy being done.
Now all of a sudden the oxen have got involved.
And if you assume that each ox consumes about 20,000 Calories a day,
and you have 2 of them, so 40,000 Calories per day for just to feed the oxen,
and you are going to do that for 6.5 days, 65 divided by 10,
the oxen are going to consume 260,000 Calories to do this task.
So the total energy input here now has gone up.
So this is an interesting phenomenon that is going on right over here.
What the human is putting in as we get better and better technology goes down substantially,
216,000 and 33,000, and we will se that with the tractor that goes down even more,
but the total energy, if you include the amount of energy that the oxen have to put in,
or if you include the amount of energy to do the gasoline that has to be used for the tractor,
the total amount of energy is going up to plough that field,
but the human energy goes down dramatically.
Now, the last thing I want to highlight here, and this is where my numbers
that depart a little bit or fairly significantly from this original study right over here, this original estimate,
is the machinery input on the tractors.
So if you look this up, you can google search it, they have much larger numbers here,
but I did a little research and it looks like for most petroleum, combustion based engines or vehicles
roughly 20% of the total energy that is used in the field,
20% of that energy is used for the actuall production and maintenance of that veihicle over its life.
So what we did over here is we said: ok, for a 6-HP tractor, I used their number,
we are going to have to use 25 hours to do it,
it is going to use this much petroleum,
assuming that is uses 23.5 litres of gas or petroleum over 24 hours,
and I just put 20% for that number for saying
how much energy had to be used to maintain that vehicle over that amount of time,
and if you think about what fraction of this vehicle's life that 25 hours represents,
that fraction times the total amount of energy required to produce that.
So remember, these things are made out of metal, they had to be made in furnaces,
so just pruducing a vehicle requires a lot of energy,
and so this right over here is 20%, and I just used the rule of thumb,
for most petroleum or combustion based vehicles, the 20% of the total energy expenditure
over the course of that vehicle's life is roughly equal to the amount of energy used to produce that vehicle.
But either way, you go all of the way over here, the human has to spend less Calories sitting on the vehicle,
so they spend less Calories per day,
and then the total human input right over here for the 6-HP tractor,
it is going to take them 2.5 days, 25 hours, 10 hours a day,
is going to be 8,500 Calories. But of course, you have the petroleum used,
and then some estimate of the amount of energy used to produce that tractor,
and you are just taking the fraction over that 25 hours,
you are not taking the entire life of that 6-HP tractor.
To produce this 6-HP tractor this number would be much larger if you talk about the total number of energy,
we are just taking this small fraction of its life that we are using right over here,
same thing for the 50-HP tractor.
But anyway, if you look at it, this is the really interesting thing,
humans, by going from human power all the way to a 50-HP tractor,
you are getting almost a factor of 200 improvement
in terms of how little energy has to be put in by the human to till that land.
But you actually get a total increase if you factor in things like the petroleum,
and then definitely the amount of energy to actually produce that machine.
So anyway, hopefully you found that interesting.
I find this kind of ... it's something that you don't think a lot about. How much energy input has to be put in.
And often times we only think about the human energy input,
but we are not thinking about the energy input from other things like oxen.