Let's say that the settlement price for delivering one thousand pounds of
Apples one October Twentieth -- which we’re going to assume is one year
From now -- Let's assume that it's two hundred dollars. Let's also assume
That the current market price for a thousand pounds of apples is
Also two hundred dollars. So that future settlement price
Is the same as the current market price. And we're also going to assume, like the last
Example, that these apples that we have never go bad. They're just things that --
They'd never rot or anything.
So there as good in year as they are right now
Let’s also assume that above and beyond the assumptions of the last video
That we can borrow and sell apples in the current market we can actually
Short apples. And when I borrow -- So I go to someone who's got a thousand pounds
Of apples who don't really see any need for them over the next year. And I say, “Can I borrow
Those apples?” and what I do is I say I’ll borrow those apples I'll sell
Those apples in the market today and of the interest that I’d get
On those apples, I'm going to give you one percent -- the person who
Actually owns the apples and that person says, “Oh sure. Why not?"
That way I actually get some money on my apples that I had no intention of using for a
Year and that is the borrower and seller will get four percent
Net. I'll get four percent net on the apples
So given that this the reality of what could I do once again to make a
Risk-free profit? Well, as you can imagine,
I can borrow and sell the apples for a year so let me write this down.
I'm going to borrow and sell
One thousand pounds of apples. One thousand pounds
Of apples. So, if I just borrow it today and sell it,
Today's market price is two hundred dollars for a thousand pounds.
So I’m going to get -- I’m going to get two hundred
I'm going to get two hundred dollars. Now on top of
That, what I want to do is agreed to be the buyer
I want to a agree to be the buyer on this futures contract.
So let me write that down. Agree you could say the go
Long on this futures contract or agree to be buyer.
To be buyer on the futures
Contract. On the futures contract. So I'm
Agreeing, a year from now, to buy a thousand pounds of apples
For two hundred dollars. So let’s fast forward, let’s fast forward
One year. So what's happened? So of the two hundred dollars I got
From shorting the apples, I got five percent on that. But I had to give
One percent to the person I borrowed the apples from. So I’m getting four
Percent net. Four percent on two hundred dollars is
Eight dollars. So I now have and I now have
Two hundred and eight dollars because I got but four percent interest
It was two hundred and ten. I gave two dollars to the person who lent me
The apples. Now I can use two hundred dollars of that
To essentially uphold my part of the future's contract
To buy the apples for two hundred dollars, for that agreed upon price.
So two hundred dollars -- two hundred dollars
To buy apples. – to by apples -- And I know I can do this
Regardless of what the market price is, because that was that was the delivery price on the
Futures contract. So now I have eight dollars net. Now I
Have eight dollars net. And those apples that I’ve just
Bought, those thousand pounds of apples, I can then use those apples to
Return it to the person that I borrowed the apples from. So they got their apples
Back, and they got that one percent on the two hundred dollars over the
Course the year and I made a risk-free eight dollars.
So if you think about it once again, this is kind of setting a lower bound on what
The actual settlement price on the futures contract is. I should
Not be able to make this risk-free profit. If it's available, then people will
Do it. And what it'll do, it will increase demand to be
The buyer here. So this price should go up. And it would increase
Supply on the selling side here. And so maybe this price
Over here would go down.