Let's say that both Ben's Shoes and Jason's Shoes
are publicly traded companies
All that means is that
both of their shares are traded on exchanges
Maybe it's the Nasdaq or the New York Stock Exchange or some other exchange
And going price on those exchanges:
The last closing price for Ben's stock was $21.50/share
The last closing price for Jason's stock was $12.00/share
What I want to explore in this video,
and probably next video, is
what is that saying for
what the market thinks of these businesses are worth
So in both of these situations
they have 10,000 shares
Remember the shares are split of the owner's equities
not the split of the assets
It's the split of just the equity part right over here
So if theshareholders are wiling to pay
$21.50/share for Ben's stock,
and there are 10,000 shares in Ben's company
So you take $21.50 times 10,000 shares
gives us a market cap of $215,000
What this says is look
if each of those 10,000 slices of the equities
are worth $21.50
then the entire equity portion is going to be
what the market is valuing it at $215,000
And this calculation, this multiplication of
market price per share times the number of shares
this is called the market cap
Short for market capitalization
the market cap of the company
And all it is, is
what is market valuing the equity part
of Ben's company worth
Let's do the same thing for Jason's company
You have $12/share times 10,000 shares
That gives us $120,000 market cap
So the market is telling us that
even though on the books Ben's equity
based on how he values his assets and liabilities
is $135,000
The market is actually valuing this at $215,000
And in the next video we'll think about
how the market is actually valuing the business
And in the case of Jason's business
Instead of $35,000 of equity
just straight up from what's on the books
the market is valuing this piece right here at $120,000
So hopefully that gives you a little sense of
One, what shares are share of
They're the share of owner's equity
and not of the asset
also gives you a good sense of what market cap is
It's the market's value of the owner's equity
And notice in both cases, and it's usually the case
it's going to be a different number than the book value
the number that's actually on the books