We are told that triangle ABC has perimeter p and inradius r
and then they want us to find the area of ABC in terms of p and r
so we know that perimeters are just the sum of the sides of the triangle
or how long of length will have to be if you wanna to go around the triangle
and let's just remind ourselves what the inradius is
if we take the angle bisectors of each of these vertexes
each of these angles right over here
so bisectors that right over there
and then bisector that right over there
this angle is going to be equal to that angle
and then this angle is going to be equal to that angle there
and the point where those angle bisectors intersect
that right over there is our incenter
and it is equal distant from all of the three sides
and the distance from those sides that's the inradius
so let me draw the inradius
so when you find the distance between the point and the line
you wanna drop a perpendicular
so this length right over here is the inradius
this length right over here is the inradius
and this length right over here is the inradius
and if you want you could draw a incircle here with the center at the incenter
and with the radius r and that circle would look something like this
we don't have to actually draw for this problem
so you could draw a circle that looks something like that
then we call that the incircle
so let's think about how we can find the area here
especially in terms of this inradius
well the cool thing about the inradius is this it looks like the altitude
well this looks like the altitude for this triangle right over here
triangle A let's label the center let's call it I for incenter
so r is this r right over here is the altitude of triangle AIC
this r is the altitude of triangle BIC
and this r which we didn't label
that r right over there is the altitude of triangle AIB
and so we could find the area of each of those triangles in terms of both r and their basis
maybe if we sum up the area of all the triangles
we can get something in terms of our perimeter and our inradius
so let's just try to do this
so the area of the entire triangle the area of ABC is going to be equal to
and I will color code this
this is going to be equal to the area of AIC
so that's what I am shading here in magenta is going to be euqal to the area of AIC
plus the area of BIC which is this triangle right over here
I will show you that in a different color I have already used blue
so let me do that in orange
plus the area of BIC so that's this area right over here
so plus the area of BIC and then finally plus the area
I will do this in let's see I will use this pink color
plus the area of AIB that is the area AIB
take the sum of the areas of these three triangles
you've got the area of the larger triangle
Now AIC the area of AIC is going to be equal to one half base times height
so this is going to be one half the basis of the length of AC one half AC
times the height times this altitude right over here
which is just going to be r times r
that's the area of AIC
and then the area of BIC is going to be one half the base which is BC
times a height which is r
and then plus the area of AIB this one right over here is going to be
one half the base which is the length of the side AB
AB times a height which is oneeagain r
and over here we can fetch out one half r for all of these terms
and you get one half r times AC plus BC plus AB
and I think you see where this is going
plus that's the different shade of pink plus AB
Now what is AC plus BC plus AB
well that's going to be the perimeter p if you just take the sum of the sides
that is the perimeter of p and it looks like we are done
the area of our triangle of ABC is equal to one half times r times the perimeter
which is kind of a neat result
one half times the inradius times the perimeter of the triangle
or sometimes we will see it written like this is equal to r times p over s
oh sorry p over 2
and this term right over here the perimeter divided by 2
is sometimes called semi perimeter and sometimes it is denoted by s
so sometimes you will see the area is equal to r times s
where s is the semi perimeter it's the perimeter divided by 2
I firstly like this way a little bit more
because I remember that p is the perimeter
this is useful because obviously now if someone gives you inradius and a perimeter
you can figure out the area of a triangle
or someone gives you the area of the triangle and the perimeter
you can get the inradius of it
if given any two of these variables you can always get the third
so for example if someone if this was a triangle right over here
which is the most famous of the right triangles
if I have a triangle that has length 3 4 and 5
we know this is a right triangle
you can verify this from the pythagorean theorem
and someone says what is the inradius of this triangle right over here
well we can figure out the area pretty easily
we know that this is a right triangle 3 squared plus 4 squared is equal to 5 squared
so the area is going to be equal to 3 times 4 times one half
so 3 times 4 times one half is 6
and the perimeter here is going to be equal to 3 plus 4 which is 7 plus 5 is 12
and so we have the area so let's write this
the area is equal to one half times the inradius times the perimeter
so here we have 12 is equal to one half times the inradius times the perimeter
so we have oh sorry we have 6 let me write this
the area 6 6 is equal to one half times the inradius times 12
and so in this situation one half times 12 is 6
6 is equal to 6r divide both sides by 6 you get r is equal to 1
so if you want to draw the inradius for this one which is kind of a neat result
so let me draw some angle bisectors here
this 3-4-5 right triangle has inradius of 1
so this distance equals this distance which is equal to this distance
which is equal to 1 just kind of a neat result