Find the value of 5 to
the third power.
Let me rewrite that.
We have 5 to the third power.
Now, it's important to remember,
this does not
mean 5 times 3.
This means 5 times itself three
times, so this is equal
to 5 times 5 times 5.
5 times 3, just as a bit of a
refresher so you realize the
difference, 5 times 3-- let
me write it over here.
5 times 3 is equal to
5 plus 5 plus 5.
So when you multiply by 3,
you're adding the number to
itself three times.
When you take it to the third
power, you're multiplying the
number by itself three times.
So 5 times 3, you've seen
that before, that's 15.
But 5 to the third power, 5
times itself three times, is
equal to-- well, 5 times 5 is
25, and then 25 times 5 is
125, so this is equal to 125.
And we're done!