A common house spider has 8 eyes. If a spider is looking at you with its 2 front eyes and 3 of its other eyes, what fraction of its eyes are looking at you?
And just to show that we're not making this stuff up, these are actual pictures of spiders and you see in each of these pictures that they have 8 eyes.
Here in this one there&#x27;s an eye over here: 1, 2, 3, 4 ,5, 6, 7, 8. And i&#x27;ve never even realised that this is quite creepy.
But anyway, let's focus on the problem:
So it's looking at you with 2 of its front eyes. 2 of its 8 eyes.
So the 2 front eyes represent what fraction of the eyes? Well it represents 2 of the 8 eyes.
You could look at it right over here. You have 8 eyes and 2 front eyes. That&#x27;s 1 and 2. 2 of the 8.
And it says it's also looking at us with 3 of its other eyes. So it's also looking at us with 3 of the 8 eyes.
So you could image, that might be that one, that one and that one.
So this is really about adding fractions. This about adding 2/8 of something to 3/8 of something.
So what fraction of its eyes are looking at us?
Well it&#x27;s still going to be a fraction of 8. 2 + 3 over 8.
Which is going to be equal to 5&#x2F;8 of the eyes. 5 out of the 8 eyes are looking at us and we see that right over here: 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
5 out of a total of 8 eyes are looking at us in a fairly creepy way.