Welcome back. We're doing problem number ten.
And I just drew the figure. They said a right,
circular cylinder with radius 5 and height 4 has volume v.
So what's the volume of this?
The volume of the cylinder-they give you the formula actually
but it's just the area of the base,
or the area of the top of the cylinder times its height.
So it's pi r squared, where the radius is 5,
so that's pi times 25--5 squared-- times the height, times 4.
So v is equal to 100 pi. Fair enough.
Then they say, in terms of v, what is the volume of
a right circular cylinder with radius 5 and height 8?
Oh, you see I didn't even have to do all this
because now this new cylinder is just like this cylinder,
right? But instead of having height 4 it has height 8.
See I didn't have to know that formula, oh my god.
I wanted to draw the ellipse.
So this new cylinder looks something like this,
although I'm not drawing it really to scale,
but I think you get the point.
The new cylinder you can kind of just--
then new cylinder has height 8.
So what, the new cylinder is twice the size of
the previous cylinder, right?
The previous cylinder had height 4, radius 5.
This new cylinder has radius 5, height 8.
So the new cylinder is going to be twice the volume, right?
The volume for this is v, so the volume for the new one is--
it's twice as high so it's going to have twice the volume--
so 2v.So it's answer B.You didn't even have to know all this.
See you can go on the wrong track very quickly.
Although if you did it that way,
you would get the right answer. Problem number eleven.
If k, n and r are integers, let k be defined--
let k diamond, n, r-- be defined to be true only if--
so k diamond is true if n is less than k,which is less than r
Then they tell us that minus 2 diamond n, 0 is true.
Which of the following could be a possible value of n?
So let's just translate this into this world, right?
So this is true. Minus 2 diamond n, 0 is true.
So that means that we just pattern match, right?
K is minus 2, n is n, and r is 0. So our n is just n.
So that means n is less than k.
K is minus 2, which is less than our r. Our r is 0.
So n is less than minus 2, which is less than 0.
I mean obviously minus 2 is less than 0.
So which of the following could be a possible value of n?
So they give us three choices.
I is minus 3, II is minus 1 and then III is positive 3.
Well , which of these numbers is less than negative 2?
Positive 3 isn't. Negative 1 is greater than negative 2,
so all we're left with is choice I.
Not too hard of a problem right? A.It just looks complicated.
Image. Invert colors. Problem twelve.
If 20% of x is equal to 80% of y--
so immediately my brain converts that to decimals.
So 0.20x is equal to 0.80y.
Which of the following expresses y in terms of x?
So we want y in terms of x, so let's solve for y.
We divide both sides by 0.80.
So y is equal to 0.20 divided by 0.80 times x. Right?
I switched them around too, right?
I switched the two sides, but I divided both sides by 0.8,
that's all I did. So y is equal to-- what's 0.2 over 0.8?
Well that's the same thing as 2 over 8, or 0.25x.
Or, y is 25% of x. And that is choice B. Next problem.
It's a very cold day today. My feet are cold.
I should go do a run, run a hill or something.
All right. Problem number thirteen.
If x, y and z-- this seems familiar, anyway- if x, y and z
are positive integers such that the value of x plus y is even
and the value of x plus y squared plus x plus z is odd,
which is the following is true?
And they give a bunch of choices.
So this is actually quite interesting.
So let's see what we can say. Can we say that x is odd?
That's choice A, x is odd. If x plus y is even,
then x plus y squared will also be even, right?
x plus y squared is also going to be even. So this is even.
But if this is even and then this whole thing is odd,
the only way you can add something to an even number
and get an odd number is if the thing you added was odd.
And you can think about that. So x plus z is odd.
So we essentially know two things. x plus y is even.
And we also know that x plus z is odd, right?
And how did we figure out x plus z is odd?
Because we know x plus y is even,
x plus y squared must be even,
and the only way to add something to something
that's even and get an odd number is
if that thing you add is odd.So we know that x plus z is odd.
This is interesting. So we know x plus y is even.
x plus z is odd. So do we know for sure that x is odd?
Well no. x could be even. x could be 2, y could be 2.
And x could be 2 and z could be 1.
So we don't know that x is odd.
And then choice B says x is even. Well, not necessarily.
x could be odd. x could be 1, y could be 1, x could be 1 here
and z could be 2. So that all works.
So choice B doesn't work either.
Now choices C and D look interesting.
If z is even then x is odd. That is true.
Because if we add these two numbers and we get an odd number
and we know that z is even, if this number is even,
then this number has to be odd.
And you can try it out with numbers
if you don't believe me. So C is true.
And we could go through the other ones
but you only have to pick one so C is definitely true.
If z is even then x is definitely odd.
Because the only way to add something to an even number
and get an odd number is if you add it to an odd number.
Let's do problem number fourteen if I have time.
Problem fourteen. 0 is less than x which is less than 1.
Which of the following statements must be true?
Statement I is, x squared is greater than x cubed.
Statement II is x is greater than x/2.
Statement III says that x is greater than x to the third.
So x is pretty much a fraction.
It's a positive fraction less than one.
And you know what, let's just try out a number.
Let's just try out x is equal to 1/2
and that'll simplify things.
Because really all the fractions between 0 and 1
have the same properties when you take the exponents.
So let's see, is this true? 1/2 squared is 1/4.
1/4 is greater than 1/8. Well yeah, sure, that's true.
Is 1/2 greater than 1/4? Right? 1/2 divided by 2 is 1/4.
Well sure, that's true.
And finally is 1/2 greater than 1/2 to the third?
Sure. 1/2 to the third is 1/8.
So 1/2 is definitely greater than 1/2 to the third, right?
And they're all positive numbers
so all three of them are true. So it's choice E.
And that's all the time I have in this video.
I will do problem number fifteen in the next video. See you