Where we had left off we had used the information from these two lines to figure out two lines to figure
out two vectors which were really just, almost you can say, were two position vectors lying in this white
plane and we took their cross-product to find a vector that's perpendicular, that's normal to this entire white plane
and that was the vector d there and vector d will have to sit, especially to visualize it, you can always
position a vector anywhere you want. If you start it at 0, it will clearly sit in that plane. But since
you can always position it anywhere, you can say, "Okay, let's start it at 0." So it will sit in this
yellow plane that we defined the equation for. Now we know vector d sits in it, we already know that
vector A sits in it. We got that early on in the first video on this problem. So we can take the cross product of d and a to find a normal vector to it
and then using that normal vector and then thinking about what an arbitrary point or an arbitrary vector
in this plane might look like, we can then figure out the equation for this yellow plane. We already
touched on it a little bit in the Linear Algebra playlist. If any of this stuff makes you confused, then
just a reminder- We take the cross product of two vectors in three dimentional space. It will give you
third vector that is perpendicular to both. That's the whole kinda tool that we're using over here. So
lets take the cross product of d and a. So this is going to be equal to. So for the i we have 1 x 4,
which is 4 minus 3 x 10, so 4 minus 30 is -26. So we have -26i and then we have negative or minus for
j, we have to swap signs for he j, so we have -8 x 4 is -32. -32 minus 2 x 10, so -20 is -52. So we put
a -52 here, we can just say positive 52, because it's minus -52, that's the same things as +52j. And
finally for the k, cross out that row that column -8 x 3 is -24 minus 2 x 1. So -2 is -26. So -26 k.
So this normal vector right here or a vector that is normal to the yellow plane, the plane that we have
to find the equation of is this over here. And just because it kinda pops out at me that all of these
are divisible by 26, I'm gonna define another normal vector-- I don't know-- let's call it -- let's call
it anything-- let's call it p or let's call it normal 1. Just to show it's a different vector. I'm just
going to divide, although it's essentially pointing in the same direction, it has the same direction
just different magnitude. I'm just going to divide all of these by -26. So if I divide all of these by
-26, I'm just scaling the vector, but it still gonna go in the same direction. That's what I care about. I
care about just finding any vector that is normal to this yellow plane right here. I wanna find any vector--I
already found one and now I'm just gonna scale it down so that it's a simpler vector. So if I divide
everything by -26, I get i plus or i should say -2j plus k. So that might look something like this right
over there. So this is our N1 vector that's normal to this. Now just using this we can now figure out t
the equation of this plane right here. So let's just think about it a little bit. Let's just say I ha
have a point or I could even say a position vector, (x,y,z) and i know (x,y,z) it sits on this plane
and we know that the point (0,0,0) is on the plane, so we also know that the position vector xi+yj+zk
have to sit on this yellow plane. And question: I am assuming that (x,y,z) is a point on this plane.
I could have put little knots here, just to make sure that this could be a particular point on the plane
or this is just any point that I am defining to be on this plane. Now this position vector will then
be on this plane and since this vector is normal to this position vector right here or in another way y
you can say it's perperdicular or orthogonal. If I were to take the dot product of this, if I were to t
take that and dot it with this vector right over here and dot it with that vector right over there. so
So I'll have to take the dot product of that and this. yj+zk. If I take the dot product of these two t
things, it has to be equal to zero. If I take the dot product of two vectors that are orthogonal to each
other, and by definition these two vectors are. I'm saying this guy is in the plane. This vector we a
already figured it out is perperdicular to the plane, which means it's perpendicular, it's orthogonal
to everything in the plane. So if we take their dot product it will be equal to zero. So what does that
give us? So if we take their dot product, we get x times 1. Let me just to term by term, so we take x t