Let's say that you dont' like company ABCD
that's right now trading for 50 dollars a share
but you don't have the stomach to short the stock
because there's a possibility that you could lose an infinite amount of money
if you short it
you still have an option
quite literally you still have an option
you can buy a put option
once again we're dealing with the American variation
and just like an American call option
an American put option gives you the right to exercise the option any time before the expiration date
a European call or put option you can only exercise on the expiration date
and the situation with the put option
a call option gave you the right to buy the stock at a specified price
a put option is the opposite
it gives you the right to sell the stock at a specified price
so this little made up put option I've constructed right here
is maybe being sold on an exchange for five dollars per option
and it gives you the right to sell company ABCD at 40 dollars a share
any time over the next month
and let's see how, if you were to buy this
how this really is a bet that the company would go down
so let's imagine the scenario where the company does what you expect
it goes down and one month later
it keeps going down
you're like, I better use it today, because it's going to expire
if I don't use it today
so you exercise the option right over there
and so what this allows you to do is sell the stock at 40 dollars
and if you don't own it, that's ok, because you can go and buy the stock
right now on the market
you knew it was going to get cheaper
so you can buy it for 20 dollars
and then exercise your option and sell it for 40
so you're buying at 20, and immediately selling for 40
so you're gonna be making 20 dollars
and then if you subtract out the price that you had to pay for the option
you're going to have a 15 dollar profit
you're going to have a 15 dollar profit over here
let me scroll over to the right so you have some space
and this is of course the situation with the put option
this is the put option
and if your bet goes against you
and the stock actually goes up
it's not gonna be like a short position where you can lose an unlimited amount of money
in that situation let's say the stock just keeps going up and up and up
well, any point above 40 dollars, it's like, you know
there's no point in me exercising the option
so you just let it expire
so in that situation you just wasted your money buying the actual option
so you just lose the actual 5 dollars
even that stock were to go up to a gazillion dollars
you're not required to buy it back like you would if you were shorting it
you can just let the option expire