Let's think a little bit about the different clues that have led us to conclude
that we have these lithospheric plates moving relative to each other.
Now, the first clue. This is something I think many students even in elementary school first experience when they first learn about geography,
it looks like the continents could kind of fit into each other.
The most obvious one of these is when you look at this kind of little pointy part of South America,
if you have a more detailed map, it really is amazing how well it seems to fit into the Nigerian basin in Africa.
It looks like at one time this little pointy part was nudged into this part of Africa that they were actually connected.
And if you're a little bit more creative, there are other parts of the world that you can kind of start to see
how they might have fit in with each other in the past.
That by itself is just a very small clue but kind of hints at,
you know, if they at one time were fitting, were next to each other or were kind of connected,
then they have had to move departed some time.
Although it doesn't tell us that it is still moving or what might have caused the move.
But it definitely doesn't tell us that they even moved.
Maybe this is just a coincidence that this coast of South America looks very similar to this coast of Africa.
Now, the next clues we really came over I would say by the last 60 or 70 years.
The first clue is that OK, if you go to the Mid-Atlantic Ridge right here, so if you look at the Atlantic Ocean,
let me look at this photograph right over here.
So this is... you normally don't see the oceans highlighted like this, so let me make it very clear to you.
This right here is South America.
This right here is Africa.
This right here is North America.
And if you actually look at the elevations in the middle of the ocean,
people noticed in the middle of the 20th century that there is a ridge in the middle of the Atlantic Ocean!
There is kind of a mountain ridge that goes straight up the middle of the Atlantic Ocean.
So, that by itself doesn't tell you that these plates are moving apart,
but it is kind of a curious thing to look at.
And that all means that at these ridges are a lot of a underwater vulcanic activity.
You have magma and lava flowing into the water and it's kind of forming this ridge
that really goes across the whole Atlantic Ocean.
There are other ridges in the world like that - underwater ridges.
You have one over here in the Pacific Ocean.
You have these here in the Indian Ocean.
So that by itself is just a little clue, but that by itself doesn't explain,
doesn't tell you that these plates are actually moving apart at the ridge.
The more conclusive, this is just the beginning of the clue, but what made this conclusive
is the separate discovery. And this is what's interesting,
because you had these separate discoveries in different domains that eventually led you to a pretty neat conclusion.
So you've had a separate discovery that if you look at different errors of magnetic rock,
or maybe I should say different magnetic rock from different periods in geologic time,
and you can tell where they are in geologic time by why they are layered,
so this would be newer rock,
and then this would be a little bit older,
and then this would be even older.
Geologists noticed something interesting. If I would take magnetic rock and if it was molten lava,
and remember, it's a magnetic rock, so it would align with the poles the same way a compass would.
So if I had a bunch of mangetic.. so let's say this is a lava right here.
And so the molecules can align themselves when it's liquid,
they can align themselves, they go in a natural one align with the poles.
So they naturally all want to align in one direction
because of Earth's magnetic field.
And so when that lava hardens into actual rock, that alignment would kind of be frozen.
Now, if Earth's magnetic field was constat over time, then when you look at magnetic rocks from any period,
you would expect them all to be aligned in the same direction.
So it's as we are taking a cross-section of this rock,
let's say an alignment towards the north pole looks like this.
I draw it like that, that's an arrow pointing into our screen.
Now, let say an alignment pointing to the south pole would look like this.
This would be an arrow pointing out of our screen.
So what you expect is that newer rock, that kind of the alignment of the rock would go into the screen.
And then the older rock, it would still go into the screen.
It looks like a top view just so let me draw like this as so I make sure every one is on the same pace.
Let my just draw a cross-section like this.
So we know what we are talking about.
Let my draw a cross-section like this.
So this is the surfcace appear.
When I talk about going into the page that means that the magnetic rock would be aligned in that direction.
And when I talk about going out of the page that means, so I would go to draw it like that,
that means that the magnetic rock would be aligned in that direction.
Now, like I said, if the magnetic field of Earth never changes,
then lava that essentially turns into hard, cools down into non-lava rock, you could say it freezes into rock,
it would all point into the same direction regardless of when it hardened.
This would be the situation in a constatn magnetic field.
But what we've seen is that that's not the case.
When you look at older magnetic rock, then, depending on how old you go,
you have the newer rock that's aligned with our current magnetick field,
you go a little bit older, and right now we think it's about 780,000 years ago roughly,
you have to find magnetic rock that hardened at that time,
it's actually in the opposite direction.
So actually the magnetick rock is hardened in a way as if the north pole was at the south pole now, the magnetic north pole.
So it's aligned in the opposite direction. So it's kind of pointing out of the page here.
And if you get even older rock, it's more aligned with our traditional direction. So it's more aligned than that.
And so the only reasonable conclusion that we can draw from this
is that Earth's magnetic field has actually fluctuated over time.
Magnetic field fluctuates.
Now you probably are thinking: 'Sal, how was this relevant to plate tectonics?'
Well, once you accept that magnetic field fluctuates over the history of the Earth,
there is another interesting observation you can make about the rock that's kind of at the basin of the ocean floor.
So not only do have this Mid-Atlanic Ridge have these volcanoes spuming kind of new rock into the ocean
creating this kind of underwater mountain ridge,
but it also turns out that the rock that forms the seafloor also contains a lot of magnetit which is magnetic.
And what's really interesting about that - so let me draw.
So we have a top-view just like we have over here.
So let's say this is the Mid-Atlantic Ridge right here.
And this is really cool. When they looked at rocks that are very close to the Mid-Atlantic Ridge,
and once again, we're looking at rocks that are at the floor of the ocean,
they're aligned in the way that you would expect with the current magnetic field.
They're aligned just like that, the way you would expect when you look at the magnetic rock that's close to the ridge.
But if you go a little bit further, when I say a little bit, I'm talking about thousands of miles,
but if you go further out of that, you have stripes of other magnetic rock that is going the opposite direction.
It's going like this.
And what's even cooler than the idea that it switches directions depending on how far you've gone from the rift,
is that there's a symetric stripe of magnetic rock on exactly the same distance,
or roughly the same distance away from the rift that's also pointing in that same direction.
And you go a little bit further out and you'll find some rock that's pointing in the original direction.
And even better, you go on the symetric other side of the actual ridge,
and you find another set of rocks that's doing the exact same thing.
So if you accept that Earth's magnetic field has kind of been flip-flopping over time,
the only reasonable conlusion that at least I can think of or geologists can think of,
is that all of this was formed at a similar period in time.
This came out as lava, magnetic lava, and the all aligned with Earth's magnetic field and that's why it looks similar.
You fast-forward in time some, or actually let's not fast-forward in time.
The only way that these could have formed and they could have been so similar,
so if we rewind in time, the only way that these purple magnetic rocks could have aligned this exactly same way in the same distances,
is that in some point they were much closer to each other and were actually connected.
So if we rewind in time maybe at the Mid-Atlantic Rift you had all of the purple rock
coming out from those underwater volcanoes and at that time Earth's magnetic field was the opposite as it's right now.
And then of course you had this blue rock that is looking like that.
And so this seems like a reasonable explanation. This rock and this rock were at some point touching,
they were actually formed at the exact place and at the same time.
And so if this is the case that one point this purple rock was all together and they formed at the same time at the Mid-Atlantic Rift,
we're assuming all the rock was, well, we don't have to make that assumption,
but if you assume that they formed at the same time, and based on the pattern it does look like they do,
it's a symetric distace away from that rift, that the only reasonable conclusion I can think of
is that the rift has had to move apart from this period to that period.
And there was a time when all this blue rock was together.
So that by itself frankly is the most affinitive evidence in the 1960s
when it kind of became conclusive that you did have these plate that were moving away from each other.
Now, obviously the plates are moving away from each other at some point,
and that means that based on how the map looks, at some point they're also going to move into each other,
we can talk more about that in future videos, but at certain point they're actually moving on,
one plate is moving under another. We'll talk about how that might partially explain,
I won't talk about all of the explanations of why we think the plates might actually be moving.
But if we fast-forward the more present time as now we have the GPS satellites and all the rest,
we can actually measure the movement of the plates.
This is an image from NASA showing the vectors of the movements at different points on the surface of the planet.
And you could see we've got a lot of vectors from the U.S., it's hard to read, it's so chock-full of vectors.
We can see right over here why the Pacific Plate at that point is moving in this northwest direction. And it's measured by GPS satellites.
And I wanna make clear - this movements is relatively slow, it's roughly the speed in which fingernails grow.
But if you do it over millions of years, that actually amounts to thousands of miles.
We're talking on the order of about a centimetre a year for most of the plates,
some of the plates might be moving a little bit faster, maybe close to 10 or 15 cm,
but most of them are moving about a centimetre a year, at the same rate your fingernails are growing.
But this is fantastic 'cause you can actually measure it because GPS is so accurate.
We can see that the North-American Plate is kind of rotating generally in that direction.
The Nazca Plate right here is moving roughly in that direction into the South-American Plate.
I'll leave you there right now... actually before I leave you there,
this is another thing that I though to recap that shows that same magnetic strenght it's maybe a slightly neater drawn,
I don't know which one might be more helpful for you.
But I'll leave you there in this video. In the next video we'll think about some of the theories.
We know now that the plates are moving. Let's about some of the theories as to why they might actually be moving.