We're at the Prado in Madrid and we are looking at Fra Angelico's Annunciation.
Now, the Annunciation by Fran Angelico that most people are familiar with is a fresco that's in San Marco in Florence
This is a painting that was made for a church not far from Florence,...
in Fiesole
It is extraordinary in that the frame is original and so not only do you have the main panel,
but you've got the predella underneath with all of its original framing elements.
I'm not sure that I've ever seen that.
These things were often taken apart and sold in pieces.
We have an Old Testament scene of Adam and Eve being cast out of the Garden of Eden, or "The Expulsion," by an angel.
And, actually, that scene is joined to the annunciation scene, because in the upper left...
...we see the hands of God releasing this divine light
and a dove, which you can see just to the left of the column, which is the Holy Spirit.
So we have, actually, The Fall and then the reason for Christ's existence.
And Adam and Eve as the precursors to Mary and Christ.
So the man and woman that cause the fall from grace and Mary and Christ who make salvation possible.
And then we have God the Father looking down, in an almost classical relief sculpture in the center just above that column.
The predella below, is a very condensed series of scenes of the life of the Virgin Mary,
from her birth, to her marriage to Joseph, to The Visitation, through to her death. Through to her death, that's right.
And they are...really meant, in a sense, to be the literal support for this later story.
So, stylistically, one of the things I find quite important is...
this sense of quiet and solemnity that Fra Angelico is able to achieve.
You have the angel who is bowing below Mary.
His hands are crossed, which is a symbol of respect, of prayer. Mary reflects that with her own hands.
I'm really taken by the density of the Garden of Eden, all of the fruit, those flowers.
That wonderful, anti-perspective field of flowers below the feet.
And then you have this stark architecture, they are both too large for the space that they occupy...?
Oh, absolutely. I think if Mary were to stand up, she would hit her head on the ceiling.
But none of that is really important because this is a kind of reverential and invented exploration of beauty as a way of representing the divine.
So this is painted contemporaneous with Masaccio painting the Brancacci Chapel.
So we have two radically different approaches going on in Florence at the same time.
And I think that's a good reminder that not everything in the Renaissance is this linear movement toward naturalism. But this kind of variety of styles.
Whereas Masaccio is looking for an almost mathematically accurate rendering, here we see an artist who is looking to celebrate the decorative as a way of expressing the moral and the spiritual.
Yeah, and if you look there are no cast shadows, there is not that kind of intense modelling that we see with Masaccio.
There's not a lot of specificity to the faces, and individuality in the faces. But there is specificity to the decorative.
I mean, look at the wings of the angel. Yeah. Or the gilding of the halos. Or just the the foliage in the garden. Its just sumptuous.
It is.