We're asked to multiply
65 times 1.
So literally, we just need to multiply 65,
and we could write it as a times sign like
that or we could write it as a dot like that
but this means 65 times 1.
And there's two ways
to interpret this.
You could view this as the
number 65 one time
or you could view this as the number 1
sixty-five times, all added up.
But either way, if you have one
65, this is literally just going to be 65.
Anything times 1 is going
to be that anything,
whatever this is.
Whatever this is times 1 is going
to be that same thing again.
If I have just some kind of
placeholder here times 1,
that's going to be that same placeholder.
So if I have 3 times 1,
I'm going to get 3.
If I have 5 times 1,
I'm going to get 5,
because literally, all this is
saying is 5 one time.
If I put-- I don't know-- 157
times 1, that'll be 157.
I think you get the idea.