Express 0.0000000003457 in scientific notation
So let's just remind ourselves what it means to be in scientific notation
Scientific notation will be some number times some power of 10
Where this number right here is going to be
Let me write it this way
It's going to be greater than or equal to 1, and it's going to be less than 10
So over here, what we want to put here is that leading number is going to be
And in general you're going to look for the first non-zero digit
And this is the number that you're going to want to start off with
This is the only number you're going to want to put ahead of
– or I guess to the left of –
Of the decimal point
So we could write 3.457
3.457
And it's going to be multiplied by 10 to something
Now let's think about what we're going to have to multiply it by
To go from 3.457 to this very, very small number
I mean we have had to move the decimal from 3.457 to get to this
You have to move the decimal to the left a bunch
You have to add a bunch of 0's to the left of the 3
You have to keep moving the decimal over to the left
To do that, we're essentially making the number much, much, much smaller
So we are not going to multiply it with a positive exponent of 10
We are going to multiply it times a negative exponent of 10
that the equivalent is you kind of dividing by a positive exponent of 10
the best way to think about it
When you move your exponent one to the left
You dividing by 10 which is equivalent to multiply by 10 to the negative 1 power
Let me give you an example here
So if I have 1 times 10 is clearly just equal to 10
1 times 10 to the negative 1
That's equal to 1 times 1/10 which is equal to 1/10
1 times---which is equal to 0--I skip the step right there
Let me add 1 times 10 to the 0
So we have something natural
So this is 1 times to the first
1 times to the 0 is equal to 1 times 1 which is equal to 1
1 times 10 to the negative 1 is equal to 1/10 which is equal to 0.1
If I do 1 times 10 to the negative 2
10 to the negative 2 is 1/10 squared or 1/100
so this is going to be 1/100 which is 0.01
What happened here?
When I read it to the negative power
I read it to the negative 1 power
I essentially move the decimal from the right of the one to the left of the one
I move from there to there
When I get to -2, I move the 2 over the left
So how many times we are going to move it over to the left to get this number right over here
So we essentially, so let's think about how many zeros we have
So we have to move it 1 times to get in front of the 3
and then we have to move it that means more times to get all of the zeros
in there
so we have to move it 1 time to get the 3
So we start here
We are going to move 1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10..10 times
So this is going to be 3.457 times 10 to the negative 10 power
Let me just rewrite it
So 3.457 times 10 to the negative 10 power
So in general, what you want to do is you want to find the first non zero number here
Remember, you want a number here that between 1 and 10
and it could be equal to 1 but it has to be less than 10
3.457 definitely fits that bill
It's between 1 and 10
And then you just want to count the leading zero between the decimal of that number and
and include the number because that tells you how many times you have to shift the decimal over to actually get this number
up here
So we have to shift this decimal 10 times to the left to get this thing up here