Part B
Find the slope of the tangent line to the path of the particle time t = 3
So the slope of the tangent line is just going to be equal to
rate of change of y with the respect to x at that point
and this is the same thing as dy dt over dx dt
and dealing with differentials is a little bit strange.
Especially when you want to deal with them rigorously, but you can view them as very little small changes
in y, small changes in t, small changes in x, small changes in t
when you view it this way, you can say, "Oh look, if I just multiply both the numerator and the denominator
by dt over dt, which if you do the same small changes, then they would cancel out and you'd get back
to the dy over dx
and the reason why I wrote it this way is that they actually give is these values
they give us dy dt and they give us dx dt.
So, if you wanted to find the slope at time equals 3,
we just have to find dy dt at time equals 3 and dx dt and time equals 3.
So dy dt at time equals 2, why this is dy dt right over here,
it's just going to be sine of 3 squared, or sine of 9.
and dx dt at time 3, that's just going to be, it tells us what dx dt is,
as a function of time, four times three plus one
Well, that's thirteen. And we can just get out calculator out and evaluate this.
We kinda did alot of this work in the first problem, so let's just actually take the values.
So we have sine of nine divided by thirteen.
That gets us zero point zero three one seven (0.0317)
and we're done, and that's the slope of the tangent line
to the path of the particle at time t is equal to three.
I think we have time to crank out part C as well.
Part C: Find the position of the particle at time t is equal to three.
So they give us x prime of t and they give us y prime of t.
This is x-prime of t and this is y-prime of t. We need to figure out x of three and y of three.
Let's write x of t and y of t, and then evaluate them at three.
So let's see. So x of t is going to be equal to the anti-derivative of this right over here.
So the anti-derivative of four t is going to be two t squared.
Take the derivative here and you just get 4t.
Anti-derivative of one is t, plus t, and your going to have, well, plus a constant.
We just took that indefinite integral of this side of 4t plus 1,
so you get your constant here,
'cause if you take the derivative of this constant, the constant will obviously disappear,
you'd like that information.