So given this diagram, we have to figure out what the length
of CF right over here is, and you might already guess
that this will have to do something to similar triangles
at least it looks that triangle CFE is similar to ABE
the intuition there is kind of embedded inside of it
and it also looks like triangle CFB
is going to be similar to triangle DEB
but once again we're gonna prove that to ourselves,
and then maybe we can deal with all the ratios of the different size
to CF right over here,
and actually figure out what CF is going to be
So first let's prove to ourselves
that these are definitely are similar triangles
So you have this 90 degree angle an ABE
and you know this 90 degree angle and CFE,
if we can prove just one other angle is,
or one other set of corresponding angles
is congruent in both and we've proved that they're similar
And there we can either show that,
they both show, they both share this angle over here
Angle is CEF is the same as angle AEB
So we've shown two angles, two corresponding angles
in these triangles, this is an angle on both triangles,
they are congruent, so these triangles are going to be similar
You can also show that this line, probably this line,
because obviously these two angles are the same
And so these angles will also be the same,
so they're definitely similar triangles
So let's just write that down, get it out of the way
We know that triangle ABE, ABE is similar with triangle CFE,
you wanna make sure get it in the right order
F is where the 90 degree angle is,
B is where the 90 degree angle is,
and so an E is where this orange angle is
So CFE, it's similar triangles CFE
Now let's see if we can figure out the same statement
going the other way, looking at triangle DEB
So once again, once again, you have 90 degree angle here
This is 90 and this is definitely gonna be 90 as well
You have a 90 degree angle here at CFB
You have a 90 degree angle at DEF or DEB,
however you wanna call it
So they have one set of corresponding angles that are congruent
And the you'll also see that they both share this angle right over here
On the small triangle, I'm not looking at,
I'm not looking at this triangle right over here
it's supposed to be the on the right
So they bout share this angle right over here
DBE, angle DBE is the same as angle CBF
So I've shown you already that we have this angle
is congruent to this angle and we have this angle is a part of both
so it's obviously congruent to itself
So we have two angles, two corresponding angles
that are congruent to each other
So we know that this larger triangle over here
is similar to this smaller triangle over there
So let me write this down, so we also know,
let's scroll over to the right a little bit,
we also know that triangle, triangle DEB, triangle DEB is similar,
triangle DEB is similar to triangle CFB, to triangle CFB
Now what can we do from here?
What we know that the ratios of corresponding sites,
one of those, each of those similar triangles
are going to have to be the same
But we only have one side of one of the triangles,
so in the case of ABE and CFE we're only given one side
In the case of DEB and CFB we've only been given one side over here
it doesn't seem to be a lot to work with
And this is why it's slightly more a challenging problem here
let's just go ahead and see if we can assume one of the sides
and actually, maybe the sides
let's just assume that this length right over here
let's just assume that BE is equal to Y
So let me just write this down
This whole length is going to be equal to Y
Because at least this give us something to work with
And Y is shared by both ABE and DEB
the shorter, the smaller triangles over there,
so maybe we'll call this length, we'll call BF X, let's call BF X
and then let's call FE, while this is X and this is Y minus X
We've introduced a bunch of,
We've introduced a bunch of variables here
but maybe with all the proportionalities of things,
just maybe things will work out,
or at least we can have a little more sense
where we can go with this actual problem
But now we can start dealing with,
we can now start dealing with the similar triangles
For example we wanna figure out what CF,
we wanna figure out what CF is
We now know that for these two triangles,
the ratio of the corresponding sides are going to be constant,
so for example the ratio between CF and 9,
the corresponding sides, the ratio between CF and 9
has got to be equal to the ratio between Y minus X, Y minus X,
that's that side right there, Y minus X
in the corresponding side of the larger triangle
While the corresponding side of the large triangle
is this entire length and that entire length over there is Y
So it's equal to Y minus X over Y
So we can simplify this a little bit,
While I'll hold off for a second,
lets see if we can do something similar with this thing on the right
not looking at triangle CFE anymore
so we have CF over DE is going to be equal to,
so CF over DE is going to be equal to X is going to be equal to,
It's going to be equal to X over, it's going to be equal to X over
this entire base right over here, this entire BE,
so which is know is over Y
And now this looks interesting because we have 3 unknowns
we have CF sorry we know what DE is already,
I could have written CF over 12
The ratio between CF and 12
is gong to be the ratio between X and Y
So we have 3 unknowns and 3 equations,
it seems it's hard to solve at first,
because its 1 unknown, another unknown,
another unknown and another unknown
But it looks like I can write this, right here,
this expression in terms of X over Y
and then we can do a substitution so that's why this is a little tricky
So this one right here we can rewrite as CF,
let me do that same green color, we can rewrite is as CF over 9
is equal to Y minus X over Y is the same thing
as Y over Y minus X over Y or 1 minus X over Y
All I did is essentially, I could you can say distributed
then 1 over Y times both of these terms
Y over Y minus X over Y, 1 over or 1 minus X minus Y
And this is usual because we already know what Y is equal to
X, sorry, X over Y is equal to
We already know that X over Y is equal to CF over 12
So this right over here, I can replace with this CF over 12,
so then we get, this is the homestretch here,
CF which is what we care about,
CF over 9 is equal 1 minus CF over 12
And now we have one equation and one unknown
We should be able to solve this right over here,
so we can add CF to both sides
so you have CF over 9 plus CF over 12
is equal to one, we just have to find a common denominator here
I think 36 will do the trick
So 9 times 4 is 36, so if you have to multiple 9 times 4,
you have to multiply CF times 4 so you have 4 CF,
4 CF over 36 is the same thing as CF over 9 and then plus,
CF over 12 is the same thing as over 3 CF over 36
and this is going to be equal to 1,
and then we are left with 4 CF plus 3 CF is equal to 7
CF over 36 is equal to and to solve for CF,
we can multiply both sides and the reciprocal of 7 over 36
So 36 over 7, so 36 over 7 multiply both sides times that 36 over 7
This side thing is cancelled out and we are left with,
our final, we get our drum roll now, CF is equal to, CF,
all of this stuff is cancelled out,
CF is equal to 36, 1 times 36 over 7 or just 36 over 7
And this is a pretty cool problem,
because what it shows you is you have two things
let's see this thing is some kind of a pole or a stick
or the wall of building
Or who knows what it is
If this is 9 feet tall or 9 yards tall or 9 meters tall
and this over here, this other one 12 meters tall, or 12 yards,
whatever you want, units you wanna use it,
if you wanna drape a string, either of them,
to the base of the other, from the top of one of them to the base
of the other, regardless of how far apart these two things
are going to be we just said how far apart
regardless of how a part they are,
the place where those two strings
will intersect are going to 36 7 tie,
I guess 5 7 tie regardless of how far they are
So that's a pretty, I don't know,
I think that was a pretty cool problem