Find the range and the midrange of the following sets of numbers
So what the range tells us is essentially
how spread apart these numbers are
And the way that you calculate it is
You just take the difference between the
the largest of these numbers and the smallest
of these numbers
And so if we look at the largest
I'll circle it in magenta, it looks like it is 94
94 is larger than every other number here
So that's the largest of the numbers
And from that we want to subtract
the smallest of the numbers
And the smallest of the numbers in our set
right over here is 65
(Circled in green)
So you want to subtract 65 from 94
and this is equal to...
if this was 95 minus 65, it would be 30
94 is one less than 95
so it is 29
So the larger this number is that means the more spread out the larger the
difference between the largest and the smallest number
the smaller this is, that means, the [tighter?]
the range [just to use the word itself?] of the numbers actually are, so that's the range
the midrange is one way of thinking
to some degree of kind of central tendency, so midrange,
midrange, and would you do with the midrange is to take the average
of the largest number and the smallest number
so, here we took the difference that's the range. The midrange would be the average of this two numbers
so 94 plus 65 when we talk about average and [talk about] arithmetic mean over 2 so this is going to be what...
90 plus 60 is 150, 150 plus...
4 plus 5 is 159, 159 divided by 2 is equal to
150 divided by 2, is 75, 9 divided by 2 is 4.5,
so this would be 79.5
so is one kind [of way?] of thinking about the middle of these numbers,
another way is obviously the arithmetical mean we [] to take []
obviously you can also look at things as the median and the mode
so range and midrange