Welcome back.
We're now starting section eight on page 547.
OK. And I think we're in the third test.
So problem number one,
if e is a set of even numbers--even integers,
sorry-- e is a set of even integers,
p is a set of positive integers,
and f is a set of integers less than 5,
which of the following integers will be
in all three sets?
So we're looking for something that meets all the constraints
So it has to be even,
it has to be positive,
and it has to be less than 5.
OK, so choice A is 6. 6 is not less than 5.
Choice B is 4.
4 is even, 4 is positive,4 is less than 5.
So the answer is B.
And the other choices don't work because, C,1 is odd.
D, 0 is not positive.
And the last choice,E, negative 2.
Well, that's not positive either.
So our answer was B.Choice B was 4
Problem number two.
If 8 plus the square root of k is equal to 15,
then what does k equal?
Well, subtract 8 from both sides,
and you get square root of k is equal to 7.
Square both sides,k is equal to 49.
Next problem.
Problem number three.
Let's see If I can clear image.
In a poll, 35 people were in favor of building a new library.
So 35, yes, they want it.
14, against it. 14 said no.
And 1 person doesn't know.
1 person just has no opinion.
What fraction of those polled were in favor of
building a new library.
So the people that were in favor were 35.
And the fraction of the total people polled--
so the total people polled was 35 plus 14 plus 1, right?
And what is this? That's 50. So that's equal to 35 over 50.
And 35 over 50, if we divide the top and bottom by 7,
you get 7/10. So the answer is A.
7/10 were in favor of the library.Problem number four
We've got a kind of crazy looking figure here.
You have a line that goes something like this,
and it goes like that and then it goes like this and looks
something like that. Close enough. And what's going on here?
So they tell us that this angle is 70. That's 70. This is 30.
They say that this is t and this is u.
You probably can't read that but you see
it in your own book.
In the figure above, what is the value of t plus u?
This is the angle game again.
Let's see what angles we can figure out.
So, this is 70, this is 30.
So this angle right here plus 70, plus 30 has
to equal 180, right?
This angle plus 70, plus 30. 70 plus 30 is 100.
So this is 80 degrees right here. If this is 80 degrees,
this is the opposite angle to 80 degrees.
So that's going to also be 80 degrees.
We learned that in geometry class.
And so if this is 80 degrees-- first of all,
what do all of these angles combined equal?
t plus u, plus 80 are all on the same triangle.
So they have to add up to 180.
So we know that t plus u has to be 100 degrees,
and that's choice C. Next problem.
OK, problem number five. Oh, there's a big graph.
According to the graph above,
between which two consecutive years was
the greatest change in the price of coffee?
Oh, I think I'm going to have to draw this.
Just so that you see what I see, hopefully.
OK, and then let me just write the years.
So this is, it goes'81 through '86.
So '81, '82, '83,'84, '85, '86.
Let's see, in 1981-- so let's see,
we have $3.00, $3.75,we have $4.00,$4.25,$4.50,$4.75.
In 1981 it cost $3.75.
It's going to take me a little time to draw this whole thing.
In 1982 it was at $3.50.
Oops, that's $3.50 down here, not $3.00.
Let me write that,that's $3.50.
Back to what I was doing. In 1983 it went to $4.25.
In 1984 it went all the way to $4.75.
In 1985 it was at $3.75 again.
That looks something like that.
And then 1986 goes to $4.50. 1986, $4.50.
OK, and what are they asking us? According to
the graph above,between which two consecutive
years was the greatest change in the price of coffee?
Well, let's figure that out.
So here, the change is $0.25.
Here, the change, going from this year to this year,
is-- let's see, $0.25,$0.50, $0.75.
That's a good contender right there. $0.75.
Going from here to here we only had a $0.50 change.
Then we went from $4.75 to $3.50.
So this is a pretty big change, actually.
This looks like our winner.
That's from $4.75 to actually $3.75, so
this is a $1.00 change.
And then we went from $3.75to $4.50,
so we had a $0.75change again.
So the biggest change happened from 1984 to 1985, choice D.
All that work for a fairly straightforward problem.
Next problem. Problem number six.
More drawing for me. OK.
let's see,more drawing.Got to be focused,Sal, focused
This is negative 1, this is negative 2,
this is 1, this is 2. 1 and 2.
And what does this graph look like?
Let's see, we go from here to here,
it looks like, and then we stay flat here,
and then we go like this, and then we go flat again.
And what are they asking?
The graph of y equals g of x.
So this is y is equal to g of x.
Shown above.
If g of k is equal to 1,
which of the following is a possible value of k?
So g of k is equal to 1.
So when does this graph equal 1?
Well, this graph equals 1--add a different color--
it equals 1 here-- oh,it equals 1 here.
It equals 1 this entire period, right?
All of these values are where g of x is equal to 1.
So what could be the values of k?
Well, the values of k could be anywhere between
negative 1 and 0.
All of those could be values of k, anywhere from here.
Because at all of these values,g of k is equal to 1.
So let's see. They have choices. Minus 1.5 is here.
No, that's over there. Minus 0.5 is right here.
And g of minus 0.5 is right here, so that's 1.
g of minus 0.5 is equal to 1.
So that looks pretty good. So that is our answer. Choice B.
Let's see if I can squeeze in problem number seven.
I think that would be the most videos I've ever done-
most problems in 10 minutes.
If a,b and c are different positive integers,
and 2 to the a,times 2 to the b, times 2 to the c,
is equal to 64, then they want to know,
what is 2 to the a, plus 2 to the b, plus 2 to the c?
Fascinating.
Well, what do we know about exponent rules?
2 to the a, times 2 to the b,times 2 to the c,
that's 2 to the a, plus b, plus c, right?
2 to the what power is 64?
2 to the sixth power, right?
2 to the sixth power is 64.
Actually, I'm going to run out of time.
So I'm going to do this in the next video.
I only have 15 seconds left. See you soon.