Here's a diagram of the four chambers of the heart, so let's name them to get started.
We've got the right atrium up here, we've got the right ventricle down here, we've got the left atrium and the left ventricle.
These are the four chambers and blood is going to flow through all of them and get out to the body.
So, to do this and to do this right the heart has got to coordinate how it squeezes.
We know that the way it squeezes down is you have a cell and that cell is usually negatively charged,
and it will at some point become more positively charged. We call that process depolarization.
Depolarization is the idea of going from a negative membrane potential to something much more positive.
And when you depolarize is when the muscle cell can squeeze down.
So, where does that begin? Let's actually draw it into our diagram.
If you were to look there's actually an area here where little cells can actually depolarize by themselves.
And that's actually quite unique because most of the cells inside the body are going to depolarize when the neighbor, when that neighboring cell depolarizes.
So, these are actually really unique cells because they actually depolarize by themselves.
We call that area the sinoatrial node, sometimes called the SA node.
And the fact that they can actually depolarize by themselves we have a word for that, too; we call that automaticity.
It just means that they can kind of automatically depolarize without having a neighbor do it first.
So once they depolarize, what happens after that?
Well, when these cells depolarize they immediately, they're connected through little gap junctions to the neighboring muscle cells.
So, they are going to start sending out waves of depolarization in all directions.
It's almost like going to a football game and watching "The Wave" start, you know, it just goes on and on and on.
So, all the neighboring cells are going to start depolarizing, as well.
That orange arrow is moving kind of slowly, right?
That depolarization wave is moving kind of slowly relative to how fast it could be moving
if it went through a specialized band of tissue.
So this band of tissue I'm drawing, this blue band
is almost like a highway compared to that orange arrow, which is like a little road.
And that highway is going to take that same depolarization wave over to the other side,
over to the left atrium and all of these cells begin to do the same thing, they start depolarizing, as well.
So, you get depolarizing happening both in the right atrium and the left atrium in a coordinated way.
It's happening all very evenly.
This band, or bundle, is called Bachmann's Bundle. It's like a bundle of tissue, right?
It's called Bachmann's Bundle.
So, we've named two things: the sinoatrial node and Bachmann's Bundle.
And actually just like Bachmann's Bundle there are actually a few more bands of tissue,
almost like little highways, that take that signal down to another node called the atrioventricular node.
So this right here is the atrioventricular node.
And the atrioventricular node is really the only major connection, I shouldn't even say only major,
only connection in most of us between the atria and the ventricles, the atrioventricular node.
And this is actually sometimes called the AV node.
The AV node is gonna get this signal and actually I didn't even tell you what a signal came through.