Let's draw a bunch of parabolic mirrors
In this video, I want to do a bunch of examples of objects in front of parabolic mirrors
and think about what the images of those objects will be
based on how far those objects are
Besides just giving us a better understanding of parabolic mirrors
this will hopefully also gives us a sense of how to conceptualize this light rays
which will be pretty useful tool when we tackle other types of reflective or refractive devices
like lenses
So that's a parabolic mirror. I've drawn its principal axis right over here
Let me just copy and paste this. Let me draw the focal point too
So this is the focus right over here
And this is the center of curvature, twice the distance from this point as the focus
So that is the center of curvature right over there
Let me copy and paste it so we can reuse it later on in the video
Alright, so I have copied that
Now let's put an object. I think we did this in the last video
Let's put an object beyond the center of curvature
So let's put an object here
The convention is to use upward pointing arrow
This isn't a light ray. It's used to show an object
And we use the tip of the arrow to really show the top of the object
and that's usually where we trace our light rays from
but it doesn't have to be there. You can do the middle; you can do the bottom
and you can figure out what the image of the object's going to be. So let me do that
We're dealing with parabolic mirrors
It's easiest to have just 2 light rays
one that goes parallel to the principal axis
and one that goes through the focus
because you know what's going to happen at each of those when they reflect
You don't have to do any math there
Let's have the parallel ray
That's the parallel incident ray. When it reflects, it'll go through the focus
And Let's have an incident ray that goes through the focus
And when it reflects, it will be parallel
This is the example we actually saw in the last video
And so whatever light is being emitted from this point over here in that direction
it will come back and converge again at this point
We could actually do it at every point along the--we could do it halfway
This halfway point of the arrow, just to make it clear. It's the same thing
You have a parallel incident ray. It will reflect through the focus
And I'll just do it for this one right over here. It will reflect through the focus
And if you have an incident ray that goes through the focus, it will reflect parallel
So this point will correspond to this point over here
I think that makes it clearer that
the image of this object was reflected by this parabolic mirror will look just like that
So it'll actually form a real image that is smaller than this original one
It's not so clear the way I did it over here but you can further back out
and it will be clear that this is going to be a smaller real image than that right over there
Now let's do a couple of more examples. So let me just paste my drawing
So I don't have to redraw it
Let's see what happens. So let me write it just so we can keep track of things
So here the image is real and smaller than the actual object
when the actual object is beyond the center of curvature
Let me make it a little bit clear by drawing another example like that
I'll do something big and way out here just to make it clear
So once again, we go parallel
reflect through the focus
and then we can go through the focus and then reflect out like that
And there you see. Now it's much clearer that the image is going to be much smaller
and of course inverted relative to the actual object
Now let's do this again
But this time, let's place the object at the center of curvature right over here
So right at that distance that's twice the distance from the vertex of the parabola to focus
So we'll do a parallel line, parallel incident ray, parallel to the principal axis
This is the principal axis right here
That's what this line is right over here. Kind of the line of symmetry of the parabola
When it reflects, it will reflect through the focus
and then let's take another incident ray that goes through the focus
and when it reflects, it will reflect parallel
My drawing isn't the neatest drawing on the planet. Actually let me draw it a little bit better
than that. Well that's pretty good. Let me just--
That's the incident ray that's parallel
and then an incident ray that goes through the focus
will then come out and reflect right over there
And they'll converge. My drawing isn't ideal
but the reality is that they'll converge so that the image will just be a
inverted same size version of this thing up here because it's symmetric
Let me see if I can redraw this whole thing so it comes out neater
So far, that looks good
Then you want to reflect like that, coming through the focus
Then you have another ray that goes through the focus
and this whole thing should be symmetric and then it would reflect
It comes back out like that. So that makes it a little bit clear
So this is the object. And its image is just an inverted version of this object
The ray converge at the same distance from the actual mirror as the actual object
And it's going to be the same size, just inverted
So here the image is real and the same size as the object
Let's just do a couple more of this
I think you've got the hang of it
You might want to try them out. You might want to pause the video and try them out on paper
Really nothing deep practice
So let's stick our object between the center of curvature and the focus, or the focal point
So if we put our object there, we could
have a light ray that goes parallel to the principal axis
And then it will reflect out through the focus
And then you could have another ray that goes through the focus
And then it will reflect out
Let me do it better than that. I should probably have used a more precise tool when I did all this
So let me draw it right over here
So I have the parallel one
Then it goes through the focus just like that when it gets reflected
Maybe I should have had a line tool for this to have neater drawings
And then a ray that goes through the focus will be reflected out parallel
At least for the light that comes from that tip, they will reconverge at that tip
And if you did it for every point on this arrow
the image would have been inverted arrow that is bigger than the original
And it is beyond--it's almost the opposite of the first example that we showed
So now the image is bigger than the original
So the image is real and it is bigger
And the image will converge beyond the center of curvature
And you can imagine if this was the object right here
then this would be the image of it, if you just trace the lines backwards
So there's some symmetry here between this example and the first one we did up here
Let's just do a couple more. Let's imagine that the object is actually at the focal point
Is actually at the focus
Let's draw an object there. Think about what would happen
So if we're at the focus
a ray that comes out parallel will go through the focal point, just like that
And then here we can't have a ray that just goes into the object
So here I'll do a slightly different ray that intersects the parabolic mirror right over there
The reason why I want to do it there is because
there the parabolic mirror is essentially flat and essentially vertical
So you can kind of imagine that the incident ray is gonna be the same thing as a reflected ray
Let me draw a ray that comes in like that. This is a departure from what we did before
The reflected ray will come out like that
So what happens when the object is at the focal point
is that all of the light that's coming off of this object in any direction
will all be made parallel. So it won't converge
So it won't converge. So it won't be able to form a real image
And it does not look like it is diverging from some point in the mirror
So it even won't form a virtual image
So here, there will actually be no image
No image when the object is actually at the focal point
And then the last case as you can imagine is if an object is closer than the focal point
Let's draw that
Let's put the object at the focal point
So right over here
And here just for the sake of argument, I can always draw a parallel
Anything that's parallel will then look
to come out in a direction that would go through the focal point
Although the object itself is blocking, it will look to go in that direction
it will be reflected in that direction
And then you can imagine a ray of light that would have been coming from the focal point
or would've been coming from the same direction as a focal point
would be reflected in a parallel direction to that principal axis
Now these two light rays are not converging
but they look like they're diverging from some point behind the mirror
So in this case, we're forming a virtual image
And the virtual image will actually look something like this
And so it will be larger than the original
Virtual image
So it's kind of a magnifying. If you were to go to a fun house or amusement park, whatever
if you were to get close enough to a parabolic mirror
it would show a magnified version of you
Actually, let me draw that a little bit bigger just because it might not be clear
This is the mirror
That is the focal point
This right here is the principal axis
This is maybe you, maybe whatever object
You could draw a ray that goes parallel
It will reflect in the direction of the focal point; it will reflect out like that
It'll be blocked by the object though
And then something that looks like it would've come from the focal point
from the same direction as a focal point
would then be reflected parallel to the principal axis
So these two rays once again they're diverging, but they look like
to the human brain, to the human eye, they look like they came from that point over there
And so this would correspond to that point on the virtual image
that point on the virtual image
So hopefully, that gives you some practice
But the most important thing, it gives you some practice dealing with these
arbitrary ray we're showing emanating from the tip of the arrow
For the whole arrow, the reason we're picking these rays and these directions
is they're easy to work with. If they go through the focus, they'll come out parallel
If the incident ray's parallel, it'll come out through the focus