What I want to do with this video is start with some point that's
not on the plane, or not necessarily on the plane.
So let me draw a point right over here
and let's say the coordinates of that point are x-naught
x-sub-zero, y-sub-zero and z-sub-zero.
Or it could be specified as a position vector.
I could draw the position vector like this.
So the position vector, let me draw a better dotted line
so the position vector for this could be x-naught i
plus y-naught-j, plus z-naught-k
specifies this coordinate right over here.
What I want to do is find the distance between this point
and the plane. And obviously there could be a lot of distances
I could find the distance between this point and that point
And this point and this point, and this point and this point
And when I say I want to find the distance,
I want to find the minimum distance
and you're actually going to get the minimum distance when
you go the perpendicular distance to the plane
or the normal distance to the plane.
We'll hopefully see that visually as we try to figure out
how to calculate the distance.
So the first thing we do, let's just construct
a vector between this point that's off the plane and some
point that's on the plane.
And we already have a point from the last video
that's on the plane: x-sub-p, y-sub-p, z-sub-p.
So let's construct a vector. Let's construct this orange vector
that starts on the plane.
its tail is on the plane, and it goes off the plane
to this vector, to this position x-naught, y-naught, z-naught.
So what would be, how could we specify this vector
right over here?
Well, that vector, let me call that vector, well
let me call that vector--what letters have I not used yet?
let me call that vector f.
Vector f is just going to be this yellow position vector
minus this green position vector.
So it's going to be--the x component is going to be
the difference in the x-coordinates.
The y-coordinate is going to be the difference in the
y-coordinates.
It's going to be x-naught minus x-sub-p.
I subtracted the x coordinates i plus y-naught minus y-p j
plus, I'll go to the next line, plus z-naught
minus z p k.
So fair enough. That's just some vector that comes
off of the plane and onto this point.
And what we want to find out is this distance.
We want to find out this distance in yellow. The distance
that if I were to take a normal off of the plane and go straight
to the point. That's going to be the shortest distance.
And actually we can see it visually now.
Because, if you look at--we can actually form
a right triangle now.
So this base of the right triangle is along the plane
This side is normal to the plane
So this is a right angle.
And you can see
if I take any point, any other point on the plane,
it will form a hypotenuse on a right triangle.
And obviously, the shortest side here, the shortest
way to get to the plane,
is going to be this distance right here
as opposed to the hypotenuse.
This side will always be shorter than that side.
So given that we know this vector here, how can we
figure out this length here in blue?
Well, we could figure out the magnitude of this vector.
So the length of this side right here is going
to be the magnitude of this vector f.
That will give us this length.
But we want this blue length.
Well, we could think about it.
If this was some angle (I know the writing's getting small)
if this was some angle theta, we could
use some pretty straight up,
pretty straightforward trigonometry.
If the distance under question is d, you could say
cosine of theta is equal to the adjacent side
over the hypotenuse.
or, is equal to d, d is the adjacent side, over the hypotenuse
Well, the hypotenuse is the magnitude of
this vector f.
Or we could say, the magnitude of the vector f
times the cosine of theta
(I'm just multiplying both sides times the magnitude
of vector f)
is equal to d.
So that's still, well you might say
well, Sal, we know what f is.
We could figure that out.
We could figure out its magnitude.
But we don't know what theta is.
How do we figure out what theta is?
And to do that, let's just think about it a little bit
This angle, this angle theta, is the same angle
so this distance here isn't necessarily the same as the
length of the normal vector, but it's definitely
going in the same direction.
So this angle here is the same thing as the angle between
this vector and the normal vector.
And so you might remember from earlier linear algebra
when we talk about the dot products of two vectors
it involves something with the cosine of the angle between them
And to make that fresh in your mind, let's divide
let's multiply and divide
both sides, let me multiply and divide the left side
of this equation by the magnitude of the normal vector.
So I'm obviously not changing its value.
I'm multiplying and dividing by the same number.
So I'm going to multiply by the magnitude
of the normal vector
and I'm going to divide by the magnitude of the normal vector.
So I'm essentially multiplying by 1.
So I have not changed this. But when you do it
in this, it might ring a bell
This expression up here,
this expression right here
is the dot product of the normal vector
and this vector right here, f.
So this right here is the dot product.
This is n dot f up here.
It's equal to the product of their magnitudes times
the cosine of the angle between them.
So the distance, that shortest distance we care about,
is the dot product between this vector
the normal vector divided by the magnitude
of the normal vector.
So let's do that. Let's take the dot product
between the normal and this.
And we already figured out in the last video
the normal vector.
If you have the equation of a plane, the normal vector
is literally, the components are just the
coefficients on the x, y, and z terms
So this is the normal vector right over here.
So let's take
let's literally take
the dot product.
So n dot f is going to be equal to
A times x-naught minus x-p
So it's going to be equal to, I'll do that in pink
So it's going to be A x-naught minus A x-p
and then, plus B times the y component here
so plus B y-naught, I'm just distributing the B
minus B y-p, and then plus
(I'll get another color here)
C (that's too close a color)
plus C times the z component.
So, plus C z-naught minus C z-p
And all of that over the magnitude of the
normal vector.
So what's the magnitude of the normal vector going to be?
It's just the square root of the normal vector
dotted with itself.
So this is just each of these guys squared, added to themselves
and then take the square root.
So the square root is (and I can make a nicer looking radical
sign than that)
So it's the square root of A-squared plus B-squared
plus C-squared.
Now what does this up here simplify to?
Let me just re-write this.
So this is the distance in question. This right here is
equal to the distance.
So let's see if we can simplify it.
So first we can take all of the terms
with the x-naught, these are involved
with the point that sits off the plane
and remember x-naught, y-naught, and z-naught sit off the plane
so this is Ax-naught plus B y-naught plus C z-naught
and then what are these terms equal to?
A x-p
negative A x-p minus B y-p minus C z-p
and if you remember up here,
D in the equation of a plane
D when we started in the last video
when we tried to figure out what the normal to a plane is
D is this point x-p sits on the plane, D is
A x-p plus B y-p plus C z-p
or another way you could say it is
negative D would be negative A (and it's just
the difference between lower case and upper case
here, right. We see that lower case a is the same as this upper case A)
So it's negative A x-p minus B y-p minus C z-p
I'm just using what we got from the last video.
This is what D is, so negative D is just this business.
And that's exactly what we have over here.
negative A x-p, negative B y-p, negative C z-p.
So all of this term, this term, and this term,
simplifies to a minus D.
And remember, this negative capital D, this is the
D from the equation of the plane
NOT the distance d.
So this is the numerator of our distance
and then the denominator of our distance
is just the square root of A-squared plus B-squared
plus C-squared.
And we're done!
This tells us the distance between any point and a plane
And this is a pretty intuitive formula here.
Because all we're doing--
if we have some
Let me give you an example.
If I have the plane 1x minus 2y plus 3z is equal to five
so that's some plane.
and let me pick some point that's not on the plane
So let's say I have the point 2,3, (and let me make sure
this is not on the plane
so it's 2 minus six is negative, yes, let me just pick
a random 1. So this is definitely not on the plane
because we have 2 minus six plus 3, that gives us negative 1
which is not 5, so this is definitely not on the plane)
We can find the distance between this point and the plane
using the formula we just derived.
We literally just evaluate it at
so this will just be
1 times 2 minus 2 times (I'm going to fill it in)
plus 3 times something minus 5
All of that over (and I haven't put these guys in,
let me do that right now)
So 1 times 2 minus 2 times 3 plus 3 times 1
minus 5 (kind of bringing it over to the left hand side)
all of that over the square root
of 1 squared (which is 1) plus negative 2 squared (which is 4)
plus 3 squared (which is 9)
so it's going to be equal to
let's see, this is 2 minus 6 (or negative 6)
and then you have plus 3, minus 5
so this is what, this is 5, 2 plus 3 is 5
minus 5, so those two just cancel out
so this is negative 6 over
the square root of 5 plus 9 is 14
over the square root of 14.
And you're done.
So hopefully you find that useful and hopefully you can apply that in other example problems