what i want to do in this video is to think about fairly traditional business.
i am going to do the orange juice business.
right over here i have written the gallons of orange juice
that i am going to produce each week
so all of these are going to be a per week basis
this is my fixed cost.
so i assume that it's going to cost me one thousand dollars.
let's say that's the rent fot this super robotic orange juicer that i bought
that can really... and through that for the sake of simplicity,
we can assume that we can produce as much orange juice as we want
as any of the amount i listed right over there
and it also takes into the cost of paying some employees
or spending some of the time uprating this super orange juice maker.
some assume that all of these are fixed cost,
that i can't get out of them or buy them overnight
that i decided that i plunked down the cost of machine, that i've already given these employees one year contract.
so these are going to be fixed at least for the next year.
now my variable cost here
this is going to be given the amount of juice i wanna produce
this is going to be my cost of oranges
and i guess we can also see the cost of transporting the oranges.
so we see here, obviously if we produce no orange juice, we have no variable cost.
if we produce a thousand oranges, then our cost of the oranges and transporting them is 500 dollars.
if we produce two thousand, it's 850.
something interesting happens.
our incremental variable cost right over here when it's only 350 dollars.
the first thousand of oranges is 500. and then the next thousand it is only 350.