My name is Marc Ecko. I am by nature, an artist.
I came up at a time when there was a very unique window in popular culture.
Hip hop was emerging. There's an entrepreneurial virus that is hip hop,
that rock and roll didn't quite have in the same way.
There was a little more self-loathing amongst the rock set,
in terms of the commercialization of their work.
Where in hip hop, it's been embraced to go create industry around your ideas.
It's become a part of the ecosystem, because it's coming from nothing, right?
And there's kind of this implied element of social justice, as well, in the business,
born out of, like, what is hip hop and street culture.
So, that's kind of baked into the DNA of what we do.
I love this fact that folks are making something from nothing, in my peer set.
We're founding value, basically in the ether amongst themselves.
Four rappers will get together, rhyme in a circle, and all of the sudden
it's like "Oh, let's make a mix tape". Like, from nothing.
I wanted to fit into the ecosystem. I couldn't rap, I couldn't breakdance, right?
But I did connect to art, so I kind of started to parrot the art of graffiti.
And started painting t-shirts. I love the emotive - the feedback.
Both the financial feedback, that someone would pay me, as 15 year old kid, to make them this t-shirt.
And then they would wear it with such pride, and kind of beat their chest.
There was that kind of emotional transaction that was really powerful
and created the feedback loop to want me to go and dig deeper.
and pull on that thread, to keep on unfolding what eventually became this path of entrepreneurship.
It wasn't like I onboarded because someone said "Be an entrepreneur!"
Right? I onboarded because I wanted to realize my dream.
I was an emotional, artistic kid, and graffiti was kind of the extreme sport of art.
That was a moment of luck for me, so when people are "Oh, graffiti is a gateway to crime"
Right? For me, it was a gateway to entrepreneurship. Go figure.
I've really kind of been a curator of, like, pop culture.
for let's say, males, 16-40. And that's been my lane, having come up in the 80's
around hip hop and skateboarding culture - kind of the emergence of technology.
I've just kind of trafficked in my hobbies.
The things I consumed, as a kid, are now the business.
Young people know, instinctively, what it is they need to do.
Just need to go out there and get it done.
Shifting from what is effectively a consumer mindset, to believing in themselves to be a producer.
Going from "I am consumer of X" to "I am maker of Y".
That's an aspiration that is amongst all of us, but some of us, we just don't know how to do it.
We kind of doubt ourselves.
Why is it that you go to a classroom of Kindergartners
You ask them &quot;Who in this room is an artist?&quot;
Everybody raises their hand.
You ask that same cohort, 20 years later, no one raises their hand. Maybe one guy.
They look at him like he's a freak.
Something is wrong there.
You have to connect to your artist, your instigator.
You know, it's right brain, it's left brain, it's chocolate, it's peanut butter. You have to find that.