Sal: This is Sal here, and I have Dr. David Agus visiting the office,
and I want you to introduce yourself, because you have kind of an interesting life.
Dr.: "Interesting Life," is scary, but I'm a Professor of Medicine and Engineering
at the University of Southern California.
I treat cancer patients and I have a lab that looks at new ways
and technologies to understand, and treat cancer.
Sal: And that's what's really interesting- the fact that you're a professor of both medicine and engineering.
And I guess that's kinda what we're gonna touch on a little bit here.
Dr.: Yeah.
Sal: And so, this is clearly a picture of eggs. Why are we looking at eggs?
Dr.: Well, if I gave you those eggs, and I put them in your office, and I say "Come back in three weeks",
what would you have?
Sal: If I . . . they would go bad. I'm not putting one in a fridge, I'm assuming.
Dr.: You have a rotten egg, exactly.
But, If I was clever and I changed the temperature of your office to 99.5 degrees Fahrenheit
and I rotated those eggs three times, it has to be an odd number,
and at the end of three weeks, I'd have a chicken.
Sal: And a chick, you'd have this,
so, you could either have a rotten egg, so this kind of crazy-mess-smelly-thing;
or you have this cute, adorable, chicken.
Well, though, they call babies "chicks".
Chicks. A babe-oo, uh, a chick. laugh
Dr.: Yes, so a small change in temperature and gravity goes from chaos to order.
Sal: Right, right.
And so, we're going to talk in a minute about cancer and all the chaos that's involved with it,
but realize that, that egg, I changed the temperature and the gravity,
and I went from chaos to order.
so, while it will seem incomprehensible and unable to model cancer,
you're going to start to see little changes can have major effects.
Sal: I see. And this is what's a little bit un-intuitive. So when we think about things like cancer,
I mean cancer's not the only one, we imagine that we just kinda kill it.
We just gotta take it out, but what you're saying is that, "Hey, maybe there's these subtle things,
that's analogous to rotating an egg, 3 times, and to get the temperature just right,
that can make it automatically do different things
Exactly. To me, cancer is a verb, not a noun.
So, you're cancering...
..when you have cancer. It's not that you have cancer, you're cancering.
So, my goal is to change your state of your body from a cancering to a healthing.
and so the fisrt question is - how do you quantitate the state? How do we say
who and what you are?
And so, technology is giving us the opportunity to do that as we go forward.
Right, I just get my head around that because that's just, you know,
word cancering, I think, you've probably invented that word, and so healthing
and it's from the idea - once again, when I imagine cancer, and I think it's the way most researchers think about cancer
?????????????????
and you have to remove them or kill them somehow, stop them from spreading
and what you're saying is not that something is going on systemically in your body
that it's cancering it's allowing cancer to thrive.
That's it. Your first definiton - you something have to cut out , the different organism
That's bacteria. That's an infection.
Something from the oustide comes inside of you
I give you the right antibiotic - it doesn't care if you are a man or a woman, you're six feet or three feet.
If that antibiotic targets the bacteria, it goes away.
The difference in cancer it's your own cells that have gone a little bit crazy
a so we have to change the interaction of the body and the cells and order to make the patient better.
Very different that something without, this is within.