Create a graph of the linear equation 5x plus 2y is equal to 20.
So the line is essentially the set of all coordinate, all x's and y's that satisfy this relationship right over here.
To make things simple what we're going to do is we're going to set up a table where we're going to put a bunch of x values in
and then figure out the corresponding y value based on this relationship.
But to make it a little bit simpler, I'm going to solve for y here so it becomes easier to solve for y for any given x.
So we have 5x plus 2y is equal to 20.
If we want to solve for y, let's just get rid of the 5x on the left hand side,
so let's subtract 5x from both sides of this equation.
The left hand side, these guys cancel out.
So we get 2y is equal to the right hand side, you have 20 minus 5x.
And then you can divide both sides of this equation by 2.
So you divide both sides by 2.
The left hand side we just have a y, and then the right hand side... we kind of leave it that way.
That actually would be a pretty straight-forward way to leave it, but or we could call this 20 divided by 2 is 10 minus 5x over 2
or minus five-halves times x.
Listen, since we're using this let's just come up with a bunch of x values and see what the corresponding y values are and then just plot them.
So let me do this in a new color.
So let me... a slightly different shade of yellow...
So we have x values and let's think about what the corresponding y value is going to be.
So I'll start... well, I can start anywhere.
I'll start at x equals zero just 'cause that tends to keep things pretty simple.
If x is zero then y is equal to 10 minus five-halves times zero which is equal to five-halves times zero is just a zero.
So it's just a 10 minus zero or 10.
So that gives us the coordinate, the point, (0,10).
When x is zero, y is 10. So zero, so x is zero so it's going to be right here in the middle of the x axis.
And then you go up 10 for the y coordinate.
[counting] 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.
So, it's right over here.
So that's the point (0,10).
Let's do another point. Let's say that x is 2.
I'm going to pick multiples of two here, just so that I've got a nice, clean answer, here.
So when x is 2, then y is equal to 10 minus five-halves times 2.
And the 2 in the denominator cancels out with the 2 in the denomin... in the numerator.
So simplifies to 10 minus 5 or just 5.
So that tells us the point.
x equals 2, y is equal to 5 is on the line.
So, 2, x is equal to [counting] one, two, right over here, and y is equal to 5.
We go up five.
[counting] 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. And just like that.
So that's the point (2,5).
Now, when you're drawing a line, you actually just need two points.
Actually, if you have a ruler or any straight edge, we can just connect these two points.
And if we do it neatly, every... every point on that line should satisfy this relationship right here.
Just so we get practice, I'll do more points.
So let me do... let's say I want x is equal to 4.
Then y is equal to 10 minus five-halves times four.
This is equal to five-halves times 4, this is equal to 10, right?
'cause the two... divide the denominator by 2; you get 1.
Divide the numerator by 2, you get 2.
Or four over two is the same thing as 2, so it becomes 2 times 5 is 10.
10 minus 10 is a ZERO, so the point (4,0) is on our line.
So, x is [counting] 1, 2, 3, 4, and then y is zero so we don't move up at all.
So we have four... (4,0).
And I could keep going. I can try other points.
You could do them if you like, but this is plenty. Just two of these would have been enough to draw the line.
So let me just, let me just draw it, so I'll do it in white.
So the line will look something like this.
The line will look something... the line will look something like... something like that.
And I can keep going in both directions.
So there you have it.
That is the graph of our linear equation.
Let me make the line, my line a little bit bolder just in case you found that first line hard to read.
So maybe we can make it a little bit bolder. I think you get the general idea.