We have 7329 - 6278.
So let's go place by place,
and see if we can subtract.
6278 is clearly less than 7329,
so we should be able to do this.
So, first we go to the ones place.
We're subtracting an 8 from a 9.
That seems pretty straightforward.
That's just going to be a 1–
a 1 in the 1's place.
It literally just represents 1.
Then we go to the the 10's place.
And we’re trying to subtract a 7 from a 2.
And this is really representing 70.
And this is really representing 20.
Well now, we’re hitting a bit of a stumbling block.
So we’re going to have to regroup or borrow.
And to understand what we're doing,
let’s rewrite both of these numbers.
So 7329.
7, we can rewrite as being equal to 7000.
... plus 300.
So this 3 in the 100's place is representing 300.
The 7 in the 1,000's place is 7000.
The 3 in the 100's place is 300.
The 2 in the 10's place, that’s 2 10’s, or 20.
And then the 9 in the 1's place
is just going to be 9.
So this is another way of representing 7329.
And then down here, we have the 6
in the 1000's place.
Well that's going to be 6000.
We’re subtracting. So minus 6000.
And then here, we have a 2 in the 100's place.
And once again, we are going to be
subtracting all of these.
So we're going to be subtracting 200.
And then here in the 10's place, we have our 7 –
and we're subtracting it.
So 7 10's, that's 70.
And then we have –
We're subtracting that 8.
And what we've already done is we've said,
"Hey, look. Subtracting 8 from 9?
That’s just going to be 1.”
But then we got over here and we said,
“Hey! How are we going to subtract 70 from 20?”
And the key here is to regroup
some of the value up here,
and give it to the 10's place,
so that we can then subtract 70 from it.
And the most natural place to go
is one place value above.
So we could take 100 from the 300 –
so we could take 100 from the 300.
So then it will become 200.
We're going to give 100 to –
We are going to give that 100 to the 10's place.
So it is going to become 120.
Notice, 200 + 120 is 320.
300 + 20 is 320.
We have not changed the value of the number.
We've just changed what place
we're representing it in.
If we wanted to do it here, we could say –
And this is kind of the –
When you think of it this way,
this is really regrouping --
and this is really what's happening.
But if you want to think of it
in a borrowing framework,
you could say, “Hey let's take 1 from the 3 –
Although that’s a 300. So you’re really taking 100.
That becomes a 2.
And you give that 1 to the 10's place.
And so that becomes a 12.
Now, what was really happening is you took 100,
and you gave it to the 20, so it became 120.
But now you can subtract.
Here, you’d say, "Well, what’s 120 - 70?"
Well, 120 - 70 is going to be 50.
Over here you could say, “Well what's 12 - 7?”
Well that's 5.
But it’s still representing the same thing.
12 10's is 120.
7 10's is 70.
And they give you 5 10's –
which is the same thing as 50.
This 5 represents that 50.
And then we can go to the other places.
You say 2 - 2. Well that's 0 100's.
And then 7000 - 6000 is 1000.
And once again, right over here,
200 - 200 is 0 100's.
And then 7000 - 6000 is 1000.
So this is going to be 1000 + 000 + 50 + 1 ...
which is the exact same thing as 1051.
The important thing is to visualize –
You don't have to write this out every time.
But [the important thing is] to make sure you visualize
in your head that this 3 is representing 300 –
that this 2 represents 20 –
that when you're taking 100 from the 300,
then you'd represent that as a 2
in the 100's place.
And then when you give a 100 to the 10's place,
it's essentially like adding –
it's essentially that the 2 10's will become 12 10's
– because you're giving it 10 more 10's.
You’re giving it a 100.
So hopefully that makes some sense.