Let's say that the economy of Country A is
stagnating, its maybe facing a deflationary crisis,
so Central Bank tries to print as much money and
lower interest rates as much as possible. And an
investor can go into Country A and borrow in A's
currency at a 1% interest rate. Lets also say that in the
rest of the world, and in particular, in Country B, one
can actually make relatively, or what you perceive as
safe investments, at a higher interest rate in Country B's currency.
And so lets say that you can get a 5% return.
So you can imagine that some opportunistic investors
might say "Wow I could borrow in Country A's currency"
and so lets say they go into Country A, they borrow
at 1% and in particular they borrow 100, and I won't call
them Dollar's or Yen, or Euros, I'll call them 100 A's where
the name of A's currency is an A. So they borrow 100 A's
and lets say the conversion rate, right now at this point in time,
1A = 2B's. So they go into currency markets
and they exchange it for every 1A they get 2B's. So
they exchange it for 200 B's, and then they go and
invest it, they are investing in B's. So they are borrowing
in A's and they are investing in B's. And so what would happen?
Well, they're going to get 5% on their money in B's, so 5%
of 200, they're going to get 10 B's (lets say that's per year)
So they're going to get 10 B's in interest every year. And then they can convert that. They
can convert those 10 B's, if we assume the exchange rate
holds constant, and that is a big assumption. They can convert that to 5A's
based on the same exchange rate. So that will be 5 A's,
but they only have to pay 1A in interest, and so they're just going to get 4 A's
per year, if we assume constant exchange rate, they're going to get 4 A's
a year for free, assuming that they could continue to do this
and then they could take those 4 A's and convert them to B's or
whatever other currency they want. So you could say
they're getting 4 A's for free every year, or they're getting
8 B's per year every year. And this little process, this
trade, this little perceived arbitrage thats going on right over here, this is
called the carry trade. You might think, where would
this break down? Well the main area where this would break down is while
you were borrowing in A, then investing in B, if A's currency
appreciates, especially relative to B's currency, because
then what happens, even though you have this interest rate
discrepancy and even though you feel like your getting 10 B's,
those 10 B's are going to give you fewer and fewer A's
if A keeps appreciating. Or another way to think about it is,
your going to in terms of B's, even though you think you only owe
1% interest A is also going to appreciate, so in terms
of B's your going to owe more and more B's every year
if A appreciates. Now what's worked out in the carry trade
or at least the most famous of the carry trades, where
starting in the mid-90's, people started borrowing in
Japan because they had low interest and then investing other places,
like the US, and especially other places like Iceland,
is that the more people do this, so you can imagine, if a
lot of people keep doing this and it becomes kind
of a big herd effect, what happens? You have a bunch
of people borrowing in A and then converting it to B. So they're taking this
currency and converting it to the magenta currency. And if that
happens, then you actually have the opposite
effect. Then you have a benefit on top of the interest rate
discrepecy because that means the demand for B's
currency goes up, and demand for A goes down. And
this is essentially what happened, relative to Japan and
a lot of the rest of the world when Japan had its lower interest rates, all the way until really about 2008.