So I have two 2-dimensional vectors right over here, vector a and vector b.
And what I want to think about is how can we define,
or what would be a reasonable way to define the sum of vector a + vector b.
Well one thing that might jump at your mind is, look each of these are 2-dimensional
they both have two components
Why don't we just add the corresponding components?
So for the sum, why don't we make the first component of the sum,
just the sum of the first two components of these two vectors
So why don't we just make it 6 + -4
Well 6 + -4 is equal to 2
And why don't we just make the second component,
the sum of the two second components
So -2 + 4 is also equal to 2
So we start with two 2-dimensional vectors
you add them together, you get another 2-dimensional vector
if you think about it in terms of real coordinate spaces
both of these are members of R2, I'll write this down here so we get used to the notation
So vector a, and vector b are both members of R2.
Which is just another way of saying that these are both two 2-tuples
They're both 2-dimensional vectors right over here.
Now this might make sense just looking at how we represented it
but how does this actually make visual or conceptual sense
and to do that, lets actually plot these vectors
Lets try to represent these vectors in some way, lets try to visualize them
So vector a we could visualize, this tells us how far this vector moves
in each of these directions, horizontal direction and vertical direction
so if we put the "tail" of the vector at the origin,
and remember, we don't have to put the tail at the origin
but that might make it a little bit easier for us to draw it
we'll go 6 in the horizontal direction, one, two, three, four, five, six
and then -2 in the vertical, so negative 2
So vector a could look like this
And once again, the important thing is the magnitude and the direction
The magnitude is represented by the length of this vector
and the direction is the direction that it's pointed in
and also just to emphasize, I could have drawn vector a like that
or I could have put it over here, these are all equivalent vectors
these are all equal to vector a
all I really care about is the magnitude and the direction
So with that in mind, let's also draw vector b
Vector b, in the horizontal direction goes -4, one, two, three, four
and then the vertical direction it goes 4, one, two, three, four
so if it's tail is at the origin, it's head would be at -4, 4
So let me draw that, just like that
So that right over here is vector b
And once again, vector b we could draw it like that or we could draw it
let me copy and let me paste it
so this would also be another way to draw vector b
once again what I really care about is its magnitude and its direction
all of these green vectors have the same magnitude, they all have the same length
and they all have the same direction
so how does the way that I drew vector a and b jell with what its sum is
So let me draw its sum like this in this blue color
So the sum, based on this definition we just used,
the vector addition would be 2, 2, so it would look something like this
So how does this make sense? That this purple vector
plus this green vector is somehow equal to this blue vector
and I encourage you to pause the video and think about if that even make sense
Well one way to think about it is, this first purple vector,
it shifts us this much, it takes us from this point to that point
and so if we were to add it, lets start at this point
and put the green vector's tail right there and see where it ends up putting us
so the green vector, we already have a version
so once again we start at the origin, vector a takes us there
Now lets start over there with the green vector and see where the green vector takes us
And this makes sense, vector a + vector b
Put the tail of vector b at the head of vector a
so if you were to start at the origin, vector a takes you there
then if you add on what vector b takes you, it takes you right over there
so relative to the origin, how much did you , I guess you can say.. shift?
And once again, vectors don't only apply to things like displacement
it could apply to velocity, it can apply to electrical acceleration
it could apply to a whole series of things
but when you visualize it this way, you see that it does make complete sense
this blue vector, the sum of the two, is what results when you
start with vector a, at that point right over there, vector a takes you there
then you take vector b's tail, start over there, and it takes you to the tip of the sum.
Now one question you might be having is, well vector a + vector b is this,
but what is vector b + vector a?
Does this still work?
Well, based on the definition we had, where you add the corresponding components
you're still going to get the same sum vector, so it should come out the same
So this would just be -4 + 6 is 2,
4 + -2 is 2, but does that make visual sense?
So if we start with vector b, so lets say you start right over here
vector b takes you right over there, and then if you were to go there
and you would start with vector a, so let's do that
actually, let me start with a new vector b
So lets say that that is our vector b, right over there
and, actually let me give this a place where I'll have some space to work with
So if that's my vector b, right over there
and then let me get my copy of vector a,
that's a good one, copy
and let me paste it
So I could put vector a's tail at the tip of vector b
and then it will take me right over there
So if I start here, vector b takes me there
and now I'm adding to that vector a, which will starting here take me there
and so from my original starting position, I have gone this far
Now what is this vector?
Well this is exactly the vector 2, 2!
Or another way of thinking about it, this vector should shift you
2 in the horizontal direction, and 2 in the vertical direction.
So either way, you are going to get the same result
And that should hopefully make visual or conceptual sense as well.