Im going to start with a fair coin and I'm going to flip it four times
and the first question i ask is what is the exact probability
exactly one head or heads which is one of those confusing things
when you're talking about what side of the coin
and I know I have been not doing this consistently
I'm tempted to say if you're saying one it feels like
you should do the singular which would be head
but I read it up on the, I read up a little bit of it
on the internet and it seems like when you're talking about coins,
you really should say one heads which seems a little difficult for me
but I'll try to go with that
So what is the probability of getting exactly 1 heads?
And I put that in quots to see the point, which is really...
We are just talking about 1 heads there.
But it's called "heads" when you are doing with coins.
Anyway I think you get what I am talking about.
Let's think about how many different possible ways
we can get four flips over a coin.
So we are going to have one flip, then another flip,
then another flip, then another flip.
And this first flip has two possibilities that could be heads or tails
The second flip has two possibilities that could be heads or tails.
The third flip has two possibilities could be heads or tails.
And the fourth flip has two possibilities that could be heads or tails
So you have 2 times 2 times 2 times 2
which is equal to 16 possibilities.
16 possible outcomes when you flip a coin 4 times.16 possible outcomes
And any one of the possible outcomes would be 1/16.
So if I want to say the probability
I am gonna not talk about this one head. If I just take,
just you know maybe this thing has three heads right here.
This is exact sequence of the event.
This is the first flip, second flip, third flip, fourth flip,
getting exactly this. This is exactly 1 out of possible of 16 events.
Now with that out of the way, let's think about
how many of those 16 possibilities involved getting exactly one heads?
We can list them. You could get your heads. So this is equal to
the probability of getting the heads in the first flip,
plus the probability of getting the heads in the second flip,
plus the probablity of getting the heads in the third flip,
remember exactly one heads, nothing at least 1, exactly 1 heads.
So the probability in the third flip,
and then or the possibility you get the heads in the fourth flip,
tails heads and tails.
And we know already what the probability of each of these things are.
There are 16 possible events.
Each of these are one of those of 16 possible events.
So this is going to be 1/16, 1/16, 1/16 and 1/16.
And so we really saying the probablity of getting exacly one heads
is the same thing as the probability of getting heads
in the first flip or heads in the second flip,
or heads in the third flip or heads in the fourth flip.
And we can add the probablities of these different things
because they are mutually exclusive.
Any two of these things can not happen in the same time.
You have to pick one of these scenarios.
So we can add the probabilities 1/16 plus 1/16 plus 1/16
plus 1/16 that gets 4 times of all.
Assume that I did. So you'll get 4/16 which is equal to 1/4.
Fair enough. Now let's ask a slightly more interesting question.
Let's ask ourselves, the probability of getting exactly 2 "heads".
There is a couple of ways we can think about it.
One is just in the traditional way.
Let's just, the way you know, the number of possibilities,
equally likely possibilities
You could only use methodology because it is a fair coin.
So how many of the total possibilities have the two heads
of the total of the equally likely possibilities.
So we know there are 16 equally likely possibilities.
How many of those have two "heads"?
So I actually ahead of times so we save time.
I have drawn all of the 16 equally likely possibilities.
And how many of these involed two heads?
Well let's see this one over here has two heads.
This one over here has two heads. This one over here has two heads.
Let's see that's this one over here has two heads.
And this one over here has two heads.
And then this one over here has two heads.
And I believe we are done after that. So if we count them 1,2,3,4,5,6
of the possibilities have exactly two heads.
So 6/16 equally likely possibilities have two heads.
So we have (what is this) 3/8 chance of getting exactly 2 heads.
Now that's kind of what we have been doing in the past.
But I do think about a way
so we wouldn't have to write out all the possibilities.
And the reason why that is useful is we are going to do
the four flips now and if we are doing with 10 flips,
there is no way that we can write out all the possibilities like this
so I really want a different way of thinking about it.
And the different way of thinking about it is
of course we are seeing exactly two heads.
You can imagine what we're having the four flips.
Flip 1, flip 2, flip3, flip 4, so these are the flips.
You can see the outcomes of the flips.
And you are going to have exactly 2 heads. You can sayŁŹ
"Well look, I am going to have 1 head in one of these positions
and then 1 head in the other positions."
So how many... If I am picking the first, so you know,
you could say I have kind of Heads 1 and I have a Heads 2.
And I don't want you to think that these are
somehow the heads in the first flip or the heads in the second flip.
What I am saying is we need 2 heads.
We need in total of 2 heads in all of our flips.
And I am just giving one of the heads a name
and I am giving the other heads a name.
And we are going to see in a few seconds
that we actually don't want a double count.
We don't want to double count the situation: Heads 1, Heads 2,
tails, tails and Heads 2 Heads 1, tails tails.
For our propers, these are exact same outcomes.
So we don't want to double count that.
We are going to have a count for that.
But if we just think about it generally,
how many different flips can that first heads show up in?
Well this 4 different flips that first heads could show up in.
So there are 4 possibilities, 4 flips or 4 places that can show up in.
Well that first head takes up one of these 4 places.
Let's just say the first heads shows up on the third flip.
Then how many different palces can that second head show up in?
Well if that first head is in one of 4 places
and then that second head can only be in three different places,
so that second head can only be (let me put it in nice color here)
can only be in three different places.
And so you know could be any one of these right over there,
any one of those three places.
And so when you think about it in terms of the first,
I don't want to say the first head, Head 1,
actually let me call Head A and Head B,
that what you want to me to talk about it,
first flip or the second flip.
So this is Head A and this right over there is Head B.
So if you had a particular, I mean these heads are identical.
These outcomes are different.
But the way we talk about right now, it looks like 4 places that
we can get this Head A and there 3 places we can get this Head.
So if you multiply all of these different ways,
you could get all of the different scenarios.
This is 4 diferent places and this is in one of the 3 left places.
You get 12 different scenarios. But there are only be 12 scenarios
if you have used this as being different than this.
Let me rewrite it with our news. This is Head A. This is Head B.
This is Head B. This is Head A.
There will be only 12 different scenarios
if you use these two things as fundementally different.
But we don't. We actually double counting because
we can always swap these two heads and have the exact same outcome.
So you want to do is actually divided by 2.
So you wanted to divided by all of different ways
that you can swamp 2 different things.
If we had 3 heads here you will think about all the different ways
that you could swamp 3 different things
if we have 4 heads here be all of the different ways,
you could swamp 4 different things.
So you have there 12 different scenatios
if you couldn't swap them but you want to be divided
by all of the different ways you could swap 2 things.
So 12 divided by 2 is equal to 6, 6 different scenarios,
fundementally different scenarios considering
that you could swamp them.
If you assume that Head A and Head B can be interchangeble
that it's completely identical outcome for us
because there are really just heads.
So there are 6 diffrent scenarios
and we know that there is a total of 16 equally likely scenarios.
So we could say the probability of getting exactly 2 heads is 6 times,
6 scenarios, and we can do this a couple ways.
There are 6 scenarios gives us 2 heads of possible 16
or you could say there are 6 possible scenarios
and the probability of each of the those scenarios is 1/16
but either way you will get the same answer.