so lets say you're walking down the street
and im going to draw you here and you decide to do a little experiment.
you take a deep breath as you're walking and you decide to blow out a cardboard tube
something like that
lets say its like a toilet paper roll
and so you blow out through it
and here in this toilet paper roll
the length is, lets call, l and the radius and i'll call it r
and you know a toilet paper roll is, lets say about 2 cm
radius. That may not be exactly right but lets just assume that.
And you do this and you find that it is so easy to do.
Very easy to take one breath of air and blow it out an blow it out of a cardboard tube