At its core, a bitcoin is just basically a chain
of digital signatures that really reflect the coin's path
through the bitcoin ecosystem. And here, I think it's actually conceptually
easier to think of bitcoins as collective
entries into a ledger rather than as a physical
coin, because if you think about it, in a ledger, you have a record of
transaction histories, which happens with in Bitcoin, whereas with a
physical coin, it's more like a memory list, there's no history
in a physical coin of where the coin has really been in the past, ok?
So, in this context, you can think of a transaction as just a digitally
signed declaration by one party
of its intent to transfer some bitcoins that they possess to
another set of parties. And, when I say that one party possesses a certain number
of bitcoins, I really just mean here that there was some previous transaction on record that everybody's agreed to
in which the party now transfering the bitcoins was itself the recepient
of a previous transfer of those bitcoins. Alright,now I realize it is a bit convoluted,
so maybe to help better understand the mechanics of a transaction, I could do an example of what would happen
in the context of an actual bitcoin transaction.
So let's say we have a party, and let's call her Alice, which is the common
name we use for parties in cryptographic schemes, and let's
say she wants to transfer some bitcoins to Bob,
and let's say she has the intention of wanting to transfer
50 bitcoins to Bob
Now, remember, that anybody who transacts in the bitcoin ecosystem is not
actually not transacting
under their real name, their actual name, but rather they are
going by a very specific identity, a pseudonym
within the bitcoin ecosystem, and that identity, that pseudonym actually
corresponds to a public verification key for a digit signature scheme
So in this case, let's say Alice's identity in the system
is really some public verification key which we'll call
"VK of A," Alice's verification key, and
in the context of Bob, let's say his public verification key is
some "VK sub B." So, these are keys that are used
within digital signature schemes, and so we can that Alice
has generated this key at some point and that she made it public, and then Bob
did the same thing, and so they now both have identities within the system, and these identities
are just sequences of numbers that correspond to public
keys for verification in the context of a cryptographic digital
signature.
Now, remember, that these values also correspond to
private values. So, each person who's got a public key will have
a corresponding private key associated with that public key,
and in this case, we'll call
the private key, or the secret key, which is in fact a sign-in key
in this context, "SK of Alice"
and we'll say that Bob's sign-in key
is some "SK of Bob."
And they're going to basically keep these private.
And let's look at Alice herself, who has received
in the past, three transactions of bitcoins from other parties:
25 bitcoins from Carol, and we'll call Carol "VK of C" to
associate that with her key.
Let's say she got 20 bitcoins from
David, and let's say she got 20 more bitcoins
from Ted. So, these
bitcoins correspond to different people
who provided Alice with bitcoins in the past
and so, as you can see, Alice now
has an aggregate of 65 (20 + 20 + 25) bitcoins.
And so, as a result, she has a sufficient number to
be able to transfer 50 of those bitcoins to Bob.
So, to start off with, a transaction from Alice to Bob for 50 bitcoins
will contain information about these previous transactions.
So, each of these previous transactions, where Alice received some bitcoins,
these have all been recorded in the bitcoin ecosystem.
So, they are going to be made public,
just like every other transaction.
And so, what Alice can actually do is
take some representation of these transactions
and include them as part of the new transaction
basically as an anchor point, saying "I've received
these bitcoins, and now I'm going to transfer
some portion of these bitcoins to you, Bob."
So, in this context, actually she
does not need to include the full transaction details in
in the actual transaction record to Bob. What she can instead do
is take th transaction details and apply a crytographic cash function
to them to get a series of digests for each transaction
So, in this case, let's say she gets a digest that corresponds to
to the transaction from Carol, she has a digest that corresponds
to the digest form David, and she has
a digest that corresponds to the digest from Ted.
So, basically, include each of these digests into the