In the last video I challenged you to write
multiple Fibonacci functions. The ones that could calculate
the "n-th" term of the Fibonacci sequence
either iteratively or recursively and I'll do the first shot
right over here. And I'll show you over the next few videos
that the is really multiple ways of even doing this
iteratively.
So let's define our function "fibonacci" and it has a peremiter "n".
That is what we are going to pass to the function and we know that
by definition the first two terms of the Fibonacci sequence are 0 and 1.
So let's make a list for ourselves and so this is interesting
so this is the first time we are really going to do some,
you know, some actual list manipulation in this video.
So the terms here, the 0-th term of the fibonacci sequence is 0
and the first one is 1.
This is by definition. So we're just gonna kinda hardcode that in right there.
And then what we're gonna do is, then we're going to construct this list
to all of the terms up to and including the "n-th" term.
And then return the "n-th" term from that list. And the reason
why I'm going to do it this way is that it is able to save up
kind of a memory of all the Fibonacci numbers, which is helpul
for computing each incremental Fibonacci number. So let's do it this way.
I'm gonna use the while-loop. You could do it using the for-loop but for me
the while-loop feels a little more natural for this.
And actually before I even define the while-loop, I'm gonna set my
variable of iteration I should say. I'm gonna set that equal to 0.
And your gonna see how this works in a second.
So I'm gonna say while "i" is less than or equal to n, so "i" is
gonna start at 0 and go up to n. And frankly I shouldn't start
at 0. Cause we already have this 0-th term here on the first term here
and we want to construct the second, third, fourth all the way
to the n-th term. So actually let's start "i" at 2. So we
already have the 0-th term in the first term, we then want to
construct the second term so thats why we are going to start "i" equals 2
all the way up to and including the n-th term.
So that's why we say less than or equal to n, we are gonna
keep adding terms to this sequence.
So while "i" is less than or equal to "n", I'm gonna take this list right here
and to the end of that list and this is a built-in function for any list in Python
and you're learning it now and you could look it up and actually my IDE
tells me how to use it. I can add to the end of that list another term.
And that next term I'm going to add at the end of the list is going to be
the SUM of the previous 2 terms. So it is going to be
terms "i" - 1, so thats the previous term, terms "i"-1 literally refers
to the previous term plus terms "i" - 2. So it is essentially going to construct this Fibonacci
sequence and build it in this list and then we are going to increment "i".
I is equal to "i" + 1. If we never increment "i" then this loop
will just keep going on for ever and ever but this way it's gonna keep going
up and up until at some point "i" is not going to be less than or equal to "n"
and then we are going to break out of the loop. And then
when we break out of the loop, we can then return the "n-th"
Fibonacci term in the sequence. So we're going to return the "n-th" term in terms.
So let's see if this works, let's see if this makes sense.
So I'm going to go all the way up to the n-th term.
And actually the "n-th" term here, yes this should work cause if I had
if this was Fibonacci of 0, I want it to return terms of 0 which is this term over here
if it's Fibonacci of 1 I wanna return this term right over here.
So it's the first term in terms over here not 0-th but the first.
So this feels like it should work and actually even before i run it,
i want you to make sure you understand what i've done here with the list.
So I'm gonna show you a little bit of example how these lists work.
So if I define a list as, I don't know, 1,2. That's my list.
And if i then say, it is doing something weird, so I'm gonna define my list as
1 coma 2
So if i type "a" it is 1,2. If I append "a", a.append.
Let's I append a 7 to it then if I look "a" I have a 7 at the end it.
If I wanna refer to the elements here a[0] should be the first element.
The second element, i've just put 2 in the bracket, should give me the 7.
So that is exactly what I'm doing over here.
I'm saying terms of "i" - 1, so we're going to add a new term over here
so this first time we go through the loop we are going to add a new term
and it is going to be the SUM of terms of "i" - 1, so in that first loop "i" is 2
"i" - 1 is 1 so terms of 1 + terms of 0.
So it is going to be terms of 1 which is + terms of 0.
And then it keeps doing that all the way until we construct the n-th term.
Well enough talk and I'll step through it a little bit clearer in the next video
with the particular example but let's just see what we wrote
actually works. So let me run it.
All right.
Let's see if we get the proper results.
Well let's just start at the beginning.
Fibonacci of 0 well that looks good.
Let's try Fibonacci of 1.
That looks good.
Fibonacci of 2 that should also be 1.
Fibonacci of 3 this should be 2 now cause we are taking the SUM of 1 + 1.
That works.
Let's try the Ficonacci of 10.
Hey that looks pretty good.
Let's try the Fibonacci of something huge.
Fibonacci of a 100.
This is a very large number and I'm not going to go into the whole
floating kind of the long numbers and super long large ones but let's try
something a little bit smaller over here.
So let's try Fibonacci of 20.
So it looks like it works and you can verify for yourself.
So this is just one implementation of it and in the next few I'm gonna try
another way to implement it. Maybe I'll do it with a for-loop or we could also do it recursively.