Now this looks like an interesting problem.
We have his polygon. It looks like a pentagon right over here,
has five sides it's an irregular pentagon; not all
the sides looked to be the same length, and the sides are kind of
continued on and we have this particular exterior angles of
this pentagon and what we're asked is what is the sum of all
these exterior angles, and it's kind of daunting 'cause like
they don't give us any other information,
they don't even give us any particular angles,
they don't even give us -- you know they don't start us off anywhere
and so what we can do, let's just think about the step by step
just based on what we do know.
Well we have these exterior angles and these exterior angles
they're all, they're each supplementary to some interior angle,
so maybe if can express them as the function of the interior angles
we can maybe write this problem in a way maybe a little bit
more doable so let's write the interior angles over here
so let's say we have this we already got to letter we already got to E
so let's call this F this interior angle F, let's call this G,
let's call this H, let's call this one I, and F let's call this one J
And so this some of this particular exterior angles
A is now the same thing A is now the same thing as 180 minus G
Because A and G are supplementary so A is 180 minus G
And then we have plus B but we can write in terms of
this interior angle It's gonna be 180 minus H because
these two angles once again Are supplementary we do
that in a new color So this is going to be 180 minus H
and we can do the same thing for each of them
C we can write as 180 minus I so plus 180 minus I
And then D we can write D we can write as 180 minus J
So plus 180 minus J
And then finally E I'm running out of colors
E we can right as 180 minus F so plus 180 plus 180 minus F
And so what we're left with if we add up all the 180s we have
We have a 180 five times
So this is going to be equal to five times 180
which is what like 900
and then we have minus G minus H minus I minus J minus F
or we could write that as minus, minus I'll try to do the same colors
G plus H I'm kind of factoring out this negative sign
G plus H we do the same colors G plus that's not the same color
G plus H, plus I, plus I, plus J, plus j, plus F, plus F
And the whole reason why I did this
And why this is interesting now is that we have expressed it
The first thing we need to figure out we have expressed it
In terms of the sum of the interior angles
So this is gonna be 900 minus all of this business
So this is this is 900 all of this business
Which is the sum of all interior angles
So this is the sum of all interior angles
So it seems like we've made a little progress if we get
at least if we can figure out the sum of the interior angles
and to do that part I'll show you a little trick
what you want to do is divide this polygon the inside of the polygon
into three non over lapping triangles
and so we can do that from any side let me just say
let's say they are all coming out of that side right over there
so there I have divided it let me do this is a in a neutral color
I'm doing it in white so so that's one triangle right over here
And then let me make another triangle just like that
So there you go I've divided it in three non overlapping triangles
And the reason why I did that, the reason why this is valuable
Is that we know what the sum of the angles of the triangles add up to
And so to make that useful we have to express
these angles in terms of the sums or in terms of angles
that we can figure out based on the fact that the sums of the angles
or the measures of an angles in a triangle add up to 180
so G is kind of already one of the angles in the triangle
F is made up of two angles in the triangle
So remember F is this entire angle right over here
So let's let's divide F into two other angles
Or two other measures of angles I should say
So let's call it let's call F is equal to let's say
that F is equal to so we've already gone as high as let's see
ABCDEFGHIJ we haven't used K yet
So let's say that F is equals to K plus L
It's equal to the sum of the measures of
these two adjacent angles right over here
So F is equal to K plus L so that that way we've split it up into
Into part into angles of these other triangles
And then we can do that with J as well with J as well
We can say coz J once again is that whole thing
So we could say that K is equal to let's see we already used L
So let's say J is equals to M plus N so J is equals to M plus N
And then finally we could split up H
H is up here remember this is whole thing
Let's say that H is the same thing as O plus P plus Q
This is O this is P this is Q
And once again I wanted to split up these interior angles
If they're not already parts of or already an angle of a triangle
I wanna split them up into angles that are parts of these triangles
So we have H is equal to O plus P plus Q
And the reason why that's interesting is now we can write
we can write the sum of these interior angles
as the sum of a bunch of angles that are part of these triangles
and then we could use the fact that those
that for any one triangle they add up to 180 degrees so let's do that
so this this expression right over here is gonna be G
G is that angle right over here we didn't make any substitutions
So this is going to be G
And you want me to write the whole thing
So we have 900, 900 minus and instead of a G
Well actually I'm not making a substitution so I can write G
Plus instead of an H instead of an H I can write
that H is O plus P plus Q plus O plus P plus Q and then plus I
plus I, I is sitting right over there, plus I
plus J...
I kinda messed up the colors, the magenta will go with I
and J is the expression right over here,
so J is equal to M plus N
so plus M plus N instead of righting J right there
and then finally we have our F
and F, we've already seen,
is equal to K plus L, plus K plus L
so once again I just rewrote
this part right over here
in terms of these component agles.
And now something very interesting
is going to happen
because we now
what these sums are going to be
because we know that G plus K plus O
is a 180 degrees.
They are the measures of the angle
for this first triangle over here
for this triangle right over here.
So G plus O plus K is a 180 degrees.
So G .... let me do this in a new color...
so for this triangle right over here
this triangle right over here
we know that G plus O plus K
are going to be equal to 180 degrees.
If we cross those out
we can write 180 instead
and then we also know
let me see, I'm definiftely out of colors here...
we know that P for this middle triangle
right over here
we know that P plus L plus M is 180 degrees.
So P plus L plus m is 180 degrees.
So you take those out and you say,
You know that the sum
is going to be equal 180 degrees.
And then finally,
this is the home stretch here,
we know that Q plus N plus I
is 180 degrees
in this last triangle.
Q plus N plus I
Q plus N plus I is 180 degrees.
THose three are also gonna be 180 degrees
and so now we know
the sum of the interior angles
for this irregular pentagon,
which is actually true for any pentagon,
is 180 plus 180 plus 180,
which is 540 degrees.
So that whole thing is 540 degrees
and if we want to get the sum
of the extra angles
we just subtract it from 900.
So 900 minus 540 is going to be 360 degrees.
And we are done. This is equal to 360 degrees.