We'll return back to 1770, and look at what
Leonard Euler said at the time.
"Mathematicians have tried in vain
to discover some order
in the sequence of prime numbers.
But we have every reason to believe
that there are some mysteries
which the human mind will never penetrate."
Okay?
And thirty years later, here's a quote from Gauss.
"The problem of distinguishing
prime numbers from composite numbers,
and resolving composite numbers into their
prime factors, is known as one of the most
important and useful [problems] in the arithmetic.
All methods that have been proposed thus far
are either restricted to very special cases,
or are so difficult that they try the patience
of even the practiced calculator.
The dignity of science itself seems to require
that every possible means be explored
for the solution of a problem
so elegant and so celebrated."
Wow!
So these two great thinkers have really
set the stage for the challenge ahead of us.
And now, I'm going to fast-forward to 2010,
and show you a paper
that came out of the 'RSA competition' --
which is a competition that no longer runs.
But the purpose of the competition was
to put out a large number and say,
"Can anyone factor it?"
So in 2010, this winning team
factored a 768-bit number.
(And that means it was a 232-digit number,
if you're thinking in base ten.)
So this team -- in 2010 -- they won the competition
by factoring a 232-digit number.
So that's how far we have come from Euler to --
(Or we can go back to Euclid.)
But from from Euler to 2010,
we're at 232-digit numbers.
And here was the answer in their paper.
So this was the first prime.
This was p1.
And this was p2.
So this is the state of the art right now.
Okay. How did they factor this number?
And what are the state-of-the-art techniques?
Well, we're going to go back
and build from the beginning.
And this kind of defines 'computational number theory.'
That is the topic of this adventure.
So what does computational number theory mean?
Well, 'computation' comes from the Greek word for 'gravel.'
Stones were used for counting.
Computation is any type of calculation --
whether you're using stones, or a ruler,
or a slide rule, or a calculator,
or this cool looking machine --
which is Babbage's 'Difference Engine' --
which was a hand-powered calculator.
It doesn't matter what you're using
or [if] you're using a computer -- [or not].
You're doing some sort of computation.
And now, what kind of computation are we doing?
Number theory.
And that involves this mysterious distribution
of prime numbers -- studying this distribution.
And what we're actually looking at
is 'multiplicative' number theory --
which is questions of
"How do you factorize numbers?"
"How do you tell me if a number is prime?"
-- and so forth.
And we begin with a very simple question, or --
not a question -- a challenge.
We need to build a machine which takes an input --
(And that input is some integer, 'x.')
And all that machine needs to do
is output 'true' or 'false.'
And that is the first step.
Now we will use the
[Khan Academy] computer-science tool
to actually build this machine together.
And one of the questions
that we will be asking is two things --
two aspects to this machine.
How much time --
That's a clock. [CHUCKLES]
How much time does it take to get the solution?
And how much space does it need?
And when I say 'space,'
I mean -- for example, in the case of
this mechanical calculator -- physical space.
How many rooms do we need to hold our machine?
Or if we're using a computer,
how much memory does it need?
So we will be returning
to these two ideas as we go.