We now live in a culture where the new is sought after,
where the new is something that we want. But in Victorian culture,
the new was something that was not always trusted. Ruskin
referred to all the new furnishings in the picture that we are looking at
within Holman Hunt's 'Awakening Conscience' having a fatal
newness. The newness of the piano, the newness of the table,
the newness of the rug. All of this was meant to suggest a kind of
falseness actually. And it is a perfect example of the
concerns of Victorian culture in this fabulous Pre-Raphaelite
image. So we are looking at a kept woman and we see her
with her lover. We are in a space that is her apartment, filled with
brand-new furniture, and new wallpaper and prints on the wall... that he
has bought for her - yes - in order to create a pied a terre place that he can
escape to. She is probably of lowly origin. I mean this is
all standard narrative that Victorians knew and it had been
repeated over and over again of a girl who came from the countryside and became a
fallen woman, or a kept woman, in the city, who is compromised by a class
above her. She has been sitting on the lap of her lover who has been playing the
piano. But unbeknownst to him he plays a song that
reminds her of her childhood and at that moment
she remembers her past innocence and experiences
a spiritual awakening, an awakening of her
conscience. So she is a subject that we see often in Victorian paintings. She is a
fallen woman but at a moment of redemption. Look at the way that
tha artist has organized the painting. We are looking at her and we are looking at her
sconced in all of this luxury of the home that he has created
for her but this artificial place that is not real. Where nothing is worn,
where nothing is used, where nothing has been transformed by the life of a
real family. But she is facing almost towards us and we can see
her reflection in the mirror and back of her and we can see that she is looking
towards the outside. And so here, nature and light take on
the role of the spiritual, take on the role of the moral that she needs
to now move towards. That is right. And that is really what interested
Holman Hunt. He was a very religious man
and is using this modern life subject to speak to a bigger issue
of spiritual transformation. And how