[MUSIC PLAYING]
Ever since people have been
lending money to each other,
there's been one fundamental
problem.
What happens when someone can't
pay back their debts?
What are you going to do?
And before I really jump into
what we do now in our modern
society, let's get a couple of
the I'll words out of the way
that we're going to use a lot.
And these are words that you'll
hear a lot in the
context of debt, or in
the context of loans.
So on one side of
the transaction,
you have the debtor.
And this is essentially
the person that
borrowed the money.
And because they borrowed the
money, they now owe money.
So you could either say they
borrowed the money or that
they owe money.
On the other side of
the transaction,
you have the creditor.
This is the entity, or the
person, that is owed the
money, or they lent the
money to the borrower.
So they lend the money.
So we have our words out of the
way, but let's go back to
our fundamental question.
What happens when the debtor
can't pay the creditor back
the money that the creditor
is apparently due?
Well, if we go back through
human history, they've come up
with various solutions to this
problem, we can call it.
If you go back to ancient
Greece, they had a very simple
solution to it.
If the debtor can't pay back
their debts, well then become
a debt slave to the creditor.
So they became a debt slave.
So if the creditor needs some
gardening done or would like
his or her house cleaned more
regularly, the debtor-- and
actually, probably the debtor's
family-- would have
then had to do whatever the
creditor wanted until they
essentially paid back their
debt through their labor.
So that's how Greece
handled it.
It's kind of shocking
to us now, but
that was their solution.
You decided to borrow money, you
can't pay it anymore, this
is what you've got to do.
Now if we fast forward a little
bit to maybe medieval
Europe, this is even-- Charles
Dickens' father was even
caught into this
kind of a bind.
But until kind of the early or
mid-1800s in Europe and the
United States you had the notion
of debtor's prison.
And frankly, when I describe
this to you, you'll find that
it's even worse in my mind than
being a debt slave. In
debtor's prison, they would
throw you in jail.
They would imprison you.
That's why it's called
debtor's prison.
And you're not coming out
until your family
pays off your debt.
Your family or maybe your
friends, if you have good
friends, pays off your debt.
Just thinking about why this
is especially horrible, at
least here you had your chance
to work off your debt.
My situation right now.
You know, if I get thrown in
prison will my 10-month-old
son be able to pay
off my debt?
No, I'm just going to rot
in prison forever.
Or what if my family
doesn't like me?
Or what if I have no
family or friends?
I might have owed someone the
equivalent of now of $1,000
and because of that,
I could serve a
life sentence in prison.
You can imagine the debtor's
prison could be quite harsh.
And actually, Charles Dickens'
dad was in debtor's prison.
It can kind of tell you a little
bit about why he writes
the type of books
that he does.
But anyway, this is the past.
We are now a civilized
society, and hopefully we have
a better way of dealing with
the situation when a debtor
owes a creditor money.
And that's the topic
of this video.
And so now what we do is
something called bankruptcy.
And just so you know, the first
versions of bankruptcy
weren't that different
from debtor's prison.
They were actually more to
protect the creditor than to
protect the debtor.
But now we have bankruptcy laws,
and for the most part,
they're to prevent this type of
craziness or for someone to
spend their entire
life on kind of
this wacky debt treadmill.
So let's talk a little
bit about bankruptcy.
And I'm going to focus on
bankruptcy as it is in the
United States.
So let me write down bankruptcy
in a new color.
Bankruptcy.
It's going to have
a U.S. focus.
And in general I'm going
to talk about personal
bankruptcy, although a lot of
what I talk about on some
level, applies to corporations
as well.
And I've actually made videos
on that as well.
So let's say I'm just
overwhelmed with debt.
I have $100,000 of credit
card loans.
I have a mortgage to pay.
I have a car lease that was
a little bit over my head.
What can I do?
So there's a couple of options
in the United States.
You have Chapter 7.
It seems very complicated.
These are all different--
literally-- chapters of the
bankruptcy code.
So you have Chapter 7.
It is called a straight
bankruptcy.
And this is literally
you go-- I mean it's
not a simple procedure.
But the gist of it is, you go
to the bankruptcy courts.
You say, look, I can't
pay back my debts.
And so what they're going to do
is they're going to take my
assets and then whatever there
is there, they're going to
split it amongst my creditors.
And then after all is said and
done, I don't owe anyone
anything, although I've lost
a lot of my assets.
Some of them are exempt.
They let you keep things that
you need to live, like your
pots and pans and maybe
one television.
And maybe a suit so that
you can find a job.
But if I have a bank account, I
probably don't because I got
so deep into debt.
But if I have some money, if I
have a nice diamond ring or a
Rolex watch, they're going
to take that from me.
The trustee, the bankruptcy
court, is going to take that
from me, sell it, and then give
it to all my creditors.
But at the end of the day, after
all is said and done,
I'll actually be free
of all of my debt.
It's kind of a way to break
from this cycle of always
owing money and always just
barely making it, or probably
not making it at all.
So that's a straight
bankruptcy.
And you might say, well, why
doesn't everyone do that who's
under a big, heavy
load of debt?
Well one, there's a lot of rules
that make this easier or
not so easy to do.
But the other thing is it stays
on your credit report
for 10 years.
10 years on credit report.
So you've got to think to
yourself, am I going to be
better off over the next
10 years continuing
to pay off my debt?
If I can pay off my debt, if
I have any chance, I should
probably do that so that I don't
ruin my credit for the
next 10 years.
But if it's just a hopeless
situation, I
might as well do it.
And just so you know.
This isn't a cure
for everything.
If you're sitting on $300,000 of
student loans, I say, wow,
that's going to take me more
than 10 years to pay anyway.
Let me just declare Chapter
7 bankruptcy.
It'll be unfortunate to find
out that student loans are
not-- cannot be forgiven in
a Chapter 7 bankruptcy.
So there's a whole set of a
types of loans, or I guess you
could say, types of liabilities,
things you owe to
other people that cannot
be forgiven.
Certain types of taxes, student
loans, child support,
those won't be forgiven.
This will definitely apply
to things maybe
like credit card loans.
But this isn't just a very,
very simple process.
So any of these things that I
talk about, you definitely
want to consult an expert on
your kind of particular
situation to get a little
bit more detail.
But this is just an overview.
So that's Chapter 7, straight
up bankruptcy.
I don't have what it takes to
keep servicing my debt.
I want a brand new start.
Now, the next one or the next
one that you're going to be
most-- going to hear the most
about in the context of a
personal bankruptcy--
is Chapter 13.
And this is often referred
to as a reorganization.
And here the idea is, look,
I have a salary.
I have a job.
But I just have more debt
than is imaginable.
And it might not be just
because I've been
irresponsible.
Maybe a medical emergency came
up in the family or I had some
unknown expenses that just
popped up out of nowhere.
And so here the situation is,
look, Mr. Creditors out there,
I really do want to pay you
back, but what you're asking
for me to do right now
is just crazy.
If you ask me to do that I'm
just going to end up in
Chapter 7 eventually.
So for both my sake-- me as the
debtor-- both for my sake
and for your sake, why don't we
come up with a plan so that
I can realistically pay
you over the next
three to five years?
And that might involve you
saying, hey, instead of being
owed $50,000, you now
owe me $40,000.
Or instead of the interest on
my credit card being 20% per
year, let's change that
to 10% per year.
So they'll be a little
bit of a negotiation.
You're going to have to
come up with a plan.
And then once you come up with
that plan, I've got to pay
that over the next three
to five years.
Now once again, you might say,
hey, well that's pretty good.
If I owe $100,000 in credit card
debt and I kind of go to
my creditors and look like a
genuine individual and make a
nice sob story, they're going
to lower my debt.
I'll be better off than
if I didn't do it.
But here again, there's
a penalty to doing it.
And once again, it shows up
on your credit report.
And so, in general, they're
going to come up with a plan
for you to pay back your
creditors over three years.
And then after that, it's
going to show up on your
credit report for
another 7 years.
So in general, from the time
you file until the time it
leaves your credit report is
going to be 10 years, just
like Chapter 7.
So in either of these
situations, these aren't
things that you want to just
jump into and then think, wow,
I found an easy out
from my debt.
These are very serious things
that will impact you for a
reasonable chunk of your life.
So these aren't just simple
things to do.
But they are good to know about
just in case you do find
yourself a little bit over
your head or a little bit
under water, or you
know someone
who's in this situation.
At least it is an out where they
can feel that look, if I
do this or that, maybe over the
next either 3 years or 10
years-- depending on how
you view it-- they can
get to a new start.
And just so you have a sense
of how often this occurs, I
looked this up a little
bit earlier.
In the U.S., and as you can
imagine, we're in the middle
of a recession now, so
bankruptcy filings are kind of
going through the roof.
So let me write this down.
So this is Chapter 7.
And here's Chapter 13.
And if you're wondering,
what are all
the chapters in between?
There's a Chapter 12, which is
essentially Chapter 13 for
farmers and fishermen.
They get a few more benefits
than the rest of us get
because we want to
promote, I guess,
people who produce food.
And then there's Chapter 11,
which is essentially business
reorganization.
It can apply to some
individuals who are
essentially kind of big shots.
Their personal portfolios of
assets and liabilities look a
lot like a business.
So for them Chapter 11 will
be more appropriate
than Chapter 13.
So those are kind of the
two other chapters.
But from a personal bankruptcy
point of view, Chapter 7 and
Chapter 13 is what most people
concern themselves with.
Now, just to give you the
numbers of how often this is
occurring, if you find yourself
in the circumstance,
just so you know you're
not necessarily alone.
And also just to see that
they really are
increasing right now.
So 2007, 2008, 2009.
So Chapter 7 filings
in the United
States in 2007: 413,000.
In 2008 it went up to 560,000.
So this is more than
a 25% increase.
And then in 2009,
819,000 filings.
Essentially double of the
number of Chapter
7 filings in 2007.
And if you look at Chapter
13, in 2007
we had 277,000 filings.
So for every two Chapter 7's it
looks like there's about--
well, for every four there's
about three of these.
Then we have 334,000 in 2008.
And then 370,000 in 2009.
So you can see that the Chapter
7 ones, I mean they're
both increasing really
fast. But Chapter 7
is even more dramatic.
And you could imagine because
in a situation where people
don't have jobs, Chapter
13 really isn't that
viable of an option.
They really have to do something
like Chapter 7.
Anyway, hopefully you found
that useful and you know a
little bit about
bankruptcy now.
[MUSIC PLAYING]