Today we're going to take a look at this
DVD player. We're gonna see what's inside
and what makes it work.
There are several key components to this.
We'll be looking at the power supply,
the control board, the CD tray as well as
the laser itself and the external housing.
So, let's go ahead and get started.
This DVD player is actually very low cost.
You can buy it for less than $30.
Part of the way they've been able to reduce the cost
is that the actual chips inside it, needed to make it run, have come down in price
and and part of it is that they've been able to simplify
the components on the board tremendeously.
Here we go!
Alright. Take a look at the insides ther.
This piece of metal is just a flat sheet
which was run through a press which created these tabs here.
And the tabs lock in the housing under the front part.
And then it also had these indentation stamped in it,
so the screws would sit flush.
And then the holes were punched in it and it was folded.
Ok, so you can see inside the DVD player here.