When we compare triangle ABC to triangle XYZ,
it's pretty clear they aren't congruent,
that they have a very different lengths of their sides
But, there does to be seem something interesting
about the relationship between this two triangles
One, all of their corresponding angles are the same
So, the angle right here, angle BAC is congruent to XYZ
Angle BCA is congruent to YZX,
And angle ABC is congruent to XYZ
So all of their angles, the corresponding angles are the same
And we also see, we also see that the sides
are just scaled up versions of each other
So the goal from the length of XZ to AC,
we can, we can multiply by 3, we multiplied by 3 there,
to go from, to go from XY, the length of XY
to the length of AB which is of course the corresponding side
We are multiplying by 3, we have to multiply by 3
And then, to go from the length of YZ to the length of BC,
we also, we also, multiplied
We also multiplied by 3
So essentially, triangle ABC is just a scaled up version
of triangle XYZ
If they were the same scale,
they would be the exact same triangles but,
one is just a bigger, a blown up version of the other one or,
this is miniaturize version of that one over there
If you just multiply all of the sides by 3, you get to this triangle
And so, we can't call them congruent but they're,
there does seem to be a bit of a special relationship
So we call this special relationship "similarity"
So we can write that triangle, triangle ABC
is similar, similar to triangle,
and we wanna make sure we get the corresponding sides right,
ABC is gonna be similar to XYZ
To XYZ
And so, based on what we just saw,
there's actually kind of 3 ideas here,
and they're all equivalent ways of thinking about similarities
One way to think about it is that,
one is a scaled up version of the other
So scaled, scaled up or down of the other
Down versions
When we talk about congruency, they have to be exactly the same
You could rotate, you could shift it, you could flip it,
but when you do all those things,
they would have to be essentially identical
With similarity, you can rotate it, you can shift it, you can flip it,
and you can also scale it up and down
in order for something to be similar
So for example, if you say, if something is congruent,
if, if, let me say triangle, let's say triangle CDE,
if we know that triangle CDE is congruent to triangle FGH,
then we definitely know that they're similar
They're scaled up by factor of one
Then, we know for a fact that CDE
Is also similar to triangle FGH,
but we can't say the other way around
If, if trianlge ABC is similar to XYZ,
we can't say that it's necessarily congruent,
and we see for this particular example,
they definitely are not congruent
So this is one way to think about similarity
The other way to think about similarity is that,
all the corresponding angles will be equal
So, if something is similar, then all of the corresponding angles
are going to be congruent
Corresponding, corresponding angle
Always having trouble spelling this
It is two R's, one S
Corresponding, corresponding angles, corresponding angles
are congruent
Are congruent
So, if we say that triangle ABC is,
triangle ABC is similar to triangle XYZ,
that is equivalent to saying that angle, angle ABC,
angle ABC is congruent,
or we can say their measures are equal to angle XYZ,
to angle XYZ,
that angle, that angle BAC,
BAC is going to be congruent to angle YXZ, to angle YXZ
And then finally, angle ACB, ACB is going to be congruent to
angle, to angle XZY
XZY
Angle XZY
So if you have two triangles, all of their angles are the same,
then you could say that they are similar
Or if you find two triangles,
and you are told they are similar triangles
then you know that all of their corresponding angles are the same
And the last, I guess the way to think about it is that,
all the sides are just scaled up versions of each other
So the sides, so sides, scaled by the same factor,
scaled by same, same factor
And the example we did here, the scaling factor was 3,
it doesn't have to be 3
It just to be the same scaling factor for every side
If this side, if we scaled this side up by 3,
and we only scaled this side up by 2 then,
we would not be dealing with a similar triangle
But, if we scaled all of these sides up by 7,
then that's still similar
As long as you have all of them scaled up by,
or scaled down by the exact same factor
So one way to think about it is, and I wanna, wanna keep having,
well, I wanna still visualize those triangles
Let me, let me re-draw em' right over here, a little bit simpler
So I'm now talkig in, now in general terms,
not even for that specific case
So, if we say that this is A B and C,
and this right over here is, X, XYZ
I just re-drew em' so I can refer to them when we write down here
If we're saying that this two things right over here are similar,
that means that corresponding sides
are scaled up versions of each other
So we could say that the length of AB,
we could say that the length of AB,
AB, is equal to some scaling factor,
and this thing could be less than one,
some scaling factor times the length of XY, the corresponding sides
And I know that AB corresponds to XY
because of the order in which I wrote this similarity statement
So some scaling factor times XY,
we know that BC, the length of BC
we know that the length of BC needs to be that same scaling factor
The same scaling factor times the length of YZ,
times the length of YZ, so that same scaling factor
And then, we know the length of AC, the length of AC,
is going to be equal to that same scaling factor times XZ
So that's XZ and this could be a scaling factor
So if AB is larger than, if ABC is larger than XYZ,
than this K's will be larger than one,
if they're the exact same size,
if they are essentially congruent triangles,
than this K's will be one
And if XYZ is bigger than ABC,
than this scaling factors will be less than one
But another way to write the same,
all I'm saying is corresponding sides
are scaled up versions of each other
This first statement right here if you divide both sides by XY,
you get AB over XY, is equal to, our scaling factor
And then the second statement right over here,
if you divide both sides by YZ, you get B, let me do that same colour
You get BC divided by YZ is equal to that scaling factor,
is equal to that scaling factor
Whatever, the example we just showed that scaling factor was,
scaling factor was 3 but, now we're saying
in a more general term, similarities,
as long as you have same scaling factor
And then finally, if you divide both sides here
by the length between X,XZ , or segment XZ's length,
you get AC over XZ is equal to K as well
Is equal to K as well
Or another way to think about it is,
the ratio between corresponding sides,
notice this is the ratio between AB and XY
AB and XY
The ratio between BC and YZ, BC and YZ
The ratio between AC and XZ, AC and XZ
That the ratio between corresponding sides
all gives us the same constant
Or you can rewrite this as, AB over XY is equal to BC over YZ,
is equal to, is equal to AC over XZ,
which would be equal to some scaling factor,
which is equal to K
So if you have similar triangles,
let me draw an arrow right over here,
similar triangles means that they're scaled up versions and,
you can also flip and rotate, do all the stuff with congruency,
and you can scale them up or down, which means,
all of the corresponding angles are congruent,
which also means that the ratio between corresponding sides
is going to be the same concept for all the corresponding sides,
or the ratio between the corresponding sides is constant