When people use the word "perimeter" in everyday language
they're talking about the boundary of some area.
And when we're talking about perimeter in math, we're talking about a related idea
but now we're not only talking about the boundary, we're actually talking about the length of the boudary,
how far do you have to go round the boundary to essentially go completely around a figure,
completely go round the area.
So let's look at this first triangle right over here.
It has three sides -- that's why it's a triangle -- so what's its perimeter?
Well, here, all the sides are the same,
so the perimeter for this triangle is going to be 4+4+4 in whatever unit this is.
And if this is 4 feet, 4 feet and 4 feet, that'll be feet+4 feet+4 feet=12 feet.
Now I encourage you to now pause the video and figure out the perimeters of these three figures.
Well, that's the exact same idea: we will just add the lengths of the sides
So, let's say that that these distances in -- let's say they are in meters.
So let's say that this is 3 meters, this is also 3 meters --
this is a rectangle here, so this is 5 meters and this is also 5 meters.
So what is the perimeter of this rectangle going to be?
What is the distance around the rectangle that bounds this area?
Well, it's going to be 3+5+3+5,
which is equal to, let's see, that's 3+3 is 6, plus 5+5 is 10,
so that's equal to 16, and if we're saying these are all in meters,
these are in meters, that is going to be 16 meters.
Now, what about this pentagon?
Let's say that each of these sides are 2, and I'll make up -- I'll make up a unit here:
Let's say they're 2 gnus - 2 gnus: that's a new unit that I have --
a new unit of distance that I have just -- that I have just invented.
2, 2 gnus, 2 gnus.
So what is the perimeter of this pentagon in gnus?
Well, it's 2+2+2+2+2 gnus.
Or: we're essentially taking 1, 3, 3, 4, 5 gnu -- 5 sides, each have a length of 2 gnus,
So the perimeter here, we could add 2 repeatedly 5 times
or you could just say this is 5 x 2 gnus, which is equal to 10 gnus
where gnus is a completely made-up unit of length that I just made up.
Here we have a more irregular polygon, but same exact idea:
How would you figure out its perimeter?
Well, you just add up the lengths of its sides.
And here I'll just do it in units: let us just assume that this is some generic unit.
And here the perimeter will be 1+4+2+2 -- we'll scroll over to the right just a little bit -- +4+6 .
So what is this going to be equal to?
1+4 is 5, +2 is 7, +2 is 9, +4 is 13, +6 is 19.
So this figure has a perimeter of 19
in whatever unit these distances are actually given.