PROBLEM: "At Hogwarts, there are four houses: Gryffindor, Hufflepuff, Ravenclaw, and Slytherin.
The bar chart below shows the number of
house points that each house received today.
How many house points did Hufflepuff receive?"
So if we look at this bar chart, we can
assume that this column right over here
is Hufflepuff, because it's the
only one that starts with an H.
This (G) would be Gryffindor, this (R) is
Ravenclaw, and this (S) must Slytherin.
And so, if we look at Hufflepuff's bar,
it looks like they have 3 points scored today.
So let's put 3 points.
Alright. Let's try one more.
So here, they're saying, "How many
house points did Slytherin receive?"
So, this is going to be Slytherin,
and it looks like they received 4 points.