Let z1 and z2 be two distinct complex numbers, and let z = (1-t) z1 + t z2, for some real number with
t being between 0 and 1. If Arg (w) denotes the principal argument of a nonzero complex number w, then you know
the argument is the angle of, kinda, the position vector specifiying the complex number in the complex plane,
and the real axis. Let me just draw that. So if we do an Argand diagram. This is the imaginary axis,
and this is the real axis. If this our complex number, if that is z, its argument, the argument of z is going to be
this angle right over here. So phi = Arg (z). That's all they're telling us in the second part.
Now, let's go through each of these and see (inaudible) are true, and just to be clear
this is one of those problems where more than one of these choices might be correct, so lets see if they are true.
So let's first figure out what |z-z1| is. So |z-z1|, is going to be, so let me write. This is going to be, lets do the z part
first. Let me write in the same colors. So if I would just focus on the z, first, z is this thing up here
and let me distribute the z1. So it's z1 - t z1 + t z2, and from that we want to subtract z1.
So from that we want to subtract z1, so minus z1. And that and that cancel out, and let's see we have, we can
factor out a t over here, so this is going to be equal to, |t (z2 - z1)|. So that is |z - z1|, this first term over here.
Let's figure out, |z - z2|. I'm going to color code it. |z - z2| is equal to, well z is just this thing up here
let me just write it out, so it is (1-t) z1 + t z2, that's z. And from that we want to subtract z2. So
|(1-t) z1 + t z2 - z2|. So, what can we do over here? We can take a t-1 out from over here, we can factor out
the z2 out of these two terms. So this is going to be equal to the magnitude of (1-t) z1, thats this term right over here,
plus, let me do it in another color, plus (t-1) z2. The magnitude of this part over here
is this thing over there. Now let's see what happens when we add this thing to this thing.
That's what choice A is doing, we're adding this thing to this thing. Let's see if we can simplify it.
So, this becomes, |t (z2 - z1)| plus, I'll do the whole thing here in magenta, plus this thing over here.
And this thing over here, actually before I even write it out, how can we simplify that?
Well I have a 1-t and a t-1, well I'll just write it out here. But I'm going to change it up a little bit.
So this is equal to, the magnitude of (1-t) z1, and so that I have a 1-t here, I'm just going to put a negative out front.
So -(1-t), I just swap 'em, -(1-t) is the same thing as positive (t-1), z2.
And then this thing over here, since I have the (1-t) out there, this becomes the magnitude of,
I'm just factoring out the (1-t), |(1-t)(z1-z2)|. So we have this thing, let me copy and paste it,
so, copy and paste, we have this thing plus this thing. This is what this expression A has simplified to.
Now let's see if we can simplify that even more! So t is just a scalar, and t is between 0 and 1.
They told us that over here, t is between 0 and 1. So this is positive, this right here is a positive value,
and then this right here is going to be a positive value. t is greater than 0, and it is less than 1.
So this is also going to be a positive value. And these are just scalars. So this is going to be the same thing,
these are just scaling the magnitude. So this is going to be the same thing, these are positive values. So
this is going to be, actually let me not skip a step. This is going to be the same thing as |t| |z2-z1|,
'cause this is just scaling it, plus the |1-t||z1-z2|. Now let me be clear, |z1-z2| is going to be equal to |z2-z1|.
These vectors are just pointing in different directions, or these complex numbers, one is just the negative of the other
but their absolute values, or their magnitudes, are going to be the same. So let me write |z2-z1| there.
The reason why I'm doing it, is so I get the same thing here, and I can factor it out. So |z2-z1|, it's the same thing as |z1-z2|
'cause we're not, it's just going in the other direction. Now, what can we do here?
Well, | t |, remember t is positive, so this is just going to be equal to t. |1-t|, once again that's positive, so that's
just going to be 1-t. So we can factor, this business out, so we're going to get t + (1-t), times |z2-z1|.
Now the t's cancel out here, we just got a 1 out front, so this is just equal to |z2-z1|. So
we see that choice A does work. This plus this, does indeed equal that. I'm going to leave you there,
and in the next video we're going to try out some of these other possibilities, to see if they might also be true.