Let's say I have two intersecting line segments. So lets call that segment AB.
And then I have segment CD
So that is C and that is D.
And they intersect right over here at point E.
And let's say we know, we're given, that this angle right over here, the measure of angle BED is 70 degrees.
Given that information, what I want to do
,based on only what we know so far, not using a protractor...
What I want to do is figure out what the other angles in this picture are.
So what are the measures of angles CEB, AEC and AED?
So the first thing that you might notice when you look at this is that angle BED and CEB are adjacent.
And we also see that if you take the outer sides of those angles it forms a strait angle.
And we also see that angle CED is a strait angle.
So we know that these two angles must also be suplementary.
They are next to each other and they form a strait angle when you take their outer sides.
So we know that angle BED and angle CEB are suplementary,
which means they add up to or their measures add up to 180 degrees.
Suplementary angles, which tells us that the measure of BED plus the measure of angle CEB
is equal to 180 degrees.
Now we already know the measure of angle BED is 70 degrees.
So we alredy know that this thing right over here is 70 degrees.
And so 70 degrees plus the measure of angle CEB is 180 degrees.
We substract 70 degrees from the both sides and we get the measure of angle CEB is equal to 110 degrees.
I just substracted 70 degrees from both sides of that.
So we figured out that this right over here is 110 degrees.