Let's say you're some type of a hunter gatherer,
and you're trying to figure out
how much of your time you should spend hunting
and how much of your time to spend gathering.
So let's think about the different scenarios here
and the tradeoffs that they involve.
And just for simplicity we're going to assume that
when you're talking about hunting,
the only animal around you to hunt for are these little rabbits.
And when we talk about gathering,
the only thing you can gather are some types of berries,
that will keep our conversation a little bit simpler.
So, let's think about all of the scenarios.
So, first let's call this first scenario scenario A.
And let's say, so let's call this the number of rabbits.
And then let's call this the number of berries.
Let's do this column the number of berries you can get.
So, if you were to spend the entire day going after rabbits,
all of your free time, out of making sure you have time to sleep
and get dressed and all those types of things,
let's say you can actually get 5 rabbits on average on a given day.
But, if you spend all of your time getting rabbits,
you're not going to have any time to get berries,
so you are going to be able to get zero berries.
Now, let's say that you were to
only try to allocate a little more time to get berries,
and a little less time to get rabbits.
So we'll call that scenario B.
We will call scenario B the reality
where you have enough time to get four rabbits on average,
and when you do that, all of a sudden,
you are able to get 100 berries.
And when we do the different scenarios,
we're assuming that everything else is equal.
You're not changing the amount of time you have either hunting or gathering.
You're not changing the amount of sleep,
you're not changing your techniques for hunting rabbits or hunting berries,
you're not somehow looking to do other things with your time.
So all other things are equal.
And the general term for this - it sounds very fancy
if you were to say it in a conversation -
is ceteris paribus,
which literally means, so anytime someone says
"Oh, and, you know, ceteris paribus, we assume this variable changes,"
or whatever else, they're saying we're assuming
everything else is being held equal.
So, ceteris means "all other things."
You're probably familiar with "et cetera".
It's the same word, essentially, "other things". And paribus, "equal".
So you're not, when you're going from scenario A to scenario B,
you're not changing the amount of time you're sleeping,
you're not changing somehow
the geography where you are in a dramatic way.
You're not changing the tools you use, or the technology.
Everything else is equal.
The only variable you are changing is
how much time you allocate to finding rabbits
versus finding berries.
So let's do some more scenarios,
assuming ceteris paribus.
So let me do scenario C.
You could, on average, have enough time to get 3 rabbits,
but if you get 3 rabbits
then all of a sudden, you will only be able to get,
or you will be able to get, or if you are only getting 3 rabbits
you're now going to be able to get 180 berries
and let's do a couple more.
I'm going to do two more scenarios.
So let's say scenario D.
If you reduce the amount of time you spend getting rabbits
so you get 2 rabbits, now all of a sudden,
you have enough time, on average, to get 240 berries,
and then let's say you spend even less time hunting for rabbits,
on average,
then you have even more time for berries,
and so you're able to get 280 berries.
And I'll do one more scenario, here.
So let's say scenario F. Let's call these scenarios.
Scenarios A through F.
So scenario F is [when] you spend all your time looking for berries,
in which case, on average,
you're going to be able to get 300 berries a day.
But since you have no time for rabbits,
you aren't going to get any rabbits.
So what I want to do is plot these,
and on one axis, I'll have the number of rabbits,
and on the other axis I'll have the number of berries.
- So let me do this right over here -
So this axis, I will call this my rabbit axis, and start at zero
this will be 1, 2, 3, 4, and that will be 5 rabbits.
And then on this axis,
I will do the berries.
So this right over here, let's make this 100 berries,
this is 200 berries,
and then this is 300 berries.
And so this is my berries axis.
Now, let's plot these points, these different scenarios.
So, first we have scenario A -
maybe I should have done all these columns
in that same scenario A color.
Scenario A, 5 rabbits, 0 berries.
We are right over there. That is scenario A.
Scenario B, 4 rabbits, 100 berries. That's right over there.
That's 100 berries. So, that is scenario B.
Scenario C. 3 rabbits, 180 berries. Let's see, this would be 150,
180 would be like right over there.
So, if you have time for 3 rabbits,
you have time for about 180 berries, on average,
So this is scenario C.
And then scenario D, we have in white.
If you have time for 2 rabbits,
you have time for 240 berries. So that is right around there.
So, this is scenario D. So this would be 250,
so 240 is a little bit lower than that,
so it will be right over there. That is scenario D.
Scenario E, if you have time for 1 rabbit,
you have time for 280 berries.
That gets us right about there.
That is scenario E. And then finally, scenario F,
you are spending all of your time looking for berries,
you have no time for rabbits,
So all of your time for berries, no time for rabbits.
Zero rabbits, 300 berries. That's right over there.
This is scenario F.
So what [do] all of these points represent?
These are all points, and this is going to be a fancy word,
but it's a very simple idea.
These are all points on you as a hunter-gatherer,
on your production possibilities frontier.
Because if we draw a line -
I just arbitrarily picked these scenarios,
although I guess you could on average,
get 4.5 rabbits on average, or, on average, get 3.5 rabbits,
and then have a different number of berries -
So these are all points on the different combinations
between the trade-offs of rabbits and berries.
Let me connect all of these,
Let me connect them in a colour I haven't used yet.
So let me connect them.
And what you see, it should just be one curve.
I'll draw them as a dotted line.
It's easier for me to draw a dotted curve than a straight curve.
So this right over here, this curve right over here, represents
all the possible possibilities of combinations of rabbits and berries.
I've only picked certain [ones] of them
but you could have a scenario right over here
maybe we could call that scenario G,
where on average, the amount of time you've allocated,
on average you would get 4.5 rabbits,
so on some days you'd get 4 rabbits,
and every other day you'd get 5 rabbits
so maybe it averages out to 4.5 rabbits.
And then maybe it looks like
you'd get about 50 berries, in that situation.
So all of these are possibilities.
You don't have to just jump from 4 rabbits to 5 rabbits,
or maybe, you know, you are spending,
maybe in this scenario, you're spending 7 hours,
and in this scenario you spend 8 hours,
but you could spend 7 hours and a minute
or 7 hours and a second, so anything in between is possible,
and all of those possibilities are on this curve.
So these 5 scenarios,
actually these 6 scenarios that we've talked about so far,
these are just, scenarios on this curve,
and that curve, we call, once again fancy term, simple idea,
our production possibilities frontier.
Because it shows all of the different possibilties we can do, we can get.
3 rabbits and 180 berries,
2 rabbits and 240 berries.
What we cannot do is something that's beyond this.
So for example, we can't get scenario like this:
So this right over here would be impossible.
So this right over here is impossible.
This point over here, where I'm getting 5 rabbits and 200 berries.
If I'm getting 5 rabbits,
I'm spending all my time getting rabbits,
I have no time for berries. Or, another way to think of it,
if I'm getting 200 berries,
I don't have enough time to get 5 rabbits.
So this point is impossible. This point would be impossible.
Any point that's on this side of the curve is impossible.
Now, any point on this side of the curve,
you can kind of view it as inside the curve,
or below the curve, or to the left of the curve.
All of these points, right over here are possible.
These points, for example,
it is very easy for me to get 1 rabbit, and 200 berries.
So that right over there, is possible.
Now, is that optimal? No!
Because if I were to really work properly,
I could get many more berries, or I could get more rabbits
for if I have 200 berries, I could get more rabbits,
or if I'm concerned, if I only want 1 rabbit,
I can get more berries, so this is possible.
All of the points down here are possible,
but they aren't optimal. They are not efficient.
So the points in here,
we'll just say that they are not efficient.
Maybe somehow I'm not using my resources optimally
to do this type of thing when I'm over here.
Or maybe I'm just not being optimally focused,
or whatever it might be.
If you're talking about a factory setting,
when you're talking about deciding to make one thing or another,
then maybe you just aren't using the resources in an optimal way.
Now, all the points on the frontier - these are efficient.
You're doing the most you can do.
Right now we're not making any judgement between whether
any of these possibilties are better than any other possibility.
All we are saying is that
you are doing the most that you can do.
Any of these things you are making the most use of your time.