When you're studying chemistry,
you'll often see reactions.
In fact, you always
see reactions.
For example, if you have
hydrogen gas, it's a diatomic
molecule, because hydrogen
bonds with itself in the
gaseous state, plus
iodine gas, I2.
That's also in the
gaseous state.
It's very easy to say, oh,
you know, if you put them
together, they're going to react
and form the product.
If you have 2 moles of hydrogen,
2 moles of iodine,
so it's going to form 2 moles
of hydrogen iodide.
That's all nice and neat, and
it makes it seem like it's a
very clean thing that happens
without much fuss, but we know
that that isn't the reality.
And we also know that this
doesn't happen just instantly.
It's not like you can just take
some hydrogen and put it
with some iodine and it
just magically turns
into hydrogen iodide.
There's some process going on
that these gaseous state
particles are bouncing around,
and somehow they must bounce
into each other and break bonds
that they were in before
and form new ones.
And that's what we're
going to study now.
This whole study of how the
reaction progresses and the
rates of the reactions is called
kinetics, which is a
very fancy word, but you're
probably familiar with it
because we've talked a lot
about kinetic energy.
Kinetics, which is just the
study of the rate of
reactions, how fast do they
happen and how do they happen.
So let's just in our minds come
up with an intuitive way
that hydrogen and iodine
can combine.
So let's think about what
hydrogen looks like.
So if we get our Periodic Table
out, hydrogen's got one
valence electron, so if they
have two hydrogen atoms, they
can share them with
each other.
And then iodine has seven
valence electrons so if they
each share one, they'd get
complete as well, so let's
just review that right now.
So hydrogen, this hydrogen,
might have one.
Well, it will have one
electron out there.
And then you could have another
hydrogen that has
another electron out there.
And then if they form a
bond, they share this.
This hydrogen can pretend like
he has this electron.
she has that electron, and
then they're happy.
They both feel like they've
completed their 1s shell.
Same thing on the iodine side
where you have two iodines.
They both have seven
valence electrons.
They're halogens.
You know that already.
Halogens are the Group
7 elements, so
they have seven electrons.
This guy's got one here.
If this guy can pretend
like he's got that
electron, he's happy.
He has eight valence
electrons.
If this guy can pretend like
he's got that one, same thing.
So there's a bond right here,
and this is why hydrogen is a
diatomic molecular gas,
and this is why
iodine is the same.
Now, when they're in the gaseous
state, you have a
bunch of these things that are
moving around, bumping into
each other.
I'll do it like this, so
the hydrogen might look
something like this.
The hydrogen has these
two atomic spheres
that are bonded together.
They have these electrons
in between that are
keeping them bonded.
The iodine might look
something like this.
It's a much bigger molecule
where it's bonded
together like this.
It's also sharing some electrons
in a covalent bond
and everything's
probabilistic.
So in order for these two
molecules to turn into this,
somehow these bonds have
to be broken and new
bonds have to be formed.
And what has to happen is that
these guys-- there's a ton of
these guys.
I could draw a bunch of them,
or I could copy and paste.
So there's a bunch of hydrogen
molecules around, and some of
these iodine gas molecules
around.
So what has to happen in order
for us to get the hydrogen
iodide is they have to collide,
and they have to
collide in exactly
the right way.
So let's say this guy--
actually, I can show it.
Let's say he's moving.
This is neat.
I'm just dragging
and dropping.
But he's moving.
He has to hit this hydrogen
molecule just right.
And maybe just right, if he
just happens to hit it and
bounce at it with enough energy,
then all of a sudden,
let's say we get to this
point right here.
These electrons are going to
say, hey, you know, it's nice
to be shared this way.
We're in a stable
configuration.
We're filling this 1s shell,
but look at this.
There's this iodine that's
close by and
they really want me.
They're much more
electronegative than me to
hydrogen, so maybe they're
kind of attracted here.
They don't know whether they
want to be here between that
hydrogen and this right here
between that, and so they kind
of enter this higher
energy state.
And similarly, these guys, they
say, hey, wouldn't it be
nicer-- I don't have
to be here.
I could kind of go back home
to my home atom if this guy
comes in here, because then
we're going to have eight
valence electrons, and the same
thing's happening here.
And this complex right here,
right when the collision
happens, this is actually
a state.
It's the high energy state,
or the transition
state of the reaction.
And this is called an
activated complex.
You know, I just drew it kind
of visually, but you could
draw it like this.
So hydrogen has a covalent bond
with another hydrogen.
And then here comes along some
iodine that has a covalent
bond with some other iodine.
But all of a sudden, these guys
like to bond as well, so
they start forming-- so there's
kind of a little bit
of an attraction on
that side, too.
So this is another
way of drawing
the activation complex.
But this is a high energy state,
because in order for
the electron, the way you can
think of it, to kind of go
from that bond to this bond, or
this bond to that bond, or
to go back, they have to enter
into a higher energy state.
A less stable energy state
than they were before.
But they do that if there's
enough energy, because you can
go from both of these
things separate.
Let me just draw
them separate.
You have both of
You have the hydrogen separate
plus the iodine separate.
They go to this, which is a
higher energy state, but if
they can get to that higher
energy state, if there's
enough energy for the collision
and they have enough
kinetic energy where they hit in
the right orientation, then
from this activated complex or
this higher energy state, it
will then go to the lowest
energy state.
And the lowest energy state
is the hydrogen iodide.
Whoops!
I want to draw iodide and
then the hydrogen.
This is actually a lower
energy state than this.
But in order to get here, you
have to go through a higher
energy state.
And I could do that with
an energy diagram.
So if we say that the x-axis
is the progression of the
reaction, and actually, we
don't know how fast it's
progressing, but you could kind
of view it as time in
some dimension, and let's say
this is the potential energy.
I don't want to draw
thicker lines.
This is the potential
energy right there.
Let me make this line
thicker as well.
This is the potential energy.
So initially, we are at this
reality, and you can kind of
view it as the combined
potential energy.
So essentially, we start
off here, and this
is the H2 plus I2.
And a lower potential energy is
when we're in the hydrogen
iodide, so this is the lower
potential energy down here.
This is the 2HI, right?
But to get here, we have to
enter this higher activation
energy, where the electrons
have to get-- they have to
have some energy to kind of be
able to at least figure out
what they want to do
with their lives.
And so you have to add
energy to the system.
You don't always have to add it,
but if it doesn't happen
spontaneously, you're going to
have to add some energy to the
system to get to this activated
state, right?
So this is when we're at
this thing right here.
We're there, so some energy
has to be in the system.
And this energy, the difference
between the energy
we were at when we were just
hydrogen molecules and iodine
molecules, and the energy we
have to get to get this
activated state-- this distance
right here-- this is
the activation energy.
If we're able to somehow put
enough energy in the system,
then this thing will happen.
They'll collide with enough
energy and bonds will be
broken and reformed.
Activation energy.
Sometimes it's written is Ea,
energy of activation.
And in the future, we'll maybe
do reactions where we actually
measure the activation energy,
but the important thing is to
conceptually understand
that it's there.
That things just don't
spontaneously go
from here to here.
And I won't go deeply into
catalysts right now, but
you've probably heard of the
word catalyst, or something
being catalyzed.
And that's some other
agent, some other
thing in the reaction.
So right now, we
have H2 plus I2
yielding 2 hydrogen iodides.
Now, you could have a
catalyst, and I'll
just say plus C.
And I actually don't know what
a good catalyst would be for
this reaction.
And how a catalyst operates is
it can actually operate in
many, many different ways, so
that's why I don't want to do
it in this video.
But what a catalyst is is
something that doesn't change.
It doesn't get consumed
in the reaction.
The catalyst was there
before the reaction.
after the reaction.
But what it does is it makes
the reaction happen either
faster, or it lowers the amount
of energy for the
reaction to happen, which is
kind of the same thing.
So if you have a catalyst, then
this activation energy
will be lower.
What it does is it might be some
molecule that allows some
other transition state that has
less of a potential energy
so that you require less heat
or less concentration of the
molecules for them to bump into
each other in the right
direction to get to that
other state, so you
require less energy.
So given how we understand how
these kinetics occur, or these
molecules interact with each
other, what do you think are
the things that will
drive whether a
reaction happens or not?
We already know that if we
have a positive catalyst,
there's something called a
negative catalyst that will
actually slow down a reaction.
But if we have a positive
catalyst, obviously, it lowers
the activation energy so this
makes a reaction faster.
More molecules are going to
bump into each other just
right to be able to get over
this hump because the hump
will be lower when you
have a catalyst.
Also, if you increase the
concentration, right?
If you increase your
concentration of molecules, if
the concentration goes up, then
you just have more stuff
to bump into each
other, right?
There's just the likelihood.
Everything is probablistic.
When people write these reaction
equations, it all
seems nice and simple and very
clear, and it happens.
But no, in the real world, you
just have things bumping into
each other.
And when we do biology videos,
it will be fascinating to talk
about, because every biological
process is really
just a chemical process, and
it's really just the byproduct
of all of these things bumping
into each other.
And you can imagine, the more
concentration you have of the
things that need to bump into
each other, the more likely
you're going to get just that
perfect bump and that perfect
amount of kinetic energy for
the reaction to happen.
Actually, I'll make a little
other note here.
This reaction, you might say,
OK, I have some-- let's see,
I'm at this energy.
How do I ever get over this?
How does this ever react?
Well, remember, in a gas, the
kinetic energies of all of the
molecules, they're
not uniform.
Some molecules will have higher
kinetic energy; some
will have lower.
Temperature just gives
you the average.
So there's always some
probability that two maybe
high kinetic energy molecules
will bump into
each other just perfectly.
Surpass the kinetic-- so they
have enough kinetic energy to
get into the activation state,
and then they can go to the
lower state, which is
the hydrogen iodide.
At all temperatures this will
occur, but obviously if you
increase the temperature, that
reaction is more likely.
So that's the other one.
So, temperature.
Temperature is probably the
single biggest thing that will
make the reaction
happen faster.
So all of these things, you
want higher temperature,
higher reaction.
And then if you just want to
think about the molecules
itself, if you have molecules
where their original bonds are
weak, they're more likely
to be able to interact.
And there's other things you
could talk about: the
molecular shape, how available
certain atoms are to interact
with other atoms. That really
becomes significant when we
start going into biology.
And the last one, and you
probably realize this, is just
the surface area.
If you increase the surface
area-- so we were just doing
gas-gas interactions, which
almost by definition have
pretty good surface
area interactions.
But if the surface area goes
up, then the reaction also
goes up, the reaction rate.
And how do you think
about that?
Well, think about the reaction
of-- you know, we've done this
multiple times.
Sodium chloride-- solid-- so
solid salt, plus liquid water,
leads to sodium-- well, we could
think of it a lot of
different ways, but we could
think of it as sodium ion
aqueous plus chloride anions--
this is a cation and anion--
aqueous, so it gets dissolved.
And how does that happen?
If you have a big block of ice--
no, not ice, of salt.
I'll do salt in grey.
If you have a big block of salt
in there, so there's a
bunch of sodium and chloride
atoms in it.
And you have water all around
it, the water is only going to
be able to interact with the
surface molecules and slowly
dissolve away the salt, slowly
make polar bonds.
These are actually polar
dipole bonds with the
different sodium or
chloride ions.
But if you were to break this up
into smaller cubes, if you
were to break it up or really
crush it into really small
pieces, then all of a sudden
the surface area that the
water molecules can interact
with, it can actually interact
with more of the sodium
chloride, so the reaction will
happen faster.
So surface area, if you increase
the surface area of
interaction, then you'll also
increase the reaction rate.
If you're trying to do it with
two fluids, what you could do
is you can kind of spray one
fluid into the other, so you
have little droplets,
so you also
increase the surface area.
So anyway, this is kind of an
introduction to the idea of
kinetics, but hopefully, it
gives you a sense that these
reactions-- and I want you
to really think about
chemistry this way.
Not think about it is as, oh,
it's just some formula I have
to remember, that these really
are bumps and bruises between
atoms. It's probabilistic
and it's messy.
And we really have to think
about what will make it more
likely that these things collide
in just the perfect
way for the reactions
to happen.