so, in this video what I wanted to focus on is one
particular area of the brain, actually 2 areas I'm going to sketch out, not just one
but I'm going to show you how I think that these 2 areas can be kind of uh
united in a way, so these 2 areas when I'm sketching out these little
green circles are going to be responsible for breathing
how fast you breathe, how deep you breathe, and there are lots of little neurons
in these 2 areas and these neurons are going to be communicating
lets say this neuron sends a little axon down here. Maybe this guy
sends an axon up here. They're going to be communicating information among themselves
and between themselves to kind of make sure they're working in coordinated ways
that the breathing that you do is, uh, is the way that it should be
you know, how fast it should be, given a particular situation. So, the way
I think of it is kind of uniting these 2 areas, in fact sometimes its subdivided
even further, but I kind of just put it all together and say this part
of the brain that I'm kind of sketching out in green, this area then, is
our respiratory center. This is going to be responsible for all the important
activities of breathing. So let me just write that out here, "respiratory"
"center". So, a respiratory center is going to
gather information from different places and then its
going to have to make a decision
and execute based on all the information
it receives. So one key piece of information
is going to come from cells right here, kind of neighborhood cells
and these cells are called the 'Central Chemo receptors'
and the reason I'm calling them central is because they're also part of the brain, right
they're right in the same neighborhood and so these central chemoreceptors don't have
to go too far to communicate their information
and specifically they're going to gather
information on things like carbon dioxide levels and pH levels
one thing they don't do is oxygen levels, so thats
these guys right here. Now if you have central chemo receptors, you also
probably can expect that there will be some peripheral chemoreceptors and these
ones are also very important and they exist
outside of the brain, right, so they're going to be actually sending their
information along through neurons that are going to
extend all the way into the brain so for example, you might have, uh, two
key groups: one is called the aortic body, and the other is
called the carotid body. The aortic body and the carotid body. They're coming from
different locations and are actually going to use different nerves to get in
to the brain so the carotid body, for example, is going to lets say extend out
this way, through a neuron. And that's going to be through a nerve
called the glossopharyngeal nerve. This is
cranial nerve number nine, also called the glossopharyngeal nerve
glossopharyngeal. So this is one of the
key peripheral chemoreceptors, you've also got
some nerves or neurons kind of projecting from the
aortic body, going through the vagus nerve. So this is our vagus nerve
or cranial nerve number ten. It goes by two different names
our vagus nerve. these peripheral chemoreceptors are going to
detect things like oxygen, in fact that's probably one of the
most important things they detect as well as carbon dioxide and pH
so that's information coming to the respiratory center
from our peripheral and central chemoreceptors is
then mostly about chemicals
you know in addition, there is another whole group
of, uh, receptors called mechanoreceptors. Mechanoreceptors.
and these ones are actually going to be sending information about pressure
now you may be thinking "well wait a second,..."
"I thought baroreceptors told us about pressure"
and it turns out baroreceptors are one type of mechanoreceptor
that's found inside of the blood vessels. So there are many
other types in many other locations, and so the bigger, kind of more general
term would be mechanoreceptor and you can find them in places
like the nose. You can find them in the lungs, in the GI (gastrointestinal) tract
there are lots of different locations for these
mechanoreceptors and they're all sending
kind of their own projection over to the, uh
the respiratory center. In fact, the lungs and the
GI tract are going to hitch a ride in the vagus nerve and
the nose mechanoreceptors, they're going to travel
through another nerve that's called the trigeminal nerve
or cranial nerve number 5. Trigeminal nerve.
So, these are the routes that these receptors are
going to take to get to the respiratory centre
but how do these work exactly, these mechanoreceptors
lets take an example. Lets say you're walking
and you inhale some pollen. Well that's going to
trigger one of these mechanoreceptors in your nose and
its going to want to relay that information over to
your respiratory center so you're going to get
you know a little nerve impulse through that
cranial nerve number 5. Similarly, in your lungs
lets say you actually inhale some
cigarette smoke and lets say the lungs don't like that
and the mechanoreceptor feels that little particle
its going to trigger cranial nerve number 10, the vagus nerve
Similarly, you have the stretch receptors in the lungs
and these are actually kind of interesting because
what they're doing is they're saying "hey, you know.."
"these lungs are starting to get really, really full, really distended"
and so they want to let the respiratory center know
that maybe its time to exhale. And similarly, in the
GI tract, you can imagine. Lets say a baby is taking milk
and the stomach is getting really distended
you might also imagine that that information would go back
to the respiratory center as well, in this case
through cranial nerve number ten
So, we have information about pressure
or stretch. We also have information about
chemicals coming in. But what about information
on things like, I don't know, things like
anxiety for instance, or fear. Lets say
someones having these emotions, right?
Their breathing patterns may change.
Maybe they're in pain. So these kinds of things
are actually coming from the hypothalamus. The hypothalamus.
So this is another region of the brain that's sending
information down to the respiratory center and
helping to affect how we breathe. And finally,
this is probably the largest part of our picture,
this is our cerebrum and the cerebrum is responsible
for all voluntary stuff that we do. Things like singing
where you gotta control your breath or maybe
you're playing a musical instrument or maybe,
you're yelling or screaming, lets put yelling down here
anything like that, you're going to want to control
your breath, right, and so that's all voluntary
control. So this is our voluntary control and its
good that actually we have this mechanism so that
we can, if we want to, we can change our breathing
pattern but its also great that our respiratory center
can work on its own. Can you imagine if you had to
always think about taking a breath, you couldn't
do anything else right? You couldn't sleep,
you couldn't eat, you'd always just be thinking
about taking a breath so that you, you wouldn't miss
the next breath and you know, subsequently,
run out of air. So this is all the information coming
into our respiratory center. Let me just scootch this over
and I shall show you now what our brain can do with
that information to actually make sure that we're
breathing comfortably. This is our spinal column
and I'm going to just label out the motor nerves and
some of the muscle groups. So we've got motor nerve
and muscle groups and there are 4 key muscle
groups that are going to be controlled by our
respiratory center and we are gonna go through
them kind of one by one. So the first one and
the one that people usually always kind of talk about
or think about is this one right here. This is going to
be C3, C4 and C5. So C3 through C5 and the muscle
is the diaphragm. This is the giant muscle that
kinda sits right below our lungs and when it contracts
you take in a nice deep breath. But it doesn't
work alone right? We've got other muscles involved
as well and so I'm actually going to sketch out what
these other muscle groups are and the first one
is T1 through T11, all these levels are going to
send off a little nerve and each nerve will go through
a different intercostal muscle. So intercostal muscles
these are the muscles that kind of go between the ribs
these are gonna help expand or pull out your ribs
right, so these are very important for breathing as well
A little bit lower then, you also have these
abdominal muscles. Abdominal muscles here
are gonna be T6 through L1. These are the levels
where the little nerve fibers come out and
are gonna help innervate or uh, help these muscles
the abdominal muscles contract. So this is our 3rd
group of muscles and they're controlled by these
spinal levels and the final group would be this
group up here. So this is actually C1
through C3. C1 through C3 and these would be the
accessory muscles. Accessory muscles are the ones
that uh usually I think of them as the ones around
your neck area and they're gonna also kinda help
pull out the ribcage and expand the lungs.
So there you have it, you have information coming
in, that's the stuff that we started talking about,
from all the different locations around chemicals
information about pressure and, you know, your
emotional status and what you're thinking about
doing, you know voluntarily. All that information
is going to come in and then the respiratory center has
to decide, uh, how to kind of balance all that
information and then on the way out, its going to be
able to execute by controlling all these different
muscle groups and sending information down
the motor nerves that we just listed to the 4 big
groups of muscles.