Let's try to evaluate seven and six-ninths minus three and two-fifths. So like
always I like to separate out the whole
number parts from the fractional parts.
This is the same thing as
seven
plus six-ninths minus three
minus
two-fifth.
And the reason why I'm saying minus
three minus two-fifths
as this is the same thing as minus three
plus two-fifths.
So you distribute the negative sign: subtracting at three and then you're
subtracting the two-fifths.
And so now we can worry about the whole
number parts: seven
minus three.
Well, seven minus three is going to give
us
four. So that's going to give us four. And then
we're going to have six-ninths
minus
two-fifths.
So let me think about what six-ninths minus two-fifths are.
Six-ninths minus two-fifths. Well we're gonna have to find a common denominator. So this is
going to be the same thing and I think
the least common multiple of nine and five is
going to be forty-five. Literally them
multiplied. They have no common
factors.
So it's going to be over forty five,
till from nine to forty-five to multiply
by five so I'm gonna have to multiply the numerator by
five.
So six times five is thirty.
And I'm gonna subtract,
to go from five to forty-five have to multiply by nine,
so have to multiply the numerator right nine
if I don't wanna change the values.
So two times nine is
eighteen.
And thirty over thirty forty-fifth minus
eighteen forty-fifths is going to be
something over forty-five. Thirty minus
eighteen is twelve.
So this is - if I subtract
these two fractions right over here -
I get twelve,
twelve forty-fifths.
So it's four plus twelve forty-fifths,
or if we want it to write it as a mixed number,
this is equal to four and twelve
fourty-fifths.
But we're not done yet! We can simplify
this further: twelve and forty-five have
common factors.
They're both divisible by,
they're both divisible by three!
So we can say that this is,
actually they are both divisible by that while we
continue to divide more after that.
So let's see if we divide the numerator by three
and the denominator
by three.
We end up with four and twelve divided
by three
is four.
And forty-five divided by three,
forty-five divided by three is fifteen.
Four and four-fifteen, so actually we're done!
These two can't be simplified anymore.
Four and four-fifteenths.