Problem 3: Let f(x) equal to e^2x. Let R be the region in the first quadrant bounded by the graph of
f, co-ordinate axes and the vertical line x=k. So they drew that right over here and its in the figure
above in the actual AP example but I put it below here so I could use this and didn't have to waste the
screen real estate above that. And you see right here this is our f(x), this is the line x=k and this
is the region R is between those and its in the first quadrant right over here.
So right over here is our region R. So, what are they asking us to do.
So, k>0, region R shown in the figure above and this is the figure.
Part A: Write but do not evaluate and expression involving an integral that gives the perimeter of R in t
erms of k. For perimeter of R, we are going to have to find the length of the sides of R and the hardest
of these is to find the length of the actual curve between this point and this point right over here