[music]
Dr. Steven Zucker: We're in the Uffizi in Florence
and we're looking at Ambrogio Lorenzetti's
"Presentation in the Temple"
--now Ambrogio Lorenzetti was one of two brothers
the other was Pietro Lorenzetti
--and they were both students of
the great early Sienese master -- Duccio
--and this is one of Ambrogio Lorenzetti's
most important paintings
--and it tells the story early in the new testament
narrative of Christ being brought to the temple
to be circumsized
--this is the moment when Simeon is presenting Christ
to the temple--and Anna, the seer, is recognizing
Christ as the redeemer--and points him out
--what I find so interesting is that whereas Christ
is so often represented as all knowing even as an infant
--here he really looks like an infant
Dr. Beth Harris: He is and he is putting his fingers in his mouth
Dr. Zucker: It's hard to miss the beautiful emphasis on architecture
--and this is something that Ambrogio often emphasizes
--look at the gothic characteristics of this church
--this panel was originally intended
for the duomo in Siena
and so it would itself have been
in this great Gothic environment
--but look at the way in which we look back
towards the apse through this nave
--all this fabulous emphasis on these
vaguely Corinthian columns
--and lots of paint on the ceiling
for instance we can see a Christ
in a mandorla with angels
--we can see ribbed vaults which actually have
painted gold stars against a blue ground
very much like what we would expect to see
in a fourteenth century church
Dr. Harris: And we have illusion of space
if we look down at the floor
we see diagonal lines that appear to recede
into this space--although this is not
correct use of linear perspective
Dr. Zucker: It's not--but it is an attempt
to create a sense of recession
--look at the capitals and the way they allow
our eye to move back slowly
but it deliberately into space as one space
opens up into another--and there is mystery
--and drama--and what's so interesting
is that we see this wonderful transhistorical
representation of Christ--this ancient figure
in a modern Gothic environment
--wonderfully lighting the past and the present
Dr. Harris: So in some way that would made
a Sienese person in the thirteen hundreds
really be able to relate to what was going on here
Dr. Zucker: I think that that's right
making this ancient scene immediate
(music)