Let's think about how put options can
give us leverage on a downside,
or should I say a bet that the stock
will go down relative to shorting
and this one is a little more complicated because
shorting is a little bit less intuitive.
But if you were to short a stock, in order to short it,
you might say"hey, I don't have to put any money up front...
"...because I essentially just borrow the stock immediately
and then I would sell it for $50..."
But the reality is that you do have to put some capital
up front because the short can move against you.
Usually you have to put at least 50%
of the value of the short.
So in our "short scenario" you would have to put
at least $25 up front and then you would borrow the stock,
sell it for $50, so essentially you will have $75
to play with that you would eventually have to
use to buy back the stock, but the upfront capital is $25.
Now in our scenario where the stock went down
which was a good thing if you're shorting,
you want the stock, that was your bet
you want the stock to go down.
In this scenario where the stock went down to $20
you made a profit of $30.
You were able to buy that stock for $20
and then give it back to the original person
so you were able to keep that $50 although net for that $20
so you made $30.
So you made $30 on a $25 investment.
So your gain -- you make $25 plus another $5
so that's a 120% gain.
So let me write that down
You made a 120% gain.
Of course in this scenario you gained
when the stock went down.
In terms of loss, here, when the stock went up
the stock went up to $80 we lost $30 by shorting.
We had a 120% loss.
So once again 120% loss.
So it's important to realize in a short situation,
the best thing that can happen for you
is your stock goes to 0.
In which case you can kind of...
buy it back for nothing which means you can keep your $50.
So in the best possible scenario you have to put $25 up
front you can keep the $50 that you got from
borrowing and selling the stock
so you can make a 200% return.
In the worst case scenario
(so the best scenario is this is 200%)
this would be infinite.
So you have to be very careful while you're shorting.
But let's think about the put option.
In the put option we only have to put $5 up front
to actually buy the put and when the stock went down to $20,
when the stock went down to $20
we made $15. So this was a 300% gain.
And on the other side of the equation
when the stock went up the worst we could do
was just lose all of our money.
So the worst thing we can do is just lose 100%.
So once again we were able to multiply,
we were able to multiply our gains relative to shorting
although it's a little more mixed on the downside
because the put gives you a little bit of protection there.