Factor out the greatest common factor.
And the expression it gives us is 4x^4 y + 8x^3 y.
When they say to factor out the greatest common factor,
they're essentially telling us to find the greatest common factor of
4x^4 y and 8x^3 y and factor it out of this expression, kind of undistribute it.
And to find that greatest common factor, now I always put it in quotes when we speak in kind of algebraic terms.
Because we don't really know what "x" and "y" are - whether they're positive or negative,
or whether they are greater than or less than 1.
So it's not always going to be the greatest absolute number,
but it's kind of the greatest and it contains the most terms of these two expressions, these two monomials.
So if we were to essentially factor out 4x^4 y, it would look like this.
We do the prime factorization of 4, which is just 2 times 2, times x^4, which is "x" times "x" times "x" times "x",
times "y", and we just kind of expanded it out as the product of its basic constituents.
Now let's do the same thing for 8x^3, so we have in this situation 8x^3 y.
So the prime factorization of 8 is 2 times 2 times 2.
It's 2 times 2 times 2.
Prime, or I should say, the factorization of x^3, the expansion of it,
is just "x" times "x" times "x", x multiplied by itself 3 times.
And then we are multiplying everything by "y" here.
So what factors are common to both of these? And you want to I include as many as possible to find
this "greatest common factor".
So we have 2 2's here, 3 2's here,
so we only have 2 2's in common in both of them.
We have 4 "x"s here, only 3 "x"s here, so we only have three "x"s in common.
3 "x"s and 3 "x"s.
We have a "y" here and a "y" here, so "y" is common to both, to both expressions,
So the greatest common factor here is going to be 2 times 2 times "x" times "x" times "x"
times "y", or 4x^3, 4x^3 y.
So this is what we want to factor out.
So that means that we can write this as