I'm gonna draw for you two of the most important organs in the body.
They're on the left and right side of the body and look pretty much like that.
They look like kidney beans and that's what they are, they're kidneys.
So we have some arteries, the renal arteries, that flow into them.
And renal is just a word referring to kidneys.
And we've got renal veins with blood flowing back out of them.
Once the blood is headed back to the heart,
we call it renal vein.
And there are two of them.
The most important part of these kidneys,
certainly the part that makes them unique,
is that they have these ureters.
And these ureters drain urine into a bladder.
I'm gonna draw that right here, that's the bladder.
The ureters are the third tube coming out of our kidney.
When you're ready to urinate you can release all that urine from your bladder into the outside world.
There's three basic things that I want you to remember coming into or out of kidneys.
The renal arteries, the renal veins and the ureters.
To really make sense of it, you gotta think about how the artery might split up.
So we go back to the artery and we follow it.
It starts kind of branching into five little branches,
it might have more branches out of those branches,
and finally maybe even some more branches,
eventually it's not even an artery anymore, right?
All these little branches are so tiny,
you would call them arterioles.
Let's just take this arteriole, this little guy
and let's see what happens.
So let's take that little guy and show you on the left side of the screen what he looks like.
Let's look at this arteriole a little bit closer.
This is our Afferent arteriole.
It's called afferent because it's headed towards something.
Afferent arteriole.
Don't forget where it comes from,
it's coming from the renal artery.
The blood is coming from the renal artery
and it's headed towards something and that's this.
The artery or the arteriole rather starts making a lot of little turnbacks on itself and finally straightens out.
When it does it's called the Efferent arteriole.
That's how we keep straight whether it's coming or going from this little network of blood vessels.
This little network of blood vessels, if you look under a microscope, is actually being hugged by something like this.
This is the first time we're taking a look at something that isn't a blood vessel in the kidney,
it begins our journey of urine.
This thing is called the Bowman's capsule,
this is the thing in yellow I've drawn for you.
Whenever things are named like this, you have to wonder 'Who was mister Bowman?'
Mister Bowman, turns out, was from England,
actually he was a very curious fellow.
So he looked under a microscope and he noticed that, if you look right where the little cups of blood vessels are,
you can actually see that there's something surrounding them, each of them.
So he called that Bowman's capsule.
And that's what we still call it today.
England was laying claim on parts of the kidney anatomy, we might not even have known then.
So that's Bowman's capsule.
That's the first part of the nephron.
I'll actually show you all the parts of the nephron.
The next part of the nephron, nephron just means kind of the unit of the kidney we care about.
The next part is looking really squiggly,
very convoluted, right?
I'm trying to draw it that way purposefully, because I want you to remember it's called the proximal,
because it's near the Bowman's capsule, thus proximal, convoluted tubule.
Because this is one long tubule, like a little tube.
This is the proximal convoluted tubule, the part of the nephron after Bowman's capsule is the proximal convoluted tubule.
Then it gets into a long deep loop, long loop like that that.
This loop is called the loop of Henle.
You're seeing now part three is called the loop of Henle.
Loop makes sense, but 'of Henle'?
You've got to wonder again
'Is this another British guy, who's mister Henle?'
Mister Henle, turns out, is actually not British,
he's from another part of Europe,
maybe you can guess before I finish this drawing.
He discovered that if you follow the nephron deep into the middle of the kidney,
it has this little loops, very delicate loops, but very important in helping urine form.
He was a German scientist. If the British are going to identify something, so will the Germans.
We still call that the loop of Henle.
After the loop of Henle we have another area that is very convoluted.
You can guess how we'll call this.
When we call things, we try to stay consistent,
If the first part was called the proximal convoluted tubule,
we would call this not the proximal, because it's not near anymore, but a little further away,
we call this the distal, meaning further away, convoluted, 'cause it's still convoluted, tubule.
This is the distal convoluted tubule.
Finally there's a fifth part of all this,
the fifth part of this is a giant tube of collection.
All this stuff goes to a collection tube.
I'm actually showing you where all the other distal convoluted tubes might be dumping in as well.
Eventually all this stuff is gonna go to the same place,
which is down to the ureter.
We've seen now how things go to the ureter.
You can see how things come from the renal artery,
but you're probably still wondering,
(oh, I see I didn't label this for you,
this is the collecting tube)
You're probably still wondering
'Where is the renal vein in all this?'
I still drew the efferent arteriole as being red,
it has oxygen.
Where does the venous blood come from?
The answer is right here, so you basically get red blood,
oxygenated blood, flowing over all these parts of the tubule.
Oxygenated blood.
The proximal convoluted tubule, the loop of Henle, the distal convoluted tubule, all get wonderful blood.
Finally, when all that is set and done,
it all drains into one thing, one final renal vein.
And that's with all of the blood coming together.
This little network of capillaries are considered the peritubular, going around the tubule, peritubular capillaries.
That makes sense.
You can see the renal artery blood coming in, going through the afferent arteriole, the efferent arteriole,
draining back into the peritubular capillaries
and finally the renal vein.
This important structure in yellow that I've drawn,
has five parts to it.
All five parts together are called the nephron.
This is an important structure and we'll talk about the different parts of the nephron in future videos.
This is an important structure, at least you'll get a sense of what it looks like and what the different parts are called.