So this is our Switch Mode Power Supply for the DVD player.
Now the Switch Mode Power Supply operates at a high frequency.
Linear power supplies operate at lower frequencies.
The key deference is that the switch mode power supplies,
Tend to be smaller and form factor ,
They produce more electromagnetic interference,
So the have to have a lot more filtering,
Um, but they also operate with, uh, much more efficiency.
They can change the amount of power they supply,
and they therefore are able to, they don't use near as much power
as a linear power supply, so those are the main differences there.
Now if you look right here you can see this is where the power comes in from the house
ah there's a fuse here,
and this fuse is to protect the house.