So we've got two figures right over here,
and I want to think about
how much space they take up on your screen.
And this idea of how much space something takes up on a surface
is area.
So, right when you look at it,
it looks pretty clear that this purple figure
takes up more space on my screen
than this blue figure,
but how do we actually measure it?
How do we actually know how much more area
this purple figure takes up
than this blue one?
Well, one way to do it
would be to define a unit amount of area.
So, for example, I could create a square over here,
This square, whatever units we're using,
we could say its [area is] one unit,
Its width right over here is one unit,
and its height over here is one unit.
We could call this a unit square.
So, one way to measure the area of these figures
is to figure out how many unit squares I could cover this thing with
without overlapping and while staying in the boundaries.
So let's try to do that.
Let's try to cover each of these
with unit squares,
and then essentially, we'll have a measure of area.
So I'll start with this blue one.
So we could put
1, 2
3, 4
5 unit squares.
Let me write this down.
So we [have] got
1, 2, 3, 4, 5 unit squares --
and I could draw the boundary
between those unit squares
a little bit clearer --
so we have 5 unit squares.
And so we could say that this figure
right over here has an area -
the area is five.
We could say five unit squares,
but the more typical way of saying it
is that you have 5 square units.
That's the area over here.
Now let's do the same thing with this purple figure.
So with the purple figure, I could put
1, 2, 3
4, 5, 6
7, 8, 9,
10. 10 of these unit squares I can cover.
They're not overlapping,
or I'm trying pretty close
to not make them overlap,
but you see you can fit ten of them,
and let me draw the boundary between them,
so you can see a little bit clearer.
So, that's the boundary between my unit squares.
Between my unit squares.
So, there you go,
and we can count them.
1 , 2 , 3 , 4 , 5 , 6 , 7
8 , 9 , 10
So we could say the area --
and let me divide these with the black boundary too,
it makes things a little bit clearer than blue --
So the area here for the purple figure
we could say is equal to 10 square units.
So what we have here -
we have an idea of how much space
something takes up on a surface,
and you could eyeball it, say,
"Hey this takes up more space."
But now we've come up with a way of measuring it.
We can define a unit square
-- here it's a 1 unit by 1 unit --
in the future we'll see that it could be
a unit centimeter, a 1 centimeter by 1 centimeter square;
it could be a 1 meter by 1 meter square;
it could be a 1 foot by 1 foot square;
but then we can use that
to actually measure the area of things.
This thing has an area of 5 square units;
this thing has an area of 10 square units.
So this one we can actually say
has twice the area -
the purple figure had twice the area -
it's 10 square units -
as the blue figure.
It takes up twice the amount of space on the screen.