-We're one the second floor of Orsanmichele, and here,
one after the other, are the monumental sculpture that had once filled the niches outside.
-It's important to remember that Orsanmichele is in many ways the place that the Rennaisance began in Florence.
It began in this space that had both a secular function as a grainery
but also a spiritual function...
-It's also a church.
...and these were sculptures commissioned by the guilds, and so it makes sense that these first Rennaisance sculptures
would be commissioned not by a church, but by guilds. By these secular organizations.
-Okay so let's take one as an example.
One of the important guilds in the city were the Linen Workers, and we're standing in front of St. Mark
which is this monumental sculpture by Donatello. We know it's the Linen Worker
because he is standing on a pillow, presumably made of linen.
-Right. If we think about him outside in that niche, and imagine walking by him,
you could almost imagine the way that you would relate to him, that you could engage with him
right on the streets of Florence. This sense of civic pride of bringing beauty to the city.
-There really is a sense of immediancy here. This is Donatello's brilliance.
I mean, here we have a figure that is first of all reviving the classical in really important ways.
This is a figure that is an incredible early expressions of contrapposto, that hasn't been seen with this kind of understanding for a thousand years.
-If you look at so many of the other figures that were created for Orsanmichele,
they still have that gothic sway to the hips and what Donatello gives us instead
is something that looks very much like an ancient Roman sculpture.
-Look for instance at the hips that push to his right, and over the engaged leg
you have the cloth falling in perfect unbroken lines, almost as if that's the fluting of a classical collumn.
It's on the other side that you can see the knee breaking the cloth,
and you can really get a sense, even though its under this heavy drapery, you still understand the movement of the body,
the turn of the spine, the turn of the hips, the axis of the knees.
-Yep, Donatello is barrowing this directly from
ancient greek and roman sculpture. There's no other place he could have gotten this from.
And so, the figure, because of the contrapposto, really looks alive. He looks like he can trully walk.
His feet are firmly planted on the ground.
The sense that the weight is shifting gives a sense that he could walk at any second.
We have an idea of sculpture beginning to be separate from the architecture,
I mean, even though he was in a niche and he was intended for the architechture,
the contrapposto, the sense of movement, gives us a sense of his autonomy from the architecture.
-But it's also the authenticity of his experience, and so it's a revival of the classical
not only in terms of the mechanics of the body, but also in terms of the experience of the individual.
You said a moment ago we would walk down the street and see this figure in a niche,
there would be a commedian kind of relationship,
and yes that's true, but at the same time he's seeing further. He's also seeing past us.
-Right, it's this bringing together of the spiritual and the human.
So close at this moment in the early fifteenth century in Florence.
-Look at the face,
there's a kind of intelligence, there's a kind of internal focus, there's a kind of awareness that is just piercing,
and he's thinking, he's reflecting on the gospels that he holds so easily at his side.
And perhaps he's about to speak them to us.
There is this way in which our eyes are drawn up through the planear quality
of the drapery to the more focused handeling of the stone
near the beard, near the eyes -- look at that furrowed brow --
so that he's somebody that we can understand or approach in some real way.
-You know, the sculptures like the ones by Ghiberti that are more in that high Gothic style
the face is often more plain, right?
-Yes.
-And less individualized, and our focus goes on those decorative forms in the drapery...
-It's distracted in a sense!
-Exactly! And so we don't have that human to human connection that we're getting here,
here instead of focusing -- although the drapery is fabulous --
we look directly at the face, and we see the furrowed brow,
the eyes that gaze out, the beard that animated his face and makes it seam even more thoughtful,
his receding hairline. Then we look down at his hands,
and we can see that Donatello has clearly been thinking about human anatomy.
Those are not just generalized shapes for hands, but a sense of bone and muscle and veins,
and then down to the feet, firmly planted on the ground.
When the Florentines looked up at St. Mark, they looked up at him and saw a figure that ...
-It ennobled.
-That ennobled them!
That they looked at St. Mark and could have a sense of their own profound diginity as human being,
as Florentines in the early fifteenth century. In a way, St. Mark is a mirror.
-And so, isn't that exactly what this notion of civic pride, that was so tied in to fifteenth century Florence, was really about?
This notion that we can rise to our own ideals.
-We can be like the ancient Romans, and be virtuous, and...
-Shake off the corruption of the medieval, and in a sense return the greatness that man had once known.