Find the sum of -15 + (-46) + (-29)
To do this, let's just first visualize
what each of these numbers look like.
So I'm going to draw a number line for each of them.
-15 might look something like this.
If this is 0, and let's say this is -15.
I can represent -15 as an arrow that points from 0 to -15.
The length of the arrow is the absolute value of this.
It's the distance from 0.
So the length here is 15
and the negative says we are pointing to the left.
So the absolute value is 15.
That's the length of that arrow.
Let's do the same thing for -46.
Once again let me draw my number line.
Put 0 is going to be right over there.
and -46 is going to be someplace over here.
Notice the same exact idea
The distance between -46 and 0
or another way to think that is the absolute value of -46.
This distance right over here is going to be 46.
And its direction is to the left.
That's why we get to the number -46.
The negative really tells you
wether you're to the left or the right of 0.
The absolute value says
how far you are to the left or the right of 0.
Finally let me do the same thing for -29.
So once again, let me draw my number line.
Use the yellow again.
So got to draw my number line.
Say this is 0, -29 is going to be roughly over here.
Once again -29 is exactly 29 away from 0.
So this length right over here is 29 and it is to the left
that is why it is -29.
If it was +29, it would be 29 to the right of 0.
So we have represented all of these numbers
and you can see what their absolute values are like.
And now let's think what happens if you add them.
One way to think about adding these numbers
is as if you added these arrows.
If you put this arrow on top of this arrow
or to the left of this arrow
If you started with this arrow leaves off,
then you put this green arrow.
And then you put the orange arrow.
So let's do that. Let's draw that.
It's going to be a longer arrow now.
So we are going to start at 0.
First we have -15.
So we are going to move 15 spaces to the left,
to get us to -15.
Then we are going to go 46 spaces to the left,
to get us to -15 + (-46)
Let me draw that. Then we are going to go...
We are going to figure out what that number is in a second.
Then we're going to go 46 to the left. That's about that far.
It's really just this arrow. I am now placing it.
I am starting off where the -15 started
or where the -15 left off.
and then I am putting that arrow after that.
And we don't know yet what number this gets us to.
We are going to have to do a little math here.
That's actually the point of this problem.
But we know the length of this arrow is 46.
It is 46 to the left.
We know the length of this magenta arrow is 15.
Then finally we have this orange arrow
which we know has a length of 29,
although it's 29 to the left.
It looks like that.
It has a length of 29.
So when all is said and done, where are we?
Where do we end up on our number line?
Well, the total length that we are to the left,
is going to be 15+46+29.
But it's going to be to the left.
So it's going to be negative.
So we can really view this as
Since all of these have the same sign
Look this is the same thing
as abs(-15)+abs(-46)+abs(-29)
But then take the negative value of it.
Let's just add that.
15+46+29 is equal to...let's see.
5+6 is 11. 11+9 is 20. Carry the 2.
2+1 is 3. 3+4 is 7. 7+2 is 9. So you get 90.
So this entire length here is 90.
If you add up the arrows, you get a 90.
But it is not 90 to the right.
If it was 90 to the right, this would all be positive.
Then we'll just get positive 90.
But this is 90 to the left.
So when you add these guys up,
you don't get to positive 90.
You get to negative 90.
So one way to think about it is, these are all the same sign.
So this is going to be equal to
the -( abs(-15)+abs(-46)+abs(-29))
and the reason why we are writing this.
this might look fancy
but this is really just the length of this purple arrow.
This absolute value of 46,
that's really just the length of the green arrow, 46.
This is just the length of the orange arrow.
So this is 15+46+29, gives us 90.
But it's to the left. So that is why it is -90.