What I want to do in this video is to show that if we start
with any arbitrary triangle, this would be the arbitrary triangle
that we're starting with starting, that we can always make
this the medial triangle of a larger triangle
When we say the medial triangle we mean that each of the vertices
of this tria, of this triangle will be the midpoint
of the sides of a larger triangle
I wanted to show you that you can always construct that
If you start with this triangle, you can always have this be
the medial triangle of larger triangle
So to do that, let's draw a line that goes through
this point right over here but that's parallel to this line down here
So this line and this line up here
are going to be are going to be parallel
So just like that
And immediately we can start to say
some interesting things about the angles
So if we have a transversal right over here,
we can view this side as a transversal
of these two parallel lines or this line and this segment
We know that alternate interior angles are congruent
So that angle is going to be congruent to that angle
And we also know that this angle, in blue,
is going to be congruent to that angle right over there
Now let's do that for the other two sides
So let' create, let's create a line that is parallel
to this side of the triangle but that goes through
this point right over here
So let me draw it as well as possible
And so these two characters are going to be parallel
And you could always construct a line that's parallel to another line
that, that goes thru a point that's not on that line
And so once again we can use alternate interior angles
We know that if this angle right over here
Just let's say we have this orange angle,
its alternate interior angle is this angle right over there
We also have corresponding angles
This blue angle corresponds to this angle right over here
So it'll correspond to that angle right over there
And now let's draw another line that is parallel to
this line right over here, parallel to this one right over here
but it goes through this vertex,
Goes to the vertex that's opposite that line
And so Let me just draw it
You can always construct these parallel lines, and just like that
And let's see what happens
So once again, these two lines are parallel
So you could view this green line as a transversal
If this green line is transversal, this corresponding angle
is this angle right over here
If we view, if we view this green line as a transversal of both
of these pink lines, then this angle corresponds to
this angle right over here
If we view this yellow line as a transversal
of both of these pink lines
Actually let's look at, let's look at it this way
View the pink line as a transversal of these two yellow lines
Then we know that this angle corresponds
to this angle right over here
And if you view this yellow line
as a transversal of these two pink lines
Then this angle corresponds to this angle right over here
And then the last thing we would have to, the last
this we should, we need to think about is, if we think about
the two green parallel lines, the two green parallel lines,
and you look at the and you view this yellow line as a transversal
Then this corresponding angle in orange is right over here
This corresponds to that angle
Cause this yellow line is a transversal on both of these green lines
So what I've just show starting with
this inner triangle right over here is that,
If I construct these parallel lines in this way,
that I now have four triangles,
if I include the original one,
and they're all going to be similar to each other
And we know that they're all similar
because they all have the exact same angles
You just need two angles to prove similarity
but all four of these triangles have the exact three angles
Now, the other thing we can show is that they're congruent
So all of these four are similar
And we also know they're congruent
For example, this side right over here in yellow
is the side in this triangle between the orange and the green side
Is the side between the orange and the green side
on this triangle right over here
So these two, that we have an angle, a side,
and an angle, Angle-Side-Angle congruency
So these two are going to be congruent to each other
Then over here, the, on this inner triangle, our original triangle,
the side that's between the orange and the blue side
is going to be congruent to the sides between the orange
and the blue side on that triangle
Once again, we have Angle-Side-Angle congruency
So this is congruent to this which is congruent to that
All of these are going to be congruent
And by the same exact argument, same exact argument
this middle triangle is going to be congruent to this bottom triangle
That the, you have an angle, blue angle, purple side, green angle,
blue angle, purple side, green angle,
they're congruent to each other
So, if all of these triangles are congruent to each other
So the corresponding sides are equal
So if you look at this triangle over here
We know that the side between the blue angle,
between the blue angle and the green angle is,
is going to be equal to this angle right over here,
and sorry, it is equal to this length
So it's going to be equal to this length
between the blue and the green, we have this length
Between the blue and the green we have that length
Between the blue and the green we have that length right over there
So you immediately see that this point
and let me label it now, maybe I should have labeled it before
If we call that point A,
we see that A is the midpoint of, of, we call
this point B and call this point C right over here
So A is the midpoint of BC
So that's fair enough
So I was able to construct it in that way
Now let's look at the other sides
So this green side on all the triangles
is the, is the, is the side between
the blue and the orange angle
So between the blue and the orange angle,
you have the green side, between the blue
and the orange angle you have the green side
So once again, this length is equal to this length
and so if we call this point over here D
and maybe this point over here E
You see that D is the midpoint of BE
And then finally, the yellow side is between
the green and the orange
So between the green and the orange we have a yellow side,
between the green and the orange you have a yellow side,
all these triangles are congruent
So once again, let me call this F,
we see that F is the midpoint of EC
So we've done what we wanted to do, we've shown
that if you start with any arbitrary triangle,
triangle ADF, triangle ADF,
we can construct a triangle BCE, we can construct, construct
a triangle BCE, so that ADF, ADF is triangle BCE's medial triangle
And all that means, all that means is that the vertices of ADF sit on
the midpoints of BCE
So you might say, "Sal, that by itself is interesting but what's
the whole point of this?"
The whole point of this is actually is I wanted to use this fact
that if you give me any triangle,
I can make it the medial triangle of a large one
To prove that the altitude of this triangle are concurrent
And to see that, let me first draw the altitudes
So an altitude from vertex A looks like this,
it starts with the vertex goes to the opposite side
it is perpendicular to the opposite side
If I draw an altitude from vertex D, it would look like this
And if I draw an altitude from vertex F, it will look like this
And what I did, this whole set-up of this video is to show, to prove
that this will always, to prove that this will always be concurrent
And you might say "wait! we How, how do how do we know
that they are concurrent "
Well, all you have to do is think about
how they interact with the larger triangle
How do these altitudes,
what are these altitudes of the larger triangle?
Well this yellow altitude to the larger triangle, remember,
these two yellow lines, line AD and line CE are parallel
So, if this is a 90 degree angle, so its, its core,
its alternate interior angle is also going to be 90 degrees
So this right over here is perpendicular to CE
and it bisects CE because we know that ADE is the medial triangle
This is the midpoint
So this right over here is perpendicular bisector
This is a perpendicular bisector, bisector for the larger triangle,
for triangle BCE
So this altitude for the smaller one is a perpendicular bisector
for the larger one
We can do that for all of them
If this angle right over here is 90 degrees,
then this angle right over there is going to be 90 degrees
Cause this line is parallel to this, this is a transversal
Alternate interior angles are the same
So this line right over here, this altitude of the smaller triangle
It bisects right at the midpoint of the larger one on this side
and it's also a perpendicular bisector
So it's a perpendicular bisector of the larger triangle
And then finally the same thing
is true of this altitude right over here
It bisects this side of the larger triangle at a 90 degree angle
We know that because these two magenta lines
is the way we constructed the larger triangle
if they're going to be parallel
So once again this is a perpendicular bisector
So this whole reason, if you just give me any, any triangle
I can take its altitudes and I know that its altitudes are going
to intersect in one point
They're going to be concurrent
Because for any triangle, I can make it the medial triangle
of a larger one and then it's altitude will be
the perpendicular bisector for the larger triangle
And we already know that the perpendicular bisector,
is for any triangle, are concurrent
They do intersect in exactly, in exactly one point