In the last video we started to explore the payments
that could flow into a country or out of a country
and now I want to continue it more
In particular, we focused on
the current account last time, and that
focused on things like trade
exports and imports
income earned from assets in another country
or income that someone from outside of the country
earns from assets
in the country that we're studying
or just transfers that are happening
Now, when we look at the capital account
in this video right over here
(I wrote capital accounts,
but there shouldn't be an "s" over here)
we'll look at other ways or other reasons
why we might have inflows or outflows of payments
In particular, the capital account is focused on
the change in assets
that either foreigners own of
in this case the US
or that US nationals own of assets
that are someplace else
An this little triangle right over here
is the greek letter delta
just shorthand for change in
So, once again, let's focus first on the inflows
and when you're talking about change in assets
these would essentially be
someone outside the US buying assets inside the US
from someone that was not foreign
So for example, if I am a homebuilder
I am an american citizen
and I build a home in the US
and I sell it for a million dollars to a Mexican national
maybe for their vacation home
that means that for just that transaction
there's been an increase
in foreign ownership of US assets
that a million dollar home
This number would be increased by a million dollars
And, so that is why it is an inflow
because when they bought that house
they would have to make a payment TO ME
And this right over here
and we have a little bunch of stuffs over here:
change in foreign-owned assets in US
it also includes financial derivatives here
and you don't have to worry too much about that
And it also has change in foreign reserves
The one way to think about the difference
between that and that right over there
you can view this as
private-owned changes in ownership
and this is essentially the offical changes in ownership
by either the government
or the central banks of foreign countries
And for a lot of countries
they are essentially one of the same thing
In the US, they kind of maintain this sort of independence
but this is, you can kind of view it as
the offical government ownership
and this over here is for the most part
private ownership
So once again if someone in the England
would come to the US
and buy, let's say, buy a share of IBM from an American
then that would increase the number right over here
But if the central bank of China decided to
buy an US government bond from some American
then this right over here would increase
But they both the general idea:
someone buys an asset
(we are not talking about the income on the asset,
we talked about the asset itself)
someone buys an asset from
or changes hands from an American national
to a foreign national
then these numbers would increase
and those foreign nationals
would have to make a payment into the US
So once again these are the inflows right over here
Now we take the other side of that coin
If I were to go out and buy vacation home in Italy
And let's say I buy it from an Italian.
Then I would have to make a payment to them
So that would be an outflow from the US
And I would get an asset in Italy
in exchange for my vacation home
So this number right over here would increase
Once again I wrote here in orange because it is an outflow:
I'm making a payment to a foreign national
And once again this is a breakdown between
this is really the private sector for the most part
and this over here is the US federal reserve
so if the US federal reserve would go
and buy an asset from a foreign government
bank or individual
let's say a foreign bond
Then this number right over here would increase
And actually the way I've classfied right over here:
government purchases
not the US federal reserve but the US government
actually still falls into this category
just the way I've set up the numbers
this right over here is the US federal reserve alone
now with that out of the way
Let's actually figure out whether we are running
a capital account deficit or a suplus
So let's get our caculator back
Let me open it right over here
so we can see our numbers
First of all let's think about the inflows
this is how much more foreigners are buying US stuff
So they are buying 625
When I'm taling about stuff
I'm talking about assets
I'm not goods and services
I'm talking about stocks and bonds and real estate
So 625 billion plus another 165 billion
if we talk about the offical purchases of
governments and central banks
So this is how much the increase of assets
This is the changing assets purchase
from foreigners in the US
So they have to put in 790 billion dollars in 2007
to make those purchases
While on the other side of that
The Americans went out and bought 380 billion
when I write (ANS), that's answer
that's just the previous answer
so we have 790 billion
which is what's inflowing
and now this is outflowing
380 billion to buy assets in other countries
that is what the non-federal actors do
and federal reserve also buys
and there is also outflows of payments
And we are left with 394 billion
A positive 394 billion
This is 394 billion larger than this right over here
So we are running a capital account surplus
let me write that
So we end up with an capital account surplus
394 billion
And so you see these numbers are
pretty close and I will tell you something
and hopefully in future videos you will understand
why this is happening in a little bit more depth
But these numbers actually should have been
the exactly same thing
but we see they are off by about 80 billion
So let me write this down
we have an 80 billion dollar discrepancy
And for most people that's a fairly large discrepancy
but for talking about an economy the size of
the United States
that is already near 15 trillion
it's not that huge a discrepancy
and you have to think of how all these stuffs are measured
They have to do serveys, they sample things
you know
they get all these numbers from all different sources
So that's actually reasonable that
you have some form of statistically discrepancy
That's what actually is right over here
This is the statistically discrepancy
In theory these numbers should be the exact amount
If you are running a current account deficit
then you should have the exact amount
in the capital account surplus
And vice versa, if you have a capital account deficit
then you would have to be running
a current account surplus
We will talk more about why this makes sense
I encourage you to think about it right now
why that makes sense
And the difference between these numbers
This is just the statistical discrepancy
by the bureau of economic analysis