The Forces on an Airplane
So this is an airplane here. Ok.
You probably already knew that.
If you've flown in one or maybe you just seen them fly.
But, even if you've seen them or been in one, do you know how they work?
Is it magic? Wingavium Leviosa.
Are there invisible fairies that hold the plane aloft?
Alright men, we've got a busy morning and lots of flights to carry.
Or is it science?
Well, you guess that the answer is indeed science.
That's ridiculous!
What?!
[Hand slap]
So to discuss how an airplane flies, we first have to talk about the forces on an airplane
which push it around in all sorts of different directions.
Now we are going to focus on airplnes today
because they're awesome!
But, most of these forces apply
to any other vehicle
The first force acts on all these vehicles
really it acts on everything
its the weight force which points down
towards the center of earth
Weight is equal to the mass of the airplane - (M) right here.
Times the acceleration due to gravity (g)
Here on earth, (g) is equal to 9.81 meters per second squared.
Now that is only for earth.
The acceleration due to gravity really depends on the mass of the planet that you're on.
The larger the planet, the higher the gravity.
So, 9.81 meters per second squared here on earth
The moon however, is smaller than earth.
So the acceleration due to gravity is only one sixth that on earth.
So one point six meters per second squared.
This is why astronauts can bounce high on the moon
but not on earth
This isn't nearly as much fun.
Obviously, there has to be another force opposing the weight and pushing the airplane up
This force is called lift
Lift operates perpendicular to the airplane's wings
which are right here in this side view
Now if these are the only two forces then our aircraft only be able to go up and down
but it won't go anywhere
So, we're going to have a force that pushes the airplane forward
And this is called thrust.
All vehicles have thrust otherwise they wouldn't go anywhere like our airplane
Why didn't you buy a car with thurst?
I'm sorry, we can at least roll down the hill.
[Huff]
On an aircraft this thurst is produced by engines
There are two main types of engines
there are propellers, like this little guy right here.
And jet engines like our first model.
Whatever the type of engines, they all work by the same principle
So we draw a little side view of an engine here
The engines accelerate air out the back, this direction
and by Newton's third law
there is an equal and opposite reaction
And that's the thurst force pushing the aircraft forward
This is really the same thing that happens when you blow up a balloon and let it go
The air comes out the back and the balloon moves forward
We have a force that opposes the thrust, its call drag.
It points opposite the direction of flight.
The major type of drag is pressure drag
which is the force caused by the air smacking into the airplane.
So we try to minimize this type of drag by making the airplane as areodynamic as possible.
This means that it has smooth lines
and the air flows nice and cleanly over the front here
You can feel the pressure drag when you stick your hand out of the window of a moving car
Ah, honey, honey, your hand, your hand please.
When your hand is horizontal its areodynamic, and you really don't feel alot of drag.
But if slowly turn your hand vertical,
you can really feel the drag increasing.
So these are our four forces on the airplane
but perhaps your're thinking
So this really cool and everything, but how do we increase and decrease the airplane's lift
to move up and down?
That's a great question
Let's look at the equation for the magnitude lift per unit wing area
we'll call that (L).
L equals one half times rau times CL times V squared.
It's that simple.
Ok, ok. I'll tell you what each of these things mean.
So rau, its not a P is the greek letter rau.
Rau is the density of the air,
which is a measure of the number of air molecules in a certain volume.
Density of the air varies with altitude and temperature.
So if you go higher up the air is thinner,
so the density is lower.
So if you want to simplify things we generally use standard density,
which is one point two seven five four kilograms per meters cubed.
(V) here is the speed of the aircraft or
fast its traveling. And (C)(L) is something called the coeffecient of lift.
Its a number that gives us some information about the shape of the aircraft's wings
These things right here.
The coeffecieint of lift changes with the angel of attack.
Angle of what?
An aircraft can pitch up and down.
And even if they pitch up, they are still traveling in a horizontal direction, like that.
Now, the angle formed here by the horizontal direction from travel,
and the direction of the aircraft's nose,
is called the angle of attack.
And we denote that with the greek letter alpha.
So we can make a little plot here of that.
We're going to put the coeffecient of lift up on the Y axis.
And the angle of attack, down on the x axis.
So as the airplane starts to pitch up, if I can get a little hand here.
Thank you.
So as the aircraft starts to pitch up, the coeffecient of lift increases.
This is a good thing because
we have more lift.
As we continue to increase we eventually reach a point where we keep pitching up
but the lift starts decreasing.
This is something called stall, and its
not a good thing.
So we generally try not to pitch up this much.
There is a similar equation for the drag per unit wing area (D).
D equals one half rau, not CL, that wouldn't make any sense, but CD.
As you can guess, its the coeffeiceint of drag times the velocity squared.
The coeffeiceint of drag is another number that tells us something about the wings.
And its also varies with the angle of attack.
So as the angle of attack increases...Oh, thank you
The coefficient of drag increases as well.
Thank you very much.
This is because as the aircraft is pitching up
there is more wing area perpendicular to the flow.
Now this reminds me of somehting that we talked about earlier.
Exactly.
This is very similar to whenever you hold your hand out the window of a car.
And so, that's pretty much everything you need to know
about how an aircraft flies.
So the next time you're on an airplane or you've just seen one
you really know exactly what is that's keeping it up in the air.
Nope.
That's not it either.
Ah...there you go.
Now you've got it.