Let's see if we can understand a thing or two
about Futures Curves
And I've drawn two futures curves here
and really all they show is the different
settlement prices for the different delivery dates of futures
So let's say that this orange curve is one of them
what this says is, if "today" for delivery today
we wanted to buy or sell an apple the market rate is $0.10/lb so this isn't
the futures contract at all this is called the spot price it's essentially
called the market price for that commodity
or that security today we're just using the example of apples
so this tells us at time "0" you can buy or sell an apple
based on the current market for $0.10
Now when we move to "1" the way I've labelled
this axis this says 1-month from now
this is not saying that the market price is going
to go up 1-month from now
you go to the futures market and say
I want to sell or I want to buy apples