Welcome to the video on 'basic subtraction.'
Let's do a little bit a review of 'basic addition' first.
If I said '4 plus 3' (4 + 3), what would this mean?
What did that equal?
Well, there are a couple of ways
we could have viewed this.
We could have said, "I had 4 of something."
Let's say I had 4 circles – or, I don't know –
I had 4 lemons for breakfast.
So 1, 2, 3, 4 lemons for breakfast.
And let's say I had another 3 lemons for lunch.
1, 2, 3.
And so you could view 4 + 3 as,
"How many total lemons did I have?"
I'm adding 3 to 4.
So how many total did I have?
Well, it's (COUNTING: 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6) 7.
So I had a total of 7 lemons.
Another way we could have viewed that
is we could have drawn our 'number line.'
(And I'll draw it in yellow because we're –
Well that's not wide enough.
I'll draw it in yellow,
because we're talking about lemons.)
So let's say that's our number line.
And if I start at the number –
(Let me draw all of the numbers.)
0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.
So you could think about this as saying,
"Well, we're on the number line.
We start at the number 4. Right?
(That's this number 4.)
And we're adding 3 to it.
So we'll increase along the number line by 3.
So we'll go 1, 2, 3 – and you end up at 7.
So you could say,
"If I have 4, and I get 3 more, I get 7.
Or, "If I increase 4 by 3, I also get 7."
So what's 'subtraction' now?
(Because that's what this video is about.)
I shouldn't waste all of our time
talking about addition.
So let's take the example of 4 minus 3 (4 - 3).
What is that equal to?
Let me switch colors, just to keep things interesting.
So what is 4 - 3 equal to?
Subtraction – or 'minus' – is the opposite of addition.
So in addition, you're doing something more.
You're adding.
(I don't want use the word 'adding'
to define 'addition' –
but that's what you're doing.)
I had 4 lemons, and then I had 3 more.
In 'subtraction,' you're taking away.
So in this example, if I started with 4 lemons –
Let's say I had 4 lemons on a plate.
If I'm subtracting 3 –
If I'm saying minus 3,
Instead of adding these 3 here, and getting 7,
I'm going to take 3 away.
So maybe I'm eating them.
Or maybe I'm giving them to you –
in exchange for you watching these videos.
So to take away 3 from this 4 –
Let's say this one goes away.
This one goes away.
And this one goes away.
How many lemons would we have left?
Well, this is the only one that I haven't crossed out.
So we would have 1 lemon left.
And this would be the lemon that's left.
It didn't have to be that one.
I could have crossed out any of the 3.
Another way to view that –
(Let's draw the same lemon colored number line.)
Let's say that this is the number line, right here.
And I'll draw all the same numbers.
So that's 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.
Of course, the number line keeps going.
There's no largest number that you can imagine,
any number that you can think of,
I can think of one higher than that.
So there is no largest number.
So that's why we draw that arrow there.
I could never draw the entire number line.
But anyway – back to subtraction.
So we're starting at 4 lemons, right?
When we added 3 – plus 3 –
We went to the right 4 spaces on the number line.
And that's because the right is increasing value.
So we went from 4 to 5.
That was 1 more.
5 to 6 was 2 more.
And 7 was 3 more.
Now we're taking away from 4.
So what do we do?
What would you think we do?
Well, since we're taking away,
we're going to decrease
the total number of lemons we have. Right?
So if we take away 1 – we get to 3.
Take away 2 – get to 2.
Take away 3. We took away 3, right?
So we'll go back [to the left]
1, 2, 3 along the number line.
And we'll end up at 1.
And that's this 1 right here.
So, just to review,
addition is when you're getting more of something.
Subtraction is when you are taking something away.
If you think about it on the number line, addition is
increasing along the number line by that amount.
So, in this case,
we increased along the number line by 3.
And so we went from 4 to 7.
In the subtraction case,
we decrease back [to the left] on the number line.
So we decrease by the amount
that you're subtracting.
So, in this case, we decreased by 3.
So we went back [to the left] 1, 2, 3.
and we had 1.
And the other way to view it –
if I have 4 of something –
if I give 3 away –
or if I ate 3 of them –
Or if I –
I don't know what I did to 3 of them.
If I lost 3 of them I
would have 1 left.
Now let me show you some
interesting things
about subtraction.
So we know that 4 minus
3 is equal to 1.
Let me show you something
else that's interesting.
What is 4 minus 1?
Well, we could use
either example.
Let's do the lemon example.
Let's do apples now; I'm
bored of the lemons.
Let's say I had 1, 2, 3, 4.
I have a new pen, sometimes
it doesn't draw right.
Let's say I had 4 apples.
This is the example
we're dealing with.
And I were to eat one of them.
So one of them were to go away.
How many apples
would I have left?
Well, 3-- 1, 2, 3.
So 4 minus 1 is equal to 3.
And if we did it on the number
line, if we started at 4 and we
subtracted 1-- we took 1 away.
So we're going to
become one smaller.
We go back one, we get 3.
Either way works.
But isn't this interesting?
4 minus 3 is equal to 1 and
4 minus 1 is equal to 3.
You might say, well, did I pick
the numbers just so it worked?
Well, it turns out that
it's always true.
Well, I don't want to get too
technical, but we're already
touching on something that
you'll learn later, maybe
in algebra one day.
But actually I don't want to
go into all that right now.
So where does this come from?
Well, this is also based on
the fact that 3 plus 1-- I
didn't want to confuse you.
So I apologize if I did.
But I'll show you another
interesting thing.
What is 3 plus 1?
3 plus 1 is equal to what?
Well, that's easy.
You know that from
basic addition.
You can start on the number
line at 3 and add 1 do it.
And where do you end up?
You end up at 4.
3 plus 1 is equal to 4.
Or you could have started at 1
on the number line and added 3.
1, 2, 3 and you would
have also ended up at 4.
So we also know that you could
have switch this either way.
Both of those are equal to 4.
What do you see here?
Well, there's a bunch of things
I've written here and they all
kind of relate to each other.
1 plus 3 is equal to 4.
3 plus 1 is equal to 4.
4 minus 1 is 3.
Essentially, 4 minus 1 and
getting 3 is the exact same--
you're saying the same thing
as 3 plus 1 is equal to 4.
This statement says if
I add 1 to 3 I get 4.
This is saying if I take
away 1 from 4 I get 3.
So if I start at 4,
move back, I get 3.
This is saying if I start at
3, and I move up 1, I get 4.
Hopefully that gives you a
little bit of intuition
about what subtraction is.
In the next video I'll just do
as many basic subtraction
problems I can do
in 10 minutes.
And then you'll be ready
to do the exercises.
See you soon.