In this video we're going to look at the definitions of acids and bases
The definition most commonly used
in organic chemistry is a Bronsted-lowry acid and a Bronsted-Lowry base
a Bronsted-lowry acid refers to a proton donor
and a Bronsted-lowry base refers to a proton acceptor
So lets really quickly review, exactly what a proton is referring to
so in the most common isotope of hydrogen
there's one proton in the nucleus, and there's an electron
somewhere outside of our nucleus, so here is a very simple picture
of a hydrogen atom. This is a neutral hydrogen atom. Its neutral because the positive
and the negative charge cancel each other out, so there's no overall charge
if we were somehow able to take away that electron,
we'd be left with just a proton
So we took away a negative charge, right, so it's no longer balanced.
So now we have H plus, we have the positively charged nucleus of a hydrogen atom,
which consists of only a proton, so H plus is equal to a proton.
This is very important to understand when you are looking at organic chemistry mechanisms
and a proton is being exchanged.
So let's go ahead and do one of those mechanisms. A very simple general chemistry reaction,
alright you could start of with water here
the dot structure for water, two non-pairs of electron on my oxygen.
and I'm going to show water reacting with HCL, so we have HCL, and my dot structure for HCL
would look like this, now and the bond between the hydrogen and the chlorine, one of those electrons
came from hydrogen and one of those electrons came from chlorine, like that
So in this mechanism, HCL is going to be our Bronsted-lowry acid
So this is going to be our Bronsted-Lowry acid, it's going to donate a proton
and water is going to accept that proton, so water is going to be our Bronsted-lowry base
like that, let's go ahead and get some more room here, so in this mechanism,
a lone pair of electrons in this oxygen are gonna take this proton from the HCL,
so if it's just taking the proton, right, the electron that hydrogen had is gonna be left behind on the chlorine
So if I go ahead and highlight that electron in blue here, this is the one that came from the hydrogen atom in the dot structure
so you can think about it being this electron right here, and so if I go ahead
and draw the product of this acid based reaction, right, so the oxygen is going to pick up a proton
So the oxygen is going to pick up a hydrogen here in the dot structure, and also a positive charge
and there's still a lone pair of electrons left on that oxygen.
So you can think about the oxygen being positively charged because it's picking up a proton
or you can think about this oxygen as having a plus 1 formal charge,
if you know how to calculate formal charge already.
So the other products would be , we would have CL over here, which use to have three lone pairs of electrons
but it's going to pick up an extra lone pair here, so the the electron in blue, the electron that use to belong to the hydrogen,
or the electron that hydrogen brought to the dot structure, now ends up on chlorine, to form the chloride anion
right so you can think about the chlorine picking up an extra electron
to having a negative 1 charge, or you can think about the chloride as having a negative 1 formal charge, so either one works
and so we've shown the transfer of one proton from HCL to water to form H3L plus and CL minus
And we know that HCL of course is a strong acid, so technically these reactions are at equilibrium,
for an extremely strong acid like HCL the equilibrium lies extremely far to the right
so I'm only going to draw an extremely small arrow in here going back to the left
So the reverse reaction is possible, although highly unlikely, so hcl is pretty much completely dissociated in practice
but lets think about the reverse reaction occurring, so if h3l plus and cl minus reacted, right
the h3l plus would be donating a proton this time, so this would be my acid, right, the h3l plus would be an acid,
and the CL minus would be a base. The cl minus would pick up a proton to form HCL and the H3L would lose a proton to form H20
So in practice of course this doesn't really occur.
but it's important to think about acid based reactions being at equilibrium.
And, we can also think about conjugate acid base pairs, and so over here on the left
HCL was functioning as a bronsted-lowry acid
Once it donates it's proton, you're left with a conjugate base, which is CL minus
and so HCL and CL minus are a conjugate acid base pair.
The differ in terms of only one proton, 1H plus.
Another conjugate acid base pair, would be water over here on the left,
which is functioned as a bronsted-lowry base,
and then over here on the right H3L plus is the conjugate acid.
So H2O and H3L plus, are also a conjugate, acid base pair.
again there's one proton difference between those two.
So the stronger the acid, the weaker the conjugate base.
That's one of those general chemistry principles, and since HCL is extremely strong,
that means the chloride anion is going to be extremely weak.
Right, so CL minus is an extremely weak base. It's not really going to take any protons from H3L plus,
if it did, that would mean that you would reform the HCL and so the HCL wouldn't be as strong as an acid as you anticipate.
Since HCL is extremely strong, CL minus is a weak base.
Let's look at another definition for acids and bases, that's sometimes used in organic chemistry.
And this is the Lewis definition. So a lewis acid is an electron pair acceptor, and a lewis base is an electron pair donor.
The good way to remember this is that Lewis Acid, right, is an electron pair acceptor
so we have two a's
lewis base is an electron pair donor. If you take this d here and you reflect it, and you get a b, right, a lowercase b, which of course would refer to a base
That's just a quick way of remembering which is which here for your definitions.
Let's go ahead and look at a reaction where you have to use the definition of Lewis acid and base.
I'm gonna go ahead and draw a cyclic ether here so with lone pairs of electrons on my Oxygen,
and then I'm gonna draw a dot structure for Borane, and so BH3 is Borane
and so there is my dot structure.
Something a little bit strange about the dot structure of borane, right it doesn't have an octet around it
it has six electrons around it, but it can form an octet, because of it's location on the periodic table.
And so that makes borane extremely reactive.
If you think about the hybridization of the boron atom right here
right, it has a ,it would be SP2 hybridized, right so this would be sp2 hybridized, meaning that the boron has a free P orbital
So there's an empty orbital here, and this is what makes borane extremely reactive
as a matter of fact, it will react with itself sometimes,
but if we think about this reaction right here,
the borane, the boron has an empty orbital, so it's capable of accepting a pair of electrons,
and this ether over here on the right, has a pair of electrons that it can donate.
So I can think about this pair of electrons filling the empty orbital and forming a bond with the boron atom.
Let's go ahead and draw this acid base reaction here and so we have our Oxygen right
One lone pair of electrons is still on our oxygen, the other lone pair formed a bond with the boron,
and the boron is still attached to some hydrogens here, like that.
If you already know your formal charges, you can calculate a formal charge of plus 1 on the oxygen here
and a formal charge on of negative 1 on the boron. like that
And so this is technically an acid base reaction and since the ether over here, on the left, donated a pair of electrons,
so this must be our Lewis Base. An electron paired donor.
The borane accepted a pair of electrons and so this must be our lewis acid.
So Lewis acid and base definition comes up occasionally in organic chemistry, and it is important to understand.
But the most important definition is definitely Bronsted Lowry, so make sure you understand that concept extremely well.