When people use the terms 'fascism' or 'fascist' today,
they're usually using it in a derogatory way
to refer to a group, a regime, or even an individual
that is overly aggressive -- and controlling -- and totalitarian.
But its roots
actually lie with Benito Mussolini,
who was in power in Italy during the 1920s and 1930s,
and through World War II.
And they proudly called themselves the 'fascists,'
and their ideology as 'fascism.'
And the word 'fasc...,' -- or the root of
'fascist' and 'fascism,' come from
the Italian word 'fascio,' which literally refers to a bundle.
It comes out of this idea that a bundle of things
will be stronger together than individually.
And this is actually the symbol for fascism.
And this symbol of this bundle - this sheath - of sticks,
this actually predates Mussolini by thousands of years.
It goes back to Roman times, and even,
based on some of the things I've read,
even predates Roman times, as a symbol of unity,
a symbol of official strength.
And even before Mussolini came around,
the term was used by many, many, many groups
that viewed themselves as a league of revolutionaries --
a group of people somehow fighting for change.
And Mussolini was no different, when in -- at the end of 1914,
and then early in 1915, he establishes
the 'Fasci d'Azione Revoluzionaria.'
And I'm once again so sorry
for my butchering of an Italian word.
But this literally translates to 'Group Action Revolutionary,'
or you could say the 'Revolutionary Action Group,'
founded by Mussolini in 1915.
And it was really a splinter of the Socialist party.
And there's an irony there, because Mussolini --
and fascism in particular -- is associated
with strongly anti-socialist ideology.
But as we enter into --
or as Europe was entering into World War I, in 1914,
in 1914, some of the social or the mainstream of the Italian Socialist Party
was against Italy entering the war.
They wanted Italy to maintain their neutrality.
But you had splinter groups, more nationalist groups,
that said, "Hey, look! This is Italy's chance
to claim what's its right.
It should join the war on the side of the Entente."
And Mussolini was one of these individuals.
And because of his strong pro-war stance,
he was actually kicked out of his --
he was head of a socialist paper, in 1914.
And then he, eventually, by 1915 establishes
the 'Fasci d'Azione Revoluzionaria.'
And by the end of World War I,
as we get into 1919, it regroups
under the name 'Fasci Italiani di Combattimento'
So this literally translates as --
You could view 'fasci' as a group or league,
or a 'Revolutionary League of Italians of Combatants,'
or the 'Combatant Italian Revolutionary Group,'
I guess is one way to think about it.
Or the 'Italian' ... 'The Group of Italian Combatants '
is another way to think about.
And their ideology wasn't well-established,
right when they set up.
It was just really around this idea
of being super pro-nationalist.
But it began to develop
over the course of the 20s and 1930s.
The core idea -- and I've already said it multiple times --
is kind of an extreme 'nationalism.'
And when we talk about extreme nationalism,
or nationalism in general,
it's talking about the interests of one nation,
of one group, above all others --
about putting the state above all other things.
Often times, fascism is viewed as a right-wing group,
but, in its purest form, it's neither left- or right-wing.
At the left end of the spectrum,
you could imagine communist or socialism.
I'll write communism,
which you can view as an extreme form of socialism.
And at the extreme right,
you can imagine just complete free market --
complete unfettered free market -- ultra ultra small government.
And fascists and extreme nationalists,
they didn't view themselves
as either end of this spectrum -
they kind of viewed themselves as a separate way,
where everything was subordinate --
the economy itself was subordinate to the state.
Now, with that said, they tended to align themselves
more with folks on the right.
So even though they weren't
completely free market capitalists,
they were staunchly anti-Communist,
and anti-socialist, which caused them to form
alliances a little bit more with the right.
But from their point of view, it wasn't one of these
extreme right-wing ideologies
that the government should be subordinate
to the economy -- that the government should
be as small as possible.
It was much more that the economy
was there to serve national interests.
Some of the other kind of ideologies that
the fascists began to hold is this idea that
force was a legitimate part of politics.
So, force in politics.
And we see this when Benito Mussolini's fascists,
through the use of the Blackshirts --
which was their paramilitary group
which allowed them to eventually take
political control and enforce political control --
And we later see it with other groups, like the Nazis,
who also tended to be associated
with fascism
and their storm troopers, and their storm battalions,
their paramilitary forces -- that are used to,
essentially, take political control.
The other aspect of them --
and as you can imagine, when we're talking about
either Mussolini or the Nazis --
is that they weren't really fans of democracy.
Not only did they think that everything should be
subordinate to the state, but
that the state should have absolute control.
So, it's not about democracy.
It's about having a strong leader at the top,
a strong one party at the top.
And in the case of Mussolini, it was the Fascists.
In the case of Hitler, it ends up being the Nazis.
So totalitarian. Completely totalitarian.
And then, they also --
And these kind of all gelled together.
-- this idea of aggressive foreign-policy.
And this aggressive foreign policy is really
rooted in this belief of cultural superiority.
And, if you take the case of the Nazis, this belief in racial,
extreme racial superiority -- cultural superiority.
And I'm making a slight distinction there,
because in Mussolini's eyes, he was actually
quite disparaging --
even though Hitler looked to Mussolini
as something of a role model,
when Mussolini took power in 1922 --
it inspired Hitler's 'Beer Hall Putsch.'
Mussolini did not think much of Hitler
through much of the 1920s, and even early 1930s.
He thought Hitler's ideas of racial purity
were really an illusion --
that there was no racially pure race.
He didn't really appreciate Hitler calling
the Italians a mongrel race.
But Mussolini, himself, did think that
the Italians were culturally superior,
and that would be their justification
for an aggressive foreign policy --
for them taking over other territory
in Europe and in Africa.
And as we'll see,
because they shared so much in common ideologically --
The Nazis were -- you could kind of view as
a more extreme form --
and the Fascists themselves were quite extreme.
But the Nazis were a more extreme form
of this same ideology.
They will, even though, in the 20s and early 30s,
Mussolini is more eager to align himself
with some of the other powers in Europe --
in particular Great Britain and France,
as we go into the second half of 1930s,
Mussolini and Hitler find themselves to be kindred spirits.
They both want to be aggressive in their foreign-policy.
They both want to secure other territory.
They both have this idea that they need
space for their superior populations --
their culturally superior -- and in the case of the Nazis --
racially superior populations -- to grow and thrive.
And so, as we enter into
the second half of the 1930s and World War II,
you have Mussolini and the Fascists
become close allies of Hitler and the Nazis.