In the last video we figured out the probability of
getting exactly three heads,
when we have five flips of a fair coin.
What I want to do in this video is
think about it in a slightly more general way.
We will start assuming a fair coin although
we will surely see we don't have to make that assumption.
But what I want to do is to figure out the probability
of getting K heads in N flips of the fair coin.
So the first thing to think about is just
how many possibilities there are.
Well there are going to be n flips.
So literally, there is the first flip, second flip,third flip,
all the way to the nth flip.
And this is a fair coin, so each of these flips
contain two equally likely possibilities.
So the total number of possibilities is going to be
2 times 2 times 2. . . n times.
So this is going to be equal to 2 to the nth possibilities.
Now let's think about how many of those equally likely,
these are all equally likely possibilities.
This is a fair coin.
Let's think about how many of those
equally likely possibilities involve k heads.
Well, just like we did for the case
where we thought about three heads.
We say "Well look, the first of those k heads,
how many different buckets could it fall into?"
Well the first of the k heads could fall into
n different buckets, right?
It could be the first flip, second flip,
all the way to the nth flip.
Then the second of those k heads,
we don't know exactly how many k is.
We will have n minus 1 possibilities.
And then the third of those k heads will have
n minus 2 possibilities,
since two of these buckets are already taken up.
And we will do this until
we have essentially counted for all of the k heads.
So this would go down all the way to,
we will multiply. The number of things
we're multiplying is going to be k,
one for each of the k heads.
So this is one, two, three,
and then you are going to all the way to n minus k minus 1.
And you could try this out in the case of five.
When n was five and k was three,
this resulted in five times four times,
actually we just have to go, times three,
actually that was this term right over here.
So I am doing a case that is a little bit longer,
where k is a slightly larger number
because this right over here is five minus two
that is this one over here.
Just not to confuse you,
let me write it like this.
So you'll have n spots for that first head.
N minus one spots for that second head.
And then you keep going and you are going to have
a total of these k things you will multiply
and that last one is going to have n-(k-1) possibllities.
And now hopefully it'll map a little better to the one
where we had five flips and three heads
because here there were five possibilities for the first head
four possibilities for the second head, and since n is 5,
5-2 is three possibilities for the last head.
So this actually works.This is the number of spots
where - or the numbers of ways that we could put,
that we can stick those heads in those,
or that we can put three heads into
five different possible buckets.
Now just like the last video,
we don't want to overcount things
because we don't care about the order.
We don't want to differentiate one ordering of heads
- and I am just going to use these letters
to differentiate the different heads -
We don't want to differentiate this from this
from this: Heads A, Heads B, or any of the other orderings of this.
So what we need to do is we need to divide this.
We need divide these numbers so that
we don't count all of these different orderings.
We need divide these by the different ways
that you can order k things,
the different ways that you can order k things.
So if you have k things, so you know, one thing, two things,
all the way to k things. How many ways can you order it?
Well, the first thing can be in k different positions.
Or maybe I'll do it like this. Maybe I will do it thing 1,
T for thing,thing 1, thing 2, thing 3, all the way to thing k.
How mant different ways can you order it?
Well thing 1 can be in k different positions.
Then thing 2 would be in k minus 1 positions.
And then all the way down to the last one
is only going to have 1 position.
So this is going to be k times k minus 1, times k minus 2,
all the way down to 1.
And in the example where we had three heads in five flips,
was three times two all the way down to 1 - 3 times 2 times 1.
And so is there a simpler way that we can write this?
Well this expression right over here,
this is the same thing as k factorial
and if you haven't have heard what a factorial is,
it's exactly this thing right over here.
K! (k factorial) literally means k times k minus 1 times k minus 2,
all the way down to 1.
So for example, 2! is equal to 2 times 1.
So, and actually it's a fun thing to play with,
factorials get large, very very very very fast.
So anyway, the denominator right over here
can be rewritten as k factorial.
And there is any way to rewrite this numerator
in terms of factorials.
So if we were to write n!, let me see how we can write this.
If we are going to write n!,
let me get some real estate over here.
So n! would be equal to n times n minus 1, times n minus 2,
all the way down to 1, that's kind of what we want.
We just want the first k terms of it.
So what if we divide this by,
so let's divide this by (n-k)!
So let's think about what that is going to do.
If we have (n-k)! that is the same thing as,
I have to do a little bit of algebraic manipulation here
right over here,
that is the same thing as n minus k,
all the way down to 1. When you divide this,
the 1 is going to cancel out,
and what you may or may not have realized is that
- and you can work out the math - everything is going to
cancel out here until you are just left with, up here,
everything from n times n minus 1 to n - (k - 1).
Because if you expand this out,
if you distribute this negative number,
this is the same thing as n minus k plus 1.
So n minus k plus 1 is the integer that's one larger
than this right over here.
So if you divide out, this would cancel with something up here.
This would cancel somnething up here.
This would cancel something up here.
And we are going to be the left with
is exactly this thing over here.
And if you don't believe me, we can actually try it out.
So let's think about 5! over (5-3)!
so this is going to be 5 times 4 times 3 times 2 times 1.
So all of that stuff over there, all the way down to 1,
over 5 minus 3 is 2, over 2!, 2 times 1. 2 cancels with 2,
1 cancels with 1.You don't have to worry about that,
and you are just left with 5 times 4 times 3,
exactly what we had up here, 5 times 4 times 3.
And so, in general, if you wanted to figure out
the number of ways to stick 2 things in 5 chairs,
and you don't care about differentiating between those 2 things.
You are going to have this expression right over here,
which is the same thing as this right over here.
So you are going to have n!/(n-k)!
and then you are going to divide it
by this expression right over here,
which we have already said the same thing as k!.
So you are also going to divide it by k!.
And then you have a generalized way of
figuring out the number of ways you can stick 2 things,
or the number of ways actually I should say
the number of ways you can stick k things
in n different buckets,
k heads in n different flips.
And so another way of writing,
this is actually a generalized formula for binomial coefficients.
So another way to write this is the number of ways
given that you have n buckets,
you can put k things in them
without having to differentiate it.
Or another way to think about it is
if you have n buckets or n flips
and you want to choose k of them to be heads,
or you want to choose k of them in some way
but you dom't want to differentiate.
So all of these are generailized ways
for binomial coefficient.
So going back to the original problem:
what is the probability of getting k heads
in n flips of the fair coin?
Well there are 2 to the nth equally likely possibilities.
So let's wrtite this down.
So the probablity of 2 to the nth of the equally
likely possibilities
and how many of those possibilities resulte
in exactly k heads?
Well we just figure that out in during this video.
That's the number of possibilities.
Now probability of a OK idea to memorize this.
But I'll just tell you frankly, you know,
the only reason why I still know how to do this
20 years after first seeing this or whenever I first saw it
is that I actually just like just to reason it through
every time, I like just to figure it out.
OK, I have got five flips, three of them need to be heads.
The first of those heads can be in five different buckets
that next in the four different buckets
and next was in three different buckets
and then of course I don't want to differentiate
between all of the different ways
that I can rearrange 3 different things.
So I have to make sure that I divided by 3!
by 3 times 2 times 1.
I want to make sure that I divided by
all of the different ways
that I can arrange three different things.