A line has a slop of negatave 3/4ths, and goes through the point (0,8).
What is the equation of this line in slope-intercept form?
So any line can be represented in slope-intercept form as y=mx+b.
Where this 'm' right over here, that is the slope of the line, and this
'b' over here, this is the y-intercept of the line.
Let me draw a quick line here just so that we can visualize that a little bit.
So that is my y-axis, and then that is my x-axis.
And let me draw a line, and since our line here has a negative slope,
I'll draw a downwards sloping line.
So let's say our line looks something like that.
So, hopefully we're a little familiar with the slope already,
the slope essentially tells us, look start at some point on the line,
and go to some other point on the line,
measure how much you have to move in the x-direction, that is your run,
and measure how much you have to move in the y-direction, that is your rise,
and our slope is equal to rise over run. And you go see over here, it will be
downward sloping, because if you move in the positive x-direction,
we have to go down. If our run is positive, our rise here is negative.
So this will be a negative over positive, and will get a negative number
Which makes sense, because we're downward sloping.
The more we go down in this situation, for every step we move to the right,
the more downward sloping we'll be; the more negative of a slope we'll have.
so that's slope. That's slope right over here.
The y-intercept just tells us where we intercept the y-axis.
So the y-intercept, this point right over here, this is where the line intersects
with the y-axis. This will be the point (0,b).
And this actually just falls straight out of this equation.
Let's evaluate this when x=0.
y=m*0+b, well anything times zero is zero, so y=0+b or y=b, when x=0, so this is
the point (0,b)
Now, they tell us what the slope of this line is.
They tell us a line has a slope of -3/4 so we know that our slope is -3/4
And they tell us that the line goes through the point (0,8)
They tell us we go through the, let me just do this in a new color
I've already used orange, let's use this green color.
They tell us that we go through the point (0,8) notice x is 0, so we're on the y-axis
when x is zero, we're on the y-axis, so this is our y-interecept
so b, we could say, we could do a couple of-- our y-intercept is the point (0,8),
or we could say b, remember, it's also (0,b) we could say b=8
So we know m=-3/4, and b is equal to 8, so we can write the equation of this line.
in slope-intercept form.
It's y=-3/4 times x, plus b, plus 8. And we are done, we are done.