Whenever we talk about money, the amount of money
is not the only thing that matters
what also matters is when you have to get, or
when you have to give the money.
So to think about this or to make it a little more
concrete, let's assume that we live in a world
that if you put money in a bank, you are guaranteed
10% interest.
10% risk free interest in a bank.
And this is high by historical standards,
but it will make our math easy.
So let's just assume that you can always get
10% risk free interest in the bank.
Now, given that, let me through out scenarios
and have you think about which of these
that you would most want.
So I could give you $100 right now
that's option 1,
I could in 1 year, instead of giving you the
$100 immediately,
in 1 year I could give you $109
and then in 2 years, this is kind of option 3
I'd be willing to give you
$120
So your choice is, someone walks up to you in the street
"I could give you $100 bill now,
"...$109 in a year, or a $120 2 years from now"
And you know in the back of your mind
you can get 10% risk free interest.
So given that you don't have an immediate
need for money
we're assuming that this money you will save.
That you don't have a bill to pay immediately.
Which of these things are the most desirable?
which of these would you most want to have?
Well, if you just cared about the absolute value
or the absolute amount of the money
you'd say, "hey look! $120! that's the biggest
amount of money. I'm gonna take that one"
because that's just the biggest number,
but you probably have in the back of your mind
"well I'm getting that later"
so there may be something I'm losing out on there
and you're right, you would be losing out on
the opportunity to get the 10% risk free interest
if you were to get the money earlier.
And if you want to
if you wanted to compare them
directly, the thought process would be
well let's see
if I got the, if I took option 1, if I got the $100
if you were to put it in the bank, what would that grow to
based on that 10% risk free interest?
Well after 1 year, 10% of $100 dollars is $10
So you would get $10 in interest
so after 1 year, your entire savings in the bank
will now be $110.
So just doing that little exercise,
we actually see that $100 given now
put in the bank at 10% risk free
will actually turn into $110 a year from now
which is better than the $109 a year from now
So, given this scenario, or this kind of situation
or this option, you would rather do this than do this
A year from now you're better off by a dollar
What about 2 years from now?
Well if you take that $100 after 1 year
it becomes $110, then 10% of $110
is $11, you want to add $11 to it
so it becomes $121
so once again, you're better off taking the $100
investing it in the bank risk free
10% per year. It turns into $121
that is a better situation than just someone
guaranteeing you to give the $120 in 2 years
once again you are better off by $1.
And so this idea, not just the amount matters
but when you get it,
this idea is called "the time value of money,"
Or another way to think about it is,
think about what the value of this money is
over time, given some expected interest rate
and when you do that, you could compare this
money to equal amounts of money at some future date.
Now another way of thinking about the time value,
or I guess another related concept
to the time value of money, is the idea of
present value.
and maybe I'll talk about present value and
future value.
So, present and future value.
So, given this assumption, this $110, this 10% assumption
if someone were to ask you,
"what is the present value of $121 2 years in the future?"
They're essentially asking you
So what is the present value?
PV stands for Present Value
So what is the present value of $121 2 years in the future?
That's equivalent to asking,
what type of money, what amount of money
would you have put into the bank, risk free
over the next 2 years to get $121?
Now we know that, if you put $100 in the bank
for 2 years, at 10% risk free
you would get $121. So the present value here
The present value of $121 is the $100
or another way to think about present and future value
if someone were to ask, what is the future value?
What is the future value of this $100 in 1 year?
So, in 1 year, if you put
if you get 10% in the bank that's guaranteed
it's future value is $110,
after 2 years, it's 2 year future value is
$121
and so with that in mind let me give you one
slightly more interesting problem:
so let's say that I have
Let's say, we're going to assume this the whole time,
that makes our math easy at 10% risk free interest,
and let's say someone says that they're willing to give us
$65 in 1 year, and we were to ask ourselves,
"what is the present value of this?"
So, remember, the present value is
just asking you, what amount of money
that if you were to put it in the bank
at this risk free interest
would be equivalent to this $65
which of these two are equivalent to you?
And so you would say, well look
whatever amount of money that is, let's call that "x"
whatever amount of money that is,
times, if I grow it at 10%
That's literally, I'm taking x plus 10% x
let me write it this way,
plus 10% times x
or let me write it, let me make it clearer this way
x plus 10% of x should be equal to our $65
If I take the amount, I get 10% of that amount
over the year, that should be equal to
$65.
And this is the same thing as 1x
or we could say that 1x plus 10% is the same thing as
0.10x is equal to 65, or you add these two
1.10x is equal to 65
and if you want to solve for the actual amount
of the present value here
you would just divide both sides by the 1.10
So you'd get x is equal to
Let me do it this way, be a little bit more clear about it
So let's divide both sides by 1.1
and really that trailing zero doesn't matter
we're not really too worried about the precision here
because this is actually exactly 10%
So this is going to be, these cancel out
and x is going to be equal to
get the calculator out
x is going to be equal to
65 divided by 1.1
$59.09 rounding it
So, x is equal to $59.09
which was the present value
of $65 in 1 year
or another way to think about it is
if you wanted to know what the future value is of $59.09 is in 1 year
assuming that 10% interest
you would get $65.00.