The word arbitrage sounds very fancy, but it's actually a very simple idea.
It's really just taking advantage of differences in price on essentially the same thing to make risk-free profits.
Let's think about it a little bit.
Let's say in one part of town, there's some type of a market.
Let's say it's a market for apples.
And let's say that in that market apples sell for $1 per apple.
And let's say in another part of town you have another market.
And in that other part of town, the apples sell for $1.50 per apple.
So how could you take advantage...?
And we're going to assume that these apples are completely identical apples.
How could you take advantage in this price difference on these identical things to make a risk-free profit?
Well ideally, you want to sell the apples in the more expensive market where you can get $1.50/apple.
And you want to buy apple in the less expensive market where you can get them for $1/apple.
And that's exactly what you would do.
You would go to this market over here....
You would buy apples; let's say you buy 10 apples for $10.
And then you would go maybe ride your bicycles to the other market over there
and you would sell your 10 apples.
So this is buy 10 apples for $10, and then you would sell those 10 apples for $15.
And so you would make an immediate risk-free profit of $5.
You are buying for $10 and selling for 15.
And you can just keep doing that over and over again
and on every trip as many apples as your bicycle can carry
You will continue to make money.
So this is what arbitrage is.
And just imagine the side effect
If someone did this enough,
then this would increase the supply of apples here
so supply would increase in this market
and in this market the demand will increase
because there's someone who keeps buying in this market and selling into that market
So what's eventually going to happen
with the demand increases the price will go up in this market
and when the supply increases in this market, the price will go down.
So in theory the more that you do this the more that you are going to make these prices come closer to each other.
And eventually you won't be able to make any profit at all.
But while there's discrepancy you have an opportunity for arbitrage.