After the last video,
if you paid a lot of attention
to why Spout wasn't backing up,
you realize that it was because
there wasn't enough friction
between the axle of the motor
and the surface Spout was running on.
So we're going to apply some electrical tape
to the axles of the motors
to increase the amount of friction
between the motor and the surface of the table –
so when Spout bumps into something,
he's able to back up right away.
So we should see an increase
in both the speed of Spout’s movement
and his ability to react to the environment around him.
So let's see how much of a difference it's made.
You can see he's frenetic now.
He wants to get out really bad.
He wants to go run and play.
So it definitely has improved his ability
to react to the environment around him,
and react to the obstacles he faces,
and improve the speed at which he moves.