In the circle below, central angle GOH has a measure of 3/2 radians.
What is the length of arc GH?
So let's define some variables that will help us manipulate them a little bit easier.
So where is central angle GOH? It's this angle right over here.
Let's call that "theta". So let's say that theta is equal to the measure of angle GOH.
Now, they're asking us "what's the length of arc GH?"
Well arc GH is this, right over here. And let's call that 's'.
So let's let s be equal to the length of arc GH.
And they also give us the radius 6cm for this circle, but let's just call that 'r' for now
so the radius is equal to 6cm.
So the first thing that we should think about when we're dealing with arc lengths and radians
is 'how do angles measured in radians relate to arc length in particular-
how does an angle measured in radians relate to the length of the arc that subtends that angle?'
In this case, the length of this arc right over here, arc GH
subtends angle theta- subtends central angle GOH.
So what's the relationship? Well the definition of radian measure says that an angle measured in radians
is the ratio between the length of the arc that subtends that angle, so s
and the radius of the circle.
If this was a unit circle, then it would just literally be equal to that arc length.
If it's not a unit circle, or I guess in all cases, unit circle or not, it's the ratio between the length of the arc
that subtends the angle and the radius.
Now, given this definition of what a radian is, let's see what we know and what we don't know.
And we can manipulate this however we see fit, we could mutiply- you could see this written as if you multiply both sides of this by r
you get r theta is equal to s
or another way of writing it is you could get s is equal to r times theta.
s is equal to r theta
And we could have solved this equation or this equation, but for this problem
- this one's actually going to be a little bit useful, because this is the unknown, the length of GH
we want to know what this is, this is the unknown that they're asking for
and this explicitly solves for the unknown, so this has essentially solved it for us.
So what else do we know?
Well, we know the radius, we know the radius is 6cm.
We multiply that times the angle in radians, which is 3/2 radians
and we are left with, so s is equal to 6cm times 3/2, and so we are left with, this is going to be equal to
6 times 3 is 18 divided by 2 is 9.
It's going to be equal to 9cm.
And we are done.