Welcome to level three exponents.
Let's get started.
So if I asked you what four to the one / two power is, your immediate
inclination is to view this probably as like a
multiplication problem and try to multiply it somehow or add
them or something.
And you always have to remind yourself this
is not multiplication.
I know when I first learned it, I always was tempted to do
something with multiplication.
Well, something to the one / two power might not be intuitive to
you, but it actually turns out that this means the same thing
as the square root of four.
Or another way, what times itself is equal to four,
and we know that the square root of four is two.
It could actually be a positive two or a negative two because we
know that either of those numbers when they're
squared could equal four.
But for the sake of this one we'll assume it's always
the positive square root.
So four to the Â½ is equal to two.
Similarly, nine to the one / two, well that would be three.
sixteen to the one / two -- oops.
sixteen to the one / two, my subconscious gave away the answer.
sixteen to the one / two power is four.
twenty-five to the one / two power is five.
I think that might make sense to you now.
So what does it mean when something is to the one / three power?
Well, if I say eight to the one / three power, you might
already catch on.
In the one / two power we said something times something
is equal to four.
Well in the one / three power we have to say that something to the
third power is equal to eight.
And if you've been practicing your exponents you know that two
to the third power is equal to eight.
So we know that eight to the one / three is equal to two.
Similarly, twenty-seven to the one / three is equal to three.
And sixty-four to the one / three is equal to four.
You might notice that I'm picking particular numbers,
like eight and twenty-seven, sixty-four.
That's because they have clean, cube roots.
And then by the way, when something is to the one / three power
that's the same thing as saying the cube root.
I just used terminology without explaining it,
which is very bad.
So I just used eight and twenty-seven and sixty-four because when I raised them to
the fractional exponents, they actually come out to
be clean numbers.
You could use a calculator and do something like five to the one / three
power and you'll get some weird decimal.
Let's do some more problems.
So we know that nine to the one / two is equal to three.
Well what do you think nine to the two / three is equal to?
Well, it turns out that this is equivalent to nine to the -- oops,
I actually didn't want to do those -- what do you think nine
to the three / two is equivalent to?
Well this is the same thing as nine to the one / two power
to the third power.
And I'll do a whole presentation on the actual
principles of exponents, but it actually turns out you
could just multiply.
When you have one exponent to another is when you can
multiply the two and that's where you get three / two .
But nine to the one / two we know is three.
And you're raising it to the third power, so that equals twenty-seven.
I'm sure at this point I have confused you.
Let's do more of these.
So you know at this point that sixteen to the one / four power --
think about what that is.
That means that some number to the fourth power is sixteen.
If you've been practicing your level one exponents, you'll
probably know that well, that equals two, because two times two
times two times two, well that equals sixteen.
So we know that sixteen to the one / four is equal to two.
So what do you think sixteen to the two / four is equal to?
Well, we already know from that last problem that that's the
same thing as sixteen to the one / four squared -- that's the two on both
sides -- and we know sixteen to the one / four is two, so that equals two
squared and that equals four.
And it all works out because we know from fractions another way
to write the fraction two / four is to write one / two.
So this is the same thing as sixteen to the one / two power.
sixteen to the one / two power, well that's just equal to four.
Now I'm going to mix it up real good and do some negative
fractional exponents.
So what if I were to tell you sixteen to the negative one / two power?
Well this might seem very daunting at first, but as we
know with the negative exponents level three,
immediately we just say well this is the same thing as one
over sixteen to the positive one / two.
And that's the same thing as one to the one / two over sixteen to the one / two.
Well the square root of one is easy, it's one.
And sixteen to the one / two is four.
So that wasn't too bad.
It's a little daunting when you see a negative exponent, but
immediately when you see that negative, just flip the sixteen and
then work it out like a regular fractional exponent problem.
Let's do another one.
eight over twenty-seven to the negative one / three.
Immediately when we see that negative, we
want to just flip it.
So we'll say that equals twenty-seven over eight to the one / three, and that
equals twenty-seven to the one / three over eight to the one / three.
And we know that twenty-seven to the one / three, well that equals three.
And eight to the one / three, well that equals two.
So we've got eight over twenty-seven to the negative one / three is three / two.
The first problem probably looked very intimidating to
you, but it only took us two steps to get there and as you
do more practice, hopefully it'll seem more and
more intuitive to you.
Let me give you another problem.
What's negative eight to the negative third power?
Let me change that.
What's negative eight to the negative one / three power?
Once again, at first this might confuse you, but when you see
that negative in the exponent, we just take the reciprocal of
the base, so that we say that that is equal to negative one
over eight to the one / three power.
And we say well that is equal to, we could write it as one
over negative eight to the one / three.
We say what number times itself three times is equal to negative eight?
Well, we know from intuition there's no real mechanical way
to do this, but we know that negative two times negative two is
four times negative two is negative eight.
So we know that this is equal to one over negative
two or negative one / two.
So negative eight to the negative one / three is
equal to minus one / two.
Let's do another one, one more problem just to thoroughly
melt your brain.
Let's say nine over four to the negative three over two.
Well, immediately we see that negative exponent,
let's flip the base.
We get four over nine to the three / two .
Well we know that that equals four over nine to the one / two, and all
of that to the third power.
four over nine to the one / two, I think at this point you know that's the
same thing as four to the one / two which is two over nine to
the one / two which is three.
Now we have to just raise everything to the third power.
And that's the same thing as two the third power which is
eight divided by three to the third power.
Well that's twenty-seven.
There we have nine / four to the negative three / two power is
equal to eight over twenty-seven.
Now hopefully you can at least do these problems.
You probably don't have a good intuitive sense for exactly
what a negative three / two power is, and hopefully I can cover that
for you in future modules.
But I think you're ready to try some of the level three
exponent practice problems.
Have fun.