so lets say that this is an equilateral triangle and
what I want to do is make another shape out of
this equilateral traingle and I'm gonna do that
by taking each of the sides of this triangle
and divide them into three equal sections
into three equal sections
so, my equilateral triangle wasn't drawn
super ideally but I think you'll get the point
and the middle section I want to construct
another equilateral triangle
so the middle section right over here
I am going to construct another equilateral triangle
so its going to look something like this
and then right over here I'm gonna put
another equilateral triangle, and so now I went
from that equilateral triangle to something that
looking like a star or a star of David.
and then I'm gonna do it again
so each of the sides now I'm going to divide into
three equal sides, and that middle segment
I'm gonna put an equilateral triangle
I'm going to put an equilateral triangle
so in the middle segment I'm going to put an
equilateral triangle, so I'm gonna do it for
everyone one the sides, so let me do it... right there
and right there, I think you get the idea but
I want to make it clear, so let me just so then
like that, and then like that, like that
and then almost done for this iteration, this pass
and then it'll look that, but then I can do it again
each of the segments I can divide into three equal
sides and draw another equilateral triangle
so I could there, there, there, there, there
I think you see where this is going.
And so I can keep going on forever and forever
So what I want to do in this video is think about whats
going on here. And what I'm actually drawing, if we just
keep on doing this forever and forever. Every
every iteration if we look at each side. We
divided it into three eequal sides and then the next iteration
with three equal segments, the next iteration, the middle
segment would turn into another equilateral triangle
this shape that we're describing right here is called a
koch snowflake, I'm sure im mispronouncing the koch
part. the koch snowflake was first described by this
gentleman right over here who was a swedish
mathematician, Niels Fabian Helge von Koch
well, I'm sure I'm mispronouncing it. And this is one of
the earliest described fractals, so this is a fractal. And
the reason why it is considered a fractal is that it looks
the same, or it looks very similar, on any scale you look
at it. So when you look at it at this scale, so if you look
at this it looks like you see a bunch of triangles with
some bumps on it, but then if you were to zoom in
right over there then you would still see that same type
of pattern. And then if you were to zoom it again, you
would see it again and again. So a fractal is anything that
on any scale or any level of zoom it kind of looks roughly
the same. So that's why it's called a fractal. Now what's
particularly interesting and why I'm putting at this point
in the geometry playlist is that this actually has an
infinite perimeter. If you were to keep doing it if you
actually wanted to make the Koch snowflake were you
keep an infinite number of times on every smaller little
triangle here you keep adding another equilateral
triangle on its side. And to show that it has an equal
perimeter, lets just consider one side over here. So let's
say that this side, let's say we're starting with that