I'm T.A. McCann, I'm the founder and CEO of Gist. Which was acquired by BlackBerry about a year ago.
Gist is sort of next generation address book, so all of us are connected to so many different people in so many different places
Gist's primary function is to bring all those address books together, bring my inbox, my contact manager, my FaceBook, LinkedIn, Twitter
All those contacts into one place. But its really about harnessing the power of your network
And understanding the context of the people you are interacting with. I think for
most entrepreneurs, they want to solve the problem for themselves. Because they're the first user.
So, I wanted to build that product for myself. But, as an engineer and as somebody who understands software,
How would I do it is almost as important as what I'm gonna do.
And without somewhat understanding of the "how", the "what" is almost irrelevant.
So I kind of play them back and forth. So how would I build a thing that kind of does this?
And in fact the ideas for Gist started with, "If I want to do that, like, where would I get the list of people."
How would I do that? How would I prioritize that?
What should it do? Who does it do it for? Why is it valuable?
So it was both the idea, but the technical implementation and hacking around on that
I think is so critical, and that where it comes back to being technical and getting into how things work, mechanically or from a code perspective
I think most good software guys tend to think in 18-24 month cycles
Because normally if you are going to do a company and you fund a company
you have 18-24 month runway. So you kind of get into this model of like, what can I do in 18 months?
And thats kind of a horizon. 18 months from now I'll probably have to raise more money, I'll probably need the business to looks like this
What is the next phase of the business look like? And what do I want to achieve with the business?
So, I think that first and foremost, you as an entrepreneur should say, what do I want to achieve in the business?
Now I'm gonna come very much back to the tactical, "What am I going to do next week? And the next 3 months?"
So, it was our way of thinking, "How do we get our interesting ideas to the largest amount of people at the fastest rate?"
I have sort of a construct that I use to sort of run through almost all of my ideas and now I can do them much more radpidly
And its really; customer, value proposition, feature set and business model.
And almost every idea I do now, I just go run through that. And if you take the construct a little further,
"What is the value I'm delivering?
So in my case it might be: A better understanding of another person.
Or saving time.
So my primary value to you is saving time and gaining deeper understanding.
So when I think about the business model I say, well, I should charge you more for more time I save you.
And thats a correlation between the value and the business model.
And so considering the business model alongside or in parallel with who's the customer, whats the features, I think is critical.
I have to say that in the things that I do, starting companies and working with different entrepreneurs,
I enjoy the process of building companies, as much as the companies themselves.
The whole process part is really exciting for me,
because if you do it well, if you have two companies that have the exact same idea, and one has a better process
you can do more features faster for less money
than the guy down the street. That ultimately ends up being the big advantage.
Ideas are easy. Execution is really hard.
And people who can execute ideas more rapidly or with higher quality or with fewer people will ultimately outpace