Welcome to the presentation on age word problems. Let's get started.
Well, I have one written down here, it says:
"In 4 years, Ali will be 3 times as old as he is today. How old is Ali today?"
Well, let's just say that x,
(that's a little too big for what I want to write)
x equals Ali's current age or his age today.
(Please forgive my handwriting)
If x is Ali's current age and here we say in 4 years
So, how old Ali is going to be in 4 years?
Well, if x is his current age, in 4 years he is going to be x plus 4 years old.
So, that is equal to Ali's age in 4 years.
Let's read what other information there is for the problem.
It says in 4 years, so, in, this situation -- that's a 4, x plus 4 --
In 4 years, Ali will be 3 times as old as he is today.
Well, today he is x.
So, we say in 4 years -- x plus 4 -- and that's just so,
So, in 4 years, so we can translate that into x plus 4
That's going to equal 3 times as old as he is today.
Well, we know today he is x , so that's going to be equal to 3x.
And now, we just well solve for x.
Subtract x from both sides, you get 2x=4, x=2.
So, Ali is 2 years old today.
Let's do another problem.
And that makes sense, cuz if he is 2 today, in 4 years he is going to be 6,
which is going to be 3 times as old as he is today.
So, it all that works out.
Let's do another problem. Let's clear this
and I am going to attempt to type, hope I don't miss up, ok.
The problem is: Nazrat is 4 years older than Umiama.
2 years ago Nazrat was 5 times as old as Umaima.
How old is Nazrat today?
Ah,this one seems more difficult, I think we will be able to get trough it.
Let's figure it out.
All right, so once again what are we trying to solve for? We're trying to solve for Nazrat today.
So, let's say this is Nazrat, we'll say Naz for short,
and let's say this is Umaima and this is today,
(I'm making a little chart)
and let's say 4 years from now, 4 ...
oh no no no not 4 years from now, I'm confusing myself,
This would be 2 years ago.
I'm still remembering the last problem,
2 years ago, ok, so this is today, 2 years in the future, let me make a little chart
It's not the cleanest chart, but I think it will do the job.
Ok, so we're trying to solve for x, How old is Nazrat today?
So, let's just say Naz today that is equal to x.
It says Nazrat is 4 years older than Umaima.
So this piece of information up here, let me underline it;
Nazrat is 4 years older than Umaima.
Well that piece of information tells us that Umaima today,
if Nazrat is x , then Umaima is going to be x - 4.
Which makes sense because Naz is 4 years older than Umaima.
Now we go into the past. Let's write, let's look at this.
So 2 years ago: so, if Naz is x today, how old was she 2 years ago?
Well, she was going to be x minus 2.
That makes sense, if I'm 10 years old today,
2 years ago I'll be 2 years less, I would be 8 years old.
So, if she is x today, two years ago she was x - 2.
And, if Umaima is x - 4 today,
then 2 years ago she'll be 2 less than that.
She'll be x - 4 - 2 and that equals x - 6.
Which makes sense and
notice that she is still 4 years younger than Naz or Nazrat.
Now, we have one final piece of information in this problem:
It says 2 years ago Nazrat was 5 times as old as Umaima.
so in this situation 2 years ago that's what the sentence says; 2 years ago Nazrat was 5 times as old as Umaima so
Nazrat which x belonges to was 5 times older than Umaima which is x minus 6 so let just right it down so Nazrat 2 years
ago was x minus 2 we get that from the chart; Nazrat was x minus 2, two years ago and that says that Nazrat was
5 times older than Umaima was 2 years ago, then Umaima was 2 years ago was x minus 6, well now we'll just solve for x
x minus 2 is equal to 5 x minus 30, now we can subtract x from both sides and we get 4x and I switch it around 2
hopefully confuse you more, 4x minus 30 equals minus 2 and then we get 4x is equal to 28 and x is equal to 7
so we solved the problem; Nazrat today is 7 years old. Is that makes sense? Well if Nazrat today is 7 years old
And then does it make sense? Umaima today is going to be 3 years old and that makes sense cause there are 4 years different
Two years ago Nazrat was 5 years old and 2 years ago Umaima was only 1 year old.
Right? Cause x minus 6. So it makes sense.
Narat is 4 years older than Umaima. Nazrat is 7, Umaima is 3 right now.
And 2 years ago Nazrat was 5 times older tham Umaima
2 years ago Nazrat was 5 and Umaima was 1.
So, it all works out. Pretty neat, no?
On the way I think you are ready to at least try some of these age problems.
And I'm gonna do some more example promlems so you can come back to the this video page
and see more if you're a little bit confused.
Have fun!