[music]
Dr. Steven Zucker: We're in the Gemäldegalerie in Berlin
looking at a really spectacular panel painting by Giotto
this is The Entombment of Mary
--and it shows the Virgin Mary tenderly being lowered into her tomb
but it also simultaneously shows her spirit rendered as an infant being cradled by Christ in heaven
Dr. Harris: It was made for the Church of Ognissanti--or All Saints Church--in Florence
--and it's certainly one of the jewels of their collection
Dr. Zucker: It's a wonderful representation of the qualities that made Giotto
such an important artist in the early 14th century
Dr. Harris: In the late 1200s--the traditional that Giotto was coming out of is the Byzantine tradition
--where the figures are elongated--where there is an emphasis of gold and patterning
--where the figures seem very distant from us
and there's no real interest in their bodies as existing three-dimensionally in space
--but that's exactly what Giotto gives us
Dr. Zucker: The figures have a sense of volume--of mass--of solidity--of gravity
--but more than that--you've got a kind of psychological intensity
and interaction that makes these figures seem as if they are autonomous in the world
Dr. Harris: So let's take for example--St. Peter--whose engrossed in reading
and if we look at the robe that he wears we can that Giotto has moved from light to dark
to indicate the folds of the drapery
and a sense of the figure being round and three-dimensional
Dr. Zucker: You can see the way in which the figure's elbow is pressing into his waist
--gathering that cloth--creating those folds
--and there is really a sense then of the reality of that moment
--something we recognize as our own elbows have pressed into our sides
Dr. Harris: Look at how gently she's being lowered into the tomb
--and the look on the face of the apostle who lowers her body
--looking into her eyes so lovingly
Dr. Zucker: The intimacy between them can be seen again
between the spirit of Mary in the body of the child and Christ
--their faces are close--they look at each other
Dr. Harris: And it's also a kind of inversion
of the image of Mary and Christ that we usually see
where Mary is shown holding Christ as a child
Dr. Zucker: And look at the way that the representation of Mary's soul--the infant
--has it's light drapery swirled around it
--it's just a beautiful kind of tender rendering by the artist
--just to the right of Christ you see a figure bending over slightly
--that's St. Andrew whose sprinkling holy water on the dead body of Christ's mother
--but perhaps my favorite figure is just to the right of that
--you can see in back of the angels who are holding tall candles
--there's a figure in a kind of yellow white gold--his cheeks are puffed out
--and if you look closely--in his right hand he's holding high a censer
--that is he is distributing incense and it seems as if he is trying to blow it towards Mary
Dr. Harris: Just to the right another angel has its mouth open
--as though she is speaking and two angels just to the right of that seem to be engaged in conversation
--so while this image is very formal and hierarchical
--with Christ in the center--larger than all the figures
--it's at the same time informal and natural
Dr. Zucker: That sense of the natural comes across so well
in the conversation between those angels
--the angel who stands in front--look at the way in which
the thumbs of that angel are hooked into belt--into its pockets
--there is this sort of wonderful sense of total informality there
Dr. Harris: In fact that angel also looks like she is about to speak
Dr. Zucker: This is a painting about Mary leaving the physical realm and becoming spirital
--but it's this kind of intimacy--this kind of detail of individual actions
through which Giotto creates this fabulous sense of reality
[music]