Let's take the number 7 and divide it by 3.
And I'm going to conceptualize dividing by 3 as let me see how many groups of 3 I can make out of the 7.
So let's imagine... Let me draw 7 things.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.
So let me try to create groups of 3.
So I can definitely create one group of 3 right over here,
I can definitely create another group of 3.
So I'm able to create two groups of 3 and then I can't create any more full groups of 3.
I have essentially this thing right over here left over.
So this right over here... I have this thing remaining.
This right over here is my remainder.
After creating as many groups of 3 as I can.
And so when you see something like this, people will often say:
Seven divided by three... Well, I can create two groups of 3,
but it doesn't divide evenly. Or 3 doesn't divide evenly into 7.
I end up with something left over. I have a leftover, I have a remainder.
I have a remainder of 1.
So this is literally saying: 7 divided by 3 is 2, remainder 1.
And that makes sense!
2 times 3 is 6, so it doesn't get you all the way to 7,
but then if you have your extra remainder, 6 plus that 1 remainder gets all the way to 7.
Let's do another one.
Let's imagine 15 divided by 4.
Let me draw 15 objects:
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15.
Now let me try to divide it into groups of 4.
So let's see... That's one group of 4, that's another group of 4 and then that's another group of 4.
So I'm able to create three groups of 4, but I can't create a fourth full group of 4.
I am then left with this remainder right over here.
I have a remainder right over here of 3.
I have 3 left over.
So we could say that 15 divided by 4 is 3, remainder 3.
4 goes into 15 three times, but that only gets us to 12.
4 times 3 is 12.
To get all way to 15 we need to use our remainder, we need to get 3 more.
So 15 divided by 4, I have 3 left over.
Now let's try to think about this doing a little bit of our long division techniques.
So let's say that I want to divide 75 by 4.
Well, traditional long division techniques:
4 goes into 7 one time.
And we're really... if you're looking at place value we're really saying that 4 is going into 70 ten times
(because we're putting this in the tens place)
and then we say: 1 times 4 is 4.
But really, once again, it's in the tens place. This is really representing a 40.
But either way, we subtract 4 from the 7, we get a 30 and then we bring down this 5.
And you say: 4 goes into 35 (let's see... 4 times 8 is 32, 4 times 9 is 36, that's too big) 8 times.
8 times 4 is 32, you subtract 35 minus 32 is 3.
And 4 doesn't go into 3 any more.
So here I have this 3 left over. I have a remainder of 3.
So you could say that 75 divided by 4 is equal to 18, remainder 3.