In this video, we're going to look at how to draw a dot structure,
which has a simple organic molecule,
which has single bonds.
So, if I look at the molecular formula,
CH4, which is methane.
I want to draw a dot structure for the methane molecule.
I will go over here to my organic periodic table,
and find carbon,
and I can see carbon is in Group 4.
Therefore, carbon will have four valence electrons.
So, I can draw a carbon with its four valence electrons
around it like that.
Remember from general chemistry,
valence electrons are the electrons
on the outer-most energy level.
So, carbon has four valence electrons
in its outer-most energy level.
Next, I have to think about hydrogen,
and hydrogen is in Group 1 on the Periodic Table.
Therefore, hydrogen will have one valence electron.
So, I can go ahead and put the hydrogen in there
with one valence electron.
I know I have to do that three more times.
So, I keep putting the hydrogens
each with one valence electron.
So, the total of four hydrogens.
And now, I can start connecting my dots.
I know that two valence electrons equal to one single covalent bond.
So, there is a single covalent bond.
There is a single covalent bond.
And then, I have two more here.
So, this is my complete dot structure for methane.
Now, I can see the carbon is surrounded by
eight electrons here.
So, we can go ahead and highlight those.
So, if I count on the electrons around the carbons,
it would be two, four,
six and eight like that.
And eight electrons around the carbon
makes carbon very stable.
And if we look at the Periodic Table,
we can see why.
So, if i look at the second period,
I can see that
the valence electron of the carbon
would be one,
two,
three and four,
and to get eight electrons,
we will go to five, six, seven, eight.
so, if carbon is surrounded by eight electrons,
it's likely to have the electron configuration of noble gas,
which makes it very stable, because all the orbitals in the energy level on are full.
so, octetable electrons is the maximum number of electrons for the carbon.
if we look at the hydrogen, we can see each hydrogen is surrounded by two electrons.
so if i find the hydrogen here, the hydrogen is in the first energy level,
so here is one electron, and here is two electrons
so on the first energy level, there is only an s-orbital, and so
that orbital holds maximum two electrons and we get to the electron
configuration of the noble gas,
and so hydrogen is stable with having only two electrons around it.
let's look at another dot structure,
and let's do one tha has a nitrogen in it.
so if i look at the molecular formula, CH3-NH2,
i'm going to once again start with the carbon in the center,
with its four valence electrons around it like that.
and i know that three hydrogens on the carbon
so i can go ahead and put three hydrogens
each hydrogen has one valence electron, like that.
and on the right side, i'm going to think about the nitrogen.
i need to find the nitrogen in my periodic table.
nitrogen is in Group 5.
Therefore, nitrogen has five valence electrons.
so i can represent the electron as one, two, three, four and five, like that.
and i still have two hydrogens to worry about, right?
so i still have two hydrogens here.
and i can see the place for them on the nitrogen.
so i can go ahead and put a hydrogen in here,
and a hydrogen in here,
and connect the dots,
and i have my dot structure.
and i can also check my octet rule,
so carbon has an octet,
and nitrogen has an actet as well,
so let's go ahead and verify that.
so there is two electrons here,
four, six, and eight.
so nitrogen is in the second period,
so nitrogen is also going to follow the octet rule, when you draw dot structures.
let's do one more.
oxygen, next.
so if i want to draw a dot structure, for methanol,
methanol is CH3OH.
so once again, i'll start carbon, with four valence electrons,
and i have three hydrogens, each one with one valence electron like that
so i can go ahead and put those three hydrogens
next i have oxygen
so i need to find the oxygen in my organic periodic table
and i can see that oxygen is in group 6 right here
so oxygen has six valence electrons around it
so i can go ahead and draw in oxygen
and i can put its six valence electrons in
one, two, three,
four, five and six like that
and then i'm going to put in the hydrogen right?
so i know now i have a hydrogen to worry about
and i know hydrogen has one valence electron,
so i can see there is a place for over here
and once again i can connect the dots
and see all of the single covalent bonds in this molecule.
so that's one bond, that's another bond,
now i can see that carbon is bonded to oxygen,
and oxygen is bonded to this hydrogen as well
again we can check our octet rule
so, the carbon has eight electrons around it
so is the oxygen
this will be two right here
and then four, and then six, and then eight
so the oxygen is following the octet rule
now when you are drawing a dot structure,
you don't always have to do this stuff where you are drawing each individual atom,
and summing all the valence electron in that way
you can just start drawing it
so for example, if i gave you C2H6, which is ethyne
another way to do it is we just do
we'd just be started drawing the bonds here
so i have two carbons,
and there is a pretty good bet that the two carbons are connected to each other
and i have six hydrogens
and if i look at what's possible around those carbons,
i could put those six hydrogens around those two carbon atoms like that
and if i do that, i will have octet around each carbon atom
so this would be my dot structure for ethyne.
to double-check yourself, you could make sure that your dot structure has the correct number of valence electrons
so if i'm thinking about each carbon,
each carbon having four valence electrons,
and i have two of them,
i'm going to get eight valence electrons from those two carbons
that i have to represent in my dot structure
each hydrogen has one valence electron
and i have six of them
so i need to worry about six valence electron of hydrogens
so the total of 14
so i'm look at my dot strcuture
i can check to make sure i have the correct number of valence electrons
i need 14, so let's go ahead and count them
so this will be two here,
four, six, eight, ten, twelve and fourteen
so i have the correct number of valence electrons
represented in my dot structure
i also have an octet of electrons
around my carbons
so this would be the dot structure for ethane