Are line segment AB
and line segment CD congruent?
So let's look at these right over QQ
AB is this line segment right over here.
And CD is this one right over here.
AB has length of 1.
It goes from 2 to 3.
And CD has length of 1.
It goes from 4 to 5.
So they they have the exact same length.
These are just line segments
with the exact same length.
So yes, they are congruent.
Yes.
Let's do a couple more.
Are a AB and CD congruent?
So AB –
And you can just eyeball this.
AB is much longer the CD.
AB is of length 4.
it goes from -5 to -1.
CD is only of length 1.
It goes from 1 to 2..
So no. They are not congruent..
They have different lengths.
Let's do one more.
Are AB and CD congruent?
Let's see. AB has length 2.
It goes from -1 to 1.
CD is of length 3.
So they're not congruent. No.