We are on problem number 19.
If a, b, c, and f are four non-zero numbers--
I don't know where they got f.
I would have expected a d--
but a, b, c, and f are four non-zero numbers,
then all of the following proportions
are equivalent except-- OK. So this is interesting.
This is one where you have to work through all of them.
So choice a, a/f is equal to b/c.
Let's see, choice b says f/c is equal to b/a.
So the real simple way of doing this,
let's cross multiply all of them, essentially, right?
So we can cross multiply.
If we multiply both sides by,essentially, fc--
and that's what cross multiplying is--
so we said a times c, ac is equal to bf, right?
a times c is equal to b times f.
And you can get there multiplying both sides by f
and multiplying both sides by c.
If we cross multiply on this side, we have af is equal to bc.
This is an f here. ac is equal to bf.
Here we have af is equal to bc.
Let's see, choice c is c/a is equal to f/b.
What does this tell us?
This tells us that cb or bc, bc is equal to af.
So these two are equal.
These two are the same thing, right?
In d, we have a/c is equal to b/f.
Now if we cross multiply, you get af is equal to bc.
These are equal. I think you see a pattern.
I suspect that e is going to look very similar to these three
and that this is the different one.
But just to do it,I'll show you.
Choice e has af/bc is equal to 1, essentially.
So that's af is equal to bc,
which is the same thing as all these.
So a is the one choice that is different.
ac is equal to bf is very different than
af is equal to bc, right?
We're multiplying different things.
These are all the same. Hopefully you see that.
And that's multiplication is communicative and all that.
So it doesn't matter what order,
fa and af are the same thing.
But here, we're multiplying.
It was saying ac is equal to bf.
Let's do problem number 20.
And you could actually, in that last problem,
literally try it with four different non-zero numbers.
It actually should work out, if you pick good numbers,
if you don't want to deal with the abstract letters.
Problem number 20.
For all numbers x and y,
let the operation square be defined as
x square y is equal to xy minus y.
If a and b are positive integers,
which of the following can be equal to 0?
So a, b positive integers.
So which can be equal to 0?
So they're saying choice number one is a square b.
And that, we learned from here,
is the same thing as a times b, right?
It's just pattern matching,wherever you see the x,
you put an a. Wherever you see the y, you put a b.
So that's ab minus y. Sorry, ab minus b, right?
And can I come up with a situation
where this comes out to be 0?
Well sure. If a is 1, what happens when a is 1?
If a is 1, then this translates to b minus b,
which equals 0, right?
And why did I think what happens when a is 1?
Well,this could also be written as a minus 1 times b,right?
If you just factored out the b's.
So I said well, if a is 1,then this term becomes 0.
So 1, this definitely can be equal to 0.
It's not always 0, but it can be, especially if a is 1.
OK, let's do choice two.
They wrote a plus b square b. And what is that equal to?
Well, every time you saw an x,replace it with a plus b.
Every time you see a y,replace it with b.
So that's equal to-- that equals--
I'll switch colors for variety,
just so you don't get confused with this top part--
that's equal to a plus b times b--
times the second term,
times b-- minus the second term, minus b.
So we can't do what we did the previous time,
because now the term a plus b can't equal 1, right?
There's no circumstance under a plus b equals 1. How?
Because they're both positive,they're both integers, right?
So in order for this to equal 1,one would have to be 1,
and one would have to be 0.
And neither of them can be negative.
So this can't equal 1.
So that's not a situation in which this is equal to 0.
So let's see if we can solve it.
What's that equal to 0?
And of course, b can't be equal to 0.
So we see a plus b. We could factor it out.
We could say a plus b minus 1 times b is equal to 0, right?
We know b can't equal 0 under any circumstances, right?
We know b can't equal 0,
because we're saying it's a positive integer.
And so this term would have to be equal to 0.
You could multiply this out and you'll see where I got--
I just factored out just the same.
I divided each of these terms by b and factored it out.
And then you're left with a plus b minus 1,
all of that times b.
So if b can't equal 0, can a plus b minus 1 equal 0?
Well a plus b minus 1 equals 0.
Then a plus b would have to equal 1, which I said,
it just can't happen.
So under no circumstances can choice two be equal to 0.
And now, what does choice three say?
Choice three is a square a plus b.
And if we map it, that's a times a plus b minus a plus b.
And now here, once again, we can factor out the a plus b.
So we could write this as a minus 1 times a plus b.
And we want to see if that equals 0,see if this is possible.
Well for this to be equal to 0,
either this term would have to be 0,
or this term, or both of them, really.
Can a plus b equal 0?
No, because a is positive,b is positive,
they're both integers. Nothing's negative.
They have to be greater than 0,
so there's no way that this is going to be equal to 0.
But can a minus one equal 0?
Well sure, a could be 1.
If a is 1, then this expression becomes 0.
So this one also works. So our choices--
the ones that could be 0-- are one and three.
And that is choice E.
I'll see you in the next section.