Solve and eliminate any extraneous solutions. What they mean by extraneous solutions are:
in the course of solving this rational equation right here we might get some solutions that if we actually
put it in the original problem would give us undefined expressions and so those solutions
are extraneous solutions, they actually don't apply, so you want to throw them out.
So let's look at this equation. We have x^2 over x+2 = 4 over x + 2
So right from the get go, we don't know if this is necessarily going to be a solution to this equation
but we know just looking at this that if x is equal to -2, then this denominator
and this denominator are going to be zero and if you're dividing by zero it will be undefined.
So right from the get go we can exclude x = -2, so x cannot be equal to -2 because that
would make either of these expressions undefined on either side of the equation.
So with that out of the way, let's try to solve it. So the first step, let's try to get the x out of
the denominator so let's multiply both sides by x+2.
x+2 divided by x+2 is 1 and we can assume x+2 isn't zero, so it will be defined
x+2 divided by x+2 is just 1 so our equation has simplified to
x^2 = 4
So, subtract 4 from both sides. Do it in the proper quadratic equation form.
So, x^2 - 4 = 0
I just subtracted 4 from both sides over here
and so you can factor this because this is a difference of squares, so you get
(x+2) * (x-2) = 0 and if the product of two things is zero then that means that either one or
both of them is equal to zero
So this tells us that x+2 = 0 or x-2 = 0
If you subtract 2 from both sides of this equation right here you get x = -2 and if you add
2 to both sides of this equation here you get x = 2
and we're saying that either of these would make this last expression zero.
Now, we know that we would exclude one of them. We know that x cannot be equal to -2. So x = -2 is an
extraneous solution. It is a solution for this, once we got rid of the natural expressions,
but it's not a solution for this original problem up here
because it would make the expressions undefined, it would cause you to divide by zero.
So, the only solution here is x=2 and you can check it yourself.
If you do 2^2 you get 4 over 2+2 is 4 and that should be equal to 4 over 2+2
which it definitely is: 1 is equal to 1.