What I've done here is list a bunch of events that might occur in a given period
And what I'm going to think about in this video is how if at all
they might be accounted for in GDP, especially in this expenditure view of GDP
I encourage you to pause this video and try it out yourself
to see how each of these events happen in a period for which we're trying
to calculate the GDP what how they will be accounted for
according to the buckets we've talked about, the compositions of the expenditure view of GDP
so now I'm assuming that you've unfold try
so let's try to go through it. Kahn academy is
Kahn Academy is A-frm it's not for profit firm, none really owns Kahn Academy, it goes to society
society owns Kahn Academy, but it is a firm. So Kahn Academy employs
a software engeneers and pays them a 100,000 USD
well this is A-firm making the expenditure and arguably
in even conceptually this also is an investment because it's
100,000 USD is going to be used to develop called as future benefit
so this is going to be the investment category
mark it with the same colours so I - i
"I" - investment is going to get plus 100,000 USD
in general the spending by firm goes into investment, now look at the second scenery
Accenture which is another firm this is A-for profit firm
earns 10 M USD we'll just say it's 10 M USD in revenue
10 M in revenue just to be clear what are we talking about
gets 10 M in revenue by building a new
IT system for California. An importand thing about
this is OK Acceture is a firm, but California is clearly the government
is clearly the government, so how do you account for this?
the expenditure view of GDP so in this situation
California is spending 10 M USD
10 M USD in a period for a new IT system
so this is going to be government. The goverment cathegory
is going to increased by 10 M because of this expenditure
Now next one:
my mother sells our house in a New Orleans to a Swedish woman
for 200 thousand USD once againg: our house is being sold
from someone in the country to someone who is foreign what we do
but an important thing to realise is that this is not a new house, this is a transfer of
of an existing house, nothing was produced here, so
this has no contribution. this has no contribution to GDP
doesn't matter that this is a Swedish woman or anything like that the house has existed before and just changed hands
a new house do not get produced so nothing happpens to GDP
here. next one: I and
I'm assuming that i'm here sitting here California American citizen I buy a Japanese
made lawnmover for 200 USD. Now that one is interesting
this one is interesting because if you think about theoretically nothing
was produced in US so nothing should be add
to GDP on net-net basis and so we'll see that's actually the case
but it's going to show up by adding to consumption and taking away from
that exports, so two things are going to happen here we'll say OK Sal in an American consumer
if we just looked how much more he spent he spent
200 USD more so it's going to be added there but we're going to take it out
of net exports so
net exports we'll do it at the same green colour
net exports - everything else is neutral so
in this thing right over here there is no foreign purchases but there is me buying a foreing product
at let me subtract it out so i'm going to subtract it out
200 USD right over there so net exports will be lower
by 200 USD and that
it was essentially this was a 200 USD's import and that completelly cancels out 200 USD increase in consumption
and so this will have zero net effect on GDP
this two term will cancel out. now I buy a new home in California
for 500,000 USD
now household spending for the most part is considered C except
when you're buing a new home so even
though that I'm not a firm because I'm buying a house
a new house this will go into investment so
investment will go up by 500,000 USD and than
finally American Airlines buys a new airbus-jet
airbus jet are made in Europe so what is going to happen here
so once again: net-net nothing was produced in the US
US so on a net base that shoud not contribute to GDP
and we''ll see that on net basis it will break out will be neutral but it will be like
this situation: there is an American firm that make A-purchase
actually I'm going to put it out here so let's say there is a 100 M USD
I think i buy
for 100 M USD so the way it is accounted for investment
would go up by 100 M USD you have an American
firm making a purchase 100 M USD is going to
also provide future goods and services
your transportation to people it's going to be netted out because
you have in net import so this
it's going to do a net export on this side of it
100 M USD because it was an import negative
taken from an export point of view and you have no corresponding
posivitve export so you're going to have net exports
net exports is going to go down 100 M USD
this was A- net import of a hundred M so it makes sense that net exports will go down
will be negative net export and these two once againg
are going to cancel out with other so you have no net GDP
which makes sense because this plane was not produced in the US.