Welcome back. I keep rushing to try to get under the wire
for these problems, but let me explain it properly.
So what we did is, we said that a new student joins.
And the average after he joins is equal to the median.
And what we did is we figured out,
what's the average and the median before the student joins.
Well, the average before the student joined was 13/12,
and the median before the student joined was 1.
If the new student has 1 or 0--and we established that
the only way to bring this average down
is for the new student to have
less than the average number of siblings, right?
That's the only way we can go from 1 1/12 to 1.
And I'll tell you right now that
he's actually going to have a 1/13 impact, right,
if he's 1 away.
So actually I can tell you right now he has one sibling,
but I'll show it to you mathematically
if you don't have that intuition on averages.
But the important thing to realize
is that he's either going to have 0 or 1 sibling.
He's going to have to have less than 1 1/12 siblings,
so it's either 0 or 1 in order to bring the average down.
And regardless of whether he has 0 or 1 sibling,
the median won't change.
If he has one sibling,
then we're just going to have another one here
and then this'll become the median.
If he has 0 siblings, then that's going to be a 0 there,
but that's still going to be a median of 1.
The median is not going to change.
So what we have to do is to figure out
how many siblings does he have to have
for the new average to be exactly 1?
So we can go back to this calculation.
Let's take the average, but now let's take it with him.
So this was our previous average where we said well,
there's three students with 0 siblings,
six students with 1, et cetera, et cetera.
But now we're going to add this new student in.
There's one student with x siblings, right?
And instead of 12 in the denominator, we have 13.
Because we now have 13 students, right?
So what happens? You essentially have 13,
so this becomes x plus 6 plus 4 plus 3.
This becomes 13 plus x,
and then the denominator is equal to 13.
And actually I was wrong before,
he's actually going to have to have 0,
my intuition was a little bit off.
Because look, this is the new average, 13 plus x over 13.
The new average is going to be 13 plus x over 13, right?
13 plus x over 13.
And what does that new average have to equal?
It has to equal 1.
Because that's the new median.
Or the old median, because we said the mean doesn't change.
So how can 13 plus x over 13 equal 1?
Well, if you can't eyeball that,you can just say 13 plus x,
multiply both sides by 13, is equal to 13.
And then subtract 13 from both sides
and you get x is equal to 0.
So that new student has 0 siblings.
I know that was a little bit convoluted,
so let me just tell you what I did again.
I said what is the current median?
And I just listed out all of the number of siblings,
and I took the middle number,and that was 1.
Then I said well, what is the current average?
And the current average was 1 1/12.
And this might confuse you a little bit.
You could just say, well this is the same thing as 0,
0 plus 0 plus 0 plus 1 plus 1 plus 1 plus 1 plus 1 plus 1
and so forth. Instead I said that's three students with 0,
six students with 1 sibling,
two students with 2 siblings, and so forth.
And I figured out that the current average--
and I divided by 12-- was 1 1/12.
So I said well,
no matter how many siblings the next student has--
and actually, it didn't even matter,
even if you had more or less,
one of the middle numbers still would have been the 1.
So the median will not change regardless of
where the new student falls into the mix.
So we said, how many siblings does that student need to have
for the average to come down back to 1?
And then I just added x to my previous average
and I divided by 13 instead
because we now have an extra student.
This was a 13 too.
And we got this equation:
13 plus x over 13 has to equal my new average, which is 1.
And then I solved for x, which is 0.
So the new student had 0 siblings.
Next problem.
And the really fast way of doing this--
not to harp on this problem too much,
and I should have done this from the beginning--
is to figure out that the median is 1,
then figure out that
it doesn't matter how many siblings the student has,
the median's still going to be 1.
You can insert a number anywhere in this list
and the median would have still been 1
because there's so many students with one sibling.
And then you just have to figure out,
well, how many siblings does the student have to have
for the average to become 1?
That's probably the most convoluted explanation I've given,
but let me just hope it helps you.
OK, problem number 9.
If 2 times x minus 3 is equal to 8,
what does x minus 3 over x plus 3 equal?
What does that equal?
Well, let's just solve for x.
So we get x minus 3
is equal to-- I'm just going to divide both sides by 2,
so 8 divided by 2 is 4, right?
2 divided by 2 is 1, so x minus 3 equals 4,
x is equal to 7. So you go here. What's x minus 3?
Well it's 7 minus 3, which is 4.
We also figured out that x minus 3 was 4 up here.
And then what's x plus 3?
That's 7 plus 3, so that's 10.
4/10, we can reduce that to 2/5,
dividing the numerator and the denominator by 2.
So that's our answer,2/5 or 0.4.
Problem 10.
When twice a number-- so whenever I start writing it,
let's say x is the number.
So they say when twice an number-- so when 2 times x,
that's twice a number-- is decreased by 3.
So, twice a number is decreased by 3, the result is 253.
What is the number? Well, while reading it, I set it up.
So now we just have to solve. So we add 3 to both sides.
2x is equal to 256, right? I added 3 to both sides.
x, divide both sides by 2. x is equal to 128.
And we are done.
Next problem. Problem 10.
OK, this says Outdoor Sneaker Company's July production.
So we have white, black,and then total.
And then they have high-tops,low-tops, and then total.
I don't know if people even wear high-tops anymore.
I used to. I guess for basketball.
OK, high-tops, low-tops,and total. I'm very not plugged-in.
High-tops, low-tops,and then total.
And what numbers do they have in the box?
So there are 3,600 here, 1,500 here, 5,500, and then 10,000.
So I could tell you they're just going to reading this question,
want us to fill in this diagram.
10,000 here.
Outdoor Sneaker Company manufactures only white
sneakers and black sneakers, both of which
are available as either high-tops or low-tops.
On the basis of the information in the table above,
how many black sneakers did Outdoor Sneaker Company
manufacture in July?
So how many black sneakers--
so they didn't differentiate with the high-tops or low-tops-
so they want to know, how many total black sneakers.
So that is black total.
So we need to figure out this square.
Total black. So let's see what we can figure out.
I'll do my figuring out in this magenta.
So if low-tops-- I need a total of 5,500 low-tops--
1,500 are black, how many are white?
Well, it's going to be 4,000,
right? I just took 5,500 minus 1,500. 4,000.
Similarly,
if I made a total of 10,000 sneakers and 5,500 are low-tops,
how many of them are high-tops?
Well, it's going to be 10,000 minus 5,500, so this is 4,500.
And out of the high-tops,
if 3,600 are white and I made a total of 4,500,
how many black are there?
Well, 4,500 total minus the white ones, that's what?
That's 900.
And so if we want to figure out the total black,
we now know how many high-top blacks there are
and how many low-top black sneakers there are,
so we just add. So 900 plus 1,500 is 2,400.
So I actually wasted both of our times figuring this out,
so I could have saved a few seconds I didn't do that.
But I was just mindlessly chugging along.
Anyway, I'll see you in the next video.