A vector is something that has both magnitude and
direction...magnitude...
and direction. So let's think of an example of what
wouldn't and what would be a vector.
So, if someone tells you that something is moving at
5 miles per hour. This information by itself is not a vector quantity.
It's only...It's only specifying a magnitude
We don't know what direction this thing is moving 5 miles per hour in.
So, this right over here, which is often referred to as a speed...
this is a speed...is not a vector quantity just by itself.
This is considered to be a scalar quantity.
If we want it to be a vector, we would also have to specify the direction.
So, for example, someone might say, "It's moving 5 miles
per hour, east." So, let's say it's moving 5 miles per hour
due east. So, now this combined, 5 miles per hour due east...
...this is a vector quantity and now we wouldn't call it speed anymore
we would call it velocity...So, velocity is a vector. We're specifying the magnitude 5 miles
per hour and the direction east. But how
can we actually visualize this? So, let's say we're operating
in two dimensions. And what's neat about linear algebra is obviously
a lot of what applies in two dimensions...we'll extend to three and then even four, five,
six...as many dimensions as we want...our brains have trouble visualizing beyond
three, but what's neat is we can mathematically deal with beyond three
using linear algebra...and we'll see that in
future videos.
But let's just go back to our straight, traditional two-dimensional vector
right over here. So, one way we could represent it as an
arrow that is 5 units long. We'll assume that each of our units
are unit here as mph. And that's pointed to
the right, where we'll say the right is east. So, for example
I could start and arrow right over here and I could make its length=5...the
length of the arrow specifies the magnitude. So, one...
two...three...four...five.
And then the direction that the arrow is pointed in, specifies
its direction. So, this right over here could
represent visually this vector. If we say that the horizontal axis is, say, east or that the positive
horizontal direction is moving in the east, this would be west, that would be north and then
that would be south. Now, what's interesting about vectors is that we only
care about the magnitude and the direction. We don't necessarily
care where we start...where we place it...when we thing of it visually like this.
So, for example, this would be the exact same vector, or would be equivalent vector
to this. This vector has the same length, so it has
the same magnitude...has a length of five. And its direction is also
due east. So, these two vectors are equivalent. Now, one thing
that you might say is, "Well, that's fair enough, but how do we represent it with a little bit more mathematical
notations. We don't have to draw it every time and we could start performing operations on it."
Well the typical way, 1.if you want a variable to represent a vector
is usually a lower case letter. If you have...if you're publishing a book,
you can bold it. But't when you're doing it in your notebook, you would typically put a little
arrow on top of it. And you usually...there're several ways that you could do it
You could say
'Hey, 5 miles per hour, east.' But that doesn't feel like you can really operate on
that easily. The typical way is to specify...if you're in two
dimensions...to specify two numbers that tell you how much is this
vector moving in each of these dimensions. So,
for example, this one only moves in the horizontal dimension and so, we'll put a
horizontal dimension first. So, you might call this vector:
(5,0). It's moving 5...positive 5
in the horizontal direction and it's not moving at all
in the vertical direction. And the notation might change. You might also see
notation and actually in a linear algebra context, it's more typical to write it as a
column vector like this. Five...Zero...
Once again, The first coordinate represents how much we're moving in the horizontal
direction and the second coordinate represents how
much are we moving in the
vertical direction. Now, this one isn't that interesting. You could have other
vectors. You can have a vector that looks like this...that's moving...let's say it's moving
3 in the horizontal direction and
+4...so...one, two, three, four...in
the vertical direction. So, let me see, it might look something like
this. So, this could be another
vector right over here. May be, we call this vector...
Vector A; and once I wanna specify that it is a vector
and you see here that if you were to break it down in its...
in the horizontal direction...it is moving
three or it's shifting
three in the horizontal direction and it's shifting four...positive four...
in the vertical direction. And we get that by literally thinking about
how much we're moving up and how much we're moving to the right when
we start at the end of the arrow(we start at the tail of the arrow and go towards its head) and go to the front of it
So, this vector might be specified as
(3,4)
And you could use the Pythagorean theorem to figure out the actual length of this
vector and you will see 'cause this is a 3-4-5 triangle, that this actually
has a magnitude of five. And as we study more
and more linear algebra, we're going to start extending these to multiple dimensions.
Obviously, we can visualize up to 3-dimensions...and four dimensions become more
abstract. And that's why this type of a notations is useful because it's very hard to draw
a 4, 5 or 20 dimensional arrow, like this.