Solve the equation and find excluded values
and when they are talking about finding excluded values
we need to think about what values would make these
either side of this equation undefined
and the reason why we wanna do that is because
as we manipulate this we might lose things in the denominator
and then we might get some answer,
but if it's one of those things that made the original..
..the original expressions on either side of the original equation
undefined, then that wouldn't be a legitimate solution,
so that's what they're talking about the excluded values
so what values do we have to exclude here right from the get go?
Well, 4 over p - 1,
won't be defined if p is 1, because if p is 1
then you're gonna be dividing by 0, and that's undefined.
so we know that p cannot be equal to 1
and over here, if p is -3,
then this denominator would be 0
and it would be undefined
and so p cannot be equal to 1, or -3
So these right here are our excluded values.
so now let's try to solve..
..let's try to solve this equation.
and I'm gonna rewrite it over here,
so if 4 over p - 1 is equal to
5 over p + 3
So the first thing we can do, especially because
we can assume now, that neither
of these expressions are 0, and this is going
to be defined, since we've excluded these values of p
is, to get the p - 1 out of the denominator
we can multiply the left-hand side by
p - 1, but remember, this is an equation
if you want them to continue to be equal,
anything you do to the left-hand side,
you have to do to the right-hand side.
so I'm multiplying by p - 1.
Now I also wanna get this p + 3 out of
the denominator here on the right-hand side
so the best way to do that is multiply
the right hand side by p + 3
but if I do that to the right-hand side,
I also have to do that to the left-hand side
p...p + 3
and so what happens, we have a
p - 1 in the numerator, p - 1 in the denominator
these cancel out
so you have just a 1 in the denominator
or you have no denominator anymore
and the left-hand side simplifies to 4 times (p + 3)
or, if you were to distribute the 4
4 times (p +3)
so that is 4p + 12
and in the right-hand side, you have a
p + 3 cancelling with a p + 3, this is
p + 3 divided by p + 3,
and all you're left with is 5 times (p - 1)
if you distribute the 5, you get
5p - 5
and now this is a pretty straightforward
linear equation to solve, we just wanna
isolate the p's on one side and the constants on the other
so let's subtract 5p from both sides-- I'll switch colors--
so let's subtract 5p from both sides
and we get, on the left-hand side
4p - 5p is negative p
plus 12, is equal to
these cancel out, is equal to -5
and then we can subtract 12 from both sides
..subtract 12 from both sides, and we get
these cancel out, we get -p is equal to
negative 5 minus 12 is negative 17
and we're almost done, we can multiply both sides
by negative 1, or divide both sides by negative 1
depending on how you wanna view it,
and we get, -1 times -p is..
..so let me scroll down a little bit so
I have a little bit of real state
and that is positive p is equal to
17.
p is equal to 17.
And let's verify that this really works
so it wasn't one of our excluded values, but just in case
let's verify that it really works.
If we go.. if we have p = 17 we get
4 over 17 - 1
needs to be equal to 5 over 17 + 3
I'm just putting 17 in for p
because that's our solution!
so this is the same things as 4 over 16
needs to be the same things as 5 over 20
or 4/16 is the same things as 1/4
and that needs to be the same thing as 5/20
which is the same thing as 1/4
so it all checks out.
So these are our excluded values and lucky for us
this wasn't one of 'em.