We're told that Jared is twice the age of his brother, Peter.
So, Jared is twice the age of his brother, Peter. Peter is four years old.
Peter is four years old, and Jared is twice the age of his brother, Peter.
So, Jared is twice Peter's age of four.
And then they tell us Talia's age is 3 times Jared's age.
How old are Talia and Jared?
So Talia's age is 3 times Jared's age.
So let's write this down. We have Peter is four years old.
So Peter- Peter's age- Peter's age,he's four years old.
Jared is twice the age of his brother, Peter.
So Jared-Let me do that in yellow-So Jared- That's not yellow.
Jared- Jared is twice the age of his brother.
So twice- twice is the same thing as two times, two times the age of his brother.
We could-though- You could say Jared is twice the age of his brother.
Or Jared is two times the age of his brother.
Well, his brother is four;they told us that right over there.
So Jared is going to be two times four years old.
Two times four years old and if you know your multiplication tables,
You know that's the same thing as eight. Two times four is eight.
Four times two is eight or you know this is the same thing as Peter's age twice.
Which is the same thing as four plus four. That would also get you eight.
So this would give you- so Jared's age is equal to eight.
And then finally they say Talia's age- let me write Talia's- Talia
right over here. Talia's age and they say it- they tell it to us right over here.
It's three times Jared's age. So Talia's age is three times Jared's age.
Well we were able to figure out Jared's age. it is eight.
It is three times Jared's age.
If you know your multiplication tables this should maybe jump out at you.
And your multiplication tables really are one of those things in mathmatics
That you should just, just really just know back and forth,
Just because it will make the rest of your life very, very, very simple,
But or you could do three times eight as literally eight three times.
So it's eight plus eight plus eight. Eight plus eight is sixteen.
Sixteen plus eight is twenty-four. So three times eight is twenty-four.
So Peter is four, Jared is eight, and Talia is twenty-four.