Let's think about what fraction of this grid is shaded in pink.
So the first thing we wanna thing about is how many equal sections do we have here.
Well this is 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 by 1, 2, 3 grid. So there's 15 sections in here.
You can also count it 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15. So they are 15 equal sections here.
And how many of those equal sections are actually shaded in this kind of pinkish colour?
We have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. So it's 6 fifteens shaded in.
But I wanna simplify this more. I have a feeling that there is an equivalent fractions that represent the exact same thing as 6/15.
And to get the sense of that. Let me redraw this a little bit where I still shade in 6 of this rectangles but I shade them little bit in one chunk.
So let me draw it in another grid right over here. And let me attempt to shade in the rectangles as fast as possible.
So that is 1 - one rectangle. We can make mine even bigger.
Alright, 2 rectangles.
3 rectangles. Half way there.
4 rectangles.
5 rectangles shaded in.
And now six rectangles shaded in.
So this right over here, what I just did, this is 6 rectangles of the 15 rectangles are shaded in.
So this is still 6/15. This represents the same thing.
But how can I simplify this even more?
Well, when you look at it numerically you see that both 6 and 15 are divisible by 3.
In fact, the greatest common factor is 3.
So what happens if we divide the numerator and the denominator by 3?
If we do the same thing to numerator and denominator we're not going to be changing the value of fraction.
So let's divide the numerator by 3 and divide the denominator by 3.
And what do we get? We get 2 over 5.
And how does this makes sense in the contex of this diagram right here?
Well, here we started off with 6 shaded in divided by 3 is 2 shaded in.
So it's actually saying "Hey, let's group these into the sections of 3". So let's say that this is...
This right over here is 1 section of 3. So that's one section of 3. And then this is another section of 3 right over here.
And so you have 2 sections of three (and actually let me colour it a little bit better).
So you have 2 sections of three and If you were combining them it looked just like this.
Notice, it is covering exact same are as your six smaller ones did. And how many equal sections of this size do you have on this entire thing?
Well, you have 5 equal sections. Let me show, cause this is one section of 3 - right over here.This is another section of 3 and this is another section of 3.
So notice you are covering the exact same area of the original thing. You are covering 2 out of 5 equal sections.
So 2 fifths (2/5) and 6 fifteens (6/15) are equivalent fractions.
If you wanna say what fraction of this is covered in the simplest form you would say 2 fifhts (2/5)