The body has a really really cool way
of controlling blood pressure.
You'll hear about this RAAS-system.
RAAS stands for Renin Angiotensin Aldosterone System.
Let's go through this RAAS-system,
kind of like an overview.
Just looking at where things start from
and where things go in terms of cells and hormones.
Those are the two things I want to distinguish between.
This RAAS-system begins with a set of cells.
I'm gonna draw all of my cells as little blue houses, like that.
The hormones they release are gonna be
orange messengers.
I'm gonna draw a little messenger,
this will be a little person.
The person is the hormone
and the blue house is the cell.
The key cell in the RAAS-system is the juxtaglomerular cell.
The JG cell.
These JG cells are actually in the kidney,
but in a specific location, in the blood vessels.
If you look closely, these JG cells are nothing more
than very special smooth muscle cells.
If you look in the blood vessels,
they're actually just like smooth muscle cells.
I'm gonna write smooth muscle,
just to remind you where they are.
Of course these are in the kidney.
It may not look like a kidney,
but that's what it's supposed to be.
The JG cells are releasing a hormone called renin.
When would they do that?
Renin is gonna help us raise blood pressure.
If the juxtaglomerular cells, these little guys,
notice the blood pressure is low,
that would be a trigger for releasing renin.
That's the first trigger, low blood pressure.
That's not the only trigger,
there are actually 3 triggers.
Let me write down 2 and 3.
Let's go through what they are.
The second trigger is a neighboring cell is actually
a sympathetic nerve cell.
We know that sympathetic nerve cells,
they fire whenever something big is going on.
For example you're running away from a bear,
or let's say you're trying to win a fight,
or let's say you're in a car accident and you start bleeding.
Any sort of major stressor is gonna cause
these nerve cells to start firing.
When they fire, that JG cell starts releasing renin.
So the second trigger would be the sympathetics.
The sympathetics, or maybe sympathetic nerves.
If these are your neighboring cells, these little sympathetic nerve cells, because they end right on the JG cells.
Then a little ways away, still in the kidney of course,
not touching the JG cells, would be the macula densa cells.
Stay with me for this,
these macula densa cells are also in the kidney
and actually they're specifically in the distal tubule of the nephron, so remember the distal convoluted tubule.
They're there, their interesting ability
is the ability to sense sodium.
When you have low blood pressure,
not a lot of blood is moving through that glomerulus.
Not a lot of blood is moving through the nephron as a result.
A lot of the salt is being reabsorbed.
So by the time it gets to the distal convoluted tubule,
the macula densa cells, they're kind of tasting or sensing the fluid that goes by
and they say 'There's not a lot of salt here.'
They put 2 and 2 together and realize that the reason there's not a lot of salt, is that the blood pressure is low.
So when they don't sense much salt,
they say 'Hey, JG cells, wake up!'
'Do something about this, raise blood pressure for us.'
They send a message over in the form of prostaglandins.
Prostaglandins are local messengers.
Unlike renin, which is more of a long distance messenger,
prostaglandins act locally.
Actually, lots and lots of cells in our body
use prostaglandins to send local messages.
The third trigger, just to summarize it,
is low salt in the distal convoluted tubule.
You know specifically that it's the macula densa cells of the convoluted tubule.
So these are the three major triggers for renin release.
This is all happening in the kidney.
That's were all this action is occurring.
But you know there are other organs
involved in blood pressure control as well.
The one that is next on our list, is the liver cells.
The liver cells, here we go, a little house for cells,
are also making a hormone of their own.
It's gonna meet up with renin in a second
and it's called angiotensinogen.
Angiotensinogen is kind of a sleepwalker,
if we would zoom in on its face, it would be asleep.
So I'm gonna draw it that way.
It's there and it's moving around the body,
but it's not active and that's the key thing, it's not active.
But it needs renin and renin literally
chops of a big chunk of angiotensinogen.
And if that doesn't wake you up, I don't know what would.
Angiotensinogen becomes angiotensin I after meeting renin.
So renin is an enzyme that cuts a big chunk
of this angiotensinogen protein away.
Angiotensin I is the result.
If you'd zoom in on this guys face, it would be awake.
Maybe even a little smile.
Angiotensin I now floats through blood vessels
and of course blood vessels have cells lining them.
So let's draw a little house.
These are the endothelial cells.
These are the cells that are lining the blood vessel inside.
Classically we used to think that
this is almost always happening in the lungs,
but more and more we're realizing that it definitely does happen in the lungs, but it's in other vessels as well.
Endothelial cells in a number of parts of our body,
including the lungs,
are able to convert angiotensin I into angiotensin II.
So angiotensin II is formed.
This is also a hormone, so I'll draw this little person.
Angiotensin II is happy as a clown,
because angiotensin II has lots of activity.
It's a very very active hormone,
it does all sorts of things.
I'm gonna draw that activity now.
Angiotensin II will go out to a number of different places.
I'm gonna draw four arrows,
1, 2 and two little ones, 3 and 4.
It goes to four places and four different cell types are affected by angiotensin II.
Keep in mind, at the beginning of all this,
we're trying to raise blood pressure.
Four different cell types are affected
and here is the fourth.
The first one over here is smooth
muscle cells in the blood vessels.
This is smooth muscle cells all over the body,
not just in the kidney.
These smooth muscle cells all over the body are
going to contract, they're gonna constrict down.
They're gonna cause increased resistance.
Remember that as the blood vessels constrict,
vasoconstrict, that will increase resistance.
That's one effect.
In a different cell type all together, in the kidney cells,
you actually have the ability to,
angiotensin II makes these kidney cells hold on to more water.
So you have more volume.
It helps the kidney to hold on to more water and more volume.
Think about it in terms of stroke volume.
It's gonna increase stroke volume.
So you have increased resistance
and now increased stroke volume.
Those are two cell types for angiotensin II to act on.
It also acts on a couple of glands.
I'm gonna try to draw for you the pituitary gland.
This pituitary gland is sitting at the base of the brain.
This gland is called that because it secretes hormones as well, actually it's sending out messengers as well.
Here's a little hormone, again in orange,
remember all our hormones are in orange.
This one is called ADH.
AntiDiuretic Hormone.
That ADH does some of the same stuff,
at the end of the day, that angiotensin II will do.
In that it will increase resistance of blood vessels
and it will also increase volume by making the kidney hold on to more water.
The fourth cell type, is gonna be the adrenal gland.
The adrenal gland is here.
It's called ad-renal because it's sitting on top of the kidney, which is the renal.
This adrenal gland is also making a hormone,
because it's a gland.
That hormone is going to act right there.
This is the little messenger
and this is called aldosterone.
So you've got aldosterone and ADH that are
also acting on some of the same cells.
I should rephrase that, not on the same cells,
but on the same organs as the angiotensin II.
So here aldosterone is gonna act
on kidney cells to increase volume.
ADH is gonna act on, like I said before,
the kidney and smooth muscle.
So let's scroll up and show you from the top some interesting things I want to point out.
We've got at the very top, all the action,
you remember, started in the kidneys.
It started in the kidney with the macula densa cell and our JG cell and even our nerve endings were in the kidneys.
One of the key target organs down
here is of course the kidney.
Things are starting in the kidney,
but they're also ending in the kidney.
Then you'll say
'Well what about the smooth muscle cells all over the body?'
You're absolutely right it does also affects
the smooth muscle in other parts of the body.
I just want to point out the fact that
the kidney is a major player in this game.
That's one point.
The other point is that when people talk about the RAAS-system, they're talking about certain pathways.
They're specifically talking about, for example,
this arrow right here, this hormone obviously.
They're talking about this angiotensinogen
and this angiotensin I.
They're also referring to angiotensin II and all of its targets.
They're gonna talk about angiotensin II affecting
the smooth muscle and the two glands,
the pituitary as well as the adrenal gland
and its effect on the kidney.
So they're really referring to all of those things.
I want to make sure you remember that it's affecting four,
at least four target cell types.
Finally that aldosterone right here has
a huge effect on the kidney as well.
These are the important points
to take away from this overview,
that there are many different hormones involved,
and I've tried to keep them color-coded all in orange,
to make sure we keep track of them.
And the fact that the kidney is
a major player in blood pressure control.