simplify 2 a square over 3 b to the fifth
All of that to the fourth power
So here we could use the property that if i have x over y to the Nth power
this is the same thing as x to the Nth power
over y to the nth power. we can see that with an exemple really fast.
if i had x over y to the 3rd power
what would be this equal to?
that would be x over y
times x over y times x over y
which is equal to x times x times x over y times y times y
This is clearly x to the power of 3 over y to the power of 3
particular example of why, hope this makes you feel more confident about it.
Makes you feel good about using this property.
Lets use it right
here in the actual problem
So we have 2 a squared over b to the fifth
all of that to the fourth power
So this going to be the same thing
as to a squared to the fourth power
Let me write it this way. It's going to be
2 a squared to the fourth power, let me do the fourth power in blue
to the fourth power, all of that,
over 3 b to the fifth, all of that over
3 b to the fifth, to the fourth power
to the fourth power
and now we can use the property that if I take the product of things
and raise that to a power, that's the same thing as
raising each of the things in the product to the power
and then taking the product, so this is going to be the same thing
Let me just write the property
So if I have x times y to the nth power, this is the same thing
as x to the nth times y to the nth power.
And you could a similar argument that we did rigth here
to see why this works out. So let's do that over here.
2 a squared to fourth power is going to be equal to
2 to the fourth power, colour coded,
2 to the fourth power times a squared to the fourth power
times a squared to the fourth power
and then all of that over
3 b to the fifth to the fourth power, that's going to be
3 to the fourth power, 3 to the fourth power
times b to the fifth, times b to the fifth,
to the fourth power, times b to the fifth to the fourth power
Now the last interesting thing here,
We can evaluate what this numbers come out to be
2 to the fourth power, let me just do it rigth now
2 to the fourth power, 2 squared is 4,
2 to the third power is 8, 2 to the fourth power is 16
So this rigth here is 16.
3 to the first power is 3, 3 squared is 9,
3 to the third power is 27, 3 to the fourth power is 81.
So this over here, this over here is
let me do it in that green colour, this is 81.
81, and to simplify this terms here
we just have to remember
the what we call to power property or the power rule of exponents.
That's just the notion that if I have,
if I have x to the nth and I raise that
to the mth power, this is the exact same thing as
x to n times m power
So if we want to simplify this,
or numerator is now, it is now 16
that's the 2 to the fourth, and then a squared
and then that to the fourth power,
That's going to be a to the 2 times 4 power,
or a to the 8th power
This is literally 2 times 4, so we are just multiplying 2 times 4
This 2 times this 4 to get that 8.
And then in the denominator
We have our 81, and then b to the fifth and that to the fourth power
That's going to be b to the 5 times 4 power
or b to the 20th power. So I got 20 by multiplying 5 times 4.
And we are done, this is about simplify as we can get.