In the last video, we touched a bit on the idea of
final goods and services
and we talked about the situation
in which in the given period that we're calculating GDP
so this might be in a given year,
where we're essentially starting from scratch
and we put in the labour, the land, we get the cotton
the market value of that is ten dollars at raw cotton
and then we are able to turn that into thread
with the market value of twenty dollars
and we keep on going and going
all the way until we get the finished product of jeans,
which has a market value of fifty dollars.
We saw in the last video
that the contribution to GDP will just be this final product
it will just be the fifty dollars worth of jeans
and we know its value based on its market value,
what people are willing to pay for it.
We will not count all of these intermediary goods,
but that probably raised a question in your head:
What if all these does not happen in a given year?
What if the year were to end right over here?
So we're thinking about GDP in a year
but we could think about GDP in a quarter, whatever.
What if the period under question ends over here?
so this is period one, let's call this period one
period one
and then this is going to be period two
so period one, we get to the point that we have a market value of twenty dollars worth of thread
and then period two, we get all the way to the jeans.
So this is period two over here.
So this might be one year and this might be the year after that.
But what happens is that in period one, we would look at this good
this intermediary good,
that's sitting in someone's inventory some place,
it's getting ready to be used, to get more finished,
we would say this is the contribution to GDP.
And we consider this as an investment that's going to be used in the future to produce other things
So in period one the contribution will be twenty dollars,
and then in period two, the contribution won't be just be the fifty dollars.
So we do get to a point where the jeans are worth fifty dollars,
but so that we haven't double counted the same twenty dollars in both period one and period two,
we'll subtract out what our starting point was
or essentially we'll subtract out the contribution
the intermediary products that were already counted in previous periods.
Or you could say we'll subtract out the market value of the input
at the beginning of that period.
So you'd say fifty dollars minus the twenty dollars.
And so you would get a contribution to GDP by taking this twenty dollar intermediary good
and turning it into a fifty dollar final good
the contribution to GDP in period two would be thirty dollars.