y is directly proportional to x.
If y = 30 when x = 6, find the value of x when y = 45.
So let's just take this each statement at a time.
"y is directly proportional to x":
that's literally just saying that y is equal to some constant times x
This statement can literally be translated to y= some constant [writes k] * x.
y is directly proportional to x.
Now they tell us if y = 30 when x = 6
so y is 30 when x is 6 [writes 30 =  6]
And we have this constant of proportionality
This second statement right over here [adds k in space]
allows us to solve for this constant -
when x is 6 it tells us y is 30
so we can figure out what this constant is.
And we can divide both sides by 6 - divide both sides by 6 -
and we get, we get - this left hand side is 5, 30/6 = 5 -
5 = k or k=5
so the second sentence tells us - this gives us the information
that y is not just kx, it tells us that y = 5x.
y is 30 when x is 6.
And then finally, they say find the value of x when y= 45.
So when y is 45, we have 45 is equal to - so this, we're just putting 45 in for y -
45 = 5x
Divide both sides by 5, to solve for x
We get 45/5 is 9. And 5x/5 is just x.
So x is, x = 9 when y=45.