A star explodes in a blinding supernova, spraying x-rays
across the galaxy to tell its tale. X-rays also
tells a dentist which tooth to drill, and a surgeon which bones to mend.
In 1895 Wilhelm Roentgen
discovered that firing streams of x-rays through arms and hands created
eerie, but detailed images of the bones inside.
X-rays are high energy light rays with wavelengths between
3 and 0.03 nanometers. So small
that some x-rays are no bigger than many individual atoms.
In laboratories, scientist fire beams of x-rays at unknown
substances to learn what elements they contain and to decode their
atomic structure. This is how scientists unraveled complex molecules
like penicillin and DNA.
Scientists can also detect the x-rays emitted from extremely hot and energetic
objects in the Universe. NASA's robotic rovers
recorded x-rays to identify the spectral signatures of elements,
such as zinc and nickel, in Martian rocks.
X-rays can also reveal an object's temperature since temperature determines
the wavelength of its radiation. The hotter the object,
the shorter that wavelength is. X-rays come from objects
that seethe at millions of degrees-such as pulsars,
black holes, supernovas, or the plasma in
our Sun's corona. Our Sun has a surface temperature of around 6,000
degrees celcius and radiates most of its energy in visible
wavelengths. But it is easier to study the massive energy flows
in the corona's energetic plasma by observing x-rays like this
image from the Hinode satellite, a joint Japanese-NASA mission.
NASA's SOHO satellite produced these x-ray images
of the Sun that allow scientists to see and record these energy flows
within the corona. NASA's orbiting Chandra x-ray
observatory detects x-rays created by objects spread far across
space such as this supernova explosion that occurred 10,000
light years from Earth. The colors in the gas and dust cloud
correspond to different energy levels of the x-rays created by the blast.
X-rays at different wavelengths provide information about an
object's composition, temperature, density, or its magnetic field.
Human eyes may not be able to see x-rays
but, from seething cosmic bodies to individual atomic
elements, x-rays provide a wealth of information
to exploring scientists.