what I want to start thinking about in this video
is giving that we do having monopoly on something in this example in this video
we're going to have a monopoly on oranges
giving that we have monopoly on oranges
and the demand curve for oranges in the market
how to we maximize our profit?
To answer that questions, we're gonna think about our total revenue for different quantities
and from that we're gonna get the marginal revenue for different quantities
and that we can compare that to our marginal cost curve
and should give us a pretty good sense of what quantity we should produce to optimize things
so let's just figure out total revenue first
so obviously if we produce nothing
if we produce zero quantity, we have nothing to sell
we know total revenue is price times quantity
your price is six, your quantity is zero
so your total revenue is going to be zero if you produce nothing
and if you produce one unit
and this over here is actually one thousand ponds per day
we'll call it unit ponds per day
if you produce one unit
then your total revenue is one unit times five dollars per pond
so that will be five times, actually, one thousand
so that will be five thousand dollars
and you can also view it as the area of this rectangle over here
you have the height is the price, and the width is the quantity
but we can that five times
whenever you produce one unit, you gonna get five thousand dollars
so this right over here is in thousands of dollars
and this right over here is in thousands of ponds
just to make sure we are consisted this right over here
let's keep going
so that was this point, when we produce one thousand ponds we get five thousand dollars
if we produce two thousand ponds
and now we are talking about our price is going to be four dollars
or we can say our price is four dollars we can sell two thousand ponds, given this demand curve
and our total revenue is going to be the area of this rectangle right over here
height is price width is quantity
four times two is eight
so if I produce two thousand ponds
then I will get a total revenue of eight thousand dollars
so this is seven and a half, eight is going to put a something right about there
and then we can keep going
if I produce, or if the price is three dollars per pond
I can sell three thousand ponds
my total revenue is this rectangle right over here
three times three is nine thousand dollars
so if I produce three thousand ponds, I can get a total revenue of nine thousand dollars
so right about there, and let's keep going
if I produce, or the price is two dollars per pond
I can sell four thousand ponds, my total revenue is two times four, which is eight thousand dollars
so if I produce four thousand ponds, I can get a total revenue of eight thousand dollars
that should be even with that one right over there, just like that
and then if I produce, or if the price is one thousand dollars
let me use a new color
the price is one dollar per pond I should say
I can sell five thousand ponds
my total revenue is gonna be one times five or five thousand dollars
so it's gonna be even with this here
so if I produce five thousand units I'm gonna get five thousand dollars of revenue
and if the price is zero, the market will demand six thousand ponds per day
it's free, but I'm not gonna generate any revenue because I'm gonna be given this away for free
so I will not be generating any revenue in the situation
our total revenue curve it looks like, if you are taking algebra you recognize this as a downward facing parabola
our total revenue looks like this
our total revenue...easier for me to draw curve with dotted line
our total revenue looks something like that
and you can even solve with algebraically that solve that this is a downward facing parabola
the formula right over here of the demand curve is y-intercept is six
so if I wanna right price as a function of quantity
we have price is equal to six minus quantity
or if you wanna right in a traditional slope intercept form, or "mx plus b" form
and if that doesn't make any sense you might wanna review some of our algebra play
that you can right as P is equal to negative Q plus six
Obviously these are the same exact thing
you have y-intercept of six and you have a negative one slope
if you increase quantity by one, you decrease price by one
or another way to think about it, if you decrease price by one, you increase quantity by one
so that's why you have a negative one slope
so this price as a function of quantity
what is total revenue? well, total revenue is equal to price times quantity
but we can write price as a function of quantity, we did it just now
now this is what it is, or we can rewrite it or we can even be written like this
we can rewrite the price part as... so this is going to be equal to negative Q plus six times quantity
and this is equal to total revenue
and if you multiply this out, you get total revenue is equal to Q times Q is negative Q squared
plus six Q
so you might recognize this, this is clearly a quadratic
since you have a negative out front before the second degree term right over here before the Q squared
it is a downward opening parabola
so it makes complete sense
now I wanna leave you there in this video
because I 'm trying to make an effort not to make my video too long
but in the next video, we're gonna think about is "what is the marginal revenue we get for each of this quantity"
just as a review
marginal revenue is equal to change in total revenue divided by change in quantity
or another way to think about it
the marginal revenue at any one of these quantities, is the slope of the line tangent to that point
and you really have to do a little bit of calculus in order to actually calculate slopes of tangent line
but we'll approximate with a little bit of algebra
but since you want to do is to figure out the slope, so we're gonna figure out the marginal revenue
when we're selling one thousand ponds, so exactly how much more total revenue do we get
if we just barely increase, if we just start selling another a million double ponds of oranges
what's going to happen?
so what we do is we're trying to figure out the slope of the tangent line at any point that you can see that
cause the change in total revenue is this
and change in quantity is that there's
so we're trying to find the instantaneus slope with that ponit
or you can think of it as the slop of the tangent line
and we will continue doing that in the next video