PROBLEM: "The perimeter of a rectangular
fence measures 0.72 kilometers.
The length of the fenced
area is 160 meters.
What is its width?"
So we have a rectangular fence.
Let me draw it.
So that is a rectangle.
You can imagine we're
looking from above.
This line is the top
of the fence.
And if you take its perimeter, the perimeter
is the distance around the fence.
If you take this distance plus this distance
plus that distance plus that distance,
it's going to be 0.72 kilometers.
That's the total combined
length of all of the sides.
Now, the length of the fenced
area is 160 meters.
So let's call this the length.
So this distance right
here is 160 meters.
Since it's a rectangle, that
distance over there
is also going to be 160 meters –
and we need to figure out its width.
They want us to figure out the width.
The width is this distance right over here –
which is also going to be this
distance right over there.
Now, what is the perimeter
of the fence?
The perimeter is the sum of
this length, plus this length,
plus that length, plus that length.
So the perimeter –
let me write it in orange –
is going to be equal to w,
the width, plus 160 meters,
plus the width, plus 160 meters.
And let's assume w is in meters.
So that w is in meters,
So we could add it all up.
So if you were to add all of these up,
you would get a certain number of meters.
you have a w plus a w,
so you would have 2w.
160 + 160 is 320. So that's plus 320.
And this whole thing is in meters.
We're assuming that w is in meters.
Now, they also told us that the perimeter
of the fence is 0.72 kilometers.
So the perimeter –
(Let me do it in that same orange color.)
The perimeter is also equal to 0.72 kilometers.
And we can abbreviate that with km.
Now, if we wanted to solve an
equation, if we wanted to set
this thing equal to the
perimeter they gave us,
we have to make sure that
the units are the same.
Here it's in meters.
Here it's in kilometers.
So let's convert this 0.72
kilometers to meters.
And the way to do that,
we want the kilometers
in the denominator, so it cancels out with the kilometers, and you want meters in the numerator.
Now, how many meters
equal a kilometer?
Well, it's 1,000 meters
for every 1 kilometer.
1 kilometer is 1,000 meters.
Now, if you multiply these two things,
the kilometers cancel out.
You're just going to be
left with the meters.
And then when you multiply 0.72 times 1,000,
you could just first say,
"OK, let's take 72 times 1,000."
72 times 1,000 would
be 72 with 3 0s. COUNTING: 1, 2, 3.
And then out of the two numbers
that you're taking the product of,
we have two numbers behind the decimal.
COUNTING: 1, 2.
So you put two numbers behind the decimal.
COUNTING: 1, 2, right over there.
So 0.72 times 1,000 is 720.
And that makes sense.
0.72, it's not quite 1,
but it's getting close to 1,
almost 3/4 of a whole,
and this is almost 3/4 of 1,000.
So it makes sense.
So the perimeter, this
information right here,
0.72 kilometers, is the
same thing as 720 meters.
So if you take 2 times the width
in meters, and add that
to the combined lengths -- it's
160 and 160. That's 320,
And all of this is in meters --
that is going to be equal to
the total perimeter,
which is 720 meters.
Now that we have the units right,
we can solve for w,
and w will tell us this
width in meters.
So 2w + 320 is equal to 720.
We can subtract 320 from both
sides of this equation.
Remember, an equation is saying,
"That is equal to that."
If we want both sides to always
be equal, whatever we do
to the left-hand side, we have
to do the right-hand side.
So we subtract 320
from both sides.
The left-hand side,
that cancels out.
That's why we subtracted 320.
And that you just leaves you with
2 times the width is equal to 720,
minus 320, which is 400.
Now you can divide both
sides of this by 2.
And then you're left with
w = 400/2,
which is 200.
And we said that w was in meters.
So the width is 200 meters.
So this is 200 meters.
And let's see if it makes sense.
200 + 200 is 400,
+ 320 is 720.
So the total perimeter is 720
meters, which is the exact
same thing as 0.72 kilometers.