We are in the Brooklyn Musuem with the George Bellows Pennsylvania Station Excavation
Circa 1907-08.
Bellows is I think a really fabulous painter and a member of a group of painters
who are usually reffered to as the "Ash Can"
Where did they get that name?
That's a pretty nasty name
Well you know their work was seen to be sotty and dusty and gritty and dark
What they were was a small group of realists that was known as the eight
This was a group of American artist that focused in New York for the most part.
They painted the world around them
It was a fairly radical idea but they didn't do it like the American impresssionists
Who mimicked the colors and sort of the light of Paris
You know this was really about New York at its really industrial moment
When New York itself was beginning to flex its muscles and really putting itself on the map.
This was the first decade of the 20th century
So not looking back at Europe to generate its style
But trying to generate an American style
It's funny to me how American artists are always in dialogue with Europe
And of course this is also but just not as clearly in the directness of that reference
This is just amazing as a document to me of what 7th avenue is like
So this is a moment when the technonlogy was steam and you had these steam powered diggers
Excavating in this enourmous area in order to put Pennsylvania station here
and you actually sort of see the city rise beyond this new industrial city
You know there is something that is almost daunting like about this
You know you've got...it's the pit of hell in a sense
Cause we've got fires burning and smoke...
But you know images of industrial scenes always evoke those kinds of scenes.
But this is creating a kind of dramatic beauty out of umm this grit
Out of this filth really
You know it's soo stark because you have the sooted snow below
You have you know sort of the terrible