Let's see if we can handle
some slightly more difficult amine naming examples.
So if we look at this blue molecule right here
we always want to start off
by finding the longest carbon chain.
It looks like it's this chain at the bottom
where we have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8 carbons.
So it's going to be octan.
We don't want to just call it octane
because we have these functional groups up here
and maybe one of them is going to take higher priority
than just the fact that this is an alkane.
And, in fact, one of them will.
So let's look at them.
So over here we an amino group.
That would make this molecule an amine.
So this is an amino group right here.
Then we have this benzene ring.
And when benzene is a functional group
we call it a phenyl group.
And that's derived from I think it's either the Greek
or the Latin word for light
because benzene was first isolated from, I guess
the air around lanterns or something
so this is called a phenyl group.
And then finally we have this OH
which would make this whole thing an alcohol
or we could call that a hydroxy group
so this right here is a hydroxy group.
Now, this is just something that you need to know.
There's no way to kind of deduce it.
The people who've decided how to name things
just decided that
certain groups take higher priority over others.
And out of these three groups
the hydroxy group
the thing that's making this whole thing an alcohol
takes the highest priority
so this is what's going to define the suffix.
So if we start numbering
we want to start numbering this chain
closest to the highest priority group.
So we'll start numbering at this end.
So it's 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
So we have a hydroxy group on the three carbon
so this is octan-3-ol.
If this was not a high priority
we would put a hydroxy in the front
but since this is the highest prioritiy
its defining this as an alcohol, octanol.
But we put the 3 there to say it's on the three carbon.
And then, of course, this would be 5-phenyl.
This right here is 5-phenyl.
And this right here is 8-amino.
And amino comes before phenyl in alphabetical order
so this whole molecule is going to be
-- let me write it over here --
it's going to be 8-amino-5-phenyl-octan-3-ol.
And we're done.
So this is an aromatic compound
because of the benzene ring.
It's an amine because of the amino group.
And it's an alcohol because of the hydroxy group.
Now let's look at this molecule here in green.
And actually, I forgot to draw part of it.
This is supposed to be a benzene ring.
So let me make clear.
That is a benzene ring.
So let's think about
the different functional groups here.
And we'll start with the one
that you've probably never seen before.
This is a nitro group, and it's highly explosive.
Maybe in a future video
I'll show you some nitroglycerin and some TNT
as you know, which are highly explosive
but they have nitro groups on them.
So this right here is a nitro group.
It takes very low precedence
in the whole scheme of things.
So this will never be the cause of naming the suffix.
We just know that this is a nitro group right here.
We, of course, have a bromo group
that we've seen many times.
That is a bromo group.
And then we have an amino group right here.
So this is going to be
-- let me do this in a different color.
This is definitely an amine.
This is an amino group right there.
And out of these three groups
the amino group is definitely of the highest priority.
So you might be tempted to name this
1-amino-2,3-bromo-4-nitrobenzene
but when a benzene ring
is attached to an amino group
this one also has one of those special names.
And let me just do it on the side right here.
So if I just have a benzene ring
attached to an amino group
so that's an NH2 right there
we call this molecule right here
and this is just the common name for it
and it's something to put in your toolkit, this is aniline.
So that will be the base name.
This whole thing right here we call aniline.
Let me write it over here.
So this is aniline.
And then we always want to start numbering
at the group that's really defining the molecules
so we start numbering here.
And you want to go in the order
where you're going to bump into something first.
So, 1, 2, 3, 4. So this is going to be
-- if we look at them
and bromo comes alphabetically before nitro --
so it's going to be 3-bromo-4-nitroaniline.
And we are done!