- We're in Santa Maria del Popolo.
- In Rome.
Looking at one of the great
Caravaggio's of the Baroque.
This may actually be my favourite Caravaggio.
Although I said that about the last Caravaggio.
You may have.
This is the Crucifixion of Saint Peter.
We talked about the diagonals of the Baroque
and the sense of action in the momentary,
but Caravaggio just makes
that seem so simple.
It's such an activated,
complex set of movements and weights,
countermovements.
- And gravity plays this intense role.
- Very powerful feeling of the pulling gravity.
But what gets me is Peter.
Caravaggio went out to the street and got a guy.
He's a real and powerful, intense figure.
And he looks really crabby just the way Peter should be.
Now with the story of course.
- He has to be crucified not the way the Christ did.
- That's right. So upside down.
Turning the cross upside down.
He looks poor and kind of messy.
Not idealised at all.
This is in such contrast that comes.
Seems like a guy hanging out in a bar in Rome.
Well, that's what Caravaggio is so known for.
It's all of the pomp and ceremony of Rome,
of the Catholic Church,
it's here turned on it's head by Caravaggio.
I think now this in contrast to the medieval traditions,
where there is no sense of gravity,
no sense of weight,
no sense of physicality.
We're really seeing the ramifications of the Renaissance
but brought into the Baroque here
with the kind of intense and emotionalism,
and physicality.
- And that even puts the Renaissance to shame.
- And it's shoved in your face.
The guy who's lifting the cross,
he's got all under it.
He's hoisting it with his back.
We see his butt in our face,
we see his leg, his dirty feet.
That's right.
And this notion of really pushing it out,
past the picture plane, into our faces.
- Absolutely...
- Into our space...
And look at the diagonal of Peter
as his feet come towards us,
you'r absolutely right.
It breaks out into our world.
Right, and in fact the cross as it moves out
into our space by his feet,
gives us a very closeup view of the nails.
As a kind of way, that it gets to you and your body,
so that you almost go "augh".
- This oldest tension actually...
- You can feel that...
And the nails through his hands are
very real and descriptive,
and the way that there is
that black background.
Because light is really emphasizing,
what you're talking about.
You know when the knees portrew,
the way in which the body sort of pushed forward.
All of that is highly controlled
by the way the light is played here.
And on his abdomen and his knees.
They make his body look very normal,
like you know, it's the regular man's body,
so different than the kind of bodies
we used to see in the Renaissance.
That's true.
Although there is some kind of heroism here
in terms of it's mass and it's strength.
- But it's only expressed...
- Belied a little bit by the face though,
- I think, which makes it so vulnerable.
- It's true.
There is this kind of incredible tension,
because, all of the forces of nature play here.
And we're not quite sure if that rope is strong enough,
we're not quite sure if those men are strong enough.
- It may just fall.
- They may though think it collapses.
Absolutely, this is kind of sense of
transience in the momentary.
And sort of human frailty.
In a sense Caravaggio's brilliance is to be able to
create the sense of newness and freshness,
as if this hadn't been rehearsed hundreds of times
in paintings for hundreds of years.
It's as if it's the first time.