Let's say that I've got two Chuck Norrises (or maybe it's Chuck Norri)
and to that I am going to add another three Chuck Norrises
So I'm going to add another three Chuck Norrises
And this might seem a little bit obvious but how many Chuck Norrises do I now have?
Well, two Chuck Norrises - we can represent this as literally a Chuck Norris plus a Chuck Norris
So let me do that, a Chuck Norris plus another Chuck Norris - two Chuck Norrises.
You can also view that as 2 times Chuck Norris and this is just another way of representing it
And three Chuck Norrises
You could view that as a Chuck Norris, plus a Chuck Norris, plus another Chuck Norris
And so we would have a grand total (and this might be very simple for you)
But you would have a grand total of 1..2..3..4..5 Chuck Norrises
So this would be equal to
5 Chuck Norrises
Now let's get a little bit more abstract here
Chuck Norris is a very tangible thing
So let's go to a little bit more of the traditional algebraic notation.
If I have two X's
And remember 2x - you can view this as two X's or two times X.
And to that I were to add 3 X's
How many X's do I have?
Well, once again, 2 X's that's 2 times X and you can view it as an X plus an X.
We don't know what the value of X is but whatever that value is we can add it to itself
And then three X's are going to be that value
I'll do it in that same green colour
Three X's are going to be that value
plus that value
plus whatever that value is
And so how many X's do I now have?
Well, I'm going to have 1..2..3..4..5 X's
So 2x plus 3x is equal to
5x
And if you think about it, all we really did (and hopefully you conceptually get it)
We just added the two numbers that were multiplying the X.
And these numbers, the two or the three
they're called "coefficients"
Very fancy word - but it's just this constant number, this regular number, that's multiplied by the variable.
You just added the two and the three to get your 5x.
Now let's think about this a little bit more
Let's go back to this original expression, the two Chuck Norrises plus three Chuck Norrises.
Let's say, to that we were to add
Let's say we were to add some type of a...
Let's say we were to add seven plums over here
So this is my drawing of a plum
So we have seven plums plus two Chuck Norrises plus three Chuck Norrises
And let's say that I add another two plums
I add another two plums here
So what would this whole thing be?
Well, I wouldn't add the seven to the two to the three plus the two
We're adding different things here!
You have two Chuck Norrises and three Chuck Norrises
So they're still going to simplify to five Chuck Norrises
And then we would separately think about the plums
We have seven plums and we're adding another two plums
We're going to have nine plums
Plus nine plums
So this simplifies to five Chuck Norrises and nine plums
Similarly, over here, if I had instead of just 2x plus 3x
If I had 7y
7y plus 2x plus 3x plus 2y
What do I now have?
Well, I can't add the X's and the Y's
They could very well represent a different number
So all I can do is really, add the X's (and then I get the 5x)
And then I'd separately add the Y's
If have seven Y's and to that I add two Y's
I'm going to have nine Y's
If I have seven of something and I have two of something, I now have nine of that something
So I'm going to have nine Y's
So you add that (we'll do that in a different colour)
You add this
... and this
... you get that
You add the X's
... you get that right over there
So hopefully that makes a little sense
Actually, I'll throw out one more idea
So given this, what would happen if I were to have
2x plus 1 plus 7x plus 5?
Well, once again, you might be tempted to add the two plus the one
But they're adding different things!
These are two X's, this is just the number one
So you really just have to add the X's together.
So you're going to say "well I've got two X's
and I'm going to add seven X's to that"
Well that means that I now have nine X's
And then separately, you would say
"Well, I've got just the abstract number one
and then I've got another five"
One plus five is going to be equal to six.