Let's say last year
I put $100 into some type of savings account in a bank.
So this is a year ago,
and that now today, exactly 1 year later,
that $100 has grown to $110.
So this is now.
So if you look at things just in the absolute dollar terms,
things have grown by $10,
so I made $10 off of an original $100 investment,
so I got a 10% return.
But what I want to think about is,
does this really capture
how much more I can buy with this $110
than I could buy with that $100 before?
Can I really buy 10% more goods and services today
than I could a year ago?
and to think about that,
let's think about, well, a hypothetical inflation rate
from last year to this year,
so let's say that the inflation ended up being 2%
between a year ago and today.
If that's the case,
what is $100 a year ago in today's money?
Well, if inflation was 2%,
then $100 a year ago would buy you the same stuff
that $102 would buy you today,
So it would be $102.
So what is the dollar return in today's money?
In the current, in today's money?
The current purchasing power?
Well, we're getting $110
We get $110
and we invest it in today's money, $102.
If we look at it from today's terms
we invested something that gives us
the same purchasing power as $102 today
and now it's giving us the purchasing power of $110.
So we've gotten $8 more of purchasing power
in today's money.
So what is the actual real return?
Let me write it... Real return
and we can do it in today's money
and you could do it either way,
you could discount the $110 back to a year ago money
and figure out the real return there
and figuring out the actual dollar return
and do the calculation
or you can do it in today's money
and maybe I'll do it the previous way in the next video.
But the real return is
we made $8 over the course of the year
in today's money
and what we originally invested in today's money
was $102.
And so we get our calculator out
8 divided by 102 is 7.8%
so this is equal to 7.8%
So even though the nominal return,
if we just look at what we got in exchange
for what we invested
even though the nominal return was 10%
because there was 2% inflation
our actual purchasing power only increased by 7.8%