We've talked a lot about the kidney,
but I want to point out
that the kidney is not the only organ
involved in controlling the blood pressure.
In fact the liver plays a really really important role in helping you create the right enzymes and proteins to control blood pressure.
So I'm gonna sketch out real quick some liver cells here.
These liver cells are busy making a lot of different proteins.
One of them is called angiotensinogen.
Angiotensinogen gets made by the liver cells
and they dump it out into the blood vessel.
If we were to draw angiotensinogen
it's actually a pretty large molecule,
it has lots and lots of amino acids.
Amino acids are these tiny little circles that I'm drawing.
I'm connecting them with little bonds.
You can imagine amino acids like pearls on a necklace.
In total angiotensinogen has about 450+ amino acids.
So it's a pretty long chain.
542 amino acids actually.
It's a pretty long chain, I'm not gonna draw all of it,
but you get the idea that it's some crazy long chain like that.
It's little amino acids all the way through.
So this huge protein gets put into the blood vessels
by the liver cells and starts floating around.
If you would zoom in on the little protein,
if you could give it a little face,
it would maybe look something like this, because
even though it's floating through the body,
it's basically asleep, it's not really active.
I just want you to keep that in the back of your mind.
Even though it's there, it's not truly active.
It's not really doing a lot.
At the same time you've got the kidney.
The kidney is not idle,
the kidney is busy making a hormone of its own.
You know there's the afferent arteriole.
The afferent arteriole is the blood vessel
that's headed into the glomerulus.
It's headed into the part of the kidney
where all of the urine is initially made.
In the afferent arteriole blood is going that way.
Lining this afferent arteriole, there are these little cells
all the way through like this.
These are called the juxtaglomerular cells.
I'm doing a simplified version of it,
because this is the part I really want to focus on.
These juxtaglomerular cells have in them little granules,
they're sometimes even called granular cells.
These granular cells sense,either themselves
or one of the neighbors helped them sense
when the blood pressure is low.
Then these granules get dumped into the blood stream.
If you look at the microscopic level,
you can see these little proteins called renin.
These are proteins that act at a distant site,
we call those hormones.
These peptide or protein hormones are basically
gonna work on cells far away.
If the renin is floating along in the blood and the angiotensinogen is floating in the blood, they might meet up.
In a blood vessels in your arm,
or maybe in a blood vessel in your leg.