We have now thought a lot about the orange juice market and least firm specific level we see
in the last week videos we talked about.
what are average total cost and average bearable cost and marginal cost.
or if we are running orange juice making business.Now lets think about what happens
at the market level.So we are gonna go back to some of what we thought about in the past
in terms of supply and demand curves.
So this is orange juice market and lets just draw some supply and demand curve right over here.
This is going to be the price per gallon and lets say this right over here is 1$.
This right over here is 50 cents.and this is 0.and let's say that this is the quantity in gallons per week.
And we are going to talk about the entire orange juice market so this is going to be
millions of gallons per week.
and that is let's say this is 1,2,3,4,5 and 6.
and let's just say and I am gonna simplified relative to what we saw in the last video
Let's just say that the supply curve for the orange juice market careful this time
this is the near term supply curve or the short term supply curve looks like looks
something like this.This is the supply curve .This is the entire market .These are all orange juice producers.
So get to make them produce even that first gallon and looks like we need about
20 cents for that first gallon and then each incremental gallon we need more and more money.
The marginal cost for that incremental gallon for the market as whole is going higher and higher
we have to get orange juice further away and transport them further and further
so this right over here is supply curve or you can view it as marginal cost.
Now let's draw an arbitrary demand curve here so the demand curve let's say it looks something like this.
Say that's our current demand.Now I am going to add to this price at which firms or the
suppliers of the orange juice make our neutral with our terms to our economic profit.
Or when our economic profit is equal to 0.
So let's say right over here which happens to be current equilibrium price.
This is the price 50cents per gallon.This is the price at which economic profit is zero.
So I just write economic profit=0.
And I want to remind you economic profit being zero does that mean the accounting profit is zero.
People could be making money at this price it just say that there is neutral whether or not they should be