Let's see if we can evaluate the indefinite integral 1/(9+ x^2) dx.
And we know that if you pattern a^2 - x^2, it could be a good idea to make the substitution x = a sin è,
but we don't see that pattern over here.
What we instead see is a^2 + x^2.
And in this context, it tends to be a good idea -- it's not always going to work, but it never hurts to try out,
it's a little bit of an art here, to try out x = a tan è.
But you might say, "Sal, why is that?"
Well, to make that substitution and see how this thing would simplify.
This thing would become a^2 + a^2 tan^2 è, which is a^2(1 + tan^2 è), and this right over here --
we could reprove it -- actually, let me just reprove it for you.
This is going to become a^2 times this is 1 can be written as cos^2 è/cos^2 è,
tan^2 è is sin^2 è/cos^2 è. And this is why I picked cos^2 è as the denominator so that I can add the two,
and this is going to become a^2 * (cos^2 è + sin^2 è/cos^2 è.
This numerator from the unit circle definition of trig functions becomes 1,
so this is 1/cos^2 è, and everything simplifies to a^2 sec^2 è, which might simplify things.
So let's see if we have what's going on over here; we could rewrite this,
so 9 + x^2, you could rewrite as 3^2 + x^2. In this case, a = 3, so we want to make the substitution x = 3 tan è.
And if we wanted to solve for x, you could divide both sides by 3,
because we later going to undo the substitution x/3 = tan è, or è = arctan, or inverse tangent, x/3.
Now we'll also going to have to figure out what dx is, we'll also going to have to figure out what that is,
so let's take the derivative, or we'll write it in differential form, dx is equal to 3 --
derivative of tan è with respect to è is sec^2 è dè.
So now it looks like we're armed with all of the things necessary to rewrite this entire integral.
It's going to be equal to the indefinite integral -- we'll going to have dx here, which is equal to 3 sec^2 è dè,
that's the dx. And all of that is going to be over this business right over here.
Our a^2 plus our x^2. Now, we already know what that's going to simplify to.
Our a^2 plus our x^2 is going -- since we made this substitution x = 3 tan è,
it's going to simplify to a^2 sec^2 è. So this is going to simplify to 9 sec^2 è.
And you can essentially read -- go through this logic, you going to get 9 + 9 tan^2 è,
factor out a 9, and you'll going to get 9(1 + tan^2 è),
and so that's going to be 9 sec^2 è. Exactly what we have here.
Lucky for us, we have the sec^2 cancelling out, you get 3/9 --
this whole thing can be rewritten as 1/3 (that's just 3/9) times the indefinite integral of just dè,
which is equal to 1/3 è + C, and now we just have to put things in terms of x.
And we see, è = arctan x/3. So this is going to be equal to 1/3 arctan x/3 + C. And we are done.
So now we know how to deal with cases where we might see something like a^2 - x^2 and a^2 + x^2.
It won't always work, but it might be useful -- it will definitely able to do this thing,
it might not always make the integral solvable, but it's not a bad thing to try.
When it looks like u-substitution isn't working, then you can look for these patterns and try some trig-substitution.