so here's a table that summarizes SN1 and SN2 Reactions
the first thing that you should do is look at the structure of the akyl halides
if its a primary alkyl halide its always going to proceed E and SN2 mechanisms
SN2 mechanisms require decreased steric hindrance in order for the nucleophile to function properly
so primary alkyl halides have the-- are the least sterically hindered
a primary alkyl halide would not react in an SN1 mechanism becuase
an SN1 mechanism produces carbocations and a primary carbocation is
not very stable, at all.
so, for all these reasons, primary alkyl halides will be SN2.
Secondary alkyl halides are a little bit harder to figure out because
it could be either SN2 or SN1
so to break that pie, you have to also look at your nucleophile and your solvent.
if you have a strong nucleophile and a polar aprotic solvent
in the last video we saw a polar aprotic solvent favor SN2 mechanisms
if you have a relatively weak nucleophile and a polar protic solvent
thats going to favor an SN1 mechanism becuase the polar protic solvent
will stabilize the resulting carbocation.
tertiary alkyl halides are always going to be SN1 because
tertiary alkyl halides produce tertiary carbocations which are very stable
SN2 mechanisms wouldn't really happen for a tertiary alkyl halide
because there'd be too much steric hindrance - too much stuff in the way.
Okay, so let's do a bunch of examples and see how to use this chart we've created here
I start with this as my alkyl halide
and im going to react an alkyl halide with water
I'm going to heat up the reaciton like that
so the first thing you do - structure of your alkyl halide
right this carbon is the one that's bonded to that bromine
its connected to one other carbon therefore this is a primary alkyl halide
primary alkyl halides are always SN2, right so this is
going to proceed via an SN2 mechanism which we
know is a concerted mechanism. what is the nucleophile?
well water is the nucleophile in this reaction.
water is also the solvent making this a solvolysis reaction
that might confuse some people because they say
oh wait this is a relatively weak nucleophile
and its polar protic so why is it
proceeding via an SN2 mechanism
the structure of your alkyl halide
always wins, so this is a polar protic solvent
which does favor SN1 but since this is a pimary alkyl halide
this is only going to react via an SN2 mechanism although this reaction does occur
rather slowly.
so we know that the first still is our nucleophile
is going to attack our partially positive carbon here
at the same time these electrons kick off onto our leaving group
so what will that give u s?
this is all a concerted SN2 mechanism so
the water molecule is going to add the same time that the bromine leavues
so our water molecule has now added to our original molecule
here and lets see its going to have an extra lone pair of electrons
and its going to have a positive one formal charge like that
so what else is going to happen? alright well
another water molecule is going to come along and instead of
functioning as a nucleophile, this time its going to function as
a base, it needs to get rid of that +1 formal charge on the oxygen.
so this lone pair of electrons is going to take that proton
these electrons are going to kick in here on this oxygen and
so we would end up with ethanol as our products right
two lone pairs of electrons on that oxygen and a hydrogen
we're lucky that we don't have to worry about stereochemistry for this reaction right
there are no chirality centers created.
so ethanol is the only product in this reaction, so
the approach is, first look at your alkyl halide and figure out what type of mechanism you're going to use
and then go to the problem with the mechnism thinking about possibilities for stereochemistry
and then you'll finally end up with your product
so there's a lot of work involved in these but if you go through these problems with those steps in mind
it'll make them much easier. let's look at another exmaple
so we have this as our alkyl halide, so a bromine right here
notice stereochemistry is involved and
we're going to react that alkyl halide with sodium cyanide
so Na plus, CN minus, and our solvent will be DMF
so we look at the structure of our alkyl halide first right
so this is the carbon connected to our halogen
that carbon is connected to
two other carbons making this a
secondary alkyl halide, we know that secondaryy alkyl halides
can proceed via SN1 OR SN2 mechanisms
so we need to look at this nucleophile and solvent
the nucleophile is cyanide anion which happens to be a relatively strong nucleophile
our solvent is DMF and we saw in the last video that's a polar
aprotic solvent.
so polar aprotic solvent strong nucleophile
this is an SN2 mechanism
so this is going to proceed via an SN2 mechanism
so that means as the nucleophile attacks
you know our halogen is going to leave
so as this negatively charged carbon is going to attack
this carbon right
so this happens at the same time the bromine leaves
and the bromine is on one side of the molecule
the cyanide has to the attack from the opposite side of the molecule
so the steric hindrance part to an SN2 mechanism.
so when you draw your products, right when you show the Cyanide
substituting with the halogen there
you're goingt o show your CN going away from you in space
okay, because it has to attack from the opposite side of where the Br is
leaving
so you get inversion of configuration right
via your SN2 mechanism
so this will be the only product of this reaction
lets look at another one
lets actually start with the same alkyl halide, okay so here;s
our sae alkyl halide
this time we're reacting that with
acetic acid, so lets go ahead and draw acetic acid in here
like that
alright so once again I
so once again its the same alkyl halide I know its secondary
so the secondary alkyl halide, this time i have a somewhat weak nucleophile
my nucleophile would be this oxygen here
so it has lone pairs of electrons on it like that
but it doesnt really have a negative one formal charge
its not really that strong of a nucleophile- its also protic
this would be the protic part of our solvent
so its going to function as our nucleophile and solvent
so we go back up here and we find polar protic solvent
relatively weak nucleophile we'll proceed via an SN1 mechanism
so an SN1 mechanism right you know the first step in an SN1 mechanism
is formation of our carbocation so these electrons have to kick off onto our
bromine right to form our carbocation
so this carbon right here ends up
at a positive one formal charge that is a secondary carbocation
so secondary carbocations have the possibility of rearranging but in this case
theres nothing that could happen
to rearrange to make this one more stable tertiary carbocation
so its going to stay as a secondary carbocation
but always think about rearrangements being possible via SN1 mechanism
so we have a secondary carbocation, this is where
our nucleophile is going to attack right so
lone pair of electrons is going to attack right here
and I'm going to go ahead and jump to the product heres
so we're going to lose a proton after that attacks and we're going to get our products
we're going to add on the oxygen and this is an SN1
mechanism, right the oxygen is going to attack from either above or below
this planar sp2 hybridized carbocation here
right so you're going to get a mixture of inversion of configuration and
retention of configuration as we saw in our SN1 video
right so when this oxygen attacks it can attack from above or below
if it attacks from this side right the oxygen is going to add onto here
and then let's see the rest of the molecule will look like that
so I already took the proton off in the mechanism just to save time
so that's one possile product the other possible product
instead of the oxygen adding on as a wedge it can add on as a dash right