Now last couple of videos we set up a scenario
where company A intends to acquire company B
and they're going to do it by issuing 2 million shares,
giving those 2 million shares to shareholders of company B,
and company B shareholders will give essentially all of their ownership away
So there will be an exchange-- 2 million of Company A shares for 1 million of Company B shares.
Or, on a per share basis, the owners of Company B will give up one of their shares
and in exchange they will get two shares of Company A.
And we saw that if everyone thought that this transaction was going to happen,
theoretically, whatever A is trading at, B should trade at twice that
because people know that, when the transaction happens, they will be able to trade in a "B"
for two of these "A" shares. Now, what happens in a situation
Or, why would a situation happen where B doesn't trade at twice of A?
So this is the theoretical, "trading twice of A," so this is two times A.
What happens if it doesn't trade there? What happens if B's shares are trading
a little bit lower there? Well that might be the case, because some people don't think that
the transaction is going to happen, so they're not willing to pay that full premium for B.
But let's say that this were to happen, and you are working at some type of a hedge fund . . .
that has some type of a model-- maybe it's a mathmatical model, maybe you have some type
of shady information-- you know for a fact, you are 100% certain
that this transaction is going to close, and it's definitely going to close with these terms: 2 million
shares of "A" in exchange for 1 million shares of "B."
Now, your temptation might be . . . why don't I just buy shares of B, because they will go up.
But what if the whole market goes down? What if the stock of A goes down like this?
Then two times A will also go down. So you don't want to just buy the stock of B thinking
it is going to go up, because if the transaction is really going to happen, B is just going to track
two times the price of A.