For any real number x, let [x] denote the largest integer less than or equal to x,
often known as the greatest integer function.
Let f be a real valued function defined, on the interval -10 to 10, including the boundaries,
by f(x) = x - [x], if the greatest integer of x ([x]) is odd and
1 + [x] - x if the greatest integer of x is even.
Then the value of pi squared over 10 times the definite integral from -10 to 10 of f(x) cos(pi*x) dx is...?
So before we even try to attempt to evaluate this integral, let's see if we can at least visualize
this function f(x) right over here. So let's do our best to visualize it.
So let me draw my x- axis, and let me draw my y- axis. So let me draw my y- axis.
And then let's think about what this function will look like.
So this is x = 0, this is x = 0 , this is x = 1, x = 2,
x = 3, ... we could go down to negative 1, negative 2, we could just keep going if we like;
hopefully we'll see some type of pattern, because it seems to change from odd to even.
So between zero and one, what is the absolute, Oh! Sorry. What is the greatest integer of x?
So between zero and one, so let me just write over here - so between zero and one,
until you get to one, so may be I should do this,
from including zero, until one, the greatest integer of x, the greatest integer of x, is equal to zero.
If I am at point five, the greatest integer of 0.5 ([0.5]) is equal to zero.
As I go from one to two, as I go from one to two, the greatest, this [x] is equal to 1, it's the greatest
integer..., from like 1.5 the greatest integer is one. If I am at 1.9, the greatest integer is one!
And then, if I go to above, from between two and three, so If I go between two and three,
then the greatest integer is going to be two. If I am at 2.5, the greatest integer is going to be two.
So with that let's at least try to draw this function over these intervals.
So between 0 and 1, the greatest integer is 0. Zero - we can consider (it) to be even.
Zero is even, especially for alternating - 1 is odd, 2 is even, 3 is odd.
So 0 is even, so we will look at this circumstance right over here, if [x] is even.
And then over this time frame, or over this part of the x- axis, the greatest integer of x is just zero,
So the equation in, or the line, or the function is just going to be 1 - x over this interval, because [x] = 0.
So 1 - x will look like this. If this is 1, 1 - x just goes down like that. That's what it looks like
from 0 to 1. Now think about what happens as we go from 1 to 2.
As we go from 1 to 2, or not including 2, but including 1 all the way up to 2, not including it
the greatest integer is 1. Or the greatest integer, [x], is odd.
So we use this case. And over here, we're going to have x - [x].
Over this interval, [x] = 1. So its going to be the graph of x - 1.
So x - 1 at (x = ) 1 is going to be 0, and at (x = ) 2, it's going to be 1 again.
So it's going to be this. It's going to look just like that. So this right here is x - 1 and this over
here essentially was 1 - x. And we could keep doing it. As we go from 2 to 3,
[x] = 2, we would look at this case. So we are going to have 1 + 2, so we're going to have 3
We're going to have 3 here, minus x. So when we start over here, when x = 2, or a little bit above that,
we're going to have 3 - 2, we're going to go to 1, it's going to be right at 1
And then, as x = 3, 3 - 3 = 0; It's going to oscillate back down like this.
So I think we have an appreciation for what this graph is going to look like.
It's keep, it's going to keep going up and down like this - with a slope of negative 1and positive 1,
then negative 1 then positive 1; It's just going to keep doing that over and over again,
You could keep trying that with other intervals, but it's pretty clear that this is the pattern.
Now, what is, what we want to do is to evaluate the integral from 10 to -10 of this function times cos(pi*x)
So let's think about cos(pi*x) - think about whether that also is periodic, and of course it is
And then if we can simplify this integral,so we don't have to evaluate it over, OVER this entire
period over here. May be we can simplify it into an simpler integral.
So cos(pi*x), cos(0) = 0. Cosine... sorry cos(0) = 1. No one could get that wrong!
That's cos(pi*0) = cos(0), so that's 1. Cos(pi) = -1, so when x = 1, this becomes cos(pi), so then the
value of the function is -1, it will be over here, and then cos(2*pi (two times pi)) is then 1 again,
So it will look like this. I mean, this of course will be, this is at one-half, when you put it over
here, it will become pi/2 , cos(pi/2) = 0, zero. So it will look like this. It will look, let me draw it as neatly as possible...
So it will look like this. cosine, and then it will keep doing that! And then it will go like this...
So it is also periodic. So if we wanted to figure out, if we wanted to figure out, the, the integral
of the product of these two periodic functions, from all the way from -10 to 10, can we simplify that,
and it looks like it would just be, cause we have this interval, Let's look at this interval over here
Let's look at just from 0 to 1. So just from 0 to 1, we are going to take this function, and take the
product of this cosine times, essentially, (1-x), and then find the area under that curve, whatever it might be...
Then when we go from 1 to 2, when we take the product of this and (x-1), it is actually going to be the
same area. Because these two, going from 0 to 1, going from 0 to 1, and going from 1 to 2, it's completely
symmetric - you could flip it over, you could flip it over this line of symmetry, and both functions
are completely, are completely, symmetric, so you are going to have the same area when you take their product.
So what we see is, every interval, over every interval, when you go from 2 to 3, is going to be...
First of all, it's clearly going, the integral from 2 to 3 is clearly the same thing as the integral
from 0 to 1, both functions look identical over that integral, over that interval.
But it will also be the same as going from 1 to 2. Because it's completely symmetric, when you, when you take
the product of the functions, that function will be completely symmetric around this axis. So the integral
from here to here will be the same as the integral from there to there. So with that said, we can rewrite
this thing over here, So we want to evaluate pi squared over 10 times the integral from -10 to 10 of
f(x) cos(pi*x), using the logic we just talked about, this is going to be the same thing as being equal
to pi squared over 10, pi squared over 10, times the integral, well, times the integral, of, from 0 to 1
but 20 times that. Because we have 20 integers between -10 and 10. We have 20 intervals of length 1.
So times 20, times the integral, times the integral, from 0 to 1, of f(x), of f(x) cos(pi*x) dx. Forgot
to write, forgot to write the dx over there. I want to make sure you understand, cause this is really
the hard part of the problem - just realizing that the integral over this interval is just one-twentieth
of the whole thing, because over every interval from 0 to 1, it's going to be the, the integral is going
to evaluate to the same thing as going from 1 to 2, which will be the same thing as going from 2 to 3,
or going from -2 to -1, So in stead of doing the whole interval from negative to the 10, we are just
doing 20 times the interval from 0 to 1. From -10 to 10, you actually have 20, you, you, there's a difference
of 20 here, so we are multiplying by 20. And this simplifies it a good bit. First of all, this part over
here simplifies to 20/10 = 2. So it's 2 pi squared, so it becomes 2 pi squared - that's just this part
over here, times the integral from 0 to 1, now from 0 to 1, what is f(x)? We just figured it out. From
0 to 1, f(x) is just (1-x). f(x) is just (1-x) from 0 to 1, times cos(pix), cos(pix), dx. And now we
just have to evaluate this integral right over here. So let's do that. So (1-x) times cos(pi*x) is the
same thing as cos(pix) - x cos(pix). Now, this right here, taking the anti-deri... Let's take the,
we're going to take the, well let's just focus on taking the anti-deri, This is pretty easy, but let's
try to do this one, cause it seems a little bit more complicated. So let's take the anti-derivative of
x cos(pi*x) dx and what should jump in your mind is that well yeah, this isn't that simple, but if I
were already able to take the derivative of x, that would simplify, it's very easy to take the anti derivative
of cos(pi*x) without making it more complicated. So may be integration by parts. And remember, integration
by parts tells us that the integral, I'll write it up here, the integral of u dv = uv minus the integral of v du
And we'll apply that here. But there's, I have done many many videos where I prove this and show examples
of exactly what that means. But let's apply it right over here. And in general, we are going to take the
derivative of whatever the u thing is. We want u to be something that's simpler when I take the derivative.
And then we are going to take the anti derivative of dv - so we want something that does not become more
complicated when I take the anti derivative. So the thing that becomes simpler when I take its derivative
is x. So if I said u = x, then clearly, du = just dx, or you say du/dx = 1, so du = dx, and then dv,
then dv is going to the the rest of this, this whole thing over here is going to be dv. dv = (is equal
to) cos(pi*x) dx and so v, which is be the anti derivative of this, with respect to x, v is going to
be equal to 1/pi, 1/pi sin(pi*x). Right? If I took the derivative here, derivative of the inside, you
get a pi, times 1/pi, cancels out, derivative of sin(pix) becomes cos(pix). So that's our u, that's
our v, so this is going to be equal to, this is going to be equal to u times v, so it's equal to x,
this x, times this, so x/pi sin(pi*x) minus, minus, the integral, minus the integral of v, which is 1/pi
sin(pix) du. du is just dx. dx. And this is pretty straightforward. The anti derivative of sin(pix),
is 1/pi, or negative 1/pi cos(pi*x). And you could take the derivative if you don't believe me. You could
do, use substitution, but hopefully, you can start to do these things in your head. Especially if you
are going to take IIT joint entrance exam. So this whole expression is going to be, this part over here is
going to be x over pi sin(pi*x), and this over here is going to be, well you have the anti derivative
of sin(pix), 1/pi, negative 1/pi cos(pix), the negatives cancel out. So you have plus, and then you the 1/pi times 1/pi,
1/(pi squared) cos(pix). That's the anti derivative right there. You can verify. Derivative of cos(pix)
is going to be negative pi sin(pi*x), one pi will cancel out - here you get the negative sign, and you
have the sin(pi*x). So this is the anti derivative of that. And so if we want the anti derivative of
this whole thing right over here, this is, this is what we care about, from 0 to 1 dx. the anti derivative
of cos(pi*x), pretty straightforward. We have actually already done it right over here. It is 1/pi, 1/pi
sin(pix), that's this first term, and the anti derivative of x cos(pix) is this thing over here, but
we are subtracting it, so we will put a negative sign out front. So minus, x/pi sin(pi*x) minus 1/(pi squared)
cosine, of cosine, of pi*x, and of course we took the anti derivative, but it's a definite integral,
we need to evaluate it from 0 to 1, 0 to 1, and we don't want to figure out, forget, that 2 pi squared
out front, that 2 pi squared out front. So let's evaluate this. So the first thing we're going to have
1/pi sin(1pi), sin(1pi) = 0. So it's 0 minus 1/pi times sin(1*pi) again, that's again 0! Minus 1/(pi squared)
cos(pi), cosine of, or cos(1*pi), cos(pi) = negative 1, negative 1 times negative 1/(pi squared) is plus
1/(pi squared). So we have evaluated at 1. And from that we want to subtract it evaluated at 0. sin(0) = 0
Minus, this is clearly zero because you have a zero out front, minus zero, and then you have minus
cos(0), cos(0) is 1, so then you have a minus 1/(pi squared), 1/(pi squared), and so this term we could
just say this is a negative, these don't matter, negative, positive, positive, and we're just left with
a 1/(pi squared) plus 1/(pi squared) which is equal to, which is equal to, 2/(pi squared). That's what
this part evaluates to. It's 2/(pi squared), we can't forget, we can't forget, that we're going to multiply
this whole thing times 2 pi squared. So we're going to multiply the whole thing times two pi squared.
That's this thing out front here. And so the pi squared cancels out the pi squared, we're left with two
times two, which is equal to 4. And we're done. This thing that looked pretty complicated just evaluates out to 4!