Let's add something moving with a constant velocity of 5 m/s
and we're assuming it's moving to the right
just to give us a direction, because this is a vector quantity
so it's moving in that direction, right over there
And let me plot its velocity against time
so this is my velocity
I'm actually going to only plot the magnitude of velocity
and you can specify that like this: ||v||
so this is the magnitude of the velocity
And then, on this axis, I am going to plot time
So we have a constant velocity of 5 m/s
so its magnitude is 5 m/s, and it's constant, it's not changing
as the seconds ticks away, the velocity does not change
So it's just moving 5 m/s
Now, my question to you is: how far does this thing travel after 5 seconds?
So after 5 seconds, so this is 1s...2s...3s...4s...5s...right over here
So how far did this thing travel after 5 seconds
Well we can think about it two ways
1) We know that velocity is equal to displacement over change in time
and displacement is just change in position
so this is change in position over change in time
or 2) another way to think about it, if you multiply both sides by change in time
you get velocity times change in time, is equal to displacement
So what was the displacement over here?
Well I know what the velocity is, it's 5 m/s
5 m/s, that is the velocity (let me color-code this)
And we know what the change in time here is, it is 5 seconds
and so you get...the seconds cancel out with seconds...
you get 5 *5 = 25 meters
And that's pretty straight forward
but the slightly more interesting thing is
is that's exactly the area under this rectangle right over here
And what I want to show you in this video
that is in general, if you plot velocity, the magnitude of velocity
...so you could say speed versus time...
or let me just stay with the *magnitude of the velocity* versus time
the area under that curve is going to be the distance traveled (or the displacement)
because displacement is just the velocity times the change in time
so if you just take out a rectangle right over there
So let me draw a slightly different one where velocity is changing
so let me draw a different situation where you have a constant acceleration
the acceleration over here is going to be 1 m/s/s, so 1 m/s^2
and let me draw the same type of graph
(although it's going to look a little different now)
So this is my velocity axis
(I'll give myself a little bit more space)
I'm just going to draw the magnitude of the velocity
and this right over here is my time axis
so this is time, let me mark some stuff off here
so...1...2...3...4...5...6...7...8...9...10
and...1...2...3...4...5...6...7...8...9...10
and the magnitude of the velocity is going to be measured in m/s
and the time is going to be measured in seconds
So what's going to happen here?
Assuming that we start with...
so my initial velocity, or I could say the magnitude of my initial velocity
so just my initial speed, you could say, this is just a fancy way of saying my initial speed...
...is zero
So my initial speed is 0
so after 1 second, what's going to happen?
After 1 second, I'm going 1 m/s faster
so now I'm going 1 m/s. After 2 seconds what's happened?
Well now I'm going another 1 m/s faster than that
After another second, if I go forward in time
if change in time is 1 second, then I'm going a second faster than that
And if you remember the idea of slope from your Algebra 1 class
that's exactly what acceleration is, in this diagram right over here
We know that acceleration is equal to...change in velocity over change in time
over here change in time is along the x-axis
so this right over here is a change in time
and this right over here is a change in velocity
When we plot velocity (or the magnitude of velocity) relative to time
the slope of that line is the acceleration
and since we're assuming the acceleration is constant
we have a constant slope
so we have just a line here, we don't have a curve
Now what I want to do is think about a situation
let's say that we accelerate at 1 m/s^2...and we do it for
so the change in time is going to be 5 seconds
and my question to you is: how far have we traveled?
Which is a slightly more interesting question than what we've been asking so far
So we start off with an initial velocity of 0
and then for 5 seconds, we accelerate at 1 m/s^2
so 1...2...3...4...5...so this is where we are
so after 5 seconds, we know our velocity
our velocity is now 5 m/s
But how far have we traveled?
So we can think about it a little bit visually
we could say, look, we could try to draw rectangles over here
we were at, maybe right over here we had a velocity of 1 m/s
so if I say 1 m/s times a second, that'll give me a little bit of distance...
and the next one I have a little bit more of distance...
calculated the same way. I could keep drawing these rectangles here
But then you're like...Wait! Those rectangles are missing...
because I wasn't...for the whole second...I wasn't only going 1 m/s...
I kept accelerating, so actually maybe I should split up the rectangles
I could split up the rectangles even more
So maybe I go, every half-second
so on this half-second, I was going at this velocity
and I go at that velocity for half a second
velocity times the time will give me the displacement
and then I do it for the next half second
same exact idea here, it'll give me the displacement
so on and so forth
I think what you see is your getting...
is the smaller the rectangles you try to make here
the closer you're going to get to the area under this curve
And just like the situation here, this area under the curve is going to be the distance traveled
and lucky for us, this is just going to be a triangle
and we know how to figure out the area for a triangle
so the area of a triangle = (1/2) * base * height
which hopefully makes sense to you
because if you just multiply base * height
you get the area for the entire rectangle, and the triangle is exactly half of that
So the distance traveled in this situation
or I should say the displacement
just because we want to make sure we're focused on vectors
the displacement here is going to be
(or I should say the magnitude of the displacement...which is the same thing as the distance)
is going to be 1/2 times the base...which is 5 seconds
times the height...which is 5 meters per second
...times 5 m/s (let me do that in another color)
the seconds cancel out with seconds
and we're left with (1/2) * 5 * 5 meters
so it's (1/2) * 25, which is equal to 12.5 meters
and so there's an interesting thing here
there's a couple of interesting things
hopefully you realize that if you're plotting velocity versus time
1) the area under the curve, given a certain amount of time, tells you how far you have traveled
2) the other interesting thing is that the slope of the curve tells you your acceleration
What's the slope over here (left)?
Well, it's completely flat, and that's because the velocity isn't changing
so in this situation, we have a constant acceleration
the magnitude of that acceleration is exactly zero
our velocity is not changing
here (right) we have an acceleration of 1 m/s^2
and that's why the slope of this line right over here is 1
the other interesting thing, is that even if you have constant acceleration
you can still figure out the distance by just taking the area under the curve...like this
so we were able to figure out...we were able to get 12.5 meters
The last thing I want to introduce you to...
(actually let me just do it in the next video)
and I'll introduce to you the idea of *average velocity*
now that we feel comfortable with the idea that
the distance you traveled is the area under this velocity versus time curve