Let's say I go to the fruit store today and they
have a sale on guavas.
Everything is thirty percent off.
This is for guavas.
And it's only today.
Only today.
So I say, you know what, let me go buy a bunch of guavas.
So I go and I buy six guavas.
So I buy six guavas.
And it ends up, when I go to the register, and we're
assuming no tax, it's a grocery and I live in a state where
they don't tax groceries.
So for the six guavas, they charge me, I get the thirty percent off.
They charge me $12.60.
$12.60.
So this is the thirty percent off sale price on six guavas.
I go home, and then my wife tells me, you know, Sal, can
you go get two more guavas tomorrow?
I say, sure.
So the next day I go and I want to buy two more guavas.
So, two guavas.
But now the sale is off.
There's no more thirty percent.
That was only that first day that I bought the six.
So how much are those two guavas going to cost me?
How much are those two guavas going to cost at full price?
At full price?
So, a good place to start is, to think about how much
would those six guavas have cost us at full price?
This is the sale price, right here?
This is the sale price.
How much would those have cost me at full price?
So let's do a little bit of algebra here.
Pick a suitable color for the algebra.
Maybe this grey color.
So, let's say that x is equal to the cost of six guarvas.
six guavas, at full price.
So, essentially, if we take thirty percent off of this,
we should get $12.60.
So let's do that.
So if we have the full price of six guavas, we're going
to take thirty percent off of that.
So that's the same thing as 0.30.
Or I could just write 0.3.
I could ignore that zero if I like.
Actually, let me write it like this.
My wife is always bugging me to write zeroes before decimals.
So that's the full price of 6 guavas minus 0.30 times
the full price of guavas.
Some I'm just taking thirty percent off of the full price,
off of the full price.
This is how we figure out the sale price.
This is going to be equal to that $12.60 right there.
That's going to be equal to $12.60.
I just took thirty percent off of the full price.
And now we just do algebra.
We could imagine there's a one in front -- you know, x
is the same thing as onex.
So 1x minus 0.3x is going to be equal to 0.7x.
So we get 0.7x, or we could say 0.70 if you like.
Same number.
Point, or 0.7x, is equal to 12.60.
And once you get used to these problems, you might just skip
straight to this step right here.
Where you say, seventy percent of the full price is equal to
my sale price, right?
I took thirty percent off.
This is seventy percent of the full price.
You might just skip to this step once you get used to these
problems in a little bit.
And now we just have to solve for x.
Divide both sides by 0.7, so you get x is equal to
12.60 divided by 0.7.
We could use a calculator, but it's always good to get a
little bit of practice dividing decimals.
So let's do that.
So we get 0.7 goes into 12.60.
Let's multiply both of these numbers by ten, which is what we
do when we move both of their decimals one to the right.
So the 0.7 becomes a 7.
Ignore that right there.
The 12.60 becomes 126, put the decimal right there.
Decimal right there.
And we're ready to just do straight up long division.
So this is now a seven, not a .seven.
So seven goes into twelve one time.
one times seven is seven.
twelve minus seven is five.
Bring down the six.
seven goes into fifty-six eight times.
eight times seven is fifty-six.
And then we have no remainder.
So it's eighteen, and there's nothing behind the decimal point.
So it;s eighteen, in our case, $eighteen.
So x is equal to $eighteen.
Remember what x was? x was the full price of six guavas.
x was the full price of six.
x is the full price of six guavas.
Now, the question is, how much will two guavas cost
me at the full price?
Well, this is full price of six.
So you immediately could figure out what's the
full price of one guava.
You divide eighteen by six.
So eighteen divided by six is $three.
That's $three per guava at full price.
And they're asking us, we want two guavas.
So two guavas is going to be two times $three, so this
is going to be $six.
$six.
Another way you could have done it, you could have just said,
hey, six at full price are going to cost me $eighteen.
two is one / three of six.
So one / three of $eighteen is $six.
So, just to give a quick review what we did.
We said the sale price on six guavas, $12.60.
That's thirty percent off the full price.
Or you could say this is seventy percent of the full price.
seventy percent of the full price.
And so you could say, thirty percent -- so if you say x is the full price
of six guavas, you could say the full price of six guavas minus
30% of the full price of 6 guavas is equal to 12.60, and
that's equivalent to saying, 70% of the full price is 12.60.
You divided -- then we just solved this algebraically.
Divide both sides by 0.7, and then we got x, the full price
of six guavas, is $eighteen, or that's $three per guava or $six for two.
Anyway, hopefully you found that helpful.