Say you're me in your math class,
and you're supposed to be graphing functions.
As if there were some deep relationship
between y and x that your teacher just
won't stop gossiping about.
But, like most gossip, you really don't
care about y's unhealthy dependency on x.
Really y, get a life.
Luckily, your friend passes you a note.
You wait till the teacher is facing the board
and sneakily open it up.
And it's this proof that pi = 4
that you've seen billions of times on the Internet.
But because you're bored and
at least it's not graphing, you take
another look.
It's like this: start with a circle,
with diameter 1 and circumference pi.
Then draw a square around it.
The length of a side of the square is 1,
so the perimeter of the square is, of course, 4.
Now you start approaching a circle by
zig-zagging this perimeter.
This shape still has perimeter 4.
And we do it again, and it's still 4.
And again, and we approach a circle.
While the perimeter never changes.
So there, 4, pi equals 4.
Obviously there's something wrong here.
The circumference of a circle is pi but
pi is more like 3.14 numbers and less like 4.
So somehow what this process approaches is something that looks like a circle but is not a circle.
I mean, what does circle mean anyway?
There's this loopy line thing, and then there's this solid disc shape.
well there related an all there not the same mathematical object
this troll proof so much FUN because you repeat this zigzag move all the way to Zigfinity
it approaches the shape of a circle in a disc seance
an it approaches the area of a circle but it dose not approach a circle
its all crinceled up an if you imagined if you put a astral in this thing
an deflated it added as much air in it as you can wile keeping the primmer as 4
all the infinite ringcals would smooth out an you get a circle with a perimeter 4 an diameter 4 over pi
in fact you can inflate the square to get the same thing