Which of the following real numbers are irrational?
Well, irrational just means it's not rational.
It means that you cannot express it
as the ratio of two integers.
So let's see what we have here.
So we have the square root of eight over two .
So the square root of eight –
If you take the square root of a number
that is not a perfect square,
it is going to be irrational.
And then if you just take that irrational number,
and you multiply it, or you divided it
by any other numbers,
you're still going to get an irrational number.
So, the square root of eight is irrational.
[Even if] you divide that by two, it is still irrational.
So this is not rational.
Or another way of saying it – it is irrational.
Now you have pi.
3.14159 and It just keeps going on and on and on forever –
without ever repeating.
So, this is irrational –
probably the most famous of all the irrational numbers.
5.0.
Well, I can represent 5.0 as five over one.
So, 5.0 is rational.
It is not irrational.
0.325.
Well, this is the same thing as 325 over 1000.
So, I can clearly represent it as a ratio of integers.
So, this is rational –
just as I could represent 5.0 as five over one –
both of these are rational.
They are not irrational.
Here I have 7.7777 –
and just keeps going on and on and on and on forever.
And the way we denote that –
You could just say these dots that say
that the sevens keep going.
Or you could say 7.7 – and this line
shows the seven part – the second seven –
just keeps repeating on forever.
Now, if you have a repeating decimal –
In other videos, we'll actually convert them into fractions.
But a repeating decimal can be represented
as a ratio of two integers –
just as one third is equal to 0.333 – on and on and on.
Or I could say it like this:
I could say three repeating.
We can also do the same thing for that.
I won't do it here.
But this is rational – so it's not irrational.
8 1/2?
Well, that's the same thing –
8 1/2 is the same thing as 17 halves (17/2).
So, it's clearly rational.
So, the only two irrational numbers
are the first two right over here.