(Vi) Hey Two. (Two) Uh, uh, hey there Vi! Whats up with you?
(Vi) Oh, nothing. Just wanted to talk, I guess. (Two) Ow!, Ooo!
(Vi) Sorry Two, but you know, you look good this way, so,
symmetric and, fundamental. (Two)Oh, I guess. I just feel a little bit off when
I'm like this. (Vi) Oh nonsense. You know Two one of the things I like about you is that your just as twoish
no matter how you look. I mean your dependable; I like that in a person.
No matter what I do,you'll always be my Two. (Two) So, uh, Vi, is something bothering you?
(Vi) I don't know Two, life has been pretty crazy. It's just nice to have some constants in my life.
(Two) Well, you know, I'm always here for ya. (Vi) I know Two. So um, how have you been lately?
(Two) Well, same as ever really. (Vi) Uh, figures. Good old Two, your always just being yourself
you know, I don't have to worry I'm going to come home some day and your going to have changed
your values. Its not like some day I'll slit you into two halves and find your not 1 + 1, your always 1 + 1.
I like that about you. Its like, I don't know, your something that makes sense in this crazy
world. (Two) Umm, well. (Vi) You ever feel, kinda different from other numbers?
I mean your prime, but your even, your the first really numbery number, I mean, one is barely a number
its just like one. (Two) But all numbers are different, well Vi? (Vi) I guess, yeah, but don't you ever feel like
lonely or something? I guess that doesn't make sense, you're a number. (Two) Vi, are your sure
there's not something bothering you? (Vi) Uh, I guess I feel a little out of control lately, I've been traveling
and working, and I'm almost two years behind on emails. (Two) Two years you say? Is, is that a long
time? (Vi) Oh, for an email reply, yeah two years is huge! (Two)Well that makes me feel good doesn't it!
(Vi) Well, I mean two years isn't long in terms of... Uh, never mind. That's another thing I like about you,
your so patient, I never to feel rushed with you, its nice to have something solid in my life. Something I
feel in control of. (Two) Well, thanks, uh, I guess. (Vi) And I've so busy lately, trying to way too many things
at once, and I'm involved in all these projects... (Two) Now, come on Vi. It can't be that bad... (Vi) And
there's all this responsibility, and everyone is trying to use me for their own purposes. (Two) Well, you know I - ouch. I can't say I have a
whole lot of sympathy, I mean, I'm pretty busy too you know. I get used quite a bit. (Vi) Yeah, in
preschoolers homework and the titles of bad movie sequels. (Two) Uh, how have you known, I'm in a
great many famous books. And, and diagrams... I'm in a lot of really good diagrams and graphs. And I'm
quite popular with young adults these days. You know I have a pretty good gig with this whole text
messaging thing. Its hard work keeping up with all that. (Vi) Yeah, I know, but, Two, your a number and
can only be in one place at a time. (Two) Well, maybe I'm tired of it too. Maybe tomorrow some kid
will be, trying to add one plus one and I'll just, refuse to show up! (Vi) But you are one plus one, and you
can't just not show up your already there. (Two) Yeah, and maybe you should think of that next time before
you start whining. I mean it isn't that hard. You just do what you have to do. Show up where you have to
show up. There's no point in stressing over it. (Vi) You know Two, that actually isn't bad advice. You're
right. I should just do stuff and set go without imagining all of it stacked into a precarious pile
looming over my near future. Might as well live in the present. After all, I can't not show up, I'm already
here. (Two) Well, not really. (Vi) I'm glad we had this chance to just sit and chat like this. You're a good
number. (Two) That's very kind of you to say. (Vi) I'm going to seize the present moment and go do some
important Vi stuff. I'll see you later Two. (Two) Well, uh, hang on, there's just a few other... Hey, where
are you going? There's a lot of cool stuff you don't know about me yet! Are you listening? Hello?
Anybody there? Well, well, I just think go hang out with Pi then.