What we're going to do in this video are some real quick tests to see if
these three random numbers are divisible by any of these numbers here
now I'm not going to focus a lot on the "why" of why they're divisible
but rather just to give you a sense of how do you actually test to see this is divisible by two
or five or nine, or ten.
so let's get started
so to test whether any of these are really divisible by two,
you really just gotta look at the ones place
and see if the ones place is divisible by 2
and right over here, it is divisible by two,
so this thing is gonna be divisible by two
Zero is considered to be divisible by two
so this is going to be divisible by two.
Another way to think about it is
is if you have an even number over here,
and Zero is considered an even number,
then you're going to be divisible by two.
So over here,
Do not have a number that is divisible by two
this is five, so this is not divisible by two
so I won't write any two there.
we've gone through the twos,
now let's go through the threes.
so to figure out if you are divisible by three,
you really just have to add up the digits
and figure out if the sum is divisible
by three.
Do that. So if I do 2 + 7 + 9
actually let me just write it out. +9 + 5
+8 +8. What's this going to be?
2 + 7 is 9, 9 + 9 is 18, + 9 is
27, + 5 is 32,
+ 8 is 40, + 8 is 48
and 48 is divisible by three,
but in case you're not sure,
since this is equal to 48, in case you're not sure
whether this is divisible by 3,
you can just add these digits up again.
So 4 + 8
is equal to 12, and 12 clearly
is divisible by 3.
And if you're not even sure there,
you can add those digits up.
1 + 2 is equal to 3.
So this is divisible by 3.
This right over here, let's add up the digits!
5 + 6 = 11
11 + 7 = 18, + 0 is 18
and if you want to add the 1 + 8 in 18,
you get 9
so the digits add up to 9.
So these add up to nine.
They add to 18, which is clearly divisible by 3,
and these two things will add up to 9.
So the important thing to know, is that when you add up all the digits, the sum
is divisible by three
So this is divisible by three, as well.
Let's add up these digits.
1 + 0 + 0 + 7 =8, + 6 = 14
+ 5 = 19
So 19 is not
divisible by 3. So this one we're not gonna write a three by there.
It's not divisible by 3.
Let's try 4.
Think about four, you just have to think about the last 2 digits,
To see are the last 2 digits
divisible by four.
Immediately, you could look at this one over here,
see it's an odd number,
if it's not divisible by 2, it's definitely not going to be
divisible by four.
This one is not divisible by any of the first four numbers
88. Is that divisible by 4?
You can do that in your head. That's 4 x 22!
So this is divisible by 4.
Now let's see, 4 goes into 60 15 times
and then to go from 60 to 70 you have to go another 10,
so it's not divisible by four.
You could even try to divide it out yourself.
Four goes into 70, 1 time, subtract get 30,
7 times, multiply, subtract, get a 2 over here as your remainder.
So it is not divisible by 4,
Now let's move on to five.
And you are probably already very familiar with this,
if your final digit is a 5 or 0, you are divisible by five.
So this one's not divisible by 5.
This one is divisible by 5.
And this you have a 5, as your ones digit, so finally this is divisible by something,
it's divisible by 5.
Now the number 6. The simple way to think about divisibility by 6
is that you have to be divisible by both 2 and 3,
to be divisible by 6, because
the prime factorization of 6 is
2 times 3. So here we're divisible by 2 and 3, so
we're going to be divisible by 6.
Here we're divisible by 2 and 3, so we're divisible by 6!
And if you were just divisible by only a 2
or a 3, you wouldn't be able to do this
you have to have both 2 and 3
and here you're divisible by neither 2 or 3,
so you're not going to be divisible by 6.
Now let's do the test for 9.
The test for 9 is very similar to the test for 3
Sum up all the digits. If the sum is divisible by 9,
then you're there.
We already summed up the digits here,
48 is not divisible by 9,
if you're not sure, you can add up the digits there and get 12,
12 is definitely not divisible by 9.
So this thing right over here is not divisible by 9.
This one over here we added up all the digits and got 18,
18 is divisible by 9.
So this one is divisible by 9.
And this one over here, you don't even have to add them up,
because we already know it's not divisible by 3,
if it's not divisible by 3, it can't be divisible by 9
but if you did add up the digits, you'd get 19
which is not divisible by 9.
So this also is not divisible by 9.
And finally, divisibility by 10.
And this is the easiest one of all.
Cause you just have to see if you have a zero
in the ones place.
You clearly do not have a zero in the ones place here.
You do have a zero in the ones place here.
So you are divisible by 10 here,
are then finally you don't have a zero in the ones place
here, so you're not going to be divisible by 10.
Another way you could think about it,
you have to be divisible by both 2 and 5
to be divisible by 10.
Here you are divisible by 5, but not 2.
Obviously the easiest way is just to see if you have
a zero in the ones place.