in this chart right here were given out scores on midterm and final exams
were the vertical axis is the scoring points
and each of this pairs of bar charts give us for an individual
where the blue bars for example how he show
dead on the midterm
the yellow is how you on the final for emily the blues how they she did on the
midterm yellows how she did on the final
we have a bunch of interesting questions here
the first question what was the median. What was the median score for the final exam?
so this is a review medium literally means what was the middle score.
really we should list all the scores for the final exam and sort them in order and and figure out what the middle score actually was
soul so they're all the scores on final exam, so scores
scores on the final exam so you have a hundred here is shawn got a hundred on the final exam remember this yellow bars the final exam
so there's a hundred emily also got a hundred on the final exam looks like it wasn't easy final exam
daniels about a hundred on the final exam
and then what's the jessica alot section got a seven five
seventy-five and william got an eighty
so for a sword these in order to assume it is an increasing order you could be could rival the loan score was a seventy five
then you have any eighty and then you have three hundreds, one hundred another hundred and another hundred
so there's five scores right over here so you will have a middle look at any given number than you would take the mean of the two center of the two center values
but here you have one center value when you when you order like this it's pretty clear that your center value your middle value is one hundred
so the median score for the final exam is one hundred and that's because you had so many hundreds here that the media in the middle score was still a hundred
what is the main arrange the mid range of the midterm scorers
alluded blue one honor of the color of the bars for the midterm
so the main range is the media your highest and lowest scores
was collected this was going to the mid range
the mid range if you can view it as the arithmetic mean or the average of your highest and lowest scores so the mid range of midterms
of made
so let's see the highest midterm score looking at the blue the highest one is right here
so i've just got a hundred on the midterm so that's your high school work
your lowest score on the midterm looks like this one out of your daniel got a sixty
got a sixty and so the mid range is going to be the mean the arithmetic mean of these two numbers so you add a hundred plus sixty divide by two you get one sixty over to or eighty
so this right over here it is going to be
what was the average student score for the final exam
pool for that we just have to add up the scores on the final exams and divide by the number of scores we have
so we might be able to that in our heads footsie close wicked magistrate of first years we have one hundred
plus one hundred plus one hundred plus seventy five plus eighty
so all of that divided by
all of that divided by five they'll give us our average someone told you have written about getting more information the probly talking about the arithmetic mean
so this is going to be three hundred plus, let's see three hundred plus, uh... another hundred fifty-five system before fifty-five over five this issue coating for fifty five over five
and c_-five this is going to be equal to
five goes in let me write down here this is equal to five goes into forty-five or four hundred fifteen ninety times and two five once this is going to be equal to ninety one
so the average score for the final exam is aiding ninety one
what was the motive for the final exam scores
so the mode is the most common score so once again we've listed all of them it's pretty clear that the most common score years a hundred a hundred shows up three times all seventy five alicia someone's an att_ only shows at once
so if you're the most common score is a hundred chills three-time
what does the range of the midterm scores
so the rangers literally the difference between the highest score and to the lowest score
so the high score we are a figured out and this is for the midterm the midterm so the highest score is a hundred
and we're gonna subtract from that the low score which was a sixty
so the range is equal to forty the mid range was the average of these two things the range is just the difference between the two
so the range of the midterm scores is forty and were done.