Up until the 1970's, cryptography had been based on symmetric keys.
That is, the sender encrypts their message using a specific key
and the receiver decrypts using an identical key.
As you may recall, encryption is a mapping from some message,
using a specific key, to a cyphertext message.
To decrypt the cyphertext you use the same key to reverse the mapping.
So for Alice and Bob to communicate securely,
they must first share identical keys.
However establishing a shared key is often impossible,
if Alice and Bob can't physically meet,
or requires extra communications overhead, when using the Diffie-Hellman key exchange.
Plus, if Alice needs to communicate with multiple people, perhaps she's a bank,
then she's going to have to exchange distinct keys with each person.
Now she'll have to manage all of these keys
and send thousands of messages just to establish them.
Could there be a simpler way?
In 1970 James Ellis a British engineer and mathematician
was working on an idea for non-secret encryption.
It's based on a simple yet clever concept.
Lock and unlock are inverse operations.
Alice could buy a lock, keep the key
and send the opened lock to Bob.
Bob then locks his message and sends it back to Alice.
No keys are exchanged.
This means she could publish the lock widely
and let anyone in the world use it to send her a message.
And she now only needs to keep track of a single key.
Ellis never arrived at a mathematical solution,
though he added an intuitive sense of how it should work.
The idea is based on splitting a key into two parts:
an encryption key and a decryption key.
The decryption key performs the inverse or undo operation,
which was applied by the encryption key.
To see how inverse keys could work, let's do a simplified example with colours.
How could Bob send Alice a specific colour
without Eve, who is always listening, intercepting it?
The inverse of some colour is called the complementary colour,
which when added to it produces white, undoing the effect of the first colour.
In this example we assume that mixing colours is a one-way function,
because it's fast to mix colours and output a third and it's much slower to undo.
Alice first generates her private key by randomly selecting a colour, say red.
Next, assume Alice uses a secret colour machine
to find the exact complement of her red,
and nobody else has acces to this.
This results in cyan, which she sends to Bob as her public key.
Let's say Bob wants to send a secret yellow to Alice.
He mixes this with her public colour and sends the resulting mixture back to Alice.
Now, Alice ads her private colour to Bob's mixture.
This undoes the effect of her public colour,
leaving her with Bob's secret colour.
Notice Eve has no easy way to find Bob's yellow,
since she needs Alice's private red to do so.
This is how it should work.
However, a mathematical solution was needed to make this work in practice.