What i want to do with this video is step through the program that we wrote in the previous video
to really understand what's happening line-by-line
you get a little bit of an intuitive understanding for for-loops and variables
and we're going to do it for a specific example
we're going to do an example where the user inputs
so when the user's prompted to input a number the user will input the number "3"
we're just going to assume that and i've picked a low number so that we don't have to keep looping through
this forever so this video can be of a reasonable length
so right when that happens when the user inputs the number "3" it assigns the variable number
to be equal to "3" and there's 2 ways that you can think about this
i tend do when i do in any programming language when i think of a variable
i tend to view it as a bucket so i have a bucket called number
and in that bucket, when the user inputs a "3", if the user inputs a "3"
i'm sticking a "3" in that bucket
Python is a little bit different than some languages and the more correct way
and they're both kind of intuitive, if you think about it, a viewing a variable
in Python is to think of the variable as referring to the 3
and i say that, because in Python, if you change a variable's
ĺet's say right under this we wrote numbers equal to 2
but we didn't do that, but if we said numbers equal to 2, what Python
does is it actually leaves that 3 there in memory and then it would then point to the number 2
instead, it wouldn't obliterate the 3 and just put a 2 there
the 3 still exists, and that's important when we
start doing more complex or nuanced things with more fancy data types
but let's rewind all of this, for the sake of this program you can view it either way
a bucket with a 3 in it or you can view it as a label that is referring to
a 3 someplace in the computer's memory
now, the next thing that happens is that we have another variable
called product, and we assign product to be equal to 1
so i'm gonna do the same two representations
so we've set up another bucket here called product
and we're putting 1 in that bucket
or you could say that product is a variable, it's a label that is referring to
a 1, and then we get to our for-loop, and this is probably the confusing part
so we have "for i in range(number)", and number in this case
so literally the interper say "what's the number" , well in this case the number is 3
so this is going to be evaluated as range of 3
this is going to be evaluated as "range of 3"
in our particular example
and once again, how did the interpret know that? it said range of number
number's a variable, look up number variable, okay, 3 sitting in it
so i'm going to put a 3 right in there
or look up the number variable, the number variable is pointing to the number 3
so i'm just going to put a 3 here and take a range of 3
and we saw in the last video, that if you evaluate just range of 3
range of 3 is equal to a sequence of numbers 0,1,2, so it creates
a sequence of 3 numbers, starting at 0, up to that number -1
and what the for-loop does, is every time we go through the for-loop
it executes this code, that's inside the for-loop
and we know it's inside the for-loop, because we indented it
and the most used convention in Python is that you don't use the tab,
you press space 4 times, and that tells the interpreter
anything at this level in indention happened every time we go to the for-loop
and when we start the for-loop, the i-variable is going to start at 0
so the first time we go to the for-loop, i is going to be the first element
in this sequence, then when we go to the for-loop again
i is going to be the second element of the sequence
and then when we go to the for-loop again, i is going to be the third element
in the sequence, and then we go to the for-loop, and it will
try to assign i to another element in the sequence
and say "hey, wait, there are no more element in the sequence"
and then it will break out of the for-loop, and then continue on
with the rest of the program
so given that, let's think about what happens for the particular
example, where the user inputed a 3
so range of number is going to evaluate
as 0,1,2
so it's going to be 0,1,2
and the first time into the loop, i, so i'm going to use this
convention right over here, the first time through the loop, i is going to
refer to the 0
or if we use this convention over here, the first time, as we go through
the loop i, could be viewed as a bucket, that is going to be
assigned to the first element of the range of 3
the first element of the sequence
it is going to be 0
and then we execute what's in the loop
we assign, we reassign product to be something new right over here
and what is this something new? the first time we go through the for-loop
i is 0, 0+1 is 1, so the first time through the loop, this is going to be 1
product is 1, this is the first time we go through the loop, let me do it in the same color
so i is 0+1, so we get 1, 1x1 is 1, so product will be assigned to be 1
so product will be reassigned to be 1
which really isn't going to change anything, because it's already 1
so it was 1 before we multiplied it by 1 and reassigned it to be 1
so i could cross out 1, it's not going to be 1 again, but i'll just leave it as 1
or we can just say it's going to be reassigned to be 1, so
nothing really has changed that first time through the loop
but now interesting things are going to happen
so now we'll go back to the beginning of the loop, and now "i" will be the next element
in the loop, so now "i", it will be reassigned to be the next element in the loop
so now "i" will be 1, that's what the for-loop does, it makes "i" each of the items in the
sequence in order, going through them, and now we execute it again
now we go look at product times "i" + 1
product is still 1, "i" is now 1, so 1+1 is now going to be 2
so 1 times 2 is going to be our new product
so the new product, it was 1, for now we're multiplying it by 2 and
assigning it again to product so the new product is now going to be 2
so the product variable is now 2
and then now we try to loop again
and now this time, "i" will be the next element
"i" is going to be the next element in the sequence
right over here, or we could say that "i" is going to be reassigned
to 2, the next element in the sequence, and we try to evaluate it again
so now, we go into the for-loop, product is now 2, "i" is now 2
2+1 is 3, so this whole expression over here is 3, so we have
2, product is now 2 times "i" + 1, "i" is 2, so "i"+1 is 3
so you have 2 times 3 is now going to be 6
so the new product times "i" + 1 is now 6, so this is now going to be 6
and now we try to execute the for-loop again, and the for-loop is going to say
"hey, let me reassign "i" to be the next item in the sequence"
it tries to find the next item in the sequence, but it says
"wait, there is no next item in the sequence" so we're done executing our for-loop
so there's nothing left in our sequence, we're done with our for-loop
now we break out of it, and we go to the next line in the program
so the next line in the program is literally just "print the product"
and at this point, we just want to output the product
and the variable product is now 6
the variable product is now 6
actually, one thing i should have done this entire time
is, i was sticking with the bucket representation, but the product here is
starting to referring to 1, it got reassigned to 1, but then it got assigned
to 2, so then this reference went to 2, and then it got reassigned to to 6
then it got reassigned to 6, so if i were to be consistent with this
representation over here, every time product is referring to another number,
or it can be viewed as a bucket, for the sake of this program, where
it keeps getting reassigned, and what's cool about this, is when we're done
with this for-loop, the number that's sitting in the bucket product, the variable
product, or you could say, the number that the variable product
is referring to, is the factorial of the number that the person inputed
it's the factorial of 3, and if you remember, 3, the symbol for factorial
is an exclamation mark, is equal to 3 times 2 times 1