In the last video,
I realized that I made a mistake near the end,
but it's not a good one
because I copied down the wrong number
and then that led to the rest of
the problem not having the right values.
We figured out that the vertical component
of our velocity earlier in the video is
-26.03 m/s.
But then I somehow -
something happened in my brain-
and it became -29.03,
so this is not -29.03,
this is -26.03 m/s.
So the total velocity, we should have
26.03^2 over here,
and then if we evaluate that,
and I just did it on my calculator,
26.03^2 + 5.61 -
actually I did it wrong again,
so let me redo it-
so 26.03^2 + 5.21^2 under the radical
gives us 26.55.
So this right over here should be 26.55 m/s.
So that is the magnitude of our final velocity.
So that is the magnitude
of our total final velocity.
And the angle, since this is not 29.03,
this is 26.03,
we can say that the tangent of this angle, theta,
tangent of theta is equal to
the length of this vector right over here,
which is the opposite side, 26.03
over the length of this vector here,
which is 5.21,
or we could say,
we could say,
if we take the inverse tangent
of both sides of this,
that the angle is equal to
the inverse tangent, or the arctangent of
26.03/5.21
and that gives us -
we have the inverse tangent of
26.03/5.21 - gives us roughly 78.7 degrees.
So the angle here is 78.7 degrees.
And it's below the horizontal,
so we can say that the vector,
the final velocity vector,
has a magnitude of 26.55 m/s
at a direction of 78.7 degrees
below the horizontal,
so I hope I didn't confuse you
too much with that
mistake at the end of that video.