Use a calcuator to find log base e of 67 to the nearest thousandth
So just as a reminder, e is one of these crazy numbers that shows up
in natures and finance and all these things and it is approximately equal to 2.71 and it just keeps on and on
so you could view log
base is as 67 and you say "What does 'e' mean?" Well, e is just a number
just like pi is just a number
This is really the same thing as saying log base 2.71 and teh actual number
so you have to write all the digits that just keep on going forever
and never repeat- of 67. So what power do I have to raise e to
to get to 67? So another way of saying that is that if this is
equal to x, e to the x is equal to 67, we need to figure out what x is
Now, traditionally, you will never see people write log base e even though
e is one of the most common bases to take a log of
so the reason you wouldn't see log base e written this way
is that log base e is the natural logarithm
and I think that's used because e shows up so many times in nature.
So log base e of 67, another way of saying that- or seeing that- and the more typical
way of seeing that is the natural log. This is ln (I think this is from french or something)
So this is the same thing as saying log base e
of 67. This is saying that exact same thing.
So what power do I have to raise e to to get 67. When you see this 'ln', is literally means
'log base e'. Now, they let us use a calculator and that's good
because I don't know off the top of my head what power you
have to raise 2.71 and so forth to to get 67.
So we'll get our calculator out. So we'll get our TI-85 out.
And different calculators will have different ways of doing it.
If you have a graphing calulator like this, you can literally type in the
statement, natural log of 67 and evaluate it.
So here, this is the button for natural log, 'log naturale (fr),' maybe.
Ln of 67, and then you press 'enter' and it will give you the answer.
If you don't have a graphing calculator, you might have to press 67
and then press 'ln' to give you the answer. But if you have
a graphing calculator you can jsut type it in the same
way as you would write it out.
So 4.20469... and we want to roud to the nearest thousandth.
So this is the thousandth place, this 4, the digit after that is 5
or larger, it's a 6, so we are going to round up.
So this is approximately equal to 4.205
and it actualy makes a lot of sense, because we know that e is greater than 2
and it is less than 3
and if you think about 2 to the 4th power, that gets you to 16
and 3 to the fourth power gets you to 81.
67 is between 16 and 81, and e is between 2 and 3
so at least if feels right
that 2.71^4 should get you pretty close to 3^4.