We're in the first room of the Uffizi
and we're looking at the absolutely monumental painting by Cimabue of the
Madonna enthroned originally for Santa Trinita
right here in Florence and it's about 12 feet high
its huge and it's so big because that's a big church Santa Trinita
and it would've needed to be able to be seen from the back of the church
and it's important to remember that it would've been behind an altar
raised up from the ground in the space of a church very different
than the space that we see it in today, so all of that gold would've glistened
in a very different way and kind of important because the church
is relatively dark and so that gold would've been really wonderful and luminous
but ofcourse it also has an important symbolic value
that's the light of heaven
one of the things that we look at when we think about Cimabue
I think going back to Vasari who really starts his history with a renaissance
of Cimabue is some hints of the beginnings of the renaissance
and so when we look at this we begin to see some of that illusionism
that we think about with the renaissance
right now ofcourse this is 2020 hindsight and - exactly - Vasari
was certainly not a careful art historian but I think that there
is a space that she can sit in
it's not a rational space -no- and you had mentioned
that this is the space of heaven and so I think there's
a certain degree of liaisons now this is a painting
that would've been hung fairly high and yet somehow
we're looking down at the step on which the Virgin's
feet rest, we're looking actually down on the seat
but we're looking across at the old testiment prophits down below
and up at Mary herself and so there's all kinds of contradictions here
right and yet we can read that the sides of her throne are closer
to us, that the parts of the throne by her shoulders are
set back into space, and theres even a kind of velocity that moves
her eye back into space if you look at the lines that are painted
on the steps for instance
where the virgins feet rest, it does bring us back into space
and it creates a kind of visual pathway
and those figures of the prophits in the fort run are even closer
still now let's start down with them, okay, because
this is curious they're in a kind of impossible space in the
basement under the throne, I mean what is that? (laughs)
they did the predict the coming of Christ right?
okay so this is very much a Christian perspective and the
Christians are looking back to the old testament
laying literally the foundation upon which Christianity is built
so I guess it makes sense that they're below
they're holding scrolls as opposed to books and that's how
we can recognize instantly that they're not the evangelists
that they're actually from the old testament
Mary was an enormously important figure at this time
Christ was a little terrifying to the medieval mind and Mary grew
an importance what is known as the cult of the Madonna
the cult of the Virgin as an intercessor to her son
that is people would pray to the Virgin Mary and hopefully
she would speak maybe to God on your behalf
that's right and that's exactly how Cimabue shows Mary to us here
she's pointing to Christ in a way addressing the viewer
and then pointing to the Christ child her son and saying this
is the pathway to God
the pathway to salvation is through Christ
now Christ for his part is looking back to us, you're absolutely right
his two fingers are raised as if he's blessing us
now the rendering of Christ is really interesting because of course
compared to Mary he's quite small and he's the appropriate scale
the problem is, atleast to our modern eyes is that he doesn't
look like an infant his head is small in relationship to his body
and he kind of has the features of a grown man -yeah- except in a little baby
and one of the ways our historians have acknowledged this
is that this is a symbolic rendering that Christ is shown as
a man of wisdom and age is sometimes a way of expressing that
symbolically then here is an all knowing God but here
is God as a child
although later in the renaissance that can eventually
dissipate and we'll see a chubby baby in it's place
so i'm noticing that the long gated features of Mary
her long nose the sort of stylization around her eyes
those almond shapes, her very elongated hand and that's coming from
a Byzantine tradition that Cimabue is painting in
what's interesting Zantham which had been a source of
power and culture in the east actually a lot of the artists
and intellectuals had come to Italy in part because of invasions
and so there was at this moment at the end of 1200s at the beginning
of the 1300s there was this infusion of intellectual capital
of artistic tradition that comes into Italy and really revitalizes
the traditions here
so sometimes our historians refer to this period as the Italo Byzantine
on the other hand Cimabue is doing things that point toward the renaissance
he's using gold lines to articulate the folds of drapery
but those lines instead of just sort of being flat and decorative
really begin to describe a sense of the three dimensional folds of drapery
and Mary herself begins to sort of fill out and be a little bit less
of that thin elongated figure without any mass that we see before this
we do have a sense of Mary actually holding the Christ child to some extent
you know, keeping her -it's a little weightless-
yeah but the figures are weightless and the striations
of those gold lines that you were speaking about help to emphasize
that almost two dimensionality of those figures
but there are traces of chiaroscuro in the neck and the nose
perhaps in the faces of the angels
you know these are hints, they're subtle but ofcourse we can look
back now and see that this is the beginning of a long
development of increasing naturalism which people like Vasari
will look back to Cimabue as the root of
look for example the two foreground angels on either side of the throne
half of their body's behind the throne
giving us a real illusion of space and their foot comes forward
and on the left the angels foot comes even a little off the throne
but they are still very decorative and one could only imagine
what those angels in the background are actually standing on (laughs)
and you know the throne itself is so decorative
maybe we should just take one moment and talk about the fact
that this is on wood that this is painted with tempera
that the artist is using very thin gold leaves, so that's real gold there
that's been attached to the wood surface
and we shouldn't underestimate the effort that it takes to create
a panel of wood that can survive for so many hundreds of years
without warping without cracking significantly
and so there's a lot of workmanship here that sometimes i think
in the era of 21st century go to the art store and buy your supplies
we kind of forget about this "handmadeness"
that we have here, in all aspects of the materials
and I think that's an important point there was not so much the seperation
between the art and the craft as we understand it now
you know he is painter and craftsman
mixing his paints, working on the wood panel, preparing it
and painting it