Solve for x and check your solution.
We have x divided by 3 is equal to 14.
So to solve for x,
to figure out what the variable x must be equal to,
we really just have to isolate it on the left hand side of this equation
It's already sitting there.
And we have x divided by 3 is equal to 14
We could also write this as 1/3 x =14.
Obviously x*1/3 is going to be x/3.
These are equivalent.
So how can we just end up with x on the left hand side
of either of these equations?
These are really the same thing.
Or another way, how can we just have a 1 in front of the x
A 1x, which is really just saying x
over here
Well, I'm dividing it by 3 right now
So if I were to multiply both sides of this equation by 3
that would isolate the x
And the reason that would work is
if I multiply this by 3 over here
I'm multiplying by 3 and dividing by 3
that's equivalent you would just, that's equivalent
to multiplying or dividing by 1
these guys cancel out
But remember, if you do it to the left hand side
you also have to do it to the right hand side
And actually, I'll do both of these equations
at the same time
Cuz they're really the exact same equation
So what are we going to get over here on the left hand side?
3 times anything divided by 3 is going to be that anything
we're just going to have an x left over
on the left hand side
And on the right hand side
what's 14*3
310 is 30, 34 is 12, so it's going to be 42
So we get x=42
And the same thing would happen here
3*1/3 is just 1
So you get 1x is equal to 14*3
which is 42
now let's just check our answer
let's substitute 42 into our original equation
So we have 42 in place for x
in place for x
over 3 is equal to 14
So what's 42 divided by 3
And we could do a little bit of
I guess we'd call it medium long division
It's not really long division.
3 into 4, 3 goes into 4 one time
1*3 is 3
You subtract: 4-3 is 1
Bring down the 2
3 goes into 12 four times
So 3 goes into 42 14 times
So this right over here simplifies to 14
And it all checks out
So we're done.