We are asked to find the cube root of -343
or another way to think about it
is some number that when I multiply it
by itself three times,
I am going to get -343
or another way to view it it
this is the same thing
as -343 to the 1/3 power
and the best way to do this is,
to really just try to factor this out
so the first thing that we could do--
so let me just factor -343
so the first thing I would like to do
is just to factor out the -1
so it is same thing as -1 times 343
and lets just think about this
is it divisible by 2? No.
Is it divisible by 3?
See the digits do not add up
to a multiple of 3 they add up
to 10 so it is not divisible by 3.
Not divisible by 4 since it's odd.
Not divisible by 5
because it doesn't end with 5 or 0.
It is not divisible by 6
because it's not divisible by 2 or 3.
Is it divisible by 7?
Let's check this out.
So 7 goes into 343.
7 goes into 34 four times,
4 times 7 is 28.
34 - 28 is going to be 6 bring down 3.
7 goes into 63 exactly 9 times.
So then we end up...
9 times 7 is 63, no remainder.
So this is going to be 7 times 49,
and we know that 49 is same thing
as 7 times 7 so how can we rewrite this?
This is the same thing as taking...
It is the same thing as taking
the cube root...
The cube root of -1...
of -1 times 7 times 7 times 7
which is the same thing
as the cube root of -1
times the cube root of 7 times 7 times 7
now what is the cube root of -1?
Well, -1 times itself three times is -1
so this right here is -1.
You could verify,
-1 times -1 times -1 is indeed -1
this becomes positive 1.
Multiply by -1 again you get -1.
So this is -1,
and then this over here
the cube root of 7 times 7 times 7.
Well, that's just going to be 7,
7 multiplied by itself three times
gives us 7 times 7 times 7 or 343.
So it's going to be -1 times 7
which is the same thing as -7.
So our answer is -7,
and we are done.