I'm Amy, and I work in the education department
And I am Anna and I am the curator of Native American Arts.
And we're standing in the Meso-American
and South American gallery.
And we are looking at a gold vessel.
Yes, this is actually from Peru,
and the culture would be Secan
and it is a gold vessel or beaker.
Now Secan, I don't see that on any other pieces.
Is this the only Secan piece we have?
Yes this is the only one. It's related to other cultures within present-day Peru and along the
west coast of South America.
And gold work in particular was something that metalsmiths excelled in.
So it's typical of cultures from that region
It's sort of a large piece in comparison
to some of the other vessels that I see in this gallery.
I think its impressive size is due to the fact that it would have been used by a very impressive person.
This would have been used by a high-ranking individual.
There would have been other vessels
made and used at the same time,
but they would have been made
out of different materials according
to who they were made for.
So-- Actually, yeah
All over the gallery there's a
lot of ceramic.
Ceramic, and you would have also
had wood beakers or drinking vessels
That is its purpose, this is
actually a vessel to be used in the
consumption of Chicha or
maize beer, or corn beer.
Would that taste anything like beer today?
I don't know.
It's definitely, was an alcoholic,
is an alcoholic beverage
and was consumed on ceremonial occasions
Perhaps a political event or occurrence
Now, it's face-up at us,but
it's actually upside-down--Yes--so
that seems kind of strange.
Yes, well, I think it's linked to the
consumption of what would be inside of it.
And you wouldn't be able to see
the figure right-side-up until
you were finished drinking what
was inside the vessel.
So there is even more motivation
to get to the bottom? (Laughs)
Well, and I think there's also a spiritual aspect
to this being that's depicted in repuse
on the surface of this.
You see those two kind of stylized eyes
and there's a mouth, perhaps with the tongue
indicated sticking out through the teeth.
Yes, actually that mouth is really
interesting, it almost looks like it has fangs.
It does! (Laughs) And then there are ears indicated,
and the figure is also
shown wearing adornment in the ears
in the form of ear plugs or ear flares.
So this was a particular deity?
It's been referred to as the Secan lord,
or Secan deity.
It has like this, interesting three-tiered neck
Is that to keep it standing, or...?
It's probably just decorative,
and also a little bit of the metalsmith
kind of showing off their skills on how
to work with the material.
How did they work with the material?
Well, this would have been possibly
pounded over a form or a mold, but also
would have been hand-worked as well.
This particular gold is probably an alloy
of gold and other materials, and we know
that in part because of the coloration
that appears on the surface. You
can see the kind of a red color coming through.
And when you say it could have been
pounded over a mold,
would that have been a mold made
out of clay, or made out of wood?
Probably wood, (Wood) and the metalsmiths
enjoyed working with this alloy,
because it made it a softer material
and more easily workable than
solid gold would be.
Okay. And why-- how has this survived,
because there was a lot of pillaging, right?
Well, it's quite remarkable actually,
that a piece of gold survived the Spanish,
who came through and melted down, you
know, hundreds of thousands of pounds
of gold to finance their--
Right, this is a large piece!
Well, it probably survives because it
would have most likely been buried
with someone, as an accompaniment
for the afterlife.
So probably with its owner, this
would have been one of the riches
that not only did he have with him in,
in his real life on Earth, but also in
the afterlife and the spiritual world.
And a thousand years later, here it is!
Here it is! Right here in the gallery.