Graph x is less than 4.
So, let's draw ourselves a numberline overhere.
So let me draw a number line.
Let me put ....I'll start here 0.
1-2-3-4-5
And we can go below 0
-1,-2,-3,-4 and I can go on
now we wanna graph all of the Xs that are less than 4
but we're not including 4
it's not less or equal than 4
it's less than 4
and to show that we're not including 4
what we're going to do is that we're going to draw a circle around 4
so this shows us that we're not including 4
if we were including 4
I would make that a solid dot
To show that we're going to do all of the values less than 4
we'll shade in the number line below 4 going down from 4
just like that just like that
and we can shade in the arrow just like that
here is all of the values less than 4
and you can test it out
take any value where there is blue
so there is blue overhere
-2,-2 is definitely less than 4
if you take this value right here, this 2. It's definitely less than 4.
4 is not included, because 4 is not less than 4.
It's equal to 4.
5 is not included because 5 is not less than 4.