We are asked to graph y is equal to log base 5 of x
and just to remind us what this is saying,
this is saying that y is equal to the power that I have to raise 5 to, to get to x.
Or if i would write this logarithmic equation as an exponential equation
5 is my base
y is the exponent that i have to raise my base to,
and then x is what i get when I raise 5 to the yth power.
So anther way of writing this equation would be
5 to the yth power is going to be equal to x.
These are the same thing.
Here we have y as a function of x, here we have x as a function of y.
But they're really saying the exact same thing:
"Raise 5 to the yth power to get x".
But when you put this as a logarithm, you are saying:
"To what power do I have to raise 5 to, to get x?
Well, I have to raise it to y."
Here, what do I get when I raise 5 to the yth power?
I get x.
Now that that is out of the way,
let's make ourselves a little table
that we can use to plot some points,
and we can connect the dots to see what this curve looks like.
So let me pick some Xs and some Ys.
And in general we want to pick some numbers
that give us some nice, round answers.
Some nice, fairly simple numbers for us to deal with
so we don't have to get a calculator.
And so in general, you want to pick x values,
you want to pick x values where the power that you have to raise 5 to to get that x value
is a pretty straightforward power.
Or another way to think about it is, you could just think about the different y values
that you want to raise 5 to the power of
and then you can get you x values.
So we could actually think about this one to come up with our actual x values.
But we want to be clear that when we express it like this,
the independent variable is x and the dependent variable is y.
We might just look at this one to pick some nice x's that give us nice, clean answers for y.
So what happens, here I'm actually going to fill out the y first
Just so that we get nice, clean x's.
So let's say that we are going to raise 5 to the --I'm going to pick some new colours--
to the negative 2 power, -- and let me do some other colours --
negative 1, zero, 1, and I'll do one more, and then 2.
So once again, this is a little nontraditional
where I'm filling in the dependent variable first,
but the way that we have written it over here, ......
it's easy to to find out what the independent variable must be for this logarithmic function.
So, what x gives me the y of negative 2?
What does x have to be for y to be equal to -2?
Well, 5 to the negative 2 power is going to be equal to x,
so 5 to the negative 2, is 1 over 25, so we get 1/25.
So another way, if we go back to this earlier one,
if we say log, base 5, of 1/25.
What power do I have to raise 5 to to get 1/25?
Well, I have to raise it to the negative 2 power.
Or you could say 5 to the negative 2 is equal to 1/25.
These are saying the exact same thing.
Now, let's do another one.
What happens when I raise 5 to the negative 1 power?
Well, I get one fifth. For this original one over there,
we are just saying that log base 5 of 1/5, you want to be careful
this is saying: "what power do I have to raise 5 to, in order to get 1/5?"
Well, I have to raise it to the negative 1 power.
Here, what happens when I take 5 tot the 0 power? I get 1.
And so this relationship is saying the same thing as log, base 5, of 1,
what power do I have to raise 5 to to get 1?
Wel, I've just got to raise it to the 0 power.
Let's... what happens when I raise 5 tot the first power?
Well, I get 5.
So if you go over here, that is just saying, what power do I have to raise 5 to to get 5?
Well, I have to just raise it to the 1st power.
And then finally, if I take 5 squared, I get 25.
So if you look at it from the logarithm point of view, you say
what power do I have to raise 5 to to get to 25?
Well, I have to raise it to the second power.
So, I kind of took the inverse of the logarithmic function. I wrote it as an exponential function.
I switched the dependent and independent variables.
So I could pick, or derive, nice clean x's that would give me nice, clean y's.
Now, with that out of the way, but I do want you to remind,
I could have just picked random numbers over here,
but then I probably would have gotten less clean numbers over here, so I would have had to use a calculator.
The only reason why I did it this way, is so I get nice clean results that I can plot by hand
So let's actually graph it.
So the y's go between -2 and 2,
the x's go from 1/25 all the way to 25
So let's graph it.
So that is my y-axis, and this is my x-axis.
So I'll drw it like that, that is my x-axis and then the y's
start at zero and then you get to positive 1, positive 2,
and then you have -1, -2 and then on the x-axis it is all positive
and I'll let you think about whether the domain here is, well we can think about it,
Is a logarithmic function defined for an x that is not positive?
Is there any power that I could raise 5 to so that I would get 0?
No. You could raise 5 to an infinitely negative power to get a very very small number
that approaches 0, but you can never get-
there is no power that you can raise 5 to to get 0.
So x cannot be 0. There is no power that you can raise 5 to
to get a negative number. So x can also not be a negative number.
So the domain of the function right over here-
and this is relevant becausewe want to think about what we are graphing -
The domain here is x has to be greater than 0.
Let me write that down.
The domain here is that x has to be greater than 0.
So we are only going to be able to graph this function in the positive x-axis.
So with that out of the way, x gets as large as 25,
so let me put those points here, so that's 5, 10, 15, 20
and 25.
And then let's plot these.
... and is blue and x is 1.25 and y is -2.
When x is 1/25, is it going to be really close to there, then y is negative 2.
So that's going to be right over there.
Not quite at the y-axis, 1/25 .. of the y-axis, but pretty close.
So that right over there is 1/25 comma -2 right over there.
Then when x is 1/5, which is slihtly further to the right,
1/5 with y = -2. So right over there.
This is 1/5, -1. And then when x is 1, y is 0.
So 1 might be there, so this is the point (1,0).
And then when x is 5, y is 1.
I;ve covered it over here, y is 1.
So that's the point (5,1).
And then finally when xis 25, y is 2.
So this is (25,2). And then I can graph the function.
And I'll do it in the colour pink.
So as x get's super super super small, y goes to negative infinity.
So what power hve you have to rais e5 to to get point .0001
That has to be a very negative power.
So we get very negative as we approach 0,
and then it kind of moves up like that.
And then starts to curve to the right like that.
And this thing right over here is going to keep going down at an ever steeper rate
and it's never going to quite touch the y-axis.
It is going to get closer and closer to the y-axis but it is never going to quite touch it.