All the parabolic mirror examples we've been doing so far have been concave
And that just means--you might know already what concave means
but just to make it clear
They were opening out towards the objects
and in most of the cases out towards where the images were formed
So we cared about the inside surface of the mirror right here
The way I always remember concave. It kind of forms a cave
We can view this part right here as the inside of the cave and we had a bunch of examples
where we had focal points
and then here was our principal axis and we had objects
and I showed you how the light would reflect off of the mirror
and go through the focal point
So we did a bunch of examples like that in the last couple of videos
In this video, I want to do a quick example of using a convex parabolic mirror
Convex parabolic mirror
and here we care about the other side of the mirror
we care about kind of the outside of the bowl
Let's imagine once again, you have something that's the shape of a parabola
This is the principal axis right over here. That is the line of symmetry
This is still the focal point. That right there is still the focus
The reflective surface is on the outside
So the reflective surfaces kind jutting out towards us
as opposed to caving in
That's another way to remember. Concave looks like it's caved in
Here it's jutting out towards us
Let's think about what would happen if I put an object over here on the outside
assuming that this is a reflective surface
If I put an object here, what is going to happen?
Let's just do the same exercise. What we're gonna do is
we're gonna have one parallel ray--
we can do rays in any direction from any of these points because
there's some light source over here
I never draw the light source, but it reflects diffusely off of this object
So this object is emitting light rays in every direction, but the useful ones
the useful diffuse light rays being emitted by this object
are the ones that are parallel to the principal axis
and the ones that would you go through the focus
Let's do one that's parallel to the principal axis. I'm not doing the math over here
but if it reflects off of the outside of this parabolic mirror
it will reflect away like it's coming from the focus
The focus is on the other side of this mirror
but it would reflect away that would look like it's coming from the focus
So that ray will reflect like that
And then if we have another ray from the head of this object, from the tip of that arrow
and that ray is going in the direction of the focus
So the focus is there. Let me draw the direction
So I have an incident ray going in the direction of the focus
When that gets reflected, it will reflect parallel to the principal axis
So it will reflect parallel to the principal axis
And so what type of image is going to be formed here?
Clearly these two rays will never converge. So we can't form a real image
We can not project that image onto a screen or cloth and see it
These two rays are converging but
if one were to observe the rays, they look like they're diverging from a single point
This ray that just got reflected out parallel looks like it's coming from
if you go straight back behind the mirror
And this one is coming out; looks like it's coming out of this point there
So it looks like they're diverging from this point on the other side of the mirror
Not only does it look like that they're coming from there
but the actual image will look like that
We can do it with other points on this arrow if we want
You can take the bottom of the arrow; that's maybe the easiest
Light that goes straight to the actual mirror will then get reflected straight back
So it would look like it's coming from a point behind the mirror, back over here
We can do other things. We can draw a stuff so you can see the whole image
You can take points over here and you say that would correspond to a point over there
But the thing that hopefully you'll realize from this video
is when you're dealing with a convex parabolic mirror
where the outside is the reflective surface
you're not going to form a real image; you're going to form a virtual image
This is a virtual image just like you'd see in your bathroom mirror
That's probably not parabolic I'm guessing
It's also going to be a smaller image
And you see this type of mirrors all the time, especially around corners
If you see a corner--let me draw corners
you'll sometimes see mirrors out here
so that you can see people as they're coming around the corner
The reason why these mirrors are useful is that they reflect light from a lot of directions
So you can kind of see around corners
This is not the best drawing. But I think you've seen these convex mirrors
mirrors that look something like this
Sometimes you'll also see them in the head of the aisles of stores and this is the way
the storeowners can have a good field of view and they can see if anyone is shoplifting
Anyway, hopefully you found that interesting