Here we're looking at the baptistry in Piza, a building that was begun in the mid-twelfth century.
and it's in a very famous location that perhaps people have seen.
It is where the Leaning Tower of Piza is
That's right. The Leaning Tower of Piza, as it's known, is actually the bell tower of the catherdral and this building
the baptisry is in front of the cathedral and usually this is how the buildings were arranged in these late medieval
Italian cities. The cathedral with the baptisry in front of it as a kind of religious and civic center of the city.
And we see that in cities like Florence. That´s right, you see the same kind of arrangement there. And baptiseries
were specially important buildings. Of course that is where baptisims would be performed.
But that had a great great importance in the cities which were dominated by their Christian faith and practices.
Because it was a place where essentially the individual, through baptism, was welcomed into the Christian community of that city.
So it makes sense that this is a place that city government would want to decorate.
They were usually very richly decorated places, focuses of a lot of patronage and attention because of their importance in the cities of this type.
Woa, who is going to say this? So, this is when the middle ages architecture, right? Exactly. Then when we go inside...well, inside it´s leading to a great transition
we are relatively revolutionary in fact. And that´s when we look at this sculture here which is inside. This is the
by Nicolo Pisano in the piece of Baptistry, which was finished by
about 1260. And pulpit would be a place where the priest
would stand to deliver a ceremony. That´s right, they would clim up and