Solve using the elimination method and they tell us the sum of two numbers is 70
Their difference is 24. What are the two numbers? So let's use this first sentence. Let's construct an equation from
this first sentence. Lets construct an constraint. The sum of two numbers, lets call them x and y.
So their sum, x + y is equal to 70. That's what this first sentence tells us.
The second sentence tells us their difference is 24. So that means that x minus y is equal
to 24. We're going to assume that x is the larger of the two numbers and y is the smaller one.
So when you take a difference like this you get a positive 24. So you have system of two
equations with two unknowns and they want us to solve it using the elimination method so let's
do that. So we can literally just add these two questions. On the left side we would have a positive
y and a negative y over here, and they would just cancel out. So if we were to just add these equations, they would
cancel out, so if we were able to just add these two equations we would be able to eliminate
the y's. So lets do that. So (x plus y) plus (x minus y). Well the plus y and the minus y
cancel out and you're left with x plus an x which is 2x. And that is going to be equal to 70 plus
24. 70 plus 24 is equal to 94. And I want to make it clear. I mentioned it in previous videos.
That this process of adding equations to each other. This is nothing new, we're really just
adding the same thing to both side of this equation. You could say we're adding 24 to both sides of t
this equation. Over here we're explicitly adding 24 to the 70. And over here you could say
we could add 24 to x plus y. But the second constraint tells us that x minus y is the same thing
as 24. So we're adding the same thing to both sides. Here we're calling it 24, here we're calling it
x minus y. And we were able to eliminate the y. So we get 2x is equal to 94 now we can divide both sides
by 2. And we are left with x is equal to 47.
And now we can substitute back into either one of these equations to solve for y.
So let's try this first one over here. So we have 47 plus y is equal to
70. We can subtract 47 from both sides of this equation. So we subtract 47 and we are left with
y is equal to 23. And you can verify that this works. If you add the two numbers
47 plus 23 you definitely get 70. If you take 47 minus 23 you definitely get 24.
So it definitely meets both constraints.