Let's say Pete over here thinks that he's a pretty good investor,
so what he does is, or he has an idea, and says
"Well look, I'm gonna create a corporation,
and I'm gonna get a bunch of people to contribute money to that corporation
and then I'll manage that money, and maybe I'll take a little fee for myself
so that I can, um, maybe hire some analysts
or get some computers, or get some office space."
So what he does is he sets up a corporation
Let's say he sets up a corporation right over here
And let's say the way he first sets up the corporation
let's say it just has 4 shares. And I making the number really small
just to make the drawing and the map easy.
This wouldn't be realistic, normally it would be something in the 100s or 1,000s of shares
or maybe even more than that, but let's say it has 4 shares
and let's say all of the 4 shares are owned by Pete initially
just to simplify the explanation.
And he puts in $400 into this corporation,
so another way to think about it, in exchange putting $400 into this corporation
he gets 4 shares, or each share is worth $100
Each of these shares right over here.
And so what he does, is he registers this corporation
I'm talking about a US specific case, but there's similar types of organizations
in other countries. He registers this organization right over here
with the US SEC (Securities and Exchange Commission)
And he also registers himself with the SEC, or even better
he registers a management company that he runs with the SEC
so let's call it "Pete, Inc." is a corporation he starts off
that he also registers with the SEC.
And when he registers with the SEC he tells them that look,
"This company right over here, we're going to issue more shares
for more people to contribute money, and I'm going to manage this money right over here
and I'm just going to take a percentage of the total
assets under management. Sometimes you'll see AUM used
that just means Assets Under Management. That will go to Pete, Inc. every year
for figuring out the best place to invest this money.
And it's usually on the order of about 1%, sometimes a little bit less
sometimes a little bit more, so 1% per year.
So right now with only $400 under management, it would only be about $4 per year
but since he registered with the SEC
he can call himself a mutual fund and he can
solicit funds from the public. So it is a mutual fund
he has met, he has jumped through all the hoops
that the SEC sets up for him, so he can market
he can market himself as some type of great fund manager
we don't know if that true or not,
and he can also solicit funds from the public
So from the public.
And we're gonna see in future videos there are other funds,
especially hedge funds, that can't just, that one
they can't market, and they can't take funds from the public,
those can only take funds from certain types of sophisticated
investors. And what happens in Pete's fund
and this isn't going to be an open-ended mutual fund,
that we're showing here, and most mutual funds are like that
let's say that Sal comes along, he likes Pete's marketing materials,
and he says, "Hey, I want Pete to manage my money too!"
So Sal goes and he gives $100 and says "Pete, give me a share!"
So Pete creates another share right over here
he creates another share, he gives it to Sal
so he gets 1 share -- that's me, I get 1 share,
an in exchange I give $100 to the fund,
and now the fund has, the fund has $500
So this is another $100 right over here,
and now Pete's annual fee is going to be 1% of this whole thing
or $5 a year, and if this whole thing grows,
let's say this whole thing doubles from $500,
let's say it doubles to $1,000,
then that $1,000 is essentially split amongst these
5 shares now, so all of the people will essentially have
their money doubled, minus whatever Pete's expenses are.
So let's say that a year goes by,
and then even after paying Pete the 1%
So we had $500 of assets under management,
this whole assets under management a year later
goes to, let's say it goes to $1,000
So Pete is either really good or really lucky
or a little bit of both. So it goes to $1,000.
So let me draw it like this.
So now it is at $1,000 and it still has the same 5 investors here
and I'm lucky enough to be one of them.
So here, the 5 investors. Let me draw the shares,
so there's 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 shares.
Now each of these shares, well the $1,000 is called the
NAV, the Net Asset Value, so let me give you that
piece of terminology, it just means
Net Asset Value, and so there's an NAV
per share, the NAV per share over here his $200
I just took the total NAV and I just divided it by the shares,
and what's special about an open-ended mutual fund
is that the close, or at the end of every day
either new shares can be removed from the fund
or can be created for the fund. So in the first video
I showed how I wanted to buy into the fund,
so I bought a share, and that increased the NAV
and also increased the number of shares,
he had to create a share for me to buy,
he didn't sell me a share that already existed.
So you can imagine after this type of performance
more people would want to buy shares,
so now they would have to buy in to make things fair
at $200 per share, because that's the current NAV per share
so let's say that 5 more people want to buy in
at $200 per share. So what Pete would do, or what
this mutual fund, it's not Pete really, it's the corporation
it would create 5 new shares, so 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
if there was only 1 person that day, it would create 1 share
that day, if there were 10 people that day,
it would create 10 shares that day
and it could keep doing this, and the NAV of each of these
are $200, so it gives these shares to each of these people
and they have to contribute $200, so essentially
it puts another $1,000 into the pool that Pete
can now manage, and so now he's met the total
NAV for the fund is $2,000 now, and Pete
will get his 1% management fee off of this entire
$2,000. Now let's say we fast forward a little bit,
we fast forward a little bit to-
let's say Pete start having a not-so-good year.
So let's say we fast forward a year past that,
and Pete's has a minus, a negative 10% return.
So if we started at $2,000, and that's when you include
taking his management fee out. You start at $2,000
you lose 10% in 1 year, so it goes down to $1,800
Let me put this in a new color.
So now he's at $1,800. That's not completely drawn to scale,
but hopefully you get the idea.
So now he's at $1,800.
But you still have a total of 10 shares,
So let me try to do my best to draw the 10 shares,
So I have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.
These should be of equal size.
And now the NAV per share, the NAV per share
is going to be $1,800 divided by 10, or $180
And let's say that I get a little bit freaked out
by this recent performance, and I have some
other commitments with my money,
so I say, "Pete, you need to buy my share back for me."
So what Pete does, is he would give me back $180,
so the total NAV would lose $180, so it would go down $180
So we would take this out of it,
$1,800 minus $180 is $1,620. So now it is $1,620.
And they would buy back a share from me,
so they would cancel 1 of the shares,
but notice, the NAV per share does not change,
by me redeeming my share, it does not change
what happens to everyone else.
Now you have $1,620 divided by 9 shares,
that should still get you to be $180 per share.
If I did my math right.
So $1,800 minus $180 gets you $1,620,
it should still be $180 per share,
but this is the nature of an open-ended fund,
you could keep creating shares and selling them to the public to raise more money
or when someone wants their money back
you essentially buy the share back from them
give them their money when you buy the share back
and you remove that share.
So an open-ended fund, really at the close of every
trading day can keep growing or shrinking.
It can keep adding more and more investors,
or their investors can take their money back.
What's difficult about this from the fund manager's point of view
is that they have to manage this,
they have to manage this constant buying and selling
with the public, they have to manage the paperwork,
and if you think about it, they can't have all of their money invested
in relatively illiquid assets,
or even in regular stocks,
they have to keep some amount of their money
and it's usually like 3-5%, they have to keep some of this
$2,000 (before he lost my money)
they have to keep some of it in cash.
And from an investor's point of view,
they would say, "Well, if I'm good at investing,
I should try to minimize the amount of cash that I have,
because I'm not getting a return on cash,
but because it's open-ended, because investors
might come by and say, "Hey, I want my money"
you have to have a little bit of cash as part of the asset pool
in order to be able to buy people's shares back.