In the last video, I've mentioned how I've been asked
to make predicitons for the year 2060.
In the last one I've focused on education,
that's obviously what I'm working on now, and I have some opinions on that.
But what I want to do in this video is do maybe slightly more broad and wild predictions,
and my one prediction I'll make is on probably not going to predict the real reality of 2060
and the probably big things to predict, I will completely miss.
But with that out of the way, it's fun to predict things, so let's give it a shot.
So the first area that I will predict is what is going to happen in the field of medicine.
And in particular I think that the human life span is going to increase dramatically.
So, I'll be conservative, and say that the average human lifespan
is going to be, especially in the developed world
and hopefully by the year 2060 most of the world is developed,
the average human lifespan is going to be over 100 years old.
And I won't say whether that's going to be a good or a bad thing.
There's arguments either way about the proper way to live
and what happens to global populations.
But if the world is for the most part developed and educated,
you actually will probably have a lower rate of reproduction
and so you might actually have some space in the world for older people.
But there is a very strong chance of this happening,
Because we are starting to understand the molecular basis of aging.
It's not a given thing that because of some form of wear tear
things have to die after 70 years or 80 years or 90 years.
And we are starting to understand the mechanisms
and how to maybe improve the repair mechanisms or how to augment in some way.
So I definietly think this is going to happen.
I don't know if it's going to be a positive or a negative,
but it's likely to happen.
The next thing, and this is kind of closely related, this is still biological,
is you are going to have a close integration between
the digital and the biological.
And once again, I won't make any statement wheter this is a good or a bad thing,
but it seem that like it is just an extrapolation
of the direction we are already going in.
Digital and biological integration.
So already you are gettin more and more in your hand-held devices,
imagine, when your your screen is no longer in your palm,
but is being projected onto your retina from some little thing.
And then eventually, you have a direct connection with your retina
and your brain can directly access areas of memory
through some biological and digital interface.
So I definitely think this is going to happen. This is a big deal,
and I think this is already happening with a lot what you see around technology,
it is really going to reshape what the individual human experience is going to be,
we already see people kind of living in virtual realities and playing these immersive games
and spending all of their time on social networking platforms.
What happens when they are literally plugged in all the time,
when almost their cell phone is in the brain, I don't know,
I am not going to comment whether it is a good or a bad thing,
but it does look like a trend that is going to keep on going through the next 50 years.
Now, if you take that even further, we are talking about digital and biological integration,
but if you go to the extreme, and actually it is probably both of these top two things combined in some way,
is that we are learning, and once again, not making comment whether it is good or bad,
it is just an extrapolation of what we already see,
we are seeing more and more ability to understand our genome,
to molecularly target things, to manipulate actual biology.
And so, what you have is that you can actually have manipulation of biology.
And while this is on some level creepy, it could be creepy or it could be exciting,
depending on how it all plays out, but it could do things like
augment human intelligence.
Which would, if you think about all of the progress of society
and all of the things that are already accelerating,
imagine how society will change if intelligence itself is augmented.
As someone with a limited intelligence I can't even imagine what will happen as soon as you do this.
And obviously, the more you augmented intelligence, the more that you can learn
how to augment intelligence and increase lifespan
and do digital and biological integration even more.
So these things I see as some form of a trend.
We will se how it all plays out. And hopefully it plays out in
the field good carebear version versus the kind of some type of crazy society
and we all turn into the borg in some way.
Now the other trend, and these are just the things that popped in my brain today when I pressed record,
but the other tred that I think is interesting is some of the things
that we have taken for granted in terms of how nations interact with each other,
and nation-states in particular interact with each other.
And just a kind of a overview, so there is a notion called a nation-state,
in everyday language the word nation and the word state
almost mean the same thing, but they kind of mean different things.
If you want to be more formal about it, that's why people use the word nation-state,
that doen't mean the same thing like saying a state-state,
the difference between a nation and a state is
these are group of people that feel some type of common identity.
It could be a language, it could be a culture, it could be a value system.
So this is some kind of common identity.
And it often is somehow associated with geography,
but it does not have to be associated with geography,
it could even be a religion or it could be whatever else. That's what a nation is.
A state is a formal governence structure
that makes the laws and has the institutions to make society function.
Now, a nation-state is what most of us live in today,
because it both has an indentity and some type of formal institutions.
So a very pure nation-state would be some place like Japan
where there is relatively uniform in term of ethnicity and religion and in terms of culture,
and you have that same group of people governing themselves.
In a place like the Unites States, ethnicity, religion, that is diverse,
but what gives indentity is a notion of shared values, and a notion of maybe a common history
or whatever else for a certain kind of world view
and obiously there is a formal state sructure.
Now, what is going to be interesting here, I actually have no idea
how all of this is going to play out,
but when you things like the some of the revolitions in the Middle East
to do the things like peolple being able to communicate irrespective of the traditional media,
I think there is going to be some interesting questions on what happens to the nation-state.
Especially nation-states that are able to secure their power
by kind of having a bullneck on access to information.
And all of that is I think going to change in a very dramatic way,
as you have more and more integration between people, cross-border comminication
when people realize that people on the other side of the borded
really aren't that different than themselves.
And another interesting thing, even the notion of democracy,
and once again, I don't know how it is going to play out,
but all notions of representational democracy that we have today
are somewhat based on geography.
And that is because when the major representational democracies came about,
that was the best way to represent each other:
hey, let me pick some representatives from our county or from our region
and they will go elect other representatives and they will go to the national government,
but now that we have this instantaneous communication with people,
you might be able to have different types of a representational democracy,
and maybe you can even have more direct democracy,
who knows, because of things like communication and technology and whatever else.
And then the other way that the nation, the way they fundamentally interact
is going to change is actually in things like warfare,
and once again, already seeing this trend,
in particular, I think developed countries are not going to have humans on the front line.
No humans on the front line.
And depending on you point of view, this could be a very good thing
or could be a kind of a scary thing.
Because if you have no humans on the front line,
and you are already seeing things like this with these Predator Drones
and you see these robot bomb detectors and all things like that,
and it doesn't really have to be these big things,
there is already a DARPA-founded project to work on military insects
that could be used as some kind of reconnaissance
or you can imagine that eventually they could have these little things on
to conduct on someone other, who know what they do.
The exciting thing is that all of a sudden a human won't be there to get shot
and so hopefully military casualties would go down,
the scary thing here is if you don't have humans on the front line,
nations might be willing to enter into war, especially developed nations,
they might not take it this serioiusly,
and so it might be something that they do a little bit more when they are in the mood,
and it would actually create a huge disparity between
developed and developing nations when this happends.
You already see that to a certain degree.
A developed nation, they don't have to put as many humans in harm's way,
and it is purely driven by their wealth to have capital
that can go into these robots and these drones, and their technological innovations,
while in the developing countries they actually would have to
use human beings so their cause would be much much higher.
So it is an interesting question, and once again,
who knows how this plays out, whether it is a good or bad thing in the long term.
I think a similar thing with this is we are going to see
more and more non-lethal weapons,
which, once again, it is very similar to this,
it sounds like it is a good thing, you know,
if there is a gun that instead of having to kill someone,
it encompasses them in some way, stuns them in some,
kind of the classic Star Trek 'put your phasers on stun' things.
The, I guess, scarier version of non-lethal weapons is
the treshold for using it becomes much lower.
So for government, you know, once to subjected citizens
are subjected to another group of citizens,
it can literally just stun them, make them pass out or control them in some way,
so this could be a little bit scarier.
So who knows how all of this plays out.
So those are my predictions or things to think about over the next 50 years.
These are just the things happened to jump into my brain today,
probably basen on some of the science-fiction books I have been reading or whatever else,
but take in what the huge grade of sold,
I don't know whether these things are really going to happen or not,
and I don't know if they are even a good thing or not,
but they seem to be a bit of an extrapolation of what we have already seen.