Given "g" of "x" is equal to eight "x" plus two
find "g" of zero, "g" of negative five and "g" of
two "x" plus three
So all this is when they say "g" of "x" is equal
to eight "x" plus two. This is a function definition
They're saying you give me any "x"
and you input it into my function of "g"
and my function "g" will output
It will associate with with that number "x"
another number that happens to
be eight "x" plus two
This is one way to create an association,
it's going to associate. If you were to put,
If you were to put one here, if this "x"
is one, you're going to do eight times one
plus two. So you would associate one
through "g", you would assocate one with
eight times one plus two which is ten.
So, its just another way of creating an association
that you could do with sets of ordered pairs
or you could do it graphically. But this is one of
the most typical ways you that you will see a
function defined. It says look, input an "x"
over here and I'm going to output eight "x" plus two
So with that out of the way lets think about what
the "g" of zero is. "G" of zero literally just means
we're inputting zero into this function and this
function says, whatever your inputting, I'm going
output eight times that plus two. So "g" of zero
is going to be, let me write it this way, so it
becomes clear what I'm doing
"G" of zero is going to be eight times zero
eight times zero, eight times zero plus two, plus
plus two. So where ever we saw the "x"
we replaced it with whatever we're inputting
that is our "x" in this situation right over here
and so this is equal to eight times zero plus two
is just equal to two. So
"g" of zero is equal to two, let me just write that
right here "g" of zero is equal to two
Now lets try "g" of negative five
so let me write it this way "g" of... I'll write "g" of negative
five is equal to, I'll try to do the color coding
a little bit better this time. It's going to be equal
to eight times our "x" which in this case is negative
five, eight times negative five plus two, eight times negative five plus two
we're inputting a negative five and we're going
to output eight times negative five plus two
wherever we saw the "x" we just replaced
it with a negative five. And this is just equal
to eight times negative five
is negative forty plus two is equal to negative
thirty-eight. So I'll write this over here on the right
We have "g" of negative five is equal to
negative thirty-eight. Now this
last one is a little bit interesting,
So we just did this one,
now let's do "g" of... "g" of two "x" plus three.
So now they're not inputting a number, they're
inputting an expression
and what we have to do, everywhere where we see
a "x" here, we're going to replace it with that
expression. If I did "g" of a circle
Let me write this down, if I did "g" of
an orange circle, an orange circle right over here
By this function definition, by this function definition
if I'm inputting an orange circle, I should output
an orange circle eight times
the orange circle, eight times the orange circle
which doesn't make a lot of sense
but hopefully you get the idea that whatever you're
inputting you're just going to multiply it times eight and add two
so if we input two "x" plus three we're going to output
this times eight plus two
wherever we see an "x" we replace it
with this right over here. So let's try that out
so now we have "g" of
two "x" plus three, "g" of two "x" plus three
is going to be equal to...
is going to be equal to eight times whatever
we're inputting, eight times whatever were inputting
plus two. If we're inputting an orange, if this was
orange, we'd put an orange here, if this is a negative
five here we'd put a negative five here, if this is a zero
we'd put a zero here. In this case, we're inputting two "x"
plus three into our function, so we put two "x" plus three
where the "x" is right over there. So two "x" plus
three. Whatever we input this function says
multiply it by eight and add two
we're inputting two "x" plus three, multiply it by
eight and then add two, and so this is going to be equal
to, we just distribute the eight... we just distribute the
eight and you get sixteen "x" plus
twenty-four and you still have this plus two out over here
you still have this plus two out over here
so this is going to be equal to sixteen "x", sixteen
"x" plus these two, you add them up you get
twenty-six. So we can write over here and I'll do
that same color so to be consistent
We have "g" of two "x" plus three is equal to
sixteeen "x" plus twenty-six and we're done.
I know this can be confusing because you're
inputting, you're replacing "x"
with something that has "x" in it.
But you really should just view this as if
this were an orange ball or a star
or even if this had "y's" in it
Wherever you see an "x" you replace it
with whatever you are inputting it. So in every
instance we replace the "x" with two "x" plus three.