What we will attempt to start to do in this video is to take the surface integral
of the function x squared over our surface where the surface
in question--the surface we're going to care about is going
to be the unit sphere, so it could be defined by x squared
plus y squared plus z squared is equal to 1
what we're going to focus on in this first video, because it will take us several videos to do it
is just the parameterization of this surface area right here
as you'll see this is often the hardest part
because it takes a little bit of visualization
and then after that it's just kind of mechanical,
but it can be kind of hairy at the same time so it's worth going through
So first let's just think about how we can parameterize
and I have trouble even saying the word,
how we can parameterize this unit sphere as a function of
two parameters
so let's think about it, let's think about it a little bit
so first let's just think about, let's just think about
the unit sphere
i'm gonna take a side view of the unit sphere,
so let's take the unit sphere, so this right over here is
our z axis
That's our z axis, and then over here I'm gonna draw
This is going to be not just the x or the y axis,
this is going to be our entire xy plane viewed from the side
That is the xy plane.
Now, our sphere, our sphere, our unit sphere might look
something like this
The unit sphere itself is not too hard to visualize
It might look something like that
The radius at any point is 1
That length right over there is 1,
and this is a sphere, not just a circle
So I could even shade it in a little bit just to make it
clear that this thing has some dimensionality to it
so that's shading it in it just makes it kind of look a
little more spherical.
Now let's just attempt to parameterize it, and the first
step, let's just think, if we didn't have to think above and
below the xy plane, if we just thought about where this
unit sphere intersected the xy plane, how we could
parameterize that.
So let's just think about where it intersects the xy plane
it intersects it there, and there, and actually everywhere
it instersects it everywhere.