(piano music)
What is perfect?
Well, the Ancient Greeks thought the human body was perfect,
but for them, it was not an individual that was perfect,
it was like almost mathematical precision
where the proportions of every part of the body
were perfect in relationship to others
We're looking at an ancient Roman copy of a Greek bronze original
by the great artist Polykleitos who thought out to demonstrate just that.
What would perfect, ideal beauty be thinking about the mathematical relationship
of each part of the human body to the other and relationship to the whole
This is a sculpture called the Doryphoros.
Doryphoros means a "spear-bearer"
and he would have originally been holding a bronze spear.
We call it the Doryphoros.
Polykleitos apparently called it "canon"
not to mean a piece of armament
but a kind of idealized form that could be studied and replicated
that is, a set of ideas that you followed
The idea that you could create a perfect human form
based on math was really part of a bigger set of ideas for the Greeks
If we think about Pythagoras for example
Pythagoras discovered that harmony and music
was based on the mathematical relationship between the notes
In fact, Pythagoras tried to understand the origin of all beauty through ratio
and so it follows that the Greeks would be looking for that
in one of the forms that they felt were most beautiful, that is the human body
the Greeks would perform their athletics nude
celebrating the body and its physical abilities
but even when they represented figures in noble pursuits like this figure
We have a figure whose clothes have been taken off
This is not because soldiers went into battle nude in Ancient Greece
but because this sculpture is not about warfare
it's not a portrait of an individual
this is a sculpture that is about the perfection of the human form
This was found in a paleastra in Pompeii
a place where athletes would work out
perhaps as a kind of inspiration for them
So that's another layer of meaning
the Romans loved Greek art
and had it copied in marble very often
and even in a city like Pompeii
we have found thousands of sculptures that are copies of Greek originals
this is based on a sculpture that is at the very beginning of the Classical period
before the Parthenon sculptures
but after the Archaic figures
it's after the standing figure we know as the Kouros
Here the Greeks have turned away from
the stiff renderings that had been so characteristic of the Archaic
and have instead begun to examine the human body
and understand its physiognomy