In the last video we started with a star in its main sequence like the sun. And inside the core of that
star you had hydrogen fusion going on. So that is hydrogen fusion and then outside of the core
you just had hydrogen. You just had hydrogen plasma.
And we say plasma, its the electrons and protons of the idividual atoms
have been disassociated because the temaptures and pressures are so high.
So they really just, kind of, its like this soup of electrons and protons
as opposed to proper atoms that we associate with at lower temperatures.
So this is a main sequence star right over here.
And we saw in the last video that this hydrogen is fusing into helium.
So we start having more and more helium here.
And as we have more and more helium the core becomes more and more dense
because helium is a more massive atom. It is able to pack more mass into a smaller volume.
So this gets more and more dense until, at some point, while the core is becoming
more and more dense, that actually makes the fusion happen faster and faster
because its more dense, more gravitational pressure, more mass wanting to get to it,
more pressure on the hydrogen that's fusing, it starts to fuse hotter.
So hydrogen fuses faster.
In fact we even see this in our sun. Our sun today is brighter and hotter.
Its fusing faster then it was when it was born 4.5 or 4.6 billion years ago.
But eventually its going to get the point where in the core you only have helium.
So at some point the entire core is all helium.
Its going to be way denser than this core over here.
All of that mass over there has been turned into helium.
Not all of it, a lot of it has been turned into energy, but most of it is now in helium.
Its going to be a much much smaller volume. The whole time the temperature