Let's see if we can write 0.0727 as a fraction.
Now let's just think about what places these are in.
This is in the tenths place...
This is in the hundredths place...
This 2 is in the thousandths place...
and this last 7 is in the ten-thousandths place.
So, there are a couple of ways we can do this. The way I like to think this,
this term right here is in the ten-thousandths place, we can view this whole thing right over here as "727 ten-thousandths,"
cuz this is the smallest place, right over here.
So let's just rewrite it. This is equal to 727 over 10,000.
And, we've already written it as a fraction, and I think that's about as simplified as we can get.
This number up here is not divisible by 2, it's not divisible by 5.
In fact, it's not divisible by 3, which means it's not divisible by 6 or 9. Doesn't even look to be divisible by 7.
It might be a prime number. But I think we are done.