This is a picture of Isaac Newton super famous British mathematician
and physicist and this is the picture of Gottfried Leibniz super famous
but maybe not as famous but maybe should be famous german
philosopher and mathematician, he was a contemprary of Isaac Newton
These two gentlemen together were really the founding
fathers of the calculus and they did some of their, most of their
major work in the late 1600's and
this right over here is Usain Bolt
Jamaican sprinter who's continuing to do some of his best work
in 2012 and as early of 2012, he is the fastest human alive
he would probably be the fastest human that has ever lived
and you might not have made the association with these three
gentlemen.Might not think they have lot in common but they
were all obsessed with same fundamental question that differantial
calculus addresses and the question is what is the instantaneous rate
of change of something. In the case of Usain Bolt how fast is he going
right now? Not just his average speed was for last second or his average
speed in his next 10 seconds. How fast is he going right now?
So this is what differential calculus is all about. Instantaneous rates of change
differential calculus and Newton's term for differential calculus
was the method of flexions which actually sound something fancier
but its all about what's happening in this instant in this instant and to think about that
why it not a super easy problem to address with the traditional
algebra, lets draw a little graph here. So on this axis on this axis I have distance
so now say y is equal to distance. I could have said d=distance we will see later
in calculus d is reserved for something else.we will say y=distance
and in this axis we will say time and i can say t=time but rather say x=time
x=time, so if we had to plot Usain Bolt's distance as a function of time
well in time 0 he hasn't gone anywhere he's right over there and we know at this
gentleman is capable of travelling a 100 metres in 9.58 seconds
so after 9.58 seconds we'll assume that this is in seconds over here, he is
capable of going 100 metres. 100 metres.
and so using this information we can actually figure out his average speed
his average speed right this way his average speed is just going to be change in distance
over his change in time
and using the variable over here we are saying y is distance and this is change in y over
change in x from this point to that point and this might look somewhat familiar to you
from basic algebra.This is the slope between two points. If I have a line that connects these two points
and if i have a line that connects two points this is the slope of that line.
the change in distance is right over here.Change in y=100 m and our change in time is this right over
here so our change in time is equal to 9.58 seconds we start with 0, we goto 9.58 seconds another way
to think about it - the rise over the run
you might have heard in your algebra class.
It's going to be a 100 meters over 9.58 seconds.
So this is 100 meters over 9.58 seconds.
And the slope is essentially just the rate of change,
or you can view it as the average rate of change,
between these two points. And you'll see if you even follow
the units it gives you units of speed here.
It'd be velocity if we also specified the direction.
And we can figure out what that is. Let me get a calculator out.
Let me, so let me ... get the calculator on the screen.
So we're going 100 meters in 9.58 seconds so it's around 10.4
approximately 10.4 and then the units are meters per second.
And that is his average speed. And what we're gonna see in a second is
how average speed is different than instantaneous speed.
How it's different that the speed that he might be going in any
given moment. And just to have a concept of how fast this is
let me get the calculator back. This is in meters per second.
If you want to know how many meters he's going in an hour
there's thirty-six hundred seconds in an hour.
So he'll be able to go this many meters thirty-six hundred times.
So that's how many meters he can, if he were able to somehow
keep up that speed in an hour, this is how fast he is going
in meters per hour. And then if you were to say how many miles
per hour, there's roughly 16 hundred, and I don't know the exact number
but roughly 16 hundred meters per mile so let's divide it
by 1600. And so you see that this is roughly a little over 23
about 23 and 1/2 miles per hour. This is approximately ...
Let me write it this way, this is approximately 23.5 mph.
Let me scroll over.
Miles per hour.
And relative to a car not so fast but
relative to me extremely fast. Now, to see
how this is different than instantaneous velocity,
Let´s think about the potential plot of his distance relative to time
He is not going to just go the speed immediately.
He is not just gonna go as soon as the gun
fires. He is not just gonna go 23 and 1/2 mph.
All the way. He is going to have to accelerate.
So at first, he starts off going a little bit slower.
His slope is going to be a little bit lower.
Than the average slope. He is going to be little bit slower.
Then he is going to start accelerating. And so his
speed and you see this slope here is getting steeper and steeper and steeper
and then maybe near the end he starts tiring off a little bit.
And so his distance part against time might be a curve
that looks something like this.
And what we calculated here is just the average slope across
this change in time. We can see in any given moment
the slope is actualy different.
In the beginning he has a slower rate of change of
distance. Then over here he accelerates,
over here it seems like his rate of change of distance would be
roughly -- or you could view it
as a slope of the tangent line at that point --
it looks higher than his average.
And then he starts to slow down again.
?? ... Average goes to 23.5 miles per hour.
And I looked it up Usain Bolt´s instantaneous velocity
his peak instantaneous velocity
is actually close to 30 miles per hour.
So the slope over here might be
23... whatever miles per hour,
but instantaneous, his fastest poin in this
9.58 seconds is closer to 30 miles per hour.
But you see it is not a trivial thing to do.
You could say: OK, let me try to approximate
the slope right over here and you
could do that by saying : OK,
well, what is the change in "y"
over the change of "x" right around this.
You could say: Let me take some change of x,
and figure out what the change of y is around it.
Or as we go past that. So we get that. But that would just be an approximation.
Because you see that the slope of this curve is constantly changing.
So what you want to do is see what happens as the change of x gets smaller and smaller.
As the change of x gets smaller and smaller and smaller
we are going to get better and better approximation.
Your change in y is going to get smaller and smaller and smaller.
So what you wanna do and we are going to get into depth of all of this
and study it more rigorously,
you want to take the limit as delta x aproaches zero.
As delta x aproaches zero of
change in y over your change in x
and when you do that you are going to
approach that instantaneous rate of change
you could view it as instantaneous slope at that point of the curve.
Or the slope of the tangent line at that point of the curve.
Or if we use calculus terminology we would view it as the derivative.
So the instantaneous slope is the derivative.
And the notation we use for derivative is dy
over dx. And that is why I reserved the letter y.
How does this relate to word "differential"?
This dy is differential.
dx is a differential. And one way to conceptualize this. This is an
infinitely small change in y, over an infinitely small change in x.
And by getting super, super small changes in y or changes in x
you are able to get this instantaneous slope
or in the case of this example
the instantaneous speed of Usain Bolt right at that moment.
And notice, you can not just put zero hero.
If we just put here change in x is 0 you are going to get something undefined.
You can not divide by zeros. You take the limit.
As it approaches zero and we will define that more rigorously in the next few videos.