You'll often hear the words "depreciation" and "amortization" used together.
And what I want to do in this video is understand a little bit better
why they are similar and the slight difference between the two.
So in our previous examples we've done depreciation
so you can imagine, in period 0 we buy a truck for $60,000
and instead of just expensing it in period 0,
instead of putting $60,000 expense right over here,
we capitalize it.
We say that we have a $60,000 asset.
So this is right at the end of period 0, or the beginning of period 1
And what we do is we spread out this expense over the period of time
that we're actually going to use the truck.
So in period 1, we depreciate the truck by $20,000.
We're assuming we have a 3-year life of this truck,
and we're just going to do what's called
"Straight Line Depreciation"
We're just going to take the cost of the truck, and divide it by its life.
There are other ways to depreciate it.
Maybe you could imagine that it depreciates faster in the first year.
But this is the simplest type, and is actually used by a lot of companies.
Just Straight Line Depreciation.
So after we use $20,000
we depreciate the truck by $20,000
we expense it in that year, so this is literally an expense.
Then at the end of period 1, it is now on our books for $40,000
Then in period 2, we depreciate it by another $20,000
it's going to be a $20,000 expense in period 2.
Now on our books, at the end of period 2, it's going to be worth $20,000
Then in period 3, we expense another $20,000 on our income statement
and then, at least for this truck, assuming we hadn't bought a new one yet
We've completely written it off.
It is now worth $0 on our books, because, based on what we assumed, it's not useful anymore.
We kind of have to scrap this truck.
That's depreciation.
Now imagine if, to run our trucking business,
we also had to pay some type of license fee.
And let's say that the license fee was $4000
and we get to use it over 4 years.
So once again, you could've just put a $4,000 expense right over here,
but that's not really accurate, you're not just using that fee in that period.
That fee is going to be useful over the next 4 years.
So once again, you would put down the asset, you know, the paid license fee,
or maybe the prepaid license fee, depending on how you view it,
and then you would amortize that cost.
Which is essentially the same thing mathematically. You say
"Oh look! I'm going to use this over the next four years
essentially $1,000/year." So my license fee amortization in year 1
I'd say is $1,000
and then on my books I would carry the license fee for $3,000
and then I'd amortize another $1,000, and it would go down to $2,000
then amortize another $1,000, and at the end of period 3 it's now worth $1,000 on my books
Period 4, amortize another $1,000, now I've completely written it off
and I probably have to get another license at the point.
So mathematically, they're the same thing
even philosophically they're the same thing
The idea that, instead of expensing those expenses all at once,
you say "Look, they have some useful life, let me spread out the expense over their useful life."
The difference between the two, and you might have already realized this,
Is the appreciation is when you have hard assets
If you have a building, or a truck, or some type of equipment you would depreciate that asset
If you have a non-hard asset, or a financial asset
or something that's less tangible, then you would amoritze it.
It's just a different word depending on how tangible the asset is.
So if it's a license fee, or some other type of fee,
or some type of, maybe intellectual property, you would amortize the cost
If you have a truck, or a building, or whatever, you would depreciate it.