Based on the examples in the last video
let's see if we can come up with some rules of thumb for figuring out how many significant figures,
or how many significant digits,
there are in a number - or a measurement.
So the first thing that is pretty obvious is that any non-zero digit,
and any of the zero digits in between are significant.
Really the 7 and the 5 here are significant and the zero's in between them, it's also going to be significant.
So let's write this over here: so, any non-zero digits and zero's in between
are going to be significant. That's pretty straightforward.
Now the zero's that are not in between non-zero digits, these become a little bit more confusing.
So let's just make sure we can rule out some of them.
So you can always rule out - when you're thinking about significant figures -
the leading zero's.
And when I talk about leading zero's, I'm talking about the zero's
that come before your non-zero digit.
So these are leading zero's here, these are leading zero's.
There's no leading zero's here, no leading zero's in this one, this one, and this one.
But in any situation, the leading zero's are not significant.
So leading zero's not significant.
And so the last question, all you have left, I mean, you only have non-zero digits
and zero's in between; you could have some leading zero's
which you've already said are not significant.
And so the only thing left that you have to figure out is what do you do with the trailing zero's,
the zero's behind the last non-zero, or to the right of, the last non-zero digit.
So that these trailing zero's here, there's actually two trailing zero's over,
and then there is three trailing zero's over here.
So let me make a little... so trailing zero's.
What do we do with them?
So the easy way to think about is, if you have a decimal,
if there is a decimal anywhere in your number, count them.
If you have a decimal count them as significant.
they are significant. Count them as significant.
If there is no decimal anywhere in the number,
then it's kind of ambiguous.
You're kind of not sure, and this is the situation.
So clearly, over here, there's a decimal in the number
so you count the trailing zeros - these are adding to the precision.
Over here, there's a decimal so you count the trailing zero.
There's a decimal here so you count the trailing zero's.
There are no trailing zero's here.
And over here, well the way I later put a decimal here,
here you would count it, so if you have a decimal there you would count all five.
If you didn't have the decimal, if you just had 37,000 like that
it's ambiguous, and if someone doesn't give you more information
you're best assumption is probably that they just measured to the nearest thousand,
that they didn't measure exactly to the one and just happened
to get exactly on 37,000.
So if there's no decimal, let me write it this way,
it's ambiguous, which means that you're really not sure what it means,
it's not clear what it means, and you're proabably safer assuming
to not count the trailing zero's.
If someone really does measure, if you were to really measure something
to the exact one, then you should put a decimal at the end like that.
And there is a notation for specifying:
let's say you do measure - let me do a different number -
let's say you do measure 56,000
and there is a notation for specifying that 6 definitely is the last significant digit
and sometimes you'll see a bar put over the 6,
sometimes you'll see a bar put under the 6.
And that could be useful, because maybe, you're last
significant digit is this zero over here,
maybe you were able to measure to the 100's with a reasonable level of precision.
And so then you would write something like,
you'd still write 56,000,
but then you would put the bar above that zero
or the bar below that zero to say that that was the last significat digit.
So if you saw something like this, you would say 3 significant digits.
This isn't used so frequently. A better way to show that you've measured
to 3 significant digits would be to write it in scientific notation.
There's a whole video on that.
But to write this in scientific notation,
you could write this as 5.60 times 10 to the fourth power, right?
Cause if you multiply this by 10 to the fourth
you'd move this decimal over four spaces
and get us to 56,000.
So 5.60 times 10 to the fourth;
and if this confuses you,
watch the video on scientific notation.
Hopefully it will clarify things a little bit.
But when you write a number in scientific notation,
it makes it very clear about your precision
and how many significant digits you're dealing with.
So instead of doing this notation that's a little bit outdated,
I haven't seen it used much,
with these bars below or above the high significant digit,
instead you can represent it with a decimal
in scientific notation
and then it's very clear you have 3 significant digits.
So hopefully that helps you out.
In the next couple of videos,
we'll explore a little bit more why significant digits are important
especially when you do calculations with multiple measurements.