Now that we know a little bit about how to construct a unit normal vector
at any point in a curve--that's what we did in the last video--
I wanna start exploring and interesting expression.
So the expression is: The line integral around a closed loop, and we're gonna go in the positive counter
clockwise orientation
of a vector field F dotted with the unit normal vector at any point on that curve ds
(I'll write ds in magenta)
ds.
So first lets conceptualize what this is even saying
and then let's manipulate it a little bit to see if we can come up with
and interesting conclusion, we actually will manipulate it
we'll use green's theorem
and we're actually gonna come up with a 2 dimensional
version of the divergence theorem
which all sounds very complicated
but hopefully we can get a little bit of an intuition
for it as to why it actually a little bit of common sense.
So, first lets just think about this.
So let me draw- let me draw a coordinate plane here
so we do it in white
So this right over here thats our y axis
that over there is our x axis
let me draw ourselves my curve so my curve might look
something like--I'll do it in a blue color
so my curve might look something like this- my contour
and its going in the positive, counterclockwise direction
just like that
and now we have our vector field, and just a reminder
we've seen this multiple times
I can- my vector field will associate a vector with any
point on the x-y plane
and it will-- it can be defined as some function
of x and y, which I'll call that P
some function of x and y times the i unit vector
so it says what the i component of the vector field is for any x and y point
and then what the j component, or what we multiply
the j component by
or the vertical component by for any x and y point
so some function of x and y times i
plus some other scalar function of x and y
times j
and so if you give me any point
there will be an associated vector with it
any point there is an associated vector depending on
how we define this function.
But this expression right over here
we're taking a line integral
we care specifically about the points about along this curve
along this contour
right over here and so lets think about what this is actually
this piece right over here is actually telling us
before we sum up all of these infinitesimally small pieces
so if we just take f dot n
so lets just think about a point on this curve
so a point on this curve may be this point right over here
so associated with that point there is a vector
that's what the vector field does
So f might look something like that right over there
so that might be f at that point
and we're gonna dot it with the unit normal vector at that point
so the unit normal vector might look something like that
that would be n hat at that point
this is the vector field at that point