So this problem here we're told that the triangle ACE is isosceles
so that's this big triangle right here
Its isosceles which means it has two equal sides and we also know
from isosceles triangles that the base angles must be equal
So this two base angles are going to be equal
and this side right over here
is going to be equal in length to this side over here
We can say AC is going to be equal to CE so we get all of that
from this first statement right over there
Then they gave us some more clues or some more information
They say CG is equal to 24 so this is CG
right over here it has length 24
They tell us BH is equal to DF BH is equal to DF so those two things
are going to be congruent they're gonna be the same length
Then they tell us that GF is equal to 12
so this is GF right over here
so GF is equal to 12 that distance right over there
And then they finally tell us that FE is equal to 6 so this is FE
And then finally they ask us what is the area of CBHFD so CBHFD
so they're asking us for the area they're asking us for the area
of this part right over here
Let me that part and that part right over there that is CBHFD
So let's think about how we can do this
We can figure out the area of the larger triangle and then from
that we could subtract the areas of this little pieces at the end
Then we'll be able to figure out this middle area this area
that I've shaded then we don't have
the information yet to solve that
We don't know the height or the altitude of this triangle is
We don't know it's base if we knew its base
We would say hey! one half base times height we'd get the area
of this triangle and then we have to figure out subtract this areas
And we don't have full information there either
We don't know this height once we know that height
then we could figure out this height but we also don't quite yet know
what this length right over here is
So let's just take it piece by piece
So the first thing we might want to do and you might guess
cause we've been talking a lot about similarities
making some type of argument about similarity here
because there's a bunch of similar triangles
For example, triangle CGE shares this angle with triangle DFE
They both share this orange angle right here
and they both have this right angle right over here
So, they have two angles in common they're going to be similar
by angle-angle you can actually show there's should be a third angle
in common because this two are parallel lines
So, we can write the triangle CGE is similar to triangle DFE
And we know that by angle-angle
We have one course set of corresponding angles congruent
and then this angle is in both triangle so it is a set
of corresponding congruent angles right over there
And so then once that we know that they're similar,
we can set up the ratio between sides
'Cause we have some information about some of the sides
so we know that the ratio we know that the ratio between DF
and this side right over here which is a corresponding side
The ratio between DF and CG so the ratio between DF and CG
which is 24 is going to be the same thing as the ratio between FE,
FE which is 6 and GE which is not 12 it's 12 plus 6 it is 18
And then let's see 6 over 18 this is just 1 over 3,
you get 3 DF is equal to 24
I just cross multiplied or you could multiply both sides by 24
Multiply both sides by 3 you would get this
Actually you could just multiply both sides 24
and then you get 24 times one-third but we'll just do it this way
divide both sides by 3 you get DF, DF is equal to 8
So, we found out that DF is equal to 8 that length right over there
And that's useful for us
Because we know that this length right over here is also equal to 8
And now what could we do?
Well we can make another seems
like we can make another similarity argument
'cause we have this angle right over here
It is congruent to that angle right over there
And we also have this angle which is going to be 90 degrees
We have a 90-degree angle there and actually said that by itself
is actually enough to say that we have two similar triangles
We don't even have to show that they have a congruent side here
and actually were gonna show this are two congruent triangles
that we're dealing with right over here
So we have two angles and actually we could just go straight to that
'cause when we talk about congruency
if you have an angle that's congruent to another angle,
another angle that's congruent to another angle
and then a side that's congruent to another side you're dealing
with 2 congruent triangles
So, we can write triangle right over here I'll write it in pink
Triangle AHB is congruent is congruent to triangle
You wanna get the corresponding vertices right
We can read the triangle EFD to triangle EFD and we know that
because we angle-angle-side postulate for congruency
And if that two triangles are congruent that makes things convenient
that means if this side is 8, that side is 8 we already knew that
That's how we established our congruency but that means
if this side is 6 has length 6
and the corresponding set on this triangle
is also going to have length 6
So we can write this length right over here is also going to be 6
Now I can imagine, you can imagine where all of this is gonna go
but we want to prove to ourselves
we want know for sure what the areas
We don't want to say "Hey maybe this is the same thing as that"
Let's just actually prove it to ourselves
So how do we figure out we've almost figure out the entire base
of this triangle but we still haven't figure out the length of HG
Well now we can use a similarity argument again
because we can see that
triangle ABH is actually similar to triangle ACG
They both have this angle here and then they both have a right angle
that one ABH has right angle there ACG
has a right angle right over there
So you have two angles two corresponding
angles are equal to each other
You're now dealing with similar triangles
So we know that triangle ABH ill just write it this as AHB
since I already wrote it this way
AHB is similar to triangle AGC
You want to make sure you got the vertices in the right order
A is orange angle G is the right angle and C is the unlabeled angle
This is similar triangle AGC
Now what that does for is that we could use the ratios to figure out
what HG is equal to so what can we say over here
Well we can say that 8 over 24
BH over its corresponding side of the larger triangle
So we say 8 over 24 is equal to 6 is equal to 6 over not HG
but over AG 6 over AG and I think you can see where this is going
You have one-third is equal to 6 over AG
or we can cross multiply here and we can get AG is equal to 18
So this entire length right over is 18 if AG is 18 and AH is,
then HG is 12
And this is what you might have guessed if you were just trying
to guess the answer right over here
But now we have proven to ourselves that this base is has length of
Well we have 18 here
and we have another 18 here so has a length of 36
so the entire base here is 36, so that is 36
And so now we can find out the area of this larger
of this entire isosceles triangle
So, the area of ACE is going to be equal to one-half times the base
which is 36 times 24
And so this going to be the same thing as one-half times 36 is 18
18 times 24 I'll just do that over here at the top so 18 times 24
8 times 4 is 32, one times 4 is 4, plus 3 is 7,
let me put a zero here
because we're not dealing math with 2 but 20
If 2 times 8 is 16, 2 times one is 2 plus 1 so it's 316
and then you have 2, 7 plus 6 is 13, one plus 3 is 4
So the area is ACE is equal to 432 but were not done yet
This area that we that we care about
is the area of the entire triangle minus this area
and minus this area right over here
So what is the area what is the area of this each
of this little wedges right over here
So it's going to be one-half times 8 times 6, so one-half times 8,
is 4 times 6
So this is going to be 24 right over there and this is going
to be another 24 right over there
So this is going to be equal to 432 minus 24 minus 24, or minus 48
Which is equal to and we could try this to do this on our head
If we subtract 32 we're gonna get to 400
and then were gonna have to subtract another 16
So if you subtract 10 from 400 its 390 so that you get to 300 you get
to 384 whatever they units for this were
If these were in meters and this would be meters squared
If this centimeters this will be in centimeters squared
And did I do that right?
Let me go the other way if I add 8 if I add 40 to this
24 plus another 8 gets me to 432
Yup and were done