We are on problem 7.
Let me draw what they have drawn.
They drew a right triangle.
The right triangle looks something like this.
And then they drew another triangle.
And it looks like an isosceles triangle,
although we can't assume anything in this life.
Nothing comes for free. So this is x. This is y.
u, v, w. Those are the angles.
In the triangles above, what is the average--
arithmetic mean-- of u, v, w, x, and y
So you have to just add up the sum of the angles
and then divide by the number of angles.
So we want to take u plus v plus w plus x plus y,
So there's one, two, three,four, five angles.
First question. What is u plus v plus w?
Well, they form the angles in a triangle,
so they're going to add up to 180 degrees.
And what's x plus y? Well, it's a right triangle.
And all three of these angles have to add up to 180.
x plus y plus this 90 have to add up to 180.
So x plus y is going to be equal to 90.
Just subtract 90 from both sides.
So x plus y is equal to 90.
So if we take the sum of the top, 180 plus 90, that's 270.
Divided by 5.
5 goes into 270-- 5, 25, 7, 20, 54.
So the average is 54 degrees.
That's the arithmetic mean of all of those angles.
And that is choice E.
Next problem.
I just inadvertently switched back to my bad-luck yellow.
All right. Problem 8.
Looks like they've drawn--It looks like a ray.
I'm going to put an arrow on one side. Let me switch colors.
They say that this is x to the third.
This is x squared. This is x.
If x, x squared, and x to the third lie on a number line
in the order shown above,
which of the following could be the value of x?
So the first thing we know, x has got to be--
well, the first thing we know, that x is a positive number.
How do I know that?
Because if x was not a positive number--
well, let me think about that. Right.
x has to be a positive number.
Because-- let me put it this way.
If any negative number-- let's say it's negative 1/2.
If you square negative 1/2, you get positive 1/4.
So for any negative number,
the square is going to be bigger than the number itself.
So we know that x is greater than 0.
That's one thing we know. What else do we know?
We also know that x is going to be less than 1.
How do I know that?
Because x squared is less than x,right?
And that only applies for numbers less than 1.
Because 1/2 squared is equal to 1/4,and 1/4 is less than 1/2.
So we also know that x is less than 1.
So we just have to find a choice
where x is greater than 0 and less than 1.
And if we look at the choices,greater than 0 and less than 1,
there's only one choice that that applies to.
And that's 3/4. Choice C.
You might want to say 3/2,but that's 1 and 1/2.
That's greater than 1.
The first two choices are negative.
The last two choices are greater than 1--
or greater than or equal to 1.
So we know it's choice C.
Next problem.
And if you didn't want to do it in an abstract way,
and if you have a lot of time,
if you're really fast on the problems you do know how to do,
you can always try out the numbers. But that takes longer.
They drew a coordinate system right here.
And this is my y-axis. This is the x-axis.
And then they draw a line that goes through the origin.
And then they tell us that
this point right here is the point 1 comma 3.
So this is 1. This is 3.
And what do they want us to do with this?
In the figure above, line l passes through the origin.
This is line l. What is the value of k/h?
Oh, and then they label another point here.
They say this is h comma k.
So what is the value of k divided by h?
So the y value over the x value, right?
And I'm going to tell you right now,
the value of it is going to be the slope of this line.
And how do we know that?
If you wanted to figure out the slope
from the origin to this point, what would it be?
The origin of course is 0, 0. So it would be change in y.
Change in y is 0 minus k.
You wouldn't have to do this on the SAT.
I just want to show you that it would be the slope.
And then change in x would be 0 minus h.
And that of course is equal to minus k over minus h.
The negatives cancel out,and that equals k/h.
So they're essentially just asking us,
what is the slope of this line?
Well, that's easy enough, because it gives us another point.
And so we can say, well, we could do this rise over run.
So here, what is the change in y?
Change in y is equal to 3 minus 0.
I'm taking this as kind of the initial point.
3 minus 0. Change in x is 1 minus 0.
So change in y over change in x is equal to 3.
And that's our slope, and that's our answer.
So the answer is A.
Next problem. Problem 10.
They're saying the absolute value of m minus 3 is equal to 5.
They're also telling us that the absolute value of k
plus 7 is equal to 15.
In the equations above,m is less than 0 and k is less than 0.
What is the value of m minus k? So m is less than 0, right?
So there's two possibilities here.
This first equation, if we didn't see that,
it could mean two different things.
You could say m minus 3 is equal to 5
or m minus 3 is equal to negative 5.
This one would solve to m is equal to 8,
and this one would solve to m is equal to minus 2.
Well, we know m is not 8,because m is less than 0.
And to solve this, I just added 3 to both sides.
So we know that m is minus 2.
Similarly, let's take that second equation.
That tells us that k plus 7 is equal to 15,
or k plus 7 is equal to minus 15.
Subtract 7 from both sides of this, you get k equals 8.
Subtract 7 from both sides of this,
you get k is equal to minus 22.
And they tell us that k is also less than 0.
So we know that this is k.
And they want us to know what m minus k is.
Well, m is minus 2,and k is minus 22.
So minus 2 minus minus 22.
So that's the same thing as minus 2 plus 22.
And that is of course 20. And that is choice E.
I will see you in the next video.