PROBLEM: "Where is 30 on the number line?"
So on the number line right over here, we see that
as we go from 0, the first slash isn't 1. It's 3.
So with each slash we move to the right,
the numbers go up by 3.
So let's see if we can figure out where 30 is.
So this slash is marked as 3.
So this is going to be 3 more. So it's 6.
Then 9, 12, 15, 18, 21, 24, 27, and 30.
Another way you could have thought about this is
since each of these marks is 3, to get to 30,
we have to step through 10 of these marks.
So we go [COUNTING] 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.
Let's do a few more.
PROBLEM: "Where is 24 on the number line?"
Well, once again, each of these marks is 3.
So it's going to be 3, 6, 9, 12, 15, 18, 21, and 24.
Let's do one more.
So in this problem, each mark is 4.
So we're going to go 4, 8,12, 16, and 20.
Another way you could think about it
is that if each step is 4,
you have to go up 5 times to get up to 20.
So this is 1 2 3, 4, 5.
Either way, this should be the right answer.