Well, now I'm gonna talk to you about pressure, resistance, and flow.
We're gonna try to make sure you feel real comfortable with all three of these things.
So, we start with the heart.
And after the heart is the aorta.
It's the largest artery in the body.
And this is one branch of the aorta.
I didn't draw a lot the other one.
This is the brachial artery.
And the blood is flowing
from the aorta to the brachial artery.
And let's say that the blood
is trying to make its way out to
a fingertips, for example.
So, on its way out there makes its way to an arteriole.
And the blood continues flowing.
And it goes into a capillary bed.
And the vessel is the small to draw,
so I just kinda do that thing.
And -then, goes into the other half of the capillary bed,
where now the blood is deoxygenated.
So I'm gonna draw that is blue.
That's the part where now the blood is without oxygen.
And then it continues to go and get collected into a venule,
which sounds little bit like the arterial in the other side, right?
We got a vein over here,
and then finally the blood gets collected in a large vein called the vena cava.
And there're actually tro vena cavas.
So, this'll be the superior vena cava,
this's also an inferior vena cava.
And the blood flow through this half is as you guess,
kind of continue to go around.
And if I were to try to figure out the pressures,
the blood pressures at different points along this system,
I'm gonna choose some points that I think would be interesting ones to check,
so it'll be good probably to check what the pressure is right at the beginning.
And then maybe at all the branch points.
So, what the pressure is as the blood goes from the aorta to the brachial artery.
Maybe as it ends the brachial artery and enters the arteriole.
Maybe the beginning and the end of the capillaries.
Also from the venule to a vein,
and also wrapping it up, what the pressure is at the end.
Obvious numbers or these pressures can be represent its number, right.
Like what is the millimeters of mercury,
that the blood is exerting on the wall
at that particular point in the system
And earlier we talked about
the systolic versus diastolic pressure.
And there we want you to use two numbers,
because that's kind of the range,
the upper and the lower range of a pressure.
But now, I'm gonna do with one number.
And the reason why I'm using one number of two,
is that this is the average pressure over time.
So the average pressure over time for me,
keep in mind my blood pressure is pretty normal,
it's somewhere around 120 over 80 in my arm.
So, the average pressure in the aorta
-kinda coming out- would be somewhere around 95
and in the artery in the arm probably somewhere around 90,
again, that's what you'd expect, somewhere between 80-120.
So 90 is the average, because it's gonna be not exactly 100.
Because remember, it's spending more time in diastole,
in relaxation, than in systole.
So, it's gonna be close to that 80, for that reason,
And then if you check the pressure over here, by this X,
probably something like --let's say 80,
And then as you cross the arteriole,
the pressure falls dramatically,
so it's somewhere closer to 30.
and then here it's about 20,
here's about 15,
let's say 10 over here.
And then, at the very end it's gonna be close to a 5 or so.
So, here I'm just write that in 10, and 5.
And the units here are millimiters of mercury,
so I just write that pressure [P] in millimeter of mercury [mmHg].