At my house, no Thanksgiving dinner is complete, without mathed potatoes.
To make mathed potatoes, start by boiling the potatoes until they soft, which will take
about 15 to 20 minutes.
After you drain them and let them cool slightly, you're ready for the math.
Take one potato and divide it evenly to get half a potato plus half a potato.
Then divide the halves into fourths and the fourths into eighths and so on.
Eventually you'll have a completely mathed potato that looks like this.
Once you have proven this result for one potato you can apply to other potatoes without going through the entire process.
That's how math works.
While I prefer refined and precise methods for mathing a potato,
many people just apply brute force algorithms.
You can also add other variables like butter, cream, garlic, salt and pepper.
Place in the hemisphere and garness with a organic hyperbolic plain and your mathed potatoes are ready for the table.
Together with a cranberry cylinder and a nice basket of bread spheres
with butter prism, you'll be well on your way to create a delicious and engaging Thanksgiving meal.
Here's a serving tip: When arranging mathed potatoes on your plate, it is important to do it in a way that holds gravy.
If you just make a mound the gravy will fall off.
It's best to create a choc or pool, but what shape will maximize the amount of gravy it can hold?
Due to the structural properties of mathed potatoes,
this can essentially be reduced to a 2 dimensional gravy pool problem.
Where you want the most gravy area given a certain potato perimeter.
When I think of this question I like to think about inflating shapes.
Say you inflated a triangle. It would add more area and round out into a circle.
And then if the perimeter can't change then it would pop!
In fact all 2D shapes inflate into circles.
And in 3D it's spheres, which is why bubbles like to be round.
And turkeys are spheroid because that optimizes for maximum stuffing.
The limited 3 dimensional capacity of mathed potatoes may confuse things a little
but since a mathed potato sphere can't support itself, you're really stuck with extrusion to 2D shapes.
So what's better: A deep mathed potato cylinder or a shallow but wider one?
Well think of it like this: If you slice the deep version in half,
you'll see it has equivalent gravy holding capacity to 2 separate shallow cylinders.
And the perimeter of 2 circles would be more efficient if combined into one bigger circle.
So the solution is to create the biggest, roundest, shallowest gravy pool you can.
In fact maybe you should just skip the mathed potatoes and get a bowl.
Anyway I hope this simple recipe helps you have an optimal Thanksgiving experience.
Advanced chefs in kitchens may which to try Banic Starkey potatoes
where in after you cut a potato in a particular way, you put the pieces back together and get 2 potatoes.
Stay tuned for more delicious and extremely practical Thanksgiving recipes this week.