We are in the British Museum
looking at a large ivory panel
usually ivories are very
small.
This is huge and apparently it's actually
one-half of a diptych, whats interesteing is that
even though it is in the British Museum it is
originally comes from Constantinople so this is a Byzantine object
It looks like the other half of the diptych
would have been on the left side
the angel who is in this ivory, let me just say this
the ivory is probably about 18 inches?
Yeah, I would say so. Probably about 5 and a half or six.
Right, the other panel would have been on the left
and the Archangel would have been looking
in the direction of what would have been the other
figure in the other panel.
And you can further tell that the panel would have been on the left because you can actually see
through the holes that would have been functioning as part of the hinge.
Right, and the deptic of course
means the work of art made out of two panels as opposed to a triptych
which is three panels.
We can assume that there would have been another saint on the other side
another Angel perhaps.
Another angel or, perhaps the Angel giving this
orb to a king or an emperor.
So we see Greek text up at the top and below that we see this incredibly ornate arch
with a cross above that and the cross is surmounting an orb
there seems to be almost kind of a sunburst
behind it, very decorative beautiful carving of a kind of
ribbon or banner just below the reef and then some
broad open areas under some dentals these are just Architectural elements
we see Corinthian pilasters framing the figure.
It actually reminded me of an apse in a church with a archway behind
those columns and may be perhaps the kind of recessed space.
Even though this is carved in such a shallow relief carving
it's so flat
You do get the sense of real architectural space there
and then the figure himself is so interesting
because it's so classicizing in some ways
This is though very much a byzantine rendering, look at the
size of the archangel in relationship, for instance, to the staircase.
He is very large so to me, yes he very much takes up
that also faces of kind of hierarchy of scale
so that his size matters his divine nature.
So this is interesting because this is
very classicizing, look at the drapery
Yeah, it's very classical
he wears even up against the wings of, you know he is an Angel
he is an Archangel and...
but he has this classical toga on.
Yes, and it's actually getting fairly late
to see that kind of synthesis, right?
Even his hair, the curls in his hair look like a Roman sculture
It's true, if you stripped away the wings
if you stripped away the cross and the orb
you could be looking at a kind of a roman potrait.
The detail here in the carving is remarkable
the lines that make up each of the feathers
in the angel's wings or the little
circular swirling decorations in his cuff,
the delicacy of his hand as he holds the staff
the other hand holding the orb with the cross on it
the symbol of power but we know that
we are not in the classical world anymore
the way that I know that is by
not only his size in relationship to the Architecture
but when I look down at his feet.
Aah, how so?
You know, he doesnt
really stand on the ground, his feet sort of flatted out
and hang over the stairs
he doesn't really make contact with the ground in a meaningful way
and that suggests to me a kind of weightlessness
a kind of spirituality that reminds me of byzantine and
medieval art.
The handling of the body, which by the way really
is transparent behind the cloth
you know the body really does swell that cloth
it's not that later medieval rejection of the body below
but this is still coming out of the classical
Look at his toes.
They are great toes!
Aren't they?
They are great.
I mean this is such a strange combination
of the spiritual and the human that is
a very funny moment in early christian and byzantine art
There is a kind of awkwardness
with the synthesis it hasn't been worked out yet
It really is a clash of traditions
of Pagan and Christian
Absolutely.