So, every winter a lot of kids come in
and see me because they've got
flu and I've got to make a decision.
For each one of them, I've got to decide
Am I going to get the flu test in this particular child?
So, when I see a kid that's sick
here's what I'm thinking
I'm thinking, well, the first thing I've got to decide is
do I really suspect the flu?
This is when I ask a lot of questions
of the person who's sick or the parents.
I say, "Well, when did it start?"
"Was it abrupt?"
That's my first clue that it really is the flu.
The second clue is, "How long did it last?"
They might say, "You know, we're in the middle of it.
It's been a few days."
But if they tell me it's been weeks and weeks
and months and months, then of course I'm thinking
it's something else. It's not the flu then.
And, finally, if they tell me that they're having
respiratory symptoms, then that's of course really important.
That sounds like the flu.
But, they also have to have some constitutional symptoms.
They have to have a fever or fatigue to convince me
that this sounds like the flu.