we go upstairs into the rooms of the noviciet
thtat is for the novices, who are joining jessuit
order. in the 1500s this was a new order
of religion founded by ignatius lowen in 1556
we've swtumbled int a room. it is almost an active
shock certainly surprised to see what appears
to be a young man on his deathbed. somtimes
in the gloom entering this room you really think that
somebody is in front of you lying on a couch
a sort of day bed. and this is stannish lez cock.
he is a young polish novice of the jessuit order
he died only at 18. and he bore his tubuleaous bread and tudious trength
and died with a vision of virgin mary before him
this was made before he was officially declared
a saint. this was made in 1703. whatwe see is a very
richly carved, a very detailed statue of a young man
lying very naturalistically on a bed and
everything is color here. it is awery ti stun that we have
sicilian jaspberry, an opal coloured marble
we have a deep black stone marble for clothing the
newart, for he as member of the jessuit order ought to be wearing black
and white pillows and of course the flesh is done
in white marble. he is holding an image of
the virgin and the crucifix. and he would have
originally had a halo which would have picked up
that sense of yellow and gold and even more.
as i said he is not realistic. he is not lying
as if he has died and we are watching him lying in state here.
he is still alive or he is in the moment of passing .
and this was something that fascinated buroka artists.
but nene who had died by the time this was done
was really one of the pioneers in showing the transition
the trapazzo from life to death or those moments
in which you go from the earthly to spiritual form
life to death but that was acomfitting return of
singular force it is very intimate . and thats why it has
shocked ina good way many of the cisitors who have
come into this room. it is a very intimate place
it is a quiet sight of the burrer.burrer does not necessarily
mean loud. it is life size.llywe are attending persona lly
to this young mans death. and this was part of the art of
jassued persuasive of. the artists persuasion
prove example thro art agian thro reading
of course as well. you are brought close to
what matters about , the passing from life to death
and in this case as you see absolutely unshakeable faith.
and the realism of this is such so moving and
upsetting in a way that the way that he
lifts his arm up to hold the framed image
of the virgin and clasps with his other hand
the rosary and the cross. its that that
moment of you know someting is happening in front of you
in the 19th century ther was a railing around it
for now there is not that mount of trust. we are
not touching it we could stretch an arm and shke it with his hand
the crucifix is a separate carved object
in the rosaries roll.but if you look closely
the details such as the eyes and the nails
of hi fingers and toenails ae crefully incised
this is a very detailed work about. while the
floor the draper and bed itself is so dramatic
work. i think itis so for this work is very hard and is
meant to be seen very close the fineness of the cloth is
as unso accurate of the undershirt and the collar
jus tthe way it should look it is not different from the collar that
i am wearing see the burro is not censored
we ar eso privilegeed that this is a very privaate moment htat we have been given access to
and it is so interesting for we have joined this moment
you have this sweetness and this intimacy
enchanting experience. but it is not conflict it is
a spectrum of experience. it is a range