Alright, this is a universal remote control; we are going to take it apart today, to see whats inside it and what makes it tick.
There are 2 different kinds of universal remote controls.
There are learning remotes and then there are ones that function on code libraries.
So this one functions on a code library, the learning remotes tend to be more expensive.
What the learning remotes do,
you can put it next to the original remote and basically,
use the original remote to train the learning remote and then it will
it will function like the original. Those like I said before tend to be more expensive.
As they are more complex. This one just has a code library built in so you
enter a certain sequence of numbers and you can pull up a certain code and then that
will allow this to trigger what ever devise that code goes with.
So I have already cut the box apart here
so lets go ahead and pull the remote out