Use your calculator to find the values of sin 28 degrees and Cosecant of 28 degrees to the nearest thousandth.
So I'll do it several ways I'll first let you give a shot at it. Using your calculator try to figure out what the sin of 28 degrees is. Try to figure that out.
Well I'll do it on several calculators first this calculator is kind of a typical scientific calculator no two calculators are completely identical but you want to make sure it is in degree mode because we are dealing with degrees here not radians and it is indeed in degree mode so if we type in 28 and then take the sin of it
So it says sin d - sin in degree mode
We want to round to the nearest thousandth so the thousandths place is the 9
And then the ten thousands is a four so we want to round down, if this was five or higher we would round up.
So we get 0.469 so we say approximately equal to 0.469
It's not exactly equal to it because we are of course rounding.
Now let me do that in a different calculator just to get a little bit of variety.
This is kind of a traditional graphing calculator and once again we want to make sure that we are in degree mode. So this over here says mode in yellow to get to that yellow function we have to press 2nd first.
so press 2nd and then we go to mode and it's good we checked because we see right over here we were in radian mode and we want to be in degree mode
So let's go to degree mode just like that so we've set degree mode now let's exit
And now let's just take the sin
Here we can just type it in the way we can write it on paper so sin of 28 and now we know we are taking degrees
And we get the exact same thing 0.469
If we round to the nearest thousandth
Now let's figure out the cosecant of 28 degrees. Cosecant of 28 degrees what is that going to be?
Or roughly equal to if we round to the nearest thousandth.
Well you might remember the cosecant is just the recipricol of the sin.
The sin is opposite over hypotenuse. The cosecant is hypotenuse over opposite.
So it is literally just going to be the reciprocal it's just going to be the reciprocal of sin 28 degrees
Or the reciprocal of this value right over here. So we could use either calculator.
So this is going to be exactly equal to 1 over the sin of 28 degrees which if we round to the nearest thousandth is going to be, so I can use the graphing calculator first, graphing calculator I can redo the whole thing
So 1 divided by I could do the last answer or I could just say 1 divided by sin of 28 degrees which gives us to the nearest thousandth 2.130
2.130 and let's verify it's the same thing that we get with the other calculator
So this is what we got for the sin of 28 degrees.
If we want to take the reciprocal of this it's literally just 1 over X. 1/X and you see we get the exact same thing 2.130