Before we go into possible theories as to why plates actually move,
what I want to do in this video is think a little bit about why we see the geological features
we do see at plate boundaries, and in particular I want to focus on the features
we see at divergent plate boundaries, where the plates are moving away from each other,
where new land is being created like we saw in the mid-oceanic ridges,
where we see new land being created right in the center and moving outwards from them.
So to do that let's think about the different layers,
and actually, I want to make one quick correction on the last video.
Over here I had drawn these arrows going in that direction,
and based on how I defined them, they should be going into the page
and so they should've had these Xs here.
Now, with that out of the way, let's draw a little diagram
of what happens at the early stages of these divergent plate boundaries.
So you might have your... here you have just your crust,
and maybe it's continental crust...
This right here is the Earth's crust,
and then you have the solid part of the mantle.
And the combination of them is the lithosphere.
And then you have the liquid part, the superhot part of the mantle,
so this down here is magma.
It hasn't solidified, it's hot enough to be in the liquid state.
And all of this combined, this right here we consider the mantle.
Now, there's some debate, and we'll talk about this in the next video,
of how hotspots actually form, it could be these mantle plumes
that start at the border between the mantle and the core,
it could be some type of convection currents in the actual mantle,
we'll talk more about that in the next video or maybe a few videos from now.
But let's take it for granted that hotspots form in the mantle,
so let's say we have an area of magma right here, that is particularly hot.
Let me draw it in in another color... pink.
So this is particularly hot magma here.
And we know, or maybe we don't know, you'll learn to know right now,
if you take the same material and you make it hotter, it's going to become less dense
because the particles essentially are going to bump into each other with more kinetic energy
and have more space in between them.
and so this really hot part of the magma or this really hot part of the mantle, it is going to move upwards,
it is going to move upwards,
because it is less dense, it will have buoyancy.
And as it moves upwards, it'll heat up the things around it
and it'll eventually make its way into the lithosphere
and it'll be able to break through the lithosphere because it's so hot it can melt its way through.
So let's fast forward this a little bit,
so this is Step 1 up here.
Now Step 2 - this hot magma is rising out through the lithosphere,
and so it's going to create a hotspot, a dome in the lithospere and actually on the crust,
and so it might look like this.
So the crust is now going to have a dome in it.
And this is the original lithosphere,
and it's now kind of been broken into by this hotspot.
So the lithosphere is now broken into, or about to be broken into by this hotspot.
All of this is still the lithosphere, I just write 'litho' for short,
this up here is the crust.
And if you take any rigid material, and the crust and the lithisphere they are rigid,
and you push outward on that, it won't stretch nicely like a nice elastic balloon,
it will start to crack, it have to be pulled apart on order to kind of take the pushing from below.
So this crust is going to start to crack.
Actually, the best example where you see this is actually in like sourdough bread
that has really hard shell around it.
You see sourdough bread, let me see if I can draw a loaf of sourdough bread.
It has these cracks on the surface
and that's because the outer layer, the outer shell of the bread is really rigid
and so if the inside heats up and the surface really has to expand,
these kind of rift form in the bread to allow that kind of rigid shell to actually expand.
The exact same thing would happend to the crust, or acutally the entire lithosphere.
So let me draw this hotspot again.
I'll do it in the pink color.
Now the hotspot has got this far.
This is the hot magma right over here.
And if we fast-forward a little bit more, the crust starts to be fully pulled apart.
So you fast-forward a little bit more,
the bottom boundary of the lithosphere might be now start to look something like this,
the magma has kind of broken through the hardened part, the rigid part of the mantle,
so maybe it looks like this right now.
You have the hotspot right over here.
It's got that far now.
And all the crust on top, what we normally see,
has now been pulled apart to kind of have to cover this new surface area.
So now it looks something like this.
It's been pushed apart, let me see how well I can draw this.
So now it's been pushed apart, and as it gets pushed apart, it kind of thins out a little bit.
As you can imagine it's almost exactly as the bread analogy.
When you look at bread like this, the rift, the depression which is expanding most vigorously,
those parts of the bread are actually thinner and they're not as hard as the parts that moved away.
And you see that exact same thing happening with the land.
And all of this stuff is going to start getting pushed, continuously getting pushed outwards,
essentially to kind of make space for this hotspot.
Now, this step right over here you might have a volcano or two,
but more importantly, you're going to have what's called a rift valley.
Right now we're assuming that we're not below the sea level yet,
or we're assuming that this kind of depression in the land that you see here
hasn't come in contact with another body of water,
and so it'll just become a little valley in between higher land.
You actually see that on Earth.
And the most famous is the African Great Rift Valley.
That's right about this region.
Actually, I've got a better diagram that depicts the African Rift Valley right over here.
This whole region of Africa is actually a big valley created by a hotspot right over there.
Now, as a hotspot kind of keeps maturing,
eventually some of the rift
will become so depressed that'll actually be below the sea level.
Remember, all of this land appear is being stretched apart.
So let me go to the next step. The next step will be right over here.
The land on top is now maybe below sea level, in this next step
and comes in contact with what we view an ocean or a sea.
And so now it might look like this.
So now the land is super-thin on top, I'll do my best to draw it.
So super-thin on top, and remember it's keep on getting pulled apart,
from this bubble of hot magma that's coming up from below.
Let me draw it like this.
This is all solid rock here.
What I do in orange is the crust, this is kind of the rocky part of the mantle,
so the combination is the lithosphere.
And now you have the hot magma coming up like this.
And it might peak through every now and then and create a volcano there,
but in generall it's keep pushing the land up and outwards.
And so this land, even though you say: 'hey, it's been pushed up!',
because of the outward motion, this land over here is going to be lower than the land around it,
like the loaf of bread,
it get low enough, below sea level actually, it comes in contact with the body of water,
or even if it doesn't actually, water will start to gather over there.
And once again, we actually see that in the rift forming
between the African and Arabian plates.
The Red Sea is actually an example of exactly that.
The Arabian Plate is moving away from the African Plate because of this hotspot.
This is pushing all of the land up and out right over here,
and so this is going out, that is going out,
it's moving outward in every direction,
and so it creates these depressions where water can flow inwards.
The Rift Valley hasn't had water flown into it, the way the Red Sea has just yet,
but if it kept capping, eventually it's get low enough so that the water will flow into it.
So the Red Sea it exactly that.
You essentially have the Indian Ocean flowing into this rift that formed from this hotspot.
And the if you fast-forward a bunch so that finally the magma can kind of surface,
so let's fast-forward from this point even more,
and let's say now the land has been pushed a good bit apart.
Now the hotspot is actually surfaced.
Now the crust might look something like this.
So it's been pushed apart a good bit at this point,
you know, now we're talking about on the order of hundreds or tens of thousands of years,
for example, the land that was here might now be out here,
and this part of the land might now be out here.
What's going to happen is that this hotspot is going to continue fuel,
and we're assuming everything is under water at this point,
since this depression that was created it now so low,
the crust was stretched thin,
We assume that all of this under water.
The hotspot is essentially going to come out of underwater volcanoes
and start creating what's now in this body of water that's got large enough
that we can call it a mid-oceanic ridge.
And so it'll actually start creating, I'll set a different color,
it'll start creating an actual ridge with volcanoes in the centre.
So that's why One: we see things like the the Rift Valley in Africa,
we see things like the Red Sea,
and maybe more importantly, we see something like The Mid-Atlantic Rift in the middle of the Atlantic Ocean.
Where you have all this depressed land, that was essentially analogous to that Rift Valley,
but is at a much later stage and that's why it's able to collect water,
because the when the land was pushed out,
it stretched thin, water was able to flow into it,
going back to the bread analogy, it's essentially when this bread was baking
in this part the crust pushed outwards, you have this rift formed,
and then if there was some water on the bread or it was raining
or it was in kind of body of water, water would eventually flow into here.
And if that bread kept growing, this rift would have kept growing
eventually in the size of the Atlantic Ocean, our theoretical bread,
and so that's why you have this huge depressed area where an ocean can form
but in the middle of it you have this submerged mountain chain,
this submerged chain of vulcanoes, this submerged rift
where the land actually does go up a little bit because of all that magma flowing directly out of it.
So hopefully that clears up a little bit, that was a little confusing to me,
why you see uplifted land and everithing around the uplifted land
is much lower, while the whole thing is submerged as it's moving away.
So hopefully that cleared things up a little bit.