Steven: We're at SF MOMA
and we're looking at Marcel Duchamp's
Fountain, which he originally made in
1917, but which he remade in 1964.
Beth: The original is gone.
Steven: Thrown away or who knows what.
Beth: So this is a small series that
was made in 1964,
after that original work in 1917.
And he over saw the making of this series.
Steven: I think we need to be really careful
with the word "making."
Beth: [laugh]
Steven:What Duchamp did for us was go
to a plumbing supply house called Mott's
and purchased this and...
Beth: He didn't make it
Steven: He made it as a work of art
through the alchemy of the artist
he transformed this.
Beth: he turned the urinal on it's side
and signed it R. Mutt and dated it.
Steven: And submitted it to an art
exhibition for a new group that he was a
founding member of
The American Society for Independent Artists
And their notion was that the juried exhibition
that was prevalent in the United States
and New York at this time.
Remeber, Duchamp had just come over from Paris
and was in fact a real problem because
the jury always selected the traditional
work they were associated with and
this new group wanted to bring in new possibilities.
Beth: Right, so they were supposed to accept every
work that was submitted, but they
rejected this one.
Steven: I think he was really pushing the boundaries.
Beth: He submitted it as sculpture,
which to me is even more remarkable,
because when you think about sculpture it
has an even more monumental, heroic
Steven: Grand tradition.
Beth: Tradition, then even than painting.
To take this urinal and turn it on it's side.
Steven: Some art historians have dealt
with this in the most absurd way
talking about it's formal qualities with it's shine
Beth: Curves
Steven: Porcelain surface.
But it's a urinal, although it is transformed
And this is what Duchamp called a readymade.
Beth: You used the word "alchemy" before
and I think that that's an interesting word
because one of the ways that we can think about
art is a kind transformation of ordinary materials
into something really wonderful, that transports
us, and makes us see things in a new
way, even though he didn't make anything
he is asking us to see the urinal in a new way
not necessarily, as an aesthetic object
but to make us ask those philisophical
questions about what art is
and what the artist does.
Steven: He separates craftsmanship and
it's relationship to the aesthetic
enjoyment and to the profundity
of a work of art.
Just throwing it out the window.
Beth: That's the philosophical question
he wants to open up, does art
have to be made by the hand of the artist?
Steven: Of course, he's doing it in the
most absurd way by putting a urinal
forward and calling it Fountain.
Beth: So, what is art?
Is it the idea? Is it the concept?
Can the artist just have the idea
and not make the object?
Steven: Can art be pure philosophy,
pure theory?
Beth: Exactly.