Let's continue with the GMAT problems
We're on problem 16 on page 279
Problem 16
Is x greater than 1.8?
That's all they're asking us
And statement one says, x is greater than 1.7
Well that doesn't help us because --I don't know
x could be 1.71, in which case this wouldn't be true
Or x could be a million, in which case this is true
So this isn't really that helpful
We immediately see that
Statement two says that x is greater than 1.9
Well, if you're greater than 1.9
you're definitely greater than 1.8
So this is all we need, statement number two
So b
Problem 17
If n is an integer, is n plus 1 odd?
Well if n plus 1 is odd, that's the same thing as asking
is n even?
And I haven't looked at the statements yet
but that's just something
your brain might automatically connect
And let's see
What do they tell us?
Statement one tells us that n plus 2 is even
Well if n plus 2 is even, then n is definitely even
If you don't believe me, think about the number 4
4 is even, and 4 plus 2 is 6, which is still even, Right?
Because if you add 1, you're going to go from even to odd
You add 2, you go back to even, right?
So this is all we need
If n plus 2 is even, then we know that n is even
and n plus 1 is odd
And you could try it out with numbers if you don't believe me
Two
What is statement two?
n minus 1 is odd
Well this is the same thing. n minus 1 is odd
Once again this tells us that n has to be an even number
If you subtract 1 from it and you get an odd number
then it has to be even
If you say that n is 4, 4 minus 1 is 3
And try it for any even number
I don't want to over-explain with a fairly simple problem
So anyway, the answer is either of them alone are
sufficient, D
And try it out with numbers if you don't believe me
Problem 18
Is x between 1 and 2?
Is essentially what they're saying
It can't be 1 or 2, because these aren't equal signs
they're less than signs
OK
So that's what they're asking
Statement one tells us that x is essentially greater than 0
They wrote it a little different, they said 0 is less than x
So x is greater than 0
That doesn't help us. x could still be 0.1
It could be still be 1/2
So that doesn't tell us where it is in this range
It could also be 100, in which case it's out of this range
Statement two tells us that x is less than 3
So this alone doesn't help us
x could still be 2.1
Or x could still be minus a million
This doesn't help us
And even if we took them together
that would just tell us that 0 is less than x
which is less than 3
Which is a superset of this, right?
If we know that x is in this range
it doesn't tell us that x is definitely in this range
For example, if we know this is true
x could still be equal to 1/2
But 1/2 isn't in this range
x could be equal to 1.5, which is in the range
Or x could be equal to 2.5, which isn't in the range
So both of these, even taken together, are not sufficient
So the answer is e
Problem 19
These are going fast. Maybe too fast
Let me know if I'm going too fast
OK
Water is pumped into a partially filled tank
at a constant rate through an inlet pipe
At the same time, water is pumped out of the tank at a
constant rate through an outlet pipe
OK
So essentially we have a tank
There's a pipe here
So water is going in at, x-- we could say, I don't know--
meters cubed per second or-- units shouldn't matter
And it's getting pumped out at y meters cubed per second
At what rate in gallons per minute--
OK, so these aren't meters cubed per second
these are gallons per minute--
at what rate in gallons per minute is the amount of water
in the tank increasing?
So in order for the water to be increasing
more has to be coming in than going out
And the rate of it is going to be the difference
So essentially they just want to know
what x minus y gallons per minute are
If x is less than y, and we get a negative number here
then actually we have more coming out than going in
And so the water isn't increasing
So anyway, they tell us that, one
the amount of water initially in the tank is 200 gallons
That's useless
Why is that useless?
Because it just tells us how much water is in the tank
It doesn't tell us anything about the rates going in or out
So that's useless
Two
Water is pumped into the tank at a rate of
10 gallons per minute
So x is equal to 10 gallons per minute
That's the rate you're pumping into it
And out of the tank at a rate of 10
gallons every 2 1/2 minutes
So y is equal to 10 gallons per 2.5 minutes
Which is equal to what?
That's 4 gallons per minute
So that second statement
that second part of statement two
is a little bit shady, but you get a y
It's 4 gallons per minute
So you actually don't have to figure it
But if you wanted to, you could say that the rate at
which water is increasing is--
the rate at which it's coming in at 10
minus the rate it's going out
So 6 gallons per minute is actually the answer to the question
But all you have to know is that
you just needed statement two
which gives us this information to figure it out
And statement one was useless
So that's b, statement two alone is sufficient
Let's do another one
OK
So we have problem number 20
Is x negative?
OK
The first statement,they tell us that 9x is greater than 10x
So this is an interesting situation
So let's try to solve this equation
Let's subtract 10x from both sides of this equation
And if you're adding or subtracting on both sides of
an equation or inequality
the inequality stays the same
So let's subtract 10x from both sides of this
So you get 9x minus 10x is greater than 10x minus 10x
And then you get minus x is greater than 0
Or you can multiply both sides by negative 1
And when you multiply or divide by a negative number
with an inequality, you switch the inequality
x is less than 0, so we know that x is definitely negative
The other way you could have done it
you could have subtracted 9x from both sides
and you would have gotten 0 is greater than x
Which is a faster way of doing it
But either way, statement one lets us know that
x is definitely negative
Let's see what statement two does for us
Statement two
x plus 3 is positive
Well I mean, x could be 100
If x is 100, then 103 is definitely positive
Or x could be negative 1, right?
Because negative 1 plus 3 is positive 2
So this doesn't tell us any information about
whether x is negative
So this is useless
So the answer is a
Statement one alone is sufficient
Statement two alone is useless
Let's see how much time I have. I'm doing well on time
I'm on problem 21
Does 2m minus 3n equal 0?
And let's just think about this
That's the same thing as asking, does 2m equal 3n?
If you just add 3n into both sides
these are equivalent questions
If you can answer one, you can answer the other
So statement one says, m does not equal 0
Well that seems fairly useless to me
I mean, m does not equal 0, so m is still--
I could pick a random m, not equal to 0
and depending on what n is
this may or may not be true
So far that seems kind of useless for me
but maybe it's useful in conjunction with two
The next thing they say, 6m is equal to 9n
This one's interesting
So what does this tell us?
So 6m is equal to 9n
So let's divide both sides by 3
We get 2m is equal to 3n
And then we can subtract 3n from both sides
And you get 2m minus 3n is equal to 0
So statement two--
I mean, you essentially just do a little bit of algebra
and you get what we're trying to prove
So statement two is good
Statement one, do we need it at all?
Well no, because-- I mean, that is one solution
that if m and n are both equal to 0, that this thing is true
But it doesn't really do as much in the way of anything else
And we don't need it, to come up with this
So the answer is b
Statement two alone is sufficient
I'm already past 10 minutes
So that's it
I'll do 22 in the next video
See you soon