What I want to do in this video is,
I want to prove that segment AC is perpendicular to segment DB
based on the information we have in this diagram over here,
that this side (DC) has the same length as that side (BC),
this side (DA) has the same length as that side (BA),
and I'll give you a hint. We're going to use one or more of our congruent postulates.
I'll just call them postulates from now on.
And so the ones that we know -- so let me draw a little line here. This is kind of our toolkit;
we have the Side-Side-Side postulate, that if the 3 sides are congruent, then the 2 triangles are congruent.
We have Side-Angle-Side. Two sides and the angle in between are congruent, then the two triangles are congruent.
We have ASA. Two angles with the side in between. And then we have AAS. Two angles and then a side.
So any of these things we've established are postulates. We're going to assume they imply congruency.
And I'm going to also do this as what we call a "two column proof," and you don't have to do something as a two column proof,
but this is what you'll normally see in introductory geometry class, so I thought it would expose you to it.
But it is a pretty basic idea that you make a statement and you just have to give the reason for your statement.
Which is what we've been doing for any proof, but we haven't always put it in a very structured way.
So I'm just going to do it like this. I'll have 2 columns like this, like that; and I'll going to have a "statement", and I'll give the "reason" for the statement.
And so the strategy that I'm going to try to do is -- it looks like right off the bat,
it seems I can prove that triangle CDA is congruent to triangle CBA based on Side-Side-Side.
That's a pretty good starting point because once I can base congruency, then I can have angles be the same.
And the reason I can do that is because this side is the same as that side, this side is the same as that side, and they both share that side.
But I don't want to do it just verbally this time; I want to write it out properly in this two column proof.
So we have the length of segment CD is equal to the length of CB; CD = CB, and that is given.
So these two characters have the same length.
We also know that the length of segment DA is the same as the length of segment BA. So DA = BA. That's also given in the diagram.
And then we also know that CA is equal to CA, I guess we could say.
So CA is equal to itself. And it's obviously in both triangles.
So this is also given or it's obvious from the diagram. It's a bit obvious; both triangles shared that side.
So we have two triangles. Their corresponding sides have the same length, and so we know that they are congruent.
So we know that triangle CDA is congruent to triangle CBA.
And we know that by the Side-Side-Side postulate and the statements given up here.
Let me actually number our statements so we can refer back to this. 1, 2, 3, and 4.
And so Side-Side-Side postulate and statements 1, 2, and 3.
So statements 1, 2, and 3 and the Side-Side-Side postulate let us know that these two triangles are congruent.
And then if these are congruent, then we know, for example, we know that all of their corresponding angles are equivalent.
So for example, this angle is going to be equal to that angle. So let's make that statement right over there.
We know that angle DCE -- so this is going to be statement 5. We know that angle DCE -- that's this angle right over here --
is going to have the same measure -- we can even say they're congruent.
I'll say the measure of angle DCE is going to be equal to the measure of angle BCE.
And this comes straight out of statement 4. Congruency. I can put it in parenthesis. Congruency of those triangles.
This applies straight -- because they're both part of this larger triangle, they're the corresponding angles.
So they're going to have the exact same measure. Now it seems like we can do something interesting
with those two smaller triangles (they're kind of at the top left and the top right of this kite-like figure).
Because we have a side -- two corresponding sides are congruent, two corresponding angles are congruent, and they have a side in common.
They have his side in common right over here. So let's first just establish that they have this side in common right over here.
So I'll just write statement 6. We have CE -- the length of that line is equal to itself. Once again, this is just obvious.
Obvious from diagram. It's the same line. Obvious from diagram. But now we can use that information -- so we don't have 3 sides,
we haven't proven to ourselves that this side is the same as that side, that DE is the same length as EB,
but we do have a side, an angle between the sides, and another side. And so this looks pretty interesting for our Side-Angle-Side postulate.
And so we can say, "By the Side-Angle-Side postulate, we can say that triangle DCE is congruent to triangle BCE."
And when I write the labels for the triangles, I'm making sure that I'm kind of putting the corresponding points.
So I started D, then went to C, then went to E. So the corresponding angle or corresponding point or vertex I could say
for this triangle right over here is B. So if I started with D, I start with B.
C in the middle is the corresponding vertex for either of these triangles, so I put it in the middle, and then they both go to E.
And that's just to make sure that we are specifying what corresponding to what.
And we know this is true by Side-Angle-Side and the information we got from --
so we got this side is established, that these two sides are congruent was from statement 1,
then that these angles are congruent is from statement 5, right over here, and then statement 6 gave us the other side.
Statement 6, just like that. And if we know that these two triangles are congruent, that means that all of their corresponding angles are congruent.
So we know, for example, that this angle right over here is going to be congruent to that angle over there.
So let's write that down. So we know statement 8. The measure of angle DEC is equal to the measure of angle BEC.
And this comes straight from statement 7. Once again, they're congruent. Congruency.
And then we also know -- we'll make statement 9 -- that the measure of angle DEC -- or maybe we should just write this way.
Angle DEC and angle BCE are supplementary. You can just look at that from inspection, but I'll write it decent --
are supplementary, which means they add up their measures add up to 180 degrees.
And we know that because they're adjacent and outer sides form straight angle.
And then, we can essentially -- the next step if we know that these two angles are equal to each other,
and if we know that they're complementary, our next step means that we can actually deduce that they must be 90 degrees.
So 10, measure of angle DEC equals the measure of angle BEC, which equals 90 degrees.
And then for the reason it might be more involved, we can put these two statements together,
so it'll be statements 8 and 9, and then statements 8 and 9 mean that DEC -- so I can write
this measure of angle DEC plus measure of angle -- actually, let me just --
since I don't want to too many steps all at once, let me just take it a little bit by a little bit.
So let me just do it all like this. So let me say, "Measure of angle DEC plus measure of angle BEC is equal to 180,
and this comes straight from point 9 that they are supplementary."
And then we can say statement (I'm taking a lot of space now) 11, we could say,
"Measure of angle DEC plus measure of angle DEC is equal to 180 degrees."
And we know that from statement 9 and statement 8. We essentially just took statement 9
and substituted that the measure of BEC is the same as the measure as DEC.
And so then if we want statement 12, we can say, "Angle DEC is equal to 90, which is equal to the measure of angle BEC."
And then, this comes, once again, straight out of point number 11 and 8.
And what you can see is I'm kind of taking a little bit more time, going a little bit more granular to the steps,
and some other person would have said, "Oh, obviously, this implies this or that." And then we're done!
Because if these are 90 degrees, -- so let me write the last statement -- so statement 13, which is what we wanted to prove.
We wanted to prove that AC is perpendicular to DB. So AC is perpendicular to segment DB,
and it comes straight out of point 12. And we're done!
We've done a two column proof, and we've proven that this line segment right over here is perpendicular to that line segment right over there.
We did it with the SSS postulate and the Side-Angle-Side postulate.