When you want to make a circle,
how is it done?
Well you probably will start with
the radius one.
Then use a compass or a string
and use a paper or the ground
and if the radius is one,
how far did you go around?
It's Tau, 6.28, yeah it's Tau, 6.28318
17958...
If you pick a certain distance
and you pick a certain spot
and you put the two together ,
then what have you got?
It makes a very special shape
and now you are the inventor
if you take all of the points
a certain distance from your center
and you've got a great collection
and it is a great invention
and it makes a lovely circle,
well depending on dimension.
Cause it's 1, 2, 3,
then there's 4 and even more,
but for a circle, how much circle's there
if you take the distance, and compare...
It's Tau, 6.28, yeah,
it's Tau, 6.28318
530717958
647692528...
I know what you are thinking,
what about that other guy,
the one that's sometimes pronouced "pee"
and is sometimes pronounced "pie".
I mean it's fine if you are building,
but does not belong in math.
All the equations make more sense
when you use "taw", you use "taff",
and while you get the same answers
no matter which way,
we get further from truth
when we obscure what we say.
Know that math makes sense
when it's beautiful and pure.
So please don't make it ugly with
your bad notation and awful curriculum.
Use Tau, 6.28, yeah
use Tau, 6.28318
530717958
647692528
67665590
05768394338
75021...
1...