almost always when we are looking at greek sculpture
we re looking at roman carvings, we aare looking at marble copies
of what had once been bronze. but bronze is
expensive.and it is reusable. so 2000 years
after these objects were made, there is ample
opportunity for it to be melted down.but
once in a while we find a greek original. we are
looking at the seated boxer,agreek helenistic
sculpture from about 100B.C. now helenitic
refers tothis period after alexander the great,
so this is the last phase of the ancient greek ode.
because the helenistic were and then the romans
conquered greece.now because it is bronze we have an opportunity to understand
how the greeks constructed their flarge scale
sculpture.this is last wax casting and you would be chased and so
you could call it in portions, that you can
actually see in the beard, and in the hair
so that the lines would cut into the surface
so this sculpture is hollow in other words. we can see that
if you look into the eyes, if you look into the mouth, you
can see the hollowness. now originally there
would have been eyes that are missing. they would have been
of ivory or some sort of glass paste, something reflective, well
polished yes we can see that this is quite thin and that if we knocked on it,
it would ring like a bell. a few moments ago
as we were looking at it, there was someone standing
in the veryplace that he seems to be looking
and i almost thought likehe was in actual dialogue with someone
he has a tremendous sense of presence. doesn't he?
he does. during the dhelenistic period we
see the real expansion of the subject matter that we really think of
the god. usually we think of ideal beautiful
nude athletic young, figures. but this is
an athletic figure, but he is not young and
he is not beautiful in the traditional sense
when i look at him i find, part of him beautiful,
but his face is certainly not.oh , the beauty
comes from our understanding his life,and his
suffering instead of the elegance of perfection of
his body, his muscular he is powerful that he is defeated
yes that is the the main kind of pathos, the sculpture engages
us emotionally. the artist has been careful
to make sure the we are into sympathy. he has
inlaid copper into parts of the face wher he
has defined wounds, so that the copper
functions as a more red color than bronze,
and we can see him bleeding. boxing is into greece
and focussed mainly on blows to his head and his face
and thats why his body, is still so beautiful and
perfect and when i said the forer that i think was mightly beautiful
i was thinking about the incredible muscles in his torso
he is so really fine and athletic but his face
is in such a contrast, and also his hands are
wrapped in leather.the face and the hands ground him in a kind of
reality of a moment. well thst is specially
true of his posture. we can see him i htat he is not
simply seated. his torso is collapsing,
his head is down. he is looking up but you can feel the exhaustion.
you can also say the way in which his body
has been beaten, the broken nerves give ashes
on his face.look at his ear which is swollen and distorted
we verily see seeded figures, and the classic
appears standing , if he is a standing a noble. he is heroic
just by virtue of his being defeated thare is a humility and
humanity to the figure. well this is also a sort of
informality.his right leg is alled upon his heel
and his left leg is still unde the weight of his arm
this is a man who'd like to lie down. so this
is a period, in recall when there really is an interest in
pathos in moving beyond the era, in moving
beyond subjects in that age and world and
its really beginning to explore the wider
variety. it is facinating, its incredibly
sophisticated moment