What I want to do in this video
is make sure we're comfortable with ways to represent
and visualize complex numbers.
So you're probably familiar with the idea
complex number -- let's call it z
and z is the variable we do tend to use for complex number.
Let's say that z is equal to a+bi.
We call it complex because it has a real part
it has a real part
and it has an imaginary part.
And it has an imaginary part.
And just so you're used to the notation, sometimes
you'll see someone write the real part,
give me the real part of Z.
This is a function that you input a complex number
and it will output the real part.
In this case the real part is equal to a.
And you can have another function
called the imaginary part.
The imaginary part of z.
You input some complex number
and it'll output the imaginary part
The imaginary part -- it'll say how much you're scaling up i.
And in this case it would be b.
It would be b -- this is a real number -- but this tells us how much the i
is scaled up in the complex number z.
Right over there.
Now, one way to visualize complex numbers
and this is actually a very helpful way to visualize them
when we start to think about roots of numbers
especially the complex roots
Is using something called an Argand diagram.
Argand diagram.
So this is this
And so it looks a lot like coordinate axes
and it is a coordinate axes
but instead of having an x and y axis
it has a real and imaginary axis
so the example of z being a+bi
we would plot it really as a position vector
where we have the real part on the horizontal axis
so let's say that this is a.
And then the imaginary part along the vertical axis
or the imaginary axis.
So let's say that this is b.
And so we would represent in an argand diagram
the vector z as a position vector
that starts at zero and has a tip
at the coordinate a, b.
So this right here -- this right here
is our complex number.
This right here is a represation in an argand diagram
of the complex number a+bi or of z.
Now when you draw it this way,
when you draw it as a position vector --
and if you're familiar with polar coordinates
you're probably thinking -- hey I don't have to
represent this complex number just as kind of coordinates
just as an a+bi, maybe I can represent this as some angle here
as some angle here - let's call that angle phi.
And some distance here - let's call that r.
Which is kind of the magnitude of this vector.
And you could.
If you gave some angle and some distance,
that would also specify this point in a complex plane.
And this is actually called the argument of the complex number
And this right here is called the magnitude
or sometimes the modulus
or the absolute value of the complex number
So let's think about it little bit
Let's think about how we would actually calculate these values
So r, which is the modulus or the magnitude
its denoted by the magnitude or the absolute value of z1.
What's this going to be?
Well we have right triangle here.
We have a right triangle here.
This side is b, length b.
The base right here has length a.
So to calculate r we could just use the pythagorean theorem
r squared is going to be a squared plus b squared
or r is going to be equal to the square root of a squared plus b squared.
If we want to figure out the argument.
Let's say we want to figure out the argument.
This is going to be equal to what?
Let's think about this a little bit.
We have b and a. So what trig function deals with
the opposite side of an angle and the adjacent side
So let me write the famous sohcahtoa appear.
Sohcahtoa - tangent deals with opposite over adjacent.
So the tangent of this angle, which we called the argument
of the complex number.
The tangent of the argument is going to be equal to
the opposite side over the adjacent side
It is equal to b over a.
And so if we wanted a solve for this argument
we would say that the argument is equal to the arctan
or the inverse tangent of b over a.
Now, if we wanted to represent -- let's say we had the complex number
Let's say that we were given the argument and the
let's say that we were given --
Let's say that we were given the modulus and the argument
Let's say we were given that.
How do we go the other way?
Right now if we have the a's and the b's of the real and complex part
I just showed you how to get the magnitude
and how to get the angle or the argument.
But if you're given this, how to you go the other way?
Well here, if you're trying to figure out a given r and theta.
So you're trying to figure out adjacent side
given an angle and the hypotenuse.
So adjacent over hypotenuse is equal to cosine.
So you would have cosine of the argument is equal to r --
is equal to the adjacent over the hypotenuse.
Is equal to a over r. Multiply both sides by r.
you get r * cosine of phi is equal to a.
Do something very similar for b.
If we use sine -- opposite over hypotenuse
sine of the argument is equal to b over r.
Is equal to b over the magnitude.
Multiply both sides by r, you get r * sine of phi is equal to b.
So how would we write this complex number?
So this complex number z.
The complex number z is going to be equal to it's real part
which is r*cosine of phi
r*cosine of phi plus the imaginary part times i
plus r -- we do that same green -- plus r*sine of phi times i.
times i -- Now this might pop out at you as something that's pretty interesting
if you've ever seen Euler's formula.
Let's factor out this r over here.
So this is going to be equal to factor of an r.
r times of cosine of phi
cosine of phi plus -- i put the i up front --
i sine of phi.
Now what is this?
And if you've seen the videos i did in the Taylor series
Series of videos in the calculus playlist --
And it's really one of the most profound results in all of mathematics
it still gives me chills -- this is Euler's formula.
This is -- or this by Euler's formula is the same thing.
This is the same thing.
And we show it by looking at the Taylor series representations
of e to the x and the Taylor series representations of
cosine of x and sine of x.
But this is -- if we're dealing with radians -- e to the i, phi
e to the i, phi.
So z is going to be equal to r
is going to be equal to r times e to the i,phi
e to the i, phi.
So there are two ways to write a complex number
You could write it like this, where you have the real and the imaginary part
That's my "do what we're used to"
or we can write it in exponential form
where you have the modulus or the magnitude
being multiplied by a complex exponential.
We're gonna see that this can be super useful especially
when we're trying do find roots
Now just to make this tangible let's actually do this,
with an actual example. So let's say that i had
I don't know -- let's say that i had z1 is equal to
square root of three over two plus i.
And so we want to figure out.
We want to figure out it's magnitude and
we want to figure out it's argument.
So let's do that. So that magnitude
the magnitude of z1 is going to be equal to the square root of this square
so this is going to be equal to
this is going to be equal to three over four -- three fourths
plus one squared -- we're gonna actually say
plus four fourths, so this is going to be equal to
square root of seven over four which is equal to
the square root of seven over two.
And now let's figure out it's argument.
So let's draw -- if I were to draw this on an Argand diagram
on an Argand diagram, it would look like this.
It's going to be in the first quadrant so that's all I have to worry about.
So let me draw it.
Let me draw it like this.
And so we have a situation.
So it's going to be square root of three
actually let me change this up a little bit
just so the numbers get a little bit cleaner
sorry about this
let me ma make it a little bit, slightly cleaner.
So just so that we have a slightly cleaner result.
We want to make our first example a simple one.
So let's make square root of three over two plus one half
plus one half i.
So let's figure out the magnitude
the magnitude here -- z1 is equal to the square root of
square three over two squared is equal to three over four
plus one half square is equal to one fourth.
This makes things a lot nicer.
This is equal to the square root of one which is one.
And now let's think about it -- let's draw it on an Argand diagram
do visualize the argument.
So this my imaginary axis.
That is my imaginary axis.
This is my real axis.
My real axis.
And so this complex number is square of three over two
square of three over two is 1.7 so if we have like one
it would be like -- so this is one -- it'll be right over here.
Some place right over here.
This is square root of three over two.
The real part.
The imaginary part is one half.
So if this is one, this is one half, the imaginary part is right over here -- one half
And we actually also know it's length -- or magnitude is one.
So how to we figure out
how do we figure out phi over here
We know this side over here is square root of three over..
Oh let me be careful -- we know that side over there is one half.
That's the imaginary part and we know the base is square root of three over two.
So a bunch of ways we can do this
One. You could just look at -- do the tangent
because that involves the opposite over the adjacent.
You could say that tangent of phi is equal to the opposite.
is equal to one half over the square root of three over two.
And then you can take the inverse tan of both sides.
So this is to be the same thing as
phi being equal to the inverse tangent
or the arc tangent of
if you multiply the numeral denominator by 2
this is one over the square root of three.
You could do it like that.
You could also say that phi is equal to the inverse sine of
So the sine of phi is going to be equal to the opposite over the hypotenuse.
So sine of phi is equal to one half over one-
Or phi is equal to arc sine of one half -- and you could put that in your calculator.
Or you could recognize, this is a 30-60-90 triangle.
This base right here is square root of three over two.
This is one half -- This is one.
So this angle right here is going to be 30 degrees
and that's just from pattern matching from a 30-60-90 triangle.
You could look at these and also get something similar.
Now, I want to put this in radiant form,
because whenever I use the exponential form you want it to be in radiant.
So phi is equal to 30 degrees.
phi is equal to 30 degrees which is the same thing as phi over six.
So if I wanted to represent z1 in exponential form
it would be exact same thing as r or it's magnitude which is 1.
I put the one out there but you really don't have to
one times e to the pi over six i
e to the pi over six i.
And we're done!