Toby is a farmer.
He plants 12 rows of carrots in a field.
Each row has six carrots.
How many carrots did Toby plant?
So let's try to visualize this thing.
So they tell us each row has 6 carrots.
Let's try to visualize a row.
So that's 1 carrot, that's 2 carrots, that's 3 carrots, that's 4 carrots,
that's 5 carrots and that's 6 carrots.
(I can even do, just so it looks nice, a little leafy part of the carrots.
So this we can visualize easy as carrots.)
So that's 1 row of carrots. He tells each row has 6 carrots.
Now there're twelve of these, he plants twelve rows of carrots. (Let me see if I can copy and paste this.)
(So... copy and paste.) So that's two rows... (I want to make sure I have enough space.)
Two rows. That's three rows. That's four rows. This is five rows. This is six rows.
(And actually I can just copy and paste the whole thing.)
This is six rows, I need... just
need to double that to get twelve rows so let me do that.
(So copy and paste... There you go.)
So there's twelve rows right over here. And let's number this.
So they tell us... they tell us each row has six carrots. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
They tell us he plants a total of twelve rows. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12.
How many carrots did Toby plant?
Well you could do this exercise and then try to count all of these carrots but that seems a little bit crazy.
These are already a lot of carrots and especially if there were even larger numbers, it would take you forever to count it!
Luckily for us, we have multiplication as a tool that we can use.
So if you have twelve rows and each of those rows has six, this is really twelve times six.
You're going to have twelve rows, in each of those you have six carrots.
So you could say you have six carrots twelve times.
So this is going to be 12 times 6. If you remember your multiplication tables up to twelve, you'll remember that 12 times 6 is 72.
So he has 72 carrots. Even if you only remember... well I'll just leave it there.
If you remember your multiplication (and you should because that is one of the things in life that will... have long lasting benefits.) it's 72 carrots.