[MUSIC PLAYING]
&gt;&gt;: WE'RE LOOKING AT A SCULPTURE
THAT IN MANY WAYS DOESN'T REALLY
SEEM TO BE --
&gt;&gt;: -- A SCULPTURE.
&gt;&gt;: RIGHT.
&gt;&gt;: IT'S NOT FREE-STANDING.
&gt;&gt;: IT'S NOT.
IT'S MORE LIKE A RELIEF, BUT --
&gt;&gt;: -- IT'S NOT REALLY A RELIEF.
&gt;&gt;: NOT REALLY, BECAUSE THERE IS
NO BACKGROUND THAT IT IS
ATTACHED TO.
&gt;&gt;: AND THEY'RE ISOLATED UNITS
ALL THE SAME.
&gt;&gt;: THAT'S RIGHT.
THIS IS A WORK BY DONALD JUDD,
AND IT'S A PIECE OF MINIMALIST
SCULPTURE.
AND IT WAS DONE IN 1969, AND
IT'S AN UNTITLED WORK.
HE WOULD HAVE HAD THE EXACT SAME
FORM REPLICATED OVER AND OVER
AGAIN.
SO EACH ONE OF THOSE BOXES THAT
YOU SEE THERE WERE NOT MADE BY
HIM AND IT WAS ALSO MADE IN A
FACTORY.
SO IT HAS A KIND OF MACHINEMADE
AESTHETIC TO IT.
&gt;&gt;: SOMEHOW IT SEEMS TO ME LIKE
IT IS MADE TO SORT OF INTERACT
IN THE SPACE OF THE GALLERY.
&gt;&gt;: ABSOLUTELY.
IN FACT HE IS VERY SPECIFIC IN
GIVING INSTRUCTIONS ON HOW TO
HANG THIS, YOU KNOW, HOW TO
ATTACH IT TO THE WALL, THAT EACH
ONE IS TO BE SPACED SIX INCHES
APART, AND USUALLY THE WORK IS
SUPPOSED TO GO, THE FIRST TIME
IT WAS MADE, IT WAS SUPPOSED TO
BE EVENLY SPACED ALL THE WAY UP
TO THE CEILING.
SO IT WOULD BE SOMEWHAT DICTATED
BY --
&gt;&gt;: -- BY THE HEIGHT.
&gt;&gt;: -- BY THE NORMAL HEIGHT OF
THE CEILING.
OF COURSE THAT WOULD CHANGE
DEPENDING ON WHAT SPACE.
&gt;&gt;: BUT THIS ONE DOESN'T DO
THAT.
&gt;&gt;: RIGHT.
I THINK THAT IS BECAUSE OF THE
PHOTOGRAPH WE ARE LOOKING AT
PARTICULARLY.
&gt;&gt;: AND IT IS MADE OF SOMETHING
THAT HAS A REFLECTIVE SURFACE.
&gt;&gt;: HIGH SHEEN TO IT.
THE OUTSIDE OF IT IS BRASS AND
THEN THE -- IT'S DIFFICULT TO
SEE HERE, BUT THERE ARE PLEXI
KIND OF WINDOWS THAT ARE THE
TOPS OF EACH ONE OF THESE BOXES.
SO YOU CAN SEE THROUGH IT AND
SOMETIMES DEPENDING ON WHICH
PIECE IT IS, THEY'RE INTENSELY
COLORED LIKE PINK, OR KIND OF A
YELLOWISH COLOR OR TRANSLUCENCY.
SO IT CREATES, IT INTERACTS WITH
THE SPACE AND CREATES A KIND OF
A SHADOW AND COLORISTIC EFFECT
ON THE WALL, THE BLANK WALL OF
THE GALLERY.
&gt;&gt;: SO SHOULD WE BE THINKING
BACK HERE TO SCULPTURES MADE OF
BRONZE?
&gt;&gt;: I THINK SO, BUT ALSO THE
NEGATION OF THAT.
ONE OF THE THINGS THAT JUDD AND
OTHER MINIMALISTS ARE TRYING TO
DO ARE TO BE OF THEIR TIME.
SO THERE THE WHOLE
TRADITION THAT
HE IS CONTINUING OF MODERN ART,
YOU KNOW, WHERE YOU CHOOSE THE
MATERIALS AND THE THEMES OF YOUR
OWN TIME, AND HERE TO CHOOSE
SOMETHING THAT IS BRASS WHICH
CAN BE USED IN OLDER ART, BUT TO
MAKE IT LOOK LIKE IT'S SHEET
METAL, SOMETHING THAT COMES OUT
OF A FACTORY, AND IN FACT IS NOT
MADE BY HIM BUT MADE BY OTHER
WORKERS IS VERY IMPORTANT.
&gt;&gt;: SO IT SPEAKS TO OUR FACTORY
INDUSTRIAL CULTURE.
&gt;&gt;: EXACTLY, AND IT IS WHAT IT
IS.
IT DOESN'T DISGUISE ITSELF.
HE IS VERY EXPLICIT ABOUT NOT
TRYING TO MAKE ILLUSIONISTIC
ART.
SO HE DOESN'T WANT TO MAKE A
SCULPTURE LOOK LIKE A PERSON OR
A SPACE THAT ISN'T THERE.
AND SO THERE ARE CLEARLY BOXES
AND THE PLEXI ALLOWS YOU TO SEE
THAT THEY ARE NOT SOLID.
SO THERE'S A CLARITY AND A
LITERAL QUALITY THAT HE WANTS TO
BRING OUT.
&gt;&gt;: AND IT ALSO REMINDS ME OF A
SKYSCRAPER, OTHER KINDS OF
MODERNIST FORMS.
&gt;&gt;: RIGHT.
IT DOES EVOKE THAT AND JUST THE
SHEER REPLICATION OF THE SAME
FORM OVER AND OVER AGAIN
SUGGESTS --
&gt;&gt;: -- VERY MODERN.
&gt;&gt;: YEAH, SUGGESTS
MACHINE PRODUCTION,
AND ONE THING BEING --
&gt;&gt;: -- GOING SHOPPING, AND
SEEING EVERY THING THE SAME IN
THE GROCERY STORE.
&gt;&gt;: EXACTLY.
&gt;&gt;: -- NINE HUNDRED VERSIONS OF
THE SAME THING.
&gt;&gt;: KIND OF A PRODUCTLIKE
QUALITY TO IT.
IT'S EASY TO SEE HOW THE CLEAN
QUALITIES OF IT, THE SHININESS
OF IT, AND ALSO THE PLEXI MAYBE
AT FIRST GLANCE IT SEEMS
OVERSIMPLIFIED, BUT ON FURTHER
SCRUTINY THERE IS A LOT OF COLOR
AND REFLECTION AND
LIGHT AT PLAY.