This is Steven Zucker and with Matthew Postal
who is an architectural historian,
we are looking at Lever House,
we are on Park Avenue, 53rd Street in New York City.
Lever House is really one of
the great iconic post-war international style buildings.
It's georgeous and it's so perfect.
It was restored several years ago by the architects
who designed it - Skidmore, Owings and Merril.
So they brought back, well not the original team,
but they brought back the original firm.
The chief designer Gordon Bunshaft had
passed away but they had the original blueprints
and they could get it back to where it was.
It is so pristine
and it's so much about reflectivity and about light.
What makes this building signifcant?
It is the first
glass curtain wall office building in Manhattan.
This building is now completely inundated
by much larger buildings that are also glass and steel.
But what did this look like
originally in 1952 when it was finished?
Can you imagine when it was finished,
all of the buildings that surrounded it
were faced in brick and stone.
This really must have stood out,
it must have been incredibly radicle.
How is it that corporation could have been
that brave to do somethinng so extraordinary.
Not to mention Skidmore, Owings and Merril.
I think a lot of it has to do with the patron.
One of the chief officers at Lever
was the man named Charles Luckman.
Not only had Luckman trained
as an architect, but he had been at Johnson Wax
when they worked with
Frank Loyd Wright on their signature headquarters.
So that's really interesting.
He saw first time the value that
really innovative architecture might have on a company
and the way that could produce
really sort of important public face for the firm.
Yeah, it's definitely about populistic.
And of course Lever interestingly enough made so
that building really just speaks of a kind of cleanness,
and a kind of sharpness and a kind of clarity.
And that feeling would have been
even stronger when it was completed
because the limestone
in brick buildings that surrounded it
would have been 30 or 40 years older that time
and they probably would have needed a good cleaning.
And so this building is georgeous
with reflective green glass, clear glass,
this steel trim aluminum
and then there is this beautiful marble,
this is white marble that just amplifies the sense
of modernity and any kind of its industrial nature.
It's really very strict in its geometry
in the way in which it is balanced.
The building is really made up of two buildings, isn't it?
It's two forms.
One horizontal and the other vertical.
Of course it is actually integrated physically but visually
it really does look like two objects, one stuck on the other.
Almost one floating over the other.
I have found them balanced against each other.
So was Gordon Bunshaft really developing his ideas
himself or were there ideas that he was borrowing?
Where does this come from?
It's in the air. When I look at
this building rather than pointing at one source,
I'd rather point to two different sources.
And that would be the ideas of the French architect
Le Corbusier and the architect Mies van der Rohe.
Both of them were really
interested in taking in industrial culture
and introducing that, do I have it up to that point
that the architecture was fairly old fashioned
and really historical in its view.
And so it is really interesting that we have
an American and putting into practice these European ideas.
How did that work?
The great depression of the thirties, the second world war.
We are one of a few places
where one could attempt to put those ideas into place.
But now here in a corporate environment, right?
They used these ideas
at the United Nations a year or two earlier
but this is the first time that
American corporation embraces these ideas.
Kind of set the trend.
One of the things I'm really interested in
about this building is its interior, but still exterior space.
Because you know,
when you look at the building from across the street,
it's the horizontal slab, it's the vertical slab
but you come underneath into the courtyard
and the whole space openes up.
Where else in New York can you sit in a centre...