Determine the domain and range for the relation described by the table
and so, what they want us to say, what they want us to figure out, when they say the domain
what are all the possible inputs that we could put into, this case, a relation
and later we'll see a function
and so over here, i guess one way to think about it
the inputs that this relationship is defined for
and so you can view the x as the input
so when x is -1, y is 3
when x is 3, y is -2
when x is 3, again, y is 2
that's why we can't describe this as a function
here because we have two y values for a given x value
but it can be a relation
when x is 4, y is 8
when x is 6, y is -1
so to answer the first part, when they ask us what is the domain of this relation
they're really just saying
what are all of the inputs, what are all of the x values for which this relation is defined?
and they list the x values over here
so it is a set, and that is what these curly brackets mean
that i'm about to describe a set
it is the set of the numbers -1, 3, 4, and 6
so all we're saying here
if we saying the domain of this relation is these 4 numbers
it says that this relation is defined for any of these four numbers
if you give any of these numbers as an x value
there is a y, at least one y value associated with it
now, when they talk about the range of this relation
and the idea also applies to functions, which are a more specific class of relations
you can view them as a well behaved relation
the range is all the possible output that this relation can give you
given the inputs, what are all the possible values that this relation can take on?
so here you'll take a look at all the possible y values that this relation can take on
we can write them in order, or we don't have to write them in order, but i'll just write them in order
actually let's just go straight this way
a set does not imply some type of order, it just means a collection of things
so the range here, well our y value can take on the value 3, it can take on the value 2, it can take
on the value 8, and it can take on the value -1
and we're done!
these are the x values for which this relation is defined
then you can actually find an association or relationship
and these are all the y values
these are kind of all the outputs of the relation that it can take on
we just look right over here to find them