Dear Nickelodeon, I've gotten over how Sponge Bob's
pants are not actually square, I can ignore most of the time
that Gary's shell is not a logarithmic spiral, but what I
cannot forgive is that Sponge Bob's pineapple house
is a mathematical impossibility!
There's three easy ways to find spirals on a pineapple.
There's the ones that wind up it going right, the ones
that spiral up to the left, and the ones that
go almost straight up. Keyword: almost.
If you count the number of spiral going left, and the number
of spirals going right, they'll be adjacent Fibonacci numbers.
Three and five, or five and eight, eight and thirteen,
or thirteen and twenty-one.
You claim that that Sponge Bob square pants lives in
a pineapple under the sea, but does he really?
A true pineapple would have Fibonacci spirals, so
let's take a look. Because these images of his house
don't let us pick it up and turn it around and count
the number of spirals going around it, it might be hard
to figure out whether it's mathematically a pineapple or not
but there's a huge clue in the third spiral, the one going upwards
In this pineapple, there's eight to the right,
thirteen to the left, you can add those numbers together
to get how many numbers are in the set spiraling steeply upwards.
In this case, twenty-one.
The three sets of spirals in any pineapple are pretty much
always adjacent Fibonacci numbers. The rare mutant
cases might show Lucas numbers or something,
but it will always be three adjacent numbers in a series
What you'll never have is the same number of spirals
both ways. Pineapples, unlike people, don't have bilateral
symmetry. You'll never have the third spiral be not
a spiral but just a straight line going up a pineapple.
Yet, when we look at Sponge Bob's supposed pineapple
under the sea, it clearly has lines of pineapple things going
straight up. It clearly has bilateral symmetry.
It clearly is not actually a pineapple at all because no
pineapple could possibly grow that way.
Nickelodeon, you need to take a long, hard look in the mirror
and think about the way you're misrepresenting the
universe to your viewers. This kind of mathematical
oversight is simply irresponsible.
Sincerely, Vi Hart.