Let us think about the above example a little bit so 'I' for Ian can rake 1 lawn and bag leaves in 5 hours - so we
can also write 5 hours for 1 lawn. But writing it this way is more useful - 1 over 5 lawn per hour
or 1/5th of a lawn per hour. Now let us do the same thing for Kyandre, he can rake the same lawn
and bag the leaves in 3 hours.
We can write it as 1/3rd of a lawn per hour and let us look at the combined
rate. Ian + Kyandre, what is going to be their combined rate?
They tell us that when working together how long will it take to rake and bag the leaves. Let 't' = how
long it will take them together to rake the lawn and bag the leaves. Then we could say combined they will do 1 lawn in every 't' hours, Assuming 't; is an hour/
1 over 't' = 1/t th of a lawn per hour. So here we have the rate of Ian and Kyandre and the combined rate, so the combined rate
is going to be the sum of each of their rates.
Their combined rate will be 1/5th of a lawn per hour and 1/3rd of a lawn per hour.
1/5th of lawn per hour for Ian + 1/3rd of lawn for Kyandre =1/t lawns per hour.
Let us total them - let us take the common denominator of 15. 3/15 +5/15 = 1/t
We have a common denominator now, 3+5 /15, 8/15=1/t.
If we flip over both sides - flip the left side we get 15/8 and we flip the right side we get t/1 hour.
15/8 hours per lawn. The whole time earlier we had lawns per hour.
15/8 is same thing as 1 and 7/8th of an hour - let us get the calculator out. If we have 60 mins in an hour x7/8=52.5 mins
Our answer combined - it will take them 1 hour and 52.5 mins per lawn or to do this lawn in question. Hope you found that useful.