Let P, Q, R and S be points on the plane with position vector -2i-j, 4i, 3i+3j and-3i+2j respectively.
The quadrilateral PQRS must be a
Lets just, lets just graph each of these position vectors.
Or graph the points that they are specifying.
So let me draw my co-ordinate axis right over here.
So that would be, This is my vertical, I can draw straighter line than that.
Draw the horizontal, thats a better job I think.
And than let me mark it off because high is four, we go upto 4i.
So 1 2 3 4.
We go low as -2i,\. So 1 2. Just making sure make it little bit even.
We have to figure out the shape of what ever we draw.
Then we are going to go up 3. 1 2 3. I think that may be I should go down 1 as well.