Congratulations!
We've reached a branching point in our lesson.
Now, a few different ideas have been introduced.
So it's important to orient ourselves here
before moving forward in various directions.
Now, what motivated this lesson?
Well, we learned about RSA encryption.
And RSA depended on two things:
1) that prime factorization is difficult.
So, if I multiply two big primes together –
p1 and p2 – and I give you n,
I can trust or feel secure in knowing that
you'll take a long time to find those primes –
and maybe more than your lifetime.
Also, 2) RSA requires that
those large primes I generated be easy –
meaning I could just quickly generate a large prime.
So let's return to the first problem:
difficulty of prime factorization.
Well, what is it about prime factorization –
or just prime numbers, themselves –
which makes problems hard?
And to find out, we began with a core problem.
Given x, is x prime or composite?
– which is a primality test.
Now we ended up building
some solutions to this problem.
And in doing so, we realized that
this problem was computationally expensive.
That is, there is no instant solution to this problem.
As our input number grew, the amount of time –
or the amount of steps involved
for our algorithm to find a solution –
also grew.
And how much it grew
we actually understand better now –
because we can predict this search space
using the prime number theorem.
Though, the real issue can be thought of
as a graph, where, on the vertical axis,
we have the number of steps our algorithm takes.
(Or you can just think of it as time.)
and on the x-axis is the input size.
And as input size increased, so did time.
And the problem we had is that
the shape of this curve is unacceptable.
Because, in our case, once n hit even 20 digits,
we can no longer solve the problem –
in the worst case.
And if we threw an input hundreds of digits long
at our algorithm, we can all agree it would not work.
In our case, it would crash.
So it's practically impossible
to check if a large input is prime,
using our current strategies.
Now let's return to the first point – factorization.
Realize –
based on our current understanding in this lesson –
factorization has to be harder than a primality test.
That is, there are more steps involved
in finding the prime factorization of some number,
versus just telling me if a number is prime.
Since, remember, factorization requires us to find
all the prime factors for some input n.
Whereas a primality test only requires
that we find one divisor.
And a nice reminder of this is that some users
have actually turned these primality tests
into prime factorization algorithms,
simply by repeating after it finds its first divisor.
So the primarily test is just kind of a subroutine
inside the main factorization algorithm.
So if we return to this graph,
a factorization algorithm would be
something like this.
As input grows, our factorization algorithm
would be above this primarily-test line.
And realize that, in any situation,
we always have a computational limit –
that is the number of primitive steps
we can calculate – which is based on our
computing power in any given situation –
and the amount of time we have.
And you can think of this as a horizontal line –
or a threshold – on this graph.
Anything above this line is out of reach –
not feasible to solve.
And in this lesson, we were limited by
the Rover's on-board computer,
which was fairly slow –
which is why we couldn't run primality tests
on numbers with even 20 digits.
However, even if we had, say, a thousand computers,
running for a year, this would simply just push this
horizontal line up to some other threshold.
And this would allow us to run tests on larger numbers.
But as you can see,
we would always hit some limit
where the input is large enough
that we can no longer solve the problems again.
Now, this leads to many interesting question paths.
However, I'll identify the two I'm going to explore next.
First of all, so far I have not been very precise
about these growth curves.
Though, it would be helpful if –
Imagine for any algorithm you give me –
no matter what it's trying to solve –
and no matter what machine it's even running on –
we could draw some corresponding
growth curve on this graph,
simply by looking at the description of the algorithm.
If we could do this, we could identify categories
of certain growth shapes –
which tell us how difficult a problem will be to solve.
And, in this way, we could understand an algorithm
before we even run it.
That's very important to think about.
And you could hand me your algorithm –
written on a piece of paper –
and I could look at it, and say,
"Uh, I know this algorithm is not solvable
with the input size needed."
And this leads us to a lesson on time complexity –
an incredibly important conceptual tool we will need.
And if you've ever heard,
"Oh, this runs in polynomial time,
or exponential time,"
these are terms which come out of time complexity.
Next, many of you have been wondering,
"Well how are we generating these
random primes in practice?"
– the second point I made about RSA.
Well, let's just walk through it quickly.
To generate a large random prime number
hundreds of digits long,,
we need to follow these instructions:
Generate a random number.
Test if its prime.
If it's prime, we're done.
If not, try again until we hit a prime.
Now, in this three-step procedure,
what's most important is the second step:
Test if its prime.
If we can't do that step, this won't work.
So, how is this working today?
Well, it's based on a subtle alteration
to our problem definition –
and more importantly the use of randomness.
And this leads us to another lesson on random algorithms.
And now, finally, if there any other
lingering question paths you have,
please post them below,
and we can plan lessons.
For example, there is some deeper mathematics
we have yet to explore, in order to speed up
our existing trial-division primality tests.
And, what else are you thinking of?
Please share below.