As we enter into the 1917
the United States has been able to
maintain its neutrality in WWI,
in fact President Wilson
has just won a reelection based on the
platform that he kept us out of war
and to a large degree
he was able to keep the US out of war
because the German Empire had pulled back
from its unrestricted submarine warfare
after the sinking of the Lusitania
and how angered America had gotten,
they said: "Okay, we're not gonna
attack passenger vessels anymore
we're only gonna attack things
that are definitely British non-passenger vessels."
But as we go into January of 1917
the British blockade
on the Central Powers was having its effect
and the Central Powers were getting
desperate, in particular Germany
so they were eager to essentially...
uh... do the same to the British once again
go with the unrestricted submarine warfare
but the Germans knew
that if they were to go back to this
that it's likely that the US
would enter the war on the side of the Allies
so knowing that was likely to happen they said:
"well how could we slow the US down?"
and the thinking was
"well, we could somehow enlist the help of Mexico"
which at the time
was not on the best terms with the US
and so Arthur Zimmermann...
Arthur Zimmermann
who was the German Foreign Secretary
the equivalent of the United States
Secretary of State or the foreign minister
Arthur Zimmermann
sends an encoded telegram
to... the Mexicans
and its encoded
especially because it has to go over lines
that are controlled by the Americans.
And in it, he actually proposes an alliance
to slow the Americans down
so this is what he wrote...
so this is the encoded telegram
and then it was actually
intercepted and decoded by British intelligence
and then shared with the Americans
and that was also then made public...
to the American public.
This is actually fascinating to read this stuff,
this is January 1917...
this is the Germans talking to the Mexicans:
"We intend to begin on the first of
February unrestricted submarine warfare.
We shall endeavour in spite of this to
keep the United States of America neutral.
In the event of this not succeeding,
we make Mexico a proposal of alliance
on the following basis:
Make war together, make peace together,
generous financial support,
and an understanding on our part that
Mexico is to reconquer the lost territories
the lost territory in Texas, New Mexico, and Arizona.
The settlement in detail his left to you,
you'll inform the President
[the President of Mexico] of the above most secretly
as soon as the outbreak of war
with the United States of America is certain
and add the suggestion that
he should, on his own initiative,
invite Japan to immediate adherence
and at the same time mediate
between Japan and ourselves.
Please call the President's attention to the fact
that the ruthless employment of our submarines
now offers the prospect of compelling England
in a few months to make peace.
Signed: Zimmermann."
Now, the Mexicans when they read this
they really didn't take it too seriously
they didn't think that they
could seriously engaged the US in a war
or they can seriously
take back our occupied territories
so they didn't really think much of it.
The real effect of this telegram was to...
make the American public angry
whether they were going to go back into the
unrestricted submarine warfare
and the Germans themselves talk about a ruthless...
ruthless employment of the submarines.
So when people talk about what were the causes
what brought the US into war
the ones that are typically cited are
the unrestricted submarine warfare,
the sinking of the Lusitania,
the Zimmerman telegram ,
that was trying to get Mexico
to somehow get into a war with the US
and reclaim these territories.
And as we'll see a few months after this,
the US actually does declare war on Germany
and enter into World War One...