multiply and simplify five times the cube root of two x squared
times three times the cube root of four x to the fourth
so the two things that pop out of my brain right here is that we can change
the order a little bit cause multiplication is both commutative
well the commutative property allows us to switch the order for multiplication
so we can get the constant terms we can multiply the five times the three
and then the other two things that we are multiplying They are both the cube root which is the
same thing as taking something to the one-third power
so the cube root of x. This is exactly the same thing as raising x to the one-third
So let's do that. Let's switch the order and let's rewrite these cube roots as
raising it to the one-third power
so I have the five and the three so that's going to be five times three
and then we have the cube root of
I will do that in a new color
then we have the cube root of two x squared
so this I can rewrite as two x squared to the one-third power
,and then I have the cube root of four x to the fourth
so that's the same thing as four x to the fourth to the one-third power
and now we know from our exponent properties: if we have two things that are both
raised to the same power and then we take the product
we could just take the product first and then
raise it to the power
so if I have a to the x power times b to the x power
This is the same thing as a times b to the x power
So we can simplify this part of the expression right over here
as two x squared
time four x to the fourth to the
one-third power and of course five times three is fifteen
and if we simplify what is in the expression right over here we
once again it is commutative so we can swap the order and
it is associative so we can
swap the grouping or how we group them does not matter
cause it is all multiplication here
This is two times four which is six times x squared times x to the fourth
x squared times x to the fourth
is x to the sixth power
and it is all of that to the one-third power
and then that is times
oh sorry not six two times four is eight what am I doing?
two times four is eight
x squared times x to the fourth is
x to the sixth
I think my brain was adding the exponents and wrote the six down
of course two times four is eight not six but we add the exponents
they had the same base
x squared times x to the fourth is x to the sixth
and we are gonna raise that to the one-third power
and then all of that is times fifteen
and then we essentially can use this property again
actually not that property
We know that this. We know if I have something
well actually exactly this property again
We have something multiplied to a power
This is the exact same thing
as eight to the one-third power times
x to the sixth to the one-third power
and then all of that is being multiplied
by fifteen and so eight to the one-third power
this is the same thing as the cube root of eight
you might recognize that eight is two times two times two
so eight to the one-third power is two
eight is two to the third so two to the third
to the one-third is two to the first
two times two times two is eight
and x to the sixth to the one-third
we know from our exponent properties that is the same thing as
x to the six times one-third power
x to the six divided by three power
or six divided by three is two or x squared so that is just x squared
so we have
fifteen times two which gives us thirty
so that is these terms right over here
and then you have this term right over here
I want to do that in a different color
that's not a different color! You have this term
right over here is x squared
and you are done
and there is a bunch of ways you could do it
You might not decide to use exponent notation
You could say look this is a cube root
This is a cube root I can take the cube root of the product of both of them
so you do not have to write the one-third here
you could just write the cube root of this whole thing over here
and then depending on how you want to group it and all the rest
you could do this in different orders
as long as you get the right exponent properties
you should be getting
you should get to this same answer