We're asked to prove that triangle ADC is congruent to triangle BEC
so this left triangle is congruent to this right triangle.
The figure is not drawn to scale.
We should never assume that it is.
And then we have some givens here:
they tell us that segment AC is congruent to BC
and they also tell us that CD is congruent to CE
I've got to mark it twice because CD is not necessarily the length of AC
In fact, they don't look anywhere close, so we can't assume it.
So what else can we figure out about this little diagram here in order to be able to say this left triangle is congruent to the right?
Well the one thing we know is that angle ACD is congruent to angle BCE
and we can say that because they are vertical angles.
vertical angles are equal
And now we can, I think that's enough information to say that they are congruent.
We can now say that triangle ADC is congruent to triangle BEC.
And we know that because we have a side, an angle, and a side.
So by side angle side congruence
And so I think I am done, let me check my answer here.
Drumroll please. . . and it worked!