I have an update.
NASA has said but there will be
a hardware random number generator
on the Rover that we have access to.
And after that, they made one more comment.
They reminded me that we just need
our algorithm to work in practice.
For something to work in practice,
it means that there's always some possibility of error,
but perhaps the possibility is so small
that we ignore it in practice.
And if this sounds crazy ,
just realize that – in the physical world –
nothing is ever certain.
There are always chances for error.
For example, chip packaging contains
small amounts of radioactive contaminants.
And when these decay,
they release alpha particles --
which can actually flip bits in memory --
and perhaps change a number unexpectedly.
And even more interesting,
cosmic rays can also cause soft errors.
We can never remove the chance of error completely.
And I asked NASA exactly --
"Well what error probability is acceptable?"
And they said [that] we just need to make sure
that the probability of error for a given trial
is less than they odds of
hitting the lottery twice in a row.
And the odds of hitting the lottery --
say 649 -- twice in a row
is 6 x 10 to -14.
So let's just be safe and round down,
and say our error probability is 10 to -15.
Safe enough.
We will not expect to see an error.
And it could run hundreds or thousands of times.
Now my question is, "Would access to randomness
help us speed-up a decision algorithm --
such as this primality test?"
And this is a deep question.
So let's step back and look at the big picture.
Given some collection of integers
from 1 to some limit, 'n,' say –
(Let's think of it as our 'universe' of integers.)
We can always divide a collection into two sets.
And a decision problem can actually be thought of
as a partition[ing] into two sets.
For example:
"Provided some n, is n less than a hundred?"
it would output 'yes' for all integers less than a hundred -
– so, here is one collection –
and 'no' for all others – which is another collection.
Okay.
So let's now focus on recognizing primes with a decision.
And ideally what we woud like is some
simply computed criteria that all primes satisfy,
and no composites satisfy.
Now if we knew some simple pattern which
describes the location of all primes –
and only primes –
then given some number n,
we could simply check if n follows that pattern.
But the problem is that – so far – no exhaustive
and simply computed pattern has been found
for all primes, and no composites –
or all composites and no primes.
But we do know fast tests for most composite numbers.
So, for example, a simply computed criterion
would be a test for 'evenness.'
And all even numbers are divisible by 2.
It's fast, because we can tell if something's even
by just looking at the last digit.
And even as n grows, the problem doesn't get any harder.
We just look at that last digit --
also known as the 'low-order bit.'
Now realize that we can use this 'evenmess' test
as a low quality composite test --
in that we could have some algorithm accept an integer n –
and all our algorithm does is check if n is even.
If n is even – and greater than 2–
then we know with 100% certainty it is composite --
because we have proof.
Think of 2 as our 'composite witness.'
However, if [it is] not [divisible by 2],
then we aren't exactly sure.
If it's odd, it could be prime – since all primes are odd.
Or it could be one of the many
composites which are odd – such as 9 or 15.
And this massive region of odd composites
makes for an unacceptable test.
Now to be clear, let's draw this.
Provided some n, –
[where] n can be either prime or composite –
If n is prime, our algorithm will say
'prime' 100% of the time –
since no primes are even – that are greater than 2.
And it will never say 'composite'
when a prime is provided.
However, if n is composite,
our algorithm will say n is composite
about 50% of the time,
and prime [about] 50% of the time.
So this means that if our algorithm outputs 'composite,'
it means it found proof – a 'composite witness.'
However, if our algorithm outputs 'prime,'
we know there is an unacceptably large chance of error.
Up until now, our strategy has dealt with this
large – unacceptably large error by iteration.
And let's draw the flow of our machine.
Given some n,
our machine does a series of divisibility tests –
starting at a = 2.
It asks, "Does a divide n?"
and if a doesn't divide n,
then we can eliminate all of this region.
Then [the next question it asks is],
"Does n divide 3?"
And if not, then we eliminate that whole section.
And then, "Does n divide five? – seven? – and so on.
And notice, these are disjoint sets,
which gradually fill up all possible composites.
Now if we ever answer 'yes' along the way,
then we have proof that n is composite –
and a – whatever it is at that point – is our witness.
So we halt and output 'composite' from our algorithm.
Otherwise, we continue trying
until we exhaust all possible composites,
until we hit the square root of n –
since we know, remember, every composite number, n,
must have a factor less than or equal to
the square root of n.
#### So this really leads to the final question an algorithm
If no witnesses are found eight is greater than the square root of and
then that we suddenly have proof
and we halt and output prime
So realize, we have two exit paths through our algorithm.
both paths represent proof of certainty that n is either prime or composite.
And when n is prime, we try our all possible divisors,
and we basically rule them all out,
and that is our proof that n is prime.
The problem with this strategy is that our test value a –
requires us to cycle through every prime --
starting from 2 [and going] to the square root of n.
so as n grows, the number of primes grows with it.
It results in too many iterations in the worst case –
such as when we provide a prime to our algorithm.
Looking at the big picture now,
realize it's providing proof when n is prime –
which we now know we'd don't exactly need.
No one said we needed to prove it.
We just need it to be 99.9999 .. (fifteen 9s) percent certain.
Hmm.
So we actually need to think about the composite test
that's being used in our algorithm.
Remember, our fastest trial division primality tests –
thus far – have tried to use prime patterns –
such as six k – or all primes are of the form
six k plus or minus one –
to help walk along the primes only,
and eliminate many of the composites – to save time.
And remember, a test like this can be
turned into a composite test –
that is given some integer, n, is of the form
six k plus or minus one,
then we could say it's probably prime –
but there are many composites still
which follow this pattern.
It doesn't include primes only –
just all primes and some composites.
And we can think of these extra composites as a leak.
And this leak is our source of error.
Now if we inverted and ask, "Is n not of the form
six k plus or minus one,
then we can say with 100% certainty it is composite.
So the leak is our source of error on the prime side.
But in this case it's unacceptable.
It's not a nonnegligible error.
There's a much larger probability [of this error occurring].
We need to find a new composite testing procedure
which is able to shrink this space,
and make the chance of error negligible –
which means we'll need to review
how we can actually shrink errors with iterations.
I think we should now post our ideas below
regarding the kind of tests we might want to perform –
and also – more importantly –
ask, "How could a random generator really help us?"