Let's find the volume of a few more solid figures, and if we have time we may be able to do more surface area problems.
So let me draw a cylinder over here.
So that is the top of my cylinder.
and then this is the height of my cylinder.
this is the bottom right over here.
if this was transparent maybe you would be able to see the backside of my cylinder.
so you can imagine this kind of looks like a soda can.
And let's say that the height of my cylinder "h"
is equal to 8. I'll give some units- 8 cm.
That is my height.
And then let's say that the radius of one of these, of the top of my cylinder, or my soda can
let's say that this radius over here is equal to 4 cm.
so what is the volume here.
what is the volume going to be?
and the idea here is really the exact same thing that we saw in some of the previous problems.
if you can find the surface area of one side
and the figure out kind of how deep it goes, you'll be able to figure out the volume.
So what we are going to do here is figure out the surface area of the top of this cylinder.
The top of this soda can
and then we are going to multiply it by it's height and that'll give us a volume.
this will tell us essentially how many square cm fit into this top
and then if we know; if we multiply that by how many cm we go down, then that will give us the number
of cubic centimeters in this cylinder, or soda can
so how do we figure out this area up here
well the area on top
this is just finding the area of a circle
you could imagine drawing it like this
if we were just to look at it straight on
that's a circle with a radius of 4 cm.
the area of a circle with an area of 4 cm
area is equal to pie r squared.
so it's going to be
pie times the radius squared
times four cm squared
which is equal to
4 squared is 16
times pie
and our units now
are going to be cm squared
or another way to think of these is square cm
so that's the area
the volume is going to be
this area times the height
so the volume is going to be equal to
16 pie cm squared times the height
times 8 cm
times 8 cm and so
when you do multiplication
you could use the associative property
you could kind of rearrange these things
it doesn't matter what order you do it.
it is all multiplication
so this is the same thing as 16 times 8
let's see 8 times 8 is 64
16 times 8 is twice that so it's going to be
128 pi, then you have cm squared times cm
so that gives us cm cubed
or 128 pi cubic cm.
remember, pi is just a number
we write it as pi because it is kind of a crazy irrational number
that if you were to write it, you could never completely write pi
3.14159 keeps going on
never repeats
so we just leave it as pi
but if you wanted to figure it out
you can get a calculator and this would be 3.14 roughtly
times 128
so it would be like you know close to 400
cubic cm
now, how would we find the surface area of this figure over here
well, part of the surface area, are the two surfaces, the top and the bottom.
so that would be part of the surface area
and then the bottom over here would also be part of the surface area
so if we are trying to find the surface area
let's do, surface
let's find the surface area of our cylinder
it's deffinitely going to have both of these areas here.
so it's going to have the 16 pi cm squared twice
this is 16 pi, this is 16 pi square cm.
so it's going to have two times 16 pi.
cm squared.
i'll keep the units still.
so that covers the top and the bottom of our soda can.
and now we have to figure out the surface area of this thing that goes around
and the way I imagine it is
imagine if you were trying to wrap this thing with wrapping paper
so let me just draw
let me just draw
a little dotted line here
so imagine if you were to cut it just like that
cut the side of the soda can. and if you were to kind of unwind
if you were to unwind
this thing that goes around it
what would you have?
Well you would have something
You would end up with a sheet of paper
Where this length right over here
This length right over here
Is the same thing as this length over here
And then it would be completely unwound
And then these two ends
Let me do this in magenta
These two ends used to touch each other
And let me do a color that I haven't used yet
I'll do it in pink
These two ends used to touch each other when it was
all rolled together
And they used to touch each other right over there
So the length of this side and that side
is going to be the same thing as the height of my cylinders
This is going to be eight centimeters
And then this over here is also going to be eight centimeters
And so the question we'd ask ourselves is
is what is going to be this dimension right over here
And remember that dimension is essentially how far
did we go around the cylinder
Well if you think about it
That's going to be the exact same thing as the
circumference of either the top or the bottom
of the cylinder
So what is the circumference?
The circumference of this circle right over here
which is the same thing as the circumference of that circle over there. It is 2 times the radius times
pi. Or 2pi times the radius. 2pi times 4 cm which is equal to 8 pi cm. So this distance right over here
is the circumference of either the top or the bottom of the cylinder. It's going to be 8 pi cm.
So if you want to find the surface area of just the wrapping. Just the part that goes around the cylinder,
not the top or the bottom. It's going to be unwinded, it's going to look like this rectangle.
And so it's area, the area of just that part is going to be equal to 8 cm by 8 pi cm.
So let me does this, it's going to be 8 cm times 8 pi cm. And thats equal to 64 pi. 8 times 8 is 64.
You have your pi centimeters squared. So when you want the surface area of the whole thing
you have the top, you have the bottom. We already threw those there. And then you want to find the area
of the thing around. We just figured that out so it's going to be plus 64 pi cm squared and now we just
have to calculate it. So this gives us 2 times 16 pi is going to be equal to 32, that is 32 pi
cm squared. Plus 64 pi, let me scroll over to the right a little bit. Plus 64 pi cm squared.
And then 32 plus 64 is 96 pi cm squared. So it's equal to 96 pi square cm is going to be a little over 300 square cm.
And notice when we did surface area. We got our answer in terms of sq cm. That makes sense because
surface area is a 2 dimensional measurement. We think about how many sq cm can we fit on the surface
of the cylinder. We did the volume we got cubed centimeters. And thats because we're trying to figure
out how many 1x1 cm cubes. 1x1x1 cm cubes can we fit inside of this structure so that's why
that's why it's cubic centimeters. Anyway hopefully that clarifies things up a little bit.