When people refer to social security in United States, they really are referring to the OASDI which
stands for - Old Age, Survivors and Disability Insurance.
And it is exactly what this acronym implies it is.
It provides retirement benefits when someone retires or when someone passes before that and they had
paid into or paid into the social security insurance, this OSADI
And when they pass away then it provides benefits to their survivors.
Or if that person doesn't pass away but becomes disabled, and can't work anymore, it will also
provide benefits for them.
Now one very very common misconception with social security is that it someone is a
retirement savings account like a 401(k) or an IRA.
It is not that. From the government's point of view they view it more as a kind of insurance, but
in reality, all it is, is a way for current workers to directly pay for retirement of existing retirees.
And the reason why they did this is when it started off in 1935, they wanted the
current retirees to immediately get benefits. They didn't want the current generation to
save enough money and only use their money, so they made it a direct transfer
from the current workers to the people who are using the benefits.
To make the point clear, a traditional retirement account - let's say this is
me over my career, and then this is when I retire, so this is when I get older
I am aging as we go to the right. So while in my working years, in a traditional
retirement plan, I would be putting money into some account some place.
This is the case with an IRA or a 401k. So this is an account, an account some place
And in the case of an IRA or 401k, they are tax deferred and you can invest this and you
can get interest on it. So it can grow as you invest, and put more and more money into it.
And if you invest it well. And once you retire, all that money, that money that you directly placed
there will be used to fund your retirement. That money will be used to fund your retirement.
Social security is not this. When you pay the FICA tax, we'll talk about that in more detail in future videos,
when you pay that tax, you're not actually putting it into a separate account
you will then tap into later. You're actually for the most part paying current retirees or survivors o
r people with disabilities, you're paying for their benefits. So the way social security works
is more like this. You have all the current workers paying their FICA taxes You have all the current
workers paying their FICA taxes. And right now, at least I think these numbers
are as of 2010, you have 157 million people paying into social security. And you have 54 million
people receiving social security. And so this ratio is pretty good, this money is right now as of 2010
2011 is enough money to pay for all these benefits and actually we are running
a little bit of a surplus, and that surplus is put into a separate trust account.
And it is informally called the social security trust, or the more formal name is
the OSADI trust. I'll just call it the social security trust. And the idea behind this is, OK, look, we're running a surplus now
we can cover at least all of our current obligations and we have a surplus.
And as more baby boomers retire and more people go from this side of the equation to this side
of the equation, then we can use the trust to kind of make up any deficits we might have.
Because if we have more people on the right, we're going to have to spend more and
we're going to have fewer people on the left so we're going to have less coming in
Well, look, we had all that saved up surplus before so we can use that. And that might
sound like overall a decent idea but the problem is that this trust is going to start shrinking because
of all the retiring of all the baby boomers. Start shrinking and we estimate 2023, and these things m
move around based on how much benefits retirees get, the economy, how many people are paying
into it and a whole other bunch of assumptions. They estimate it is going to start shrinking roughly
a deacade from now. And the really bad thing is, that this thing will be
completely depleted so it won't be able to that extra funding for these kinds of deficits not having e
enough money to pay for all the retirees. It will be completely depleted
sometime between 2030 and 2040. Once again, this is a little ways out but
it is actually not that far out. This is actually going to affect - Let's see
I'm right now 35, in 2011, so in 2031, I'll be 55, so I, this will potentially affect my
retirement. By the time I retire, I dunno, 20 - hopefully I'm around - 2042. Actually I'll
probably have to be 67. So I'll have, what is it, 2045 or whatever
I retire - based on the current taxes that are coming in, the current level of the
Social Security trust, the interest the social security trust is getting on its invested money,
and its all being invested in treasuries securities, so it's being invested in treasuries, so
it is not getting crazy interest, it's getting like only a few percentage points
per year. But it has to, because it has to be invested in a very safe place - given this,
there are 3 possible eventualities. Either the FICA tax goes up,
so based on the number of people working here you get more revenue per person right over here.
Eventuality #2 is the benefits go down or even possibly disappear. And eventuality #3
is by this timeframe right over here, that other parts of the government's budget
is going to have to fund social security to make up the shortfall because
if you don't have enough revenue coming from the FICA tax and you don't have enough money from
the social security trust so other parts of the budget. But as we'll see, there won't be a lot of other p
parts to the budget because you also have medi-care growing and really medi-care
is the really unsustainable one. The one that is growing even faster than social security.
So this is very much in question whether there is even another part of the budget that you can even
possibly take from