Here is the dot structure of ethyne molecule, also called acetylene molecule.
and we can see there is triple bond present now.
and each carbon is only bonded to two atoms this time.
So look at this carbon on the left and
it is bonded to two other atoms.
So I can see that the fact that there is triple bond here
and the fact that is bonded to two other atoms.
It would make me think of different type of hybridization, right?
This can't be sp3 or sp2 hybridization.
Let's look at the orbital notation.
This way we can figure out the type of hybridization here.
So once again, this shows the excited states
for the valence electrons of carbon, right?
So the four valence electrons.
One of the electrons on the 2s orbital has already been promoted to 2p orbital.
For the example of acetylenes,
its carbons are bonded to two other atoms.
We need to form two, new hybridized orbitals.
and we are going to form those hybridized orbitals
by promoting, the s-orbital.
So, this is the s-orbital with one valence electron.
and demoting this time only one of the p-orbitals.
We are good to demote one of the p-orbitals, right?
with one valence electron.
That leaves two p-orbitals untouched.
So, we are going to leave these two p-orbitals unhybridized up here.
So, we are going to take one s-orbital and one p-orbital
and we are going to hybridize them together.
to create two sp-hybrid orbitals.
so there is s-orbital on the left,
what used to be s-orbital is now sp-hybrid orbital.
This p-orbital on the right is no longer p-orbital,
it is now sp-hybrid oribital.
Since we formed our new orbitals from one s-orbital and one p-orbital, right?
this is called sp-hybridization.
so sp hybri-di-zation, like that.
and when you see a triple bond present, right?
you know that this carbon on the left is sp-hybridized
and the carbon atom on the right is also sp-hybridized.
so we have our new sp-hybrid orbitals
which must therefore have 50% s-character right?
and 50% p-character.
so the shape of sp-hybrid orbital is going to look a little bit more like
like an s orbital than our previous examples.
right? so it's still going to have two lobes.
The front lobe and the back lobe.
Just like we saw in sp3 and sp2.
The difference is we increased the amount of s-character even more.
Now we are up to 50% s-character.
right? and since s-orbitals are spherely shaped and smaller than p-orbitals.
we can expect these lobes to be a little bit smaller as well.
so we can expect the lobe to be a little bit smaller.
once again we are going to ignore the back lobe which we are drawing so that it doesn't confuse us.
All right. So 50 s-character and 50% p-character.
If i want to draw a picture showing the acetylene molecule and showing with its sp-hybridized orbitals right?
So, here is our acetylene molecule.
Now we know that each carbon has sp-hybridized.
which means that each carbon is going to have two sp-hybrid orbitals around it.
So, these maybe two sp-hybrid oribitals around it.
Each sp-hybrid orbital contains one valence electron.
Let's go ahead and draw that.
S,o we are going to draw this acetylene molecule showing sp-hybrid orbitals.
Here is one of the carbons of acetylene.
and each carbon has two sp-hybrid orbitals
so here is one of the sp-hybrid orbitals.
so once again I'm ignoring the back lobe here.
and here is the other sp-hybrid orbital.
Each orbital has one valence electron.
So, we are going to put our valence electrons in there.
For the acetylene molecule, there is another carbon.
It also is sp-hybridized.
So I'm going to draw this carbon with its sp-hybridized
meaning, there is one sp-hybrid orbital.
There is another sp-hybrid orbital.
I'm ignoring the back lobe, so it's not confusing.
Each sp-hybrid orbital has one valence electron.
So, I'm going ahead and put one valence electron in each.
Alright. For the acetylene molecule, I have two hydrogens.
One hydrogen is on the carbon on the left.
and one hydrogen is on the carbon on the right.
so I know that hydrogen has one valence electron.
and that valence electron is in s-orbital.
s-orbitals are shaped like spheres.
so here is the s-orbital for the hydrogen atom.
and then here is the valence electron for the hydrogen atom.
So, go ahead and put in hydrogen atom over here, like that.
Let's go back up here to our orbital diagram, right?
so we can see that each sp-hybridized carbon has
two un-hybridized p-orbitals.
Each of those un-hybridized p-orbitals
has a valence electron in it.
Let's go ahead and draw that down here.
This carbon on the left is sp-hybridized.
Therefore, I know it has two un-hybridized p-orbitals.
Each p-orbital shapes like a dumbbell.
So, here is one p-orbital.
and I know it has one valence electron in it, like that.
and so I need to draw another un-hybridized p-orbital, right?
So, here is another un-hybridized p-orbital.
and there is this one valence electron.
I do the same thing for the carbon on the right.
So, the carbon on the right is also sp-hybridized,
which means it has two un-hybridized p-orbitals.
So, here is one un-hybridized p-orbital with a valence electron in it.
and then I need one more.
So here is the other p-orbital,
and here is the valence electron.
Let's analyze our diagram
and figure out what types of bonds we have.
So, I can see that between my two carbon atoms
there is an overlap of this sp-hybrid orbitals.
Side, uhm, head-on i should say, so that, of course, is a sigma-bond, right?
The sigma bond comes from the head-on overlapped orbitals.
I can see this is also a sigma-bond
between the sp-hybridized orbital of the carbon,
and s-orbital of the hydrogen.
and there is a sigma-bond over here as well.
So, I can immediately see
there are three sigma bonds in the acetylene molecule.
When I look at the p-orbitals, right?
so these p-orbitals here can never overlap head-on
but if they were big enough,
and they got close enough together in space,
you can see there be side-by-side overlap of those p-orbitals.
So, we call that pi-bonds, right?
So, there is one pi-bond
resulting from the side-by-side overlap
of those two p-orbitals.
and if you look over here there is also an opportunity
for these p-orbitals to overlap side-by-side.
So, there is another pi-bond in the molecule.
So, there is a total of two pi-bonds.
There are three sigma-bonds,
and two pi-bonds in the molecule.
Let's go back to the sigma-bond really quickly.
So, look at this sigma-bond
one that is between my two carbon atoms, right?
This sigma-bond are formed from two sp-hybrid orbitals,
which we know are smaller than sp3 or sp2.
And, that's the reason why
you are going to see a triple bond
being shorter than a double bond or a single bond
that has to do with the sp-hybrid orbitals.
Go ahead and sketch out the dot structure really fast, right?
We can see the triple bond there between the carbon atoms.
And, if we analyze these bonds here,
Let's do that really quickly.
So, if I look at the dot structure,
and I'm trying to figure out how many sigma or pi-bonds I have,
all I have to do is to count of the single bonds,
and now that will tell me how many sigma-bonds I have.
So, here is the single bond, that is the sigma-bond.
Here is the single bond, that is a sigma bond.
and here is the triple bond between my carbons.
I know that one of those bonds is a sigma-bond.
This doesn't really matter which one you say it is
for the dot structure.
So, I'm just going to say this one, right?
So, that gives me my three sigma-bonds.
What I'm trying to figure out is pi-bonds,
I know that the triple bond, there is one sigma-bond and two pi-bonds,
so these must represent my pi-bonds.
So, those are my two pi-bonds, like that.
and so once again, for a triple bond, right?
this is going to be the shortest bond like
due to the fact that the sigma-bond comes from the overlap,
the head-on overlap of two sp hybrid orbitals.
When I think about the bond angles,
When I think about the bond angle
between this hydrogen and this carbon, and this carbon here.
I can see that it's going to be, right?
this is a straight line over here in my diagram
so, let me see if i can draw this really fast, right?
so this is a straight line, running through
all of these atoms, right here.
So, therefore, the bond I go must be 180 degrees.
So, I have 180 degrees here.
and you can see that that straight line runs through all my sp-hybrid orbitals.
So, it's those hybrid orbitals
that are going to determine the geometry.
The pi-bonds will help to stabilize that
and prevent any free rotation, right?
So, the pi-bonds are going to make sure
that the triple bond cannot undergo any kind of free rotation.
Let's do one example
to sum up everything we have learned about
sp3-hybridization, sp2 and sp.
So, if I start with just drawing
of a molecule here.
Let's go ahead and put in some carbons
right? and some hydrogens like that.
So, here we have a molecule.
and let's try to answer a few questions about this molecule.
The first question would be to identify the hybridization state
of each carbon, right?
So, if I look at this carbon, right?
I can see that there is a double-bond present,
so I can immediately see it's sp2-hybridized.
The same thing for this carbon, right?
It also has a double-bond, so it's sp2-hybridized.
This carbon over here
This one only has a single bond around it.
So, we saw in a video of sp3-hybridization that
this carbon must be sp3-hybridized.
and we've just seen in this video
how if you have a triple bond present, those carbons must be sp-hybridized.
All right, next.
Let's think about the shape and also the bond angle.
So, we think about
Let's start with sp3-hybridized carbon
we saw in sp3 in the video of sp3-hybridization
that the atoms around it want to try to adopt the tetrahedral bond angle,
and try to get as close as possible to 109.5 degrees.
So, that takes care of sp3-hybridization.
sp2-hybridization, right?
We saw that that's going to give us a trigonal planar geometry
for the atoms around those carbons
with the bond angle approximately 120 degrees.
For sp-hybridization, we saw in this video,
that's going to be linear, which is why I've drawn the dot structure in linear
and giving us the bond angle of 180 degrees.
Finally, let's count up the number of sigma- and pi-bonds in this molecule.
So, I'm going to start with the number of sigma-bonds.
So, all I have to do is to count up my single bonds.
so this is a, this is one, two, three,
for a double-bond, I know one of those is a sigma-bond from my video on sp2-hybridization.
so four, five, six, seven, eight
nine, and then,
in this video, we saw that for triple bond, one of those is sigma-bond, right?
so one of those is a sigma-bond there,
so there is a total of ten, sigma-bonds.
so we just count 10 sigma-bonds.
What about pi-bonds?
Well, those will be the ones that are left, right?
So, for the double-bond, you have one sigma-bond and one pi-bond.
So, this should be a pi-bond.
For triple bond, we have one sigma-bond and two pi-bonds.
So, there are total of three pi-bonds for this molecule.
So, this is the type of question that you are usually asked
in a test for organic chemistry.
You should be able to analyze an organic molecule in this way
it's an important skill for later in the course.