Where we left off on the last video,
I think we're getting a reasonably good appreciation
for how huge the Sun is especially relative to the Earth
and how far the Earth is away from the Sun.
And most of these diagrams that we see in science textbooks,
they don't give justice...
In fact, when I showed this Sun over here
that was about 5 or 6 inches across,
I said that the Earth would be this little speck,
about 40 feet to the left or the right,
or its orbit would have a radius of about 40 feet.
So you wouldn't even notice it,
if you were looking at this thing over here.
It would be this little speck orbiting at this huge, huge distance.
If you look at this Sun over here
--if I were to draw the whole Sun--
it would have a diameter of about 20 inches.
So in this situation, this Earth right here
--this is drawn to scale--
this Earth would not be anywhere near this close,
it would be about 200 feet that way,
or about 60 or 70 meters.
So if you could imagine, if the Sun was this size
sitting on something like a football field,
this little speck of an Earth, this little thing right here,
would be sitting on the other 40 yard line,
60 meters away.
So huge, you wouldn't even notice it.
You might notice this from a distance.
But you wouldn't even see this thing over here.
And the other planets are even further,
well not all the other planets.
Obviously you have Mercury,
you have Mercury here.
I think most of us are familiar with these,
but I'll just list them in case.
That's Mercury. This is Venus.
Mercury is the smallest of the planets
that is not debated whether it is a planet.
Pluto is the smallest, but some people debate
whether it's really a planet or kind of a large solar body
or dwarf planet or one of those kind of things
And then you have Venus,
which is probably the closest in size to the Earth
or it is the closest in size to the Earth
and then you have Mars and then you have Jupiter.
And just to give you a sense of
once again how far these things are.
If I were to go back to the analogy of
this being the size of the Sun,
then Jupiter is five times further than Earth.
So this would be,
if I were to actually do this scale distance,
this would be 300 meters away.
So if I had a nice big medicine-ball-sized Sun,
or maybe a basketball-sized Sun--
a little bit bigger than a basketball
as it looks on my screen.
Then I would put this little thing
that's smaller than a ping-pong ball,
I would put this three football fields away.
That's how far Jupiter is.
And then Saturn's about twice as far as that.
Saturn is about nine times the distance.
Let me make that clear,
the Earth is one astronomical unit away from the Sun, roughly.
Its distance changes. It's not a perfectly circular orbit.
Jupiter is approximately a little bit 5+ astronomical units,
so a little bit more than
5x the distance from the Sun to the Earth.
And Saturn is approximately 9 astronomical units
or 9x the distance from the Sun to the Earth.
So once again this would be 9 football fields away.
Or another way to think of it is
that it's essentially a kilometer away,
if we had kind of a medicine-ball-sized Sun.
This little, smaller-than-a-ping-pong-ball Saturn
would be a kilometer away.
And I just want to really reiterate that,
because you never kind of visuallize it that way.
Just for the sake of being able to draw it on a page,
you see diagrams that look like this
and they really don't give you a sense of
how small these planets are relative to the Sun
and especially relative to their distances from the Sun.
And after Saturn you have Uranus and then Neptune.
And obviously these guys are even further.
Just to give you a sense, you know, it's very easy
to start talking about galaxies and the universe.
But what I really just want to get, you konw,
already we're talking about huge distances, huge scale.
We already talk about that it would take a jet plane
17 years to travel from the Earth to the Sun.
Multiply that by five,
that's about 100 years to go from Jupiter to the Sun.
200 years to go from Saturn to the Sun.
So you could have had Abraham Lincoln get into a jet plane,
and he still wouldn't have got (if he left from Saturn),
he still would not have got to the Sun.
So these are huge, huge distances.
But we're not done, with the solar system there.
Just to give a sense of scale.
So this is, this right here, that's the Sun
and each of these planets is narrower than these orbits.
So they just draw these orbits,
but you wouldn't actually even see
the actual planets here at this type of scale.
but this is one astronomical unit right over here,
the distance from the Sun to the Earth.
Then you have Mars. Then you have the asteroid belt.
There you have the asteroid belt,
which also has some pretty big things in itself.
It has these things
that are kind of considered almost dwarf planets.
Things like Ceres, you could look those kind of things up.
And then you have Jupiter out here,
and once again we said it would take about 100 years
or roughly 100 years
for a jet plane to get from Jupiter to the Sun.
But even if you take this whole box here,
which is a huge amount of distance,
roughly about five astronomical units,
It would take about 40 minutes
for light to get from the Sun to Jupiter,
So this is a huge, huge distance.
Even this huge distance,
we could put it into this little box right over here.
So this whole box, this whole box, right over there,
can be fit into this box,
and you need to do that
in order to appreciate the orbits of the outer planets.
And so on this scale,
the Earth and Venus and Mercury and Mars,
their orbits look pretty much,
You can't even differentiate them from the Sun.
They look so close.
They almost look like that they're part of the Sun,
when you look at it on this scale.
And then you have Nepp..
you have the outer planets Saturn, Uranus, Neptune
and then you have a Kuiper belt.
This is more asteroids, but these are kind of more frozen...
You know when we think of ice,
we always think of water ice.
But if you are out here it's so cold,
that it's relatively getting dark now
because we're pretty far from the Sun,
that things that we normally associate as gases
are going to be in their solid form out here.
So this isn't just rocky elements.
This will also be things that you normally associate
as gases like methane, frozen methane.
But even here, we're not done.
We're not even out of the solar system yet.
And actually, just ot give you a sense of the scale,
we're operating on right here.
I have this chart right here from the voyager mission.
So the voyager missions, Voyager 1 and 2,
actually Voyager 2 left a little bit earlier, a month eariler,
Voyager 1 was just travelling faster.
They left about a year after I was born.
And their current velocity,
just to give you a sense of how fast Voyager 1,
Voyager 1 right here is right now travelling at 61,000 km/hr.
That's about 17 km/s.
That's the size of a city every second.
It's going that fast,
that's at least in my mind unfathomably fast velocity.
This thing has been travelling roughly that fast.
Well you know it has been going around planets
and gaining acceleration as it went around orbits.
But for most of the time it's been going at a pretty fast speed.
Just to translate it to people who don't relate to kilometers,
that's about 38,000 miles/hr.
So this huge, huge, unfathomably-fast speed,
and it's been doing it since 1977.
I was learning to walk, and when I was learning to walk
it was travelling at this super fast speed
and then when I was learning...
I mean our whole lives when we're sleeping, everything.
When we're eating, when I'm in elementary school,
it's still rocketing out of the solar system at roughly the speed.
Its velocity is changed.
But especially once it got outside of the planets
it has been roughly at this velocity.
So it has just been rocketing out
and I don't want to say only,
but it has gotten this far.
It has gotten about that far right there.
It's about a 115 or 116 astronomical units.
And to give a sense, there's 2 ways to think about this,
one says "Like wow! That's really far."
Because if you even know that even on this scale
you can't even see Earth's orbit,
so this looks like it's a pretty, pretty far distance.
And just to give you a sense of
how far 116 astronomical units are,
if 2000 years ago, Jesus got on a plane.
I actually cut and pasted a copy of Jesus
for visualization purposes.
But if He got on a jetliner at a 1,000 km/hr
when straight in that direction,
in the direction of the Voyager.
The Voyager would only just know be catching up to Jesus.
So this is a huge, huge, huge, huge distance
and at the same time even though it's a huge distance,
especially relative to the everything else we've talked about.
Relative to just even the outer regions of the solar system.
We are still talking in terms of a small scale.
So that is how far Voyager is and just to give a sense on this scale,
so this whole box over here can be contained in this box,
and when you look at this box,
Voyager is only gotten about that far.
After travelling at this unbelievable velocity for over 30 years,
for 33, for about 33 years,
just to give you an idea of these other things,
Sedna right here is one of the ...
it's a reasonably large sized outer-solar-system object.
It's one of the further-est objects
that we know of in the solar system.
And has this very eccentric orbit, so it gets,
I don't want to say relatively close,
but not unreasonably far away,
but then it gets really far away from the Sun.
So even Sedna's orbit,
if I were to look at this whole box over here,
can be contained right over here.
So in this diagram right here, you couldn't even,
you wouldn't even be able to see,
it would be like a speck,
how far Voyager has travelled in 33 years, at 38,000 miles/hr.
You wouldn't even be able to notice, that distance.
And even though you can't even notice that distance,
we still have the Sun's influence.
The gravitational pull is still attracting things to it,
and this right here, we speculate is the Oort cloud,
and this is where the comets originate from.
This is just a bunch of frozen, you can almost view it
as frozen gases and ice particles, things like that.
But this is kind of,
we're starting to get to outer regions of the solar system.
This distance right here is about 50,000 astronomical units.
And just to give you a scale,
because you hear a lot about light years and all of that.
Light years are about 63,000 astronomical units.
So if you go a light year out from the Sun,
then you will end up in the Oort cloud,
the hypothesized Oort cloud.
And just to give a sense of the scale,
the Oort cloud is actually,
you know most of the planets orbits
are roughly in the same plane,
but this right here is the orbits of the planets,
and once again these lines are drawn too thick!
They are just drawn the thinnest possible so that you can see them.
But they are still drawn too thick.
And this goes all the way to the Kuiper belt all of these over here,
so all the way out to the Kuiper belt.
All the way out to all of the major planets.
This is Pluto's orbit right over here.
This whole diagram is only sitting in, right over there.
You can barely see it.
That's this whole diagram, is just that dot in this.
And then you can see the Oort cloud all around it.
It's more of a spherical cloud, and we think it exists.
Obviously it's hard to observe things at that distance.
So hopefully that gives you
a beginning sense of the scale of the solar system.
And what's really going to blow your mind is that,
if this hasn't blown your mind already is that
this whole thing is going to start looking like a speck.
When you even just start looking
at the local area around our galaxy,
Much less than the universe as a whole.
Anyway I don't want to get ....
Well anyway...This starts to get crazy.