An emulsion is a uniform mixture of oily substances and watery substances
which usually don't mix.
To take the most common example of salad dressing,
ah, you'll know that olive oil and vinegar don't mix unless you add the egg to it
then you can froth it up and make a uniform mixture of the two.
Well, in paint, emulsions work the same way
in fact, one of the same emulsifiers is used and that is egg yolk.
de Kooning among others would add egg to his oil paint
which is typically compatible with the solvent, turpentine
but after adding egg yolk, it was compatible with water as well.
By adding water, he then could froth up the paint to get a very
interesting texture, as well as quality of that paint.