Where we left off in the last video,
Toussaint L'Ouverture had just been betrayed by,
on some level, first by some of his right-hand men,
because they joined the side of Leclerc
or essentially they gave up rebelling against Leclerc,
convinced that Leclerc wasn't that bad,
that he had no intention of reinstating slavery
or taking away the civil rights
of the freemen of African descent.
This is another picture of Leclerc, right here.
This is Leclerc.
So he had to essentially give up his arms.
He went to negotiate with Leclerc,
Leclerc imprisoned him,
put him on a boat,
and sent him to France
and he died the next year in 1803.
So he was betrayed.
And died in prison in 1803.
And he really was, on a lot of levels,
one of the most important leaders
not just in Haitian history, but in general.
When he took power, as I said before,
he didn't take revenge on the white population.
He helped the economy of Haiti
get back up and running.
He actually helped defend what is now Haiti,
but Saint-Domingue against the British Royal Navy.
I forgot to mention that in the...
Defended against the British Navy,
which at the time was the...
by far the dominant navy in the world.
So this is what really earned his reputation
as a great general
on top of being a great leader
in terms of not exacting revenge,
in terms of not having slash and burn tactics,
in terms of not just ravaging his enemies.
So he was betrayed,
and then just to make it clear that
Leclerc really does deserve devil horns of a sort
although we're about to meet someone
who deserves much bigger devil horns,
or maybe that he was actually the henchman
for someone who deserves devil horns
In May of 1802
Napoleon signs a law that says...
that reinstates slavery where it has not disappeared.
Slavery where not gone
And so it was a little bit ambiguous.
There were some areas where
slavery had still not disappeared.
Those include the French colonies at Martinique,
at Saint Lucia, at Tobago.
But in Haiti, things were ...
-- or Saint-Domingue, at that time--
things were a little ambiguous.
Had slavery truly disappeared,
or had it not disappeared yet?
Apparently, slaves were free in Haiti.
So it wasn't clear exactly what this meant for Haiti,
but at the same time,
the Haitians didn't even know this was happening.
This was May of 1802.
But just to make things clear,
Napoleon actually sent Leclerc a secret memo
to essentially reinstate slavery
when the time was right.
reinstate slavery when right
So these guys, they were no jokers.
They knew the situation.
They knew that they needed the help
of some of Toussaint L'Ouverture's former generals,
former right-hand men,
in order to keep control of Haiti.
But the intention the entire time was,
when they have the upper hand,
to actually clamp down, reinstate slavery,
and take away the civil rights of the freemen of color.
Now these guys weren't stupid either.
So you might remember Dessalines.
This was one picture of him.
He was also a former slave,
one of Toussaint L'Ouverture's right-hand men,
very effective general.
And, as you remember,
near the end of the fight against Leclerc,
he gave up the fight against Leclerc
and to some degree you could say
he turned on Toussaint L'Ouverture.
But he and some of the other
former followers of L'Ouverture
saw the writing on the wall.
They didn't even have to intercept that secret memo.
They got word from Martinique and Tobago and Saint Lucia
they got word that slavery was being reinstated.
The French at this time
were not people that you wanted to deal with or trust
when it came to issues of slavery.
So Dessalines and his comrades re-took up arms.
And Dessalines was a very different character
than Toussaint L'Ouverture.
The one similarity is that
they were both very effective military men.
The big difference between the two was that
Dessalines was not one to hold back.
He wasn't afraid to
essentially take an eye for an eye, so to speak.
So here you had Dessalines in charge of what was,
I guess you could call, the slave rebel army.
And then on the other side of it,
you have Leclerc with the 40,000 troops
that he showed up, with Napoleon.
But lucky for Dessalines,
yellow fever-- and it's not lucky.
I mean, people died across the board.
But this did really turn the tide of war
in favor of the people of African descent on the island.
Yellow fever struck the island, it killed Leclerc,
and it also took out twenty something thousand--
or the number I read was 24,000--
of the actual French soldiers,
and another 8,000 were hospitalized.
So that's 32,000 out of commission,
so you're essentially only left with 8,000 soldiers.
So all of a sudden, it completely turned the tide,
completely changed the numbers in terms of
what types of forces the rebel army had to fight against.
But it wasn't all, I guess, good at this point because Leclerc-
I mentioned, I gave him little devil horns--
he was replaced by someone
who deserves very big devil horns named Rochambeau.
Not to be confused with his father,
who goes by the same name
who was a hero of the American Revolution.
He fought for France on the side of the Americans.
But his son...
And he, as far as I can tell,
seemed like a decent guy.
But his son was really evil.
And there are very few people in history
that you can say are unambiguously evil.
He is one of them.
Now that he was kind of desperate,
his forces were ravaged by yellow fever,
he's going against a fairly aggressive enemy,
he did things like, he would bury ---
let me write these down because they are evil.
He would bury African--
or I guess I should say African Americans.
He would bury former slaves, or people of African descent--
bury in, bury alive in pits of insects.
He would boil people alive in molasses.
I read one account that says that at one point he held a ball
where he invited all of the prominent mixed-race people
to a party essentially at his place
and at the stroke of midnight he announced that
all of the men are to be murdered.
So this guy, I mean, you know, cruelty... he definitely..
The only bounds on his cruelty
was the people that he could get his hands on,
especially the people of African descent.
The one positive of his cruelty is that
he for the first time really unified
the population of African descent on the island.
So he unified both the slaves, the former slaves,
and the mixed-race.
And at the same time, we're now in 1803.
And, I've said it before,
we're still at war with Britain.
And Britain is-- and I've mentioned it before--
they had the most dominant navy in the world.
Dominant navy
This guy, despite how evil and how cruel he was,
he needed reinforcements from Napoleon
if he had to take on Dessalines.
And let me be very clear about this.
Dessalines, as I mentioned,
he was not hesitant to take an eye for an eye.
In one incident,
Rochambeau buried 500 rebel prisoners alive,
then Dessalines went and hung 500 French prisoners.
So he wasn't someone
to kind of shy away from, I guess, blood.
And this is very different to Toussaint L'Ouverture.
It's kind of a lesson.
If you are fighting an enemy,
if you get rid of the more reasonable leaders of your enemy,
you might end up getting maybe a leader
more similar to yourself and your cruelty,
if you betrayed the more reasonable ones.
But anyway, enough of my commentary.
So the stage is set.
War with Britain.
Britain owns the seas, especially the Caribbean.
This guy needs reinforcements going against
a very strong leader of the former slave rebels.
But Napoleon, he's known to be one to cut his losses.
He did it with his troops in Egypt.
He's really not someone who really cares,
I think, about the individual.
He cares much more about his ego and his power.
So Napoleon leaves them hanging.
Napoleon saw the writing on the wall.
He wouldn't be able to get through the British fleet.
And at the same time,
Napoleon's fighting all of these wars in Europe.
As you remember, the whole French Revolution
was precipitated by France being broke.
So Napoleon, not only does he give up on this guy--
and he essentially got what he deserved--
Napoleon gives up on maintaining all of their colonies
or any major presence in the Western Hemisphere.
So essentially to raise funds,
Napoleon also sells Louisiana to the Americans.
Now when I say Louisiana, I'm not talking about
just the state of Louisiana in its present state,
which is about that big.
That's actually where I was born.
We're talking about the whole--
this is like 1/3 of the United States today.
Sold all of this.
And he was clearly desperate.
He sold it for $15 million,
or that's the equivalent of F60 million
And I've been told, in today's money,
that would be on the order of $10 billion.
So, this is still a very...
You know, if someone said for $10 billion,
you could own 1/3 of the land of the United States,
you would say that's a pretty good deal.
$10 billion in today's money.
So $15 million 1803, $10 billion today,
that's still not a lot of money, but he was desperate.
He realized that he couldn't maintain control of
something halfway around the world
when Britain owned the seas
and he was busy having his own troubles in Europe
So the Americans got a good deal.
And frankly, if he didn't sell it to the Americans,
either the British or the Americans could have probably
just taken it anyway.
So being left to hang to dry by Napoleon,
Dessalines is able to destroy Rochambeau
and essentially declare independence for Saint-Domingue.
And in 1804, January 1,
Dessalines declares independence for,
and he names the new country Haiti,
which is the indigenous peoples' name for the island.
It means land of the mountains.
Now I want to just leave with one note,
because you may or may not be aware.
Haiti is still a very, very, very, very poor country.
And besides, after Dessalines, they had many, many, many--
and eventually, I'll do videos on it--
rounds of one dictator after another.
And the people have really been through a lot.
But I just want to make it clear that
they really got started off on a horrible foot.
Because even though Dessalines
declared independence in 1804,
the French did not recognize Haiti until 1805-- sorry- 1825.
French recognize
And the only reason that not recognize...
And you might say, well, who cares about recognition?
Who cares what the former colonial masters think?
But until they recognized them,
they were essentially embargoing Haiti.
They weren't allowing any trade
to actually go on with Haiti.
So it was really on the front of a barrel gun.
And in order to be recognized,
Haiti had to agree to F90 million of debt to France.
And just to be clear how much money this is,
here's a small island-- or half of an island--
of newly freed slaves
and they were forced to owe France--
and this actually was further reinforced by
the United States and Great Britain.
So it goes to show you,
even former enemies can kind of agree
when it comes to a oppressing small impoverished islands.
But they had to owe France
the equivalent of one and a half times
what the United States paid for the Louisiana Purchase.
This was F60 million.
They got all of Louisiana.
Now France is telling Haiti, you owe us F90 million.
Or that's roughly the equivalent of
$14 or $15 billion in today's terms.
And this is for a population of
essentially half a million freed slaves.
So it's kind of a horrendous amount of debt.
And just to be clear, this isn't something...
this wasn't like the crazy colonials in the early 19th century,
forcing to do this.
This debt was not paid off with the interest until 1947.
They were continuing to pay the debt.
And just to add insult to injury,
the reason for the debt, they claim, was for lost property.
So that's why France claimed that
Haiti owed them the money, for lost property.
Where, included in the list of lost property
was land and slaves.
Essentially, now that you've got your freedom,
you owe us a ton of money for,
essentially us losing the rights to own you.
So it's just insult to injury.
And actually, I was shocked
the first time I learned this number,
that they were forced to continue to pay debts from
one poor country, one small poor country, right over here,
they had to continue to pay debts
to a Western developed nation until 1947,
essentially to buy their freedom.