What I want to do in this video is make sure that
we are good at picking out what
the normal vector to a plane is
if we are given the equation for a plane.
So, to understand, let's start off with some plane here.
Let's start off！！
So, this is a plane and I have write part of it,
obviously it keeps going in every direction.
So let's say that that is our plane.
And let's say this is a normal vector to the plane.
So, that is our normal vector to the plane.
It's given by ai plus bj plus ck.
And let's say that we have！！ So it's perpendicular
to every other vector that's on the plane.
Let's say we have some point on the plane.
We have some point.
It's the ponit x sub p.
And I will say p for plane.
So it's the point on the plane, xp, yp, zp.
If we pick the origin,
So let's say that our axes are here.
So let me draw, let me draw a cord in axis.
So let's say that our cord in axes look like that.
This is our z-axis. That is y-axis.
And let's say this is our x-axis.
Let's say this is our x-axis coming out like this.
This is our x-axis.
You can specify this as a position vector.
There is a position vector. Let me draw it like this.
Let me draw it like this.
And then it would be behind the plane right over there.
You have a position vector.
That vector would be xpi plus ypj plus zpk.
It specifies this coordinate right here
that sits on the plane.
Let me call that something.
Let me call that position vector. I don't know.
Let me call that,P, let me call that, p1.
This is a point on the plane.
So it is p1.
It is equal to this.
Now, we could take another point on the plane.
This is a particular for.
We just say any other point on the plane x, y, z.
But we say that x, y, z sits on the plane.
So let's say we take this point right over here, x, y, z.
That clearly saying logic can be specified
by another position vector.
We could have a position vector that looks like this,
In dotted line,
It's going under the plane right over here.
And this position vector.
I don't know. Let me just call it.
Let me just call it p, instead of that particular p1.
This would just be xi plus yj plus zk.
That the whole reason why I did this setup is
because I want to find, given some particular point
that I know on the plane and any other xyz
that is on the plane,
I can find, I can construct a vector
that is definitely on the plane.
And we have learned this before.
We try to figure out what the equations for a plane are.
That the vector that is definitely on the plane
is going to be the difference of this two vectors.
So, I will do that in blue.
So if you take the yellow vector, minus the green vector.
We will take this position.
You will get the vector.
If you view it that way,
that connects this point to that point.
Although you can shift the vector.
But you will get a vector
that definitely lies along the plane.
Even if you！！
If you start with one of these points.
It will definitely lie along the plane.
So, the vector will look like this.
And it would be lying along our plane.
So this vector lies along our plane.
That vector is p minus p1.
This is the vector p minus p1.
It is this position vector minus
that position vector gives you this one.
Another way to view this is this green position vector
plus that blue position vector
that sits on the plane
will clearly equal this yellow vector.
Right! Heads to tails, clearly equals it.
And the whole reason why that I did that is
now we can take the dot product
between this blue thing and this magenta thing.
And we have done this before.
And they have to be equal to zero,
because this lies on the plane.
This is perpendicular to everything that sits the plane.
And it equals to zero,
and we will get the equation for the plane.
But before I do that,
let me make sure that we know
what the components of the blue vector are.
So p minus p1, that's the blue vector.
You are just going to subtract each of the components.
So it's going to be
x minus xpi, plus y, minus ypj, plus z, minus zpk.
And we just said, this is in the plane.
And this right, the normal vector,
is normal to the plane.
You take their dot product.
is going to be equal to zero.
So n dot, this vector,
But it is also equal to this a times this expression.
I will do it right over here.
So this. I will find some good colors.
So, a times that.
Which is ax minus axp, plus b times that.
So, that is plus by, minus byp.
And then, I have to make sure that I have enough colors.
And then it's going to be plus that times that.
So that's plus cz minus czp.
And all of these is equal to zero.
Now, what I am going to is: I am going to rewrite this,
so we have all of these terms
that I am looking for right color.
We have all the x terms ax.
Remember, this is any x that sits on the plane
that will satisfy this.
So ax, by, and cz.
Let me leave that one the right hand side.
So we have ax plus by plus cz is equal to！！
And what I want to do is:
I am going to subtract each of these from both sides.
Another way is:
I am going to move them all over to the, let me do it.
Not doing too many things.
I'm going to move them over
to the left hand side. .
So I'm going to add positive axp to both sides
as equivalent to subtracting negative axp.
So, this is going to be positive axp, and then,
we are going to have positive byp, plus,
we are going to do that in the same green.
Plus byp and then finally plus czp,
plus czp is going to be equal to that.
Now, the whole reason that why I do this！！
I have done this in previous video
where we were trying to find the formula
or we were trying to find the equations of the plane.
And now you said that hey!
If you have a normal vector,
and you are given a point on the plane.
We say xp yp zp.
We now have a very quick way to figure out the equation.
But I want to go the other way.
I want you to be able to！！
If I were to give you.
If I were to give you an equation for a plane.
Where I would to say ax plus by plus cz, is equal to D
So, this is a general equation for the plane.
If I want to give you this.
I want you to be able to figure out
the normal vector very quickly.
So, how could you do that?
Well, this ax plus by plus cz is completely
analogous to this part right up over here.
Let me rewrite this over here.
so that this part becomes clear.
This part is ax plus by plus cz is equal
to all of these stuff on the right hand side.
Sorry, on the left hand side.
So, let me copy and paste it.
Copy and paste it.
So I just essentially flip this expression.
But now you see, this all of this.
This a has to be this A, this b has to be this B
and this c has to be this thing.
And D is going to be all this.
And this is just going to be a number.
This is just going to be a number.
assuming you mean that you knew
what the normal vector is.
What you a,b,and cs are.
You know the particular values.
So, this is what, this is what D is.
So, this is how you can get the equation for a plane.
Now, what if I were to give you the equation for a plane.
What is a normal vector?
Well. We just saw.
The normal vector, this a corresponds that A.
This b corresponds to that B.
That c corresponds to that C.
The normal vector to this plane we started off with is,
and has the components of a, b, and c.
So, if you are given an equation for a plane here.
The normal vector.
The normal vector to this plane right over here,
is going to be Ai plus Bj plus Ck.
So it's very easy thing to do
if I were to give you an equation of a plane.
Let me give you a particular example.
If I were to tell you
that I have some plane, in three dimensions.
Let's say it's negative 3.
although we could work for more dimensions.
Let's say I have negative 3x,
plus the square root of 2, y, minus,
So it's crazy, I mean it's not crazy.
It should be the plane in three dimensions.
And what's the normal vector to this plane?
You literally,
literally can just pick out these coefficients.
You say a normal vector to this plane
is negative 3i plus square root of 2 j plus 7 k,
and you can ignore the D part there.
And the reason why you can just ignore that
is that can just shift the plane.
but won't fundamentally change how the plane is tilted.
So, this normal vector will also normal
if this was e, if this was a hundred.
It will be normal to all of those planes
because all of those planes are shifted
but they all have the same inclinations.
So it would all come to point at the same directions.
So, it would have normal vectors would point
in the same direction.
So, hopefully you found that vaguely useful.
So now build on this,
define the distance between any point
in three dimensions and some plane,
the shortest distance we can get to that plane.