PROBLEM: Joelle is working on a school report
in a word processor.
She wants to place a figure, which is 13.09 cm wide,
so that it appears centered on the page.
The width of the page is 21.59 cm.
How wide a margin should she leave on the left
so that the figure is centered?"
So, let's visualize what's going on.
We have a page that is 21.59 cm wide.
So, this distance right over here is 21.59 cm.
So this right over here, that is our page.
Let me draw the actual page.
Let me draw that in white,
since paper tends to be white.
So this is her page.
It’s 21.59 cm wide.
It’s just like that .
(That’s a bit of an unusual dimension
for a piece of paper.
But we'll go with it.)
And then she wants to place a figure
that is 13.09 cm wide in the center of the page.
So the figure --
I’ll do it in magenta.
That's not magenta --
The figure is 13.09 cm.
So let’s say that this is the figure right over here.
So this is the figure that she wants to place
in the middle of the page.
So this is 13.09 cm.
So the question is, "How wide a margin
should she leave on the left,
so that the figure is centered?"
So they're really asking,
"What should this distance be here,
so that the figure is centered?"
And the key thing is, if the figure is centered,
this distance is going to be
the same as this distance --
so that the figure is right in the middle.
Whatever this is, it's going to be the same as this.
So one way we could think about it --
We could say, "Okay.
Let's take 13.09 cm from 21.59 cm."
And if we do that, then we'll know how much
left over space this plus this combined is.
And then, we just want to split that space in half.
We want half of it to go on the right side,
and we want half of it to go on the left side.
So let's see how much the left margin
and the right margin combined needs to be.
And that's just 21.59 cm –
That's just going to be 21.59 cm minus 13.09 cm.
And this, we get to – Let’s see.
This is 8.50 cm – which is the combined margins –
Not just the left or not just the right.
This – the left plus the right margin – is 8.50 cm.
This is this distance plus this distance.
Now, if we want to figure out
what the left margin should be –
if we want to center it –
well, we just want to split this evenly
between the left and the right margin.
So we just want to divide this by 2.
So if you divide 18.50 by 2 –
(Or multiply it by 1/2, I guess.
That might be a little bit more obvious. Either way.)
So if we multiply this by 1/2,
we are left with half of 8.50, which is 4.25 cm.
So if we want it centered,
then this is going to be 4.25 cm.
And, of course, this is going to be 4.25 cm, as well.
And you see, when you add 4.25 to 4.25,
you get 8.50 cm.
And when you add that to 13.09,
you get the entire width of the piece of paper.
So how wide a margin should she leave on the left?
4.25 cm.