I want to clarify some of the terminology I used in the last video.
But before I do that, let's just make sure that we understand the mechanism of how arteries get blocked.
So in the last video we talked about these plaques forming, and if this plaque is unstable
at some point it could rupture. And when it ruptures, this material can flow out into the bloodstream.
Two things will happen--I want to make it clearer relative to the last video,
especially since I can zoom in on these arteries--two things can happen:
Plaques, or I should say, clotting factors can clot these released pieces from the plaque.
And the other thing that can and will happen--and I didn't talk about this in depth in the last video--
When this thing ruptures, you can also have blood clots form here.
Let me just draw this in a reddish color, because you can have blood clots form on the ruptured plaque.
So, everything: the part of the plaque that hasn't moved can experience clotting,
and the part of the plaque that is dumped in the bloodstream can also clot.
And in the last video we saw that one of these clots can go downstream to some point
where the arteries get narrow enough so that they actually block the arteries.
And that restricts the blood flow, so all of a sudden you do not have any blood flow going that way,
and all of the muscle tissue that needs the blood flow from this point,
that needs oxygen from that, it might die in a mild myocardial infarction, or even a heart attack.
Now, what I want to clarify is the actual terminology--[the last video] was a little bit "hand wavy"
with the terminology, and I want to go deeper here.
This actual clot that forms, that can restrict the blood vessel, this is a thrombus.
Thrombosis is the process of a thrombus forming.
So [thrombi] are these blood clots that form, that can help to obstruct a blood vessel.
So this thrombus right here is going to make it harder for the blood to flow through this vessel.
Now any of these released pieces or chunks in any of these blood vessels,
that can float around and eventually lodge themselves in and eventually block the blood flow,
these are called emboli, or if I use it in the singular, one of these is an embolus.
I want to be clear, embolus is the general term for anything that can float around in your blood
and eventually lodge itself at some point in your circulatory system and restrict blood flow.
What we drew in the last video--and this one as well--these emboli that are also clotted,
they are also thrombi and emboli at the same time, this would be called a thromboembolus.
So it would not be wrong to call it an embolus, but in particular if you know it is a thromboembolus,
you know it is the clotted material from a released plaque that can go lodge itself.
In the last video I called this a thrombosis but that's really not quite right,
thrombosis is the formation of the clot that can restrict the blood flow,
but when it breaks off, becomes an embolus, and lodges itself further off and restricts blood flow,
this is called a thromboemoblism.
Hopefully I'm not confusing too much--these medical terms confuse ME a lot--
but I want to make it very clear, thrombosis is formation of a blood clot inside of a blood vessel
than can restrict the flow of blood.
So this right here is thrombosis occurring.
Once things break off and become an embolus--that's the general term for it--and in particular,
if it's broken off material that is due to a clot, it is a thromboembolus.
So, thromboembolus is a more specific way of calling it an embolus,
and once one of these things lodge themselves and block the blood flow,
that's a thromboembolism. You can also call it an embolism.
Just that when you say, "thromboembolism," it specifies it as clotted material.
Hopefully that clarifies things and doesn't confuse you to much.