In the middle of the seventeenth century
Rome was reborn.
It was a tremendous building camapign
and I think about the extravagance spaces
of the church of il Gesu
with its extraordinary illusionistic ceiling.
this was operatic, it was theatrical.
It's hard to imagine how
at a very same time
there we have that broke theatricality
we have the classicism, the repose, the peacefulness
the rationalism of Poussin.
We're in the Art Institute of Chicago.
We're looking at Possin's landscape with Sant John on Patmos.
This is a painting that really is about
classical order and measured reality.
We know this is Saint John because of the eagle that stands beside him,
which is a traditional symbol of this Evangelist.
We're looking at Saint John
sitting in the foreground writing the book of Revelation,
writing about the end of time, the second comming of Christ
are really violent moments,
but within this incredibly serene and peaceful landscape.
And of course it's Pussain who has been credited
with inventing the ideal landscape and
that's exactly what we have here.
And it's going to be very important for art history,
for actually centuries to come.
Artists will look back at the classical landscape
and reinterprete it.
In fact Pussin style was so infuential
that it became a standard for the French Academy.
And those who painted landscapes in this way,
with a sense of rigor and order and rationalism,
in a kind of ideal landscape,
became known as poussinists.
So what has he actually done here?
He's placed the main figure in the foreground but he's really quite small
in relationship to the landscape. He sits in a very classicised pose.
In fact we think that Poussin took this pose directly
from representations of river gods from ancient Rome.
And of course Poussin, although he was French,
was in Rome for most of his life.
And that figure, Saint John, is enromanited in the foreground.
He's surrounded by the ruines of classical antiquity.
We see ruines to his left and to his right.
And also in the background, where we see the ruins
of a classical temple and an ancient obelisk.
So he's in this landscape that has a sense of the passage of time
as he's writing his book about the end of time.
The notion of passage, I think, is important to understanding
the way Pussin constructs a landscape.
Saint John is placed in the very foreground,
right at the bottom of the painting,
but we can't raise back to the middle ground
where that temple is that you had mentioned.
Instead, we have a couple of visual paths.
We may try to go down and straight back, but
we see water, not once but twice.
And also a curtain of trees.
And so that way seems too difficult. So instead,
our eye meanders over to the right
and we see a road that seems to go back,
but it draws our eyes slowly through this landscape
so that we slow down
and enjoy the space that he's created.
And at each point in this landscape
he gives us something to look at, the foreground
with Saint John and the ruins, that path way
punctuated by trees, into the middle ground
with that temple and obelisk and then again into the background
with the mountains and furter back with the area perspective and
more mountains and clouds. At each place
our eye has a place to rest in the landscape.
The lanscape is not a specific place.
This is very much a collage of ideal forms and it makes sens
for an artist whose aesthetic has been shaped by Rome,
which itself is layers of cultures.
Look for instance at this painting where
you've got the classical Greek or Roman temple
but it's next to an Egyptian obelisk.
We actually see references to two cultures,
both of which had ruled but had both fallen.
The idea here by showing those ruins is to show that
there is a new Christian order that will be eternal,
foretold by Saint John's book of Revelation.
The landscape is carefully, rigorously composed.
Everything has a sens of order and structure and geometry.
But that is so counter to what we expect or
what we think about Saint John writing the Apocalypse.
This is a widely violent vision, it is the end of time.
It's an important reminder that this artist was
actually studying stoic philosophy from ancient Greece,
this idea that the control of emotion was of the utmost importance.
And not just Poussin but the circle of painters that he found in Rome.
We need to remember that there was more going on in Rome.
Then the pope's commisioning these theatrical works of art
in the churchers of counterreformation.
Poussin found a circle of painters, many of whom were
interested in stoic philosophy, and that he painted canvases like this one.
So Poussin has accomplished what seems to be nearly impossible.
He's created poetry out of the rational, out of the ideal.