As promised, lets do a couple of
simple Snell's Law examples.
So lets say
lets say that I have
Lets say that I have two, two media.
I guess the plural of Medium's.
So lets say that I have air right here.
Air
And then right here is the surface
that is the surface.
Let me do that in a more appropriate color.
That is the surface of...
the Water!
So this right here is the surface of water.
And I know that I have a light ray.
I have a light ray.
Coming in, with an incident angle of
So it has an incident angle, so relative to the perpendicular
It has an incident angle of, of 35째.
And what I want to know is, I want to know what the
angle of refraction will be.
So it will refract a little bit, it will bend inwards a little bit.
Since this outside's going to be in the air a little longer if you
buy into my 'car traveling into the mud' analogy.
So, It will then bend a little bit.
And i wanna figure out what this new angle will be.
I wanna figure out the angle of refraction.
I'll call that 'theta 2'
What is this?
And so we can just, this is just straight up applying Snell's Law.
And I'm going to use the version with the
Using the refraction indices.
Since we have a table here from the ck12.org flexbook.
On the refraction indices.
And you can go get it, uh, for free if you like.
And that just tells us
That just tells us that the refraction index for
The first medium, so, that is air.
The refraction index for air times the sine of the incident angle
In this case its 35째
Is going to be equal to the refraction index for water
Times the sine of this angle right over here.
Times the sine of 'theta 2'
And we know what the refraction index for air
and for water is
Then we just have to solve for 'theta 2'
So lets just do that.
The refraction index for air is
This number right over here, 1.00029.
So its going to be 1.00-theres only, theres three zeros
1.00029 times the sine of 35째
Is going to be equal to the refraction index for water
Which is 1.33, so its 1.33 times sine, times sine of 'theta 2'
Now we can devide both sides of the equation by 1.33
We divide one, both sides by 1.33
On this side we are just left with
Sine of theta 2
on the left hand side, lets get our calculator out for this
so let me get the handy calculator
so we want to calculate, and i made sure my calculator
is in degree mode
1.00029 times the sine of 35째
So thats the numerator, of this expression right here.
The green part. Thats 0.5737, divided by 1.33.
Im just dividing by the numerator here.
This, when you just do, divide this "Ans", it means your last answer.
So thats this numerator up here divided by that denominator.
And so I get 0.4314. I'll just round a little bit.
So I'll get, so I get. I'll switch colors.
0.4314 is equal to sine of 'theta 2'
And now to solve for theta, you just have to take the inverse sine
of both sides of this. So you get the inverse
So you get the inverse sine- this doesn't mean sine to the -1.
You could also do as the arc-sine.
The sine inverse of 0.4314 is going to be equal to the inverse sine
of sine is just the angle itself.
Or, i gues when we're dealing with, uh, When we're dealing with angles
in a normal range, its going to be the angle itself.
And thats going to be the case with this right over here.
And if any of that is confusing, you might want to reveiw
The videos on the inverse sine and the inverse cosine.
And they are in the trigonometry playlist