What we have here is a simulation created
by Peter Collingridge
in response to one of our computer science challenges
so, how many particles might interact gravitationally
and the whole point of this is to get an intuition
for how galaxies form, why they have
the structures they have
why solar - how solar systems form and how
they have the structures they have and how
gravity alone can kind of define that structure
and what's really interesting about the simulation
besides the fact that it's just mesmerizing
and extremely cool
where it shows the particles collide, get
once they get to a certain critical mass
-you see that they get colored yellow-
maybe to indicate that they
are now a star
-fusion can now occur-
and you can zoom in at different levels
to really see how the different particles
, the different masses are interacting
and you can actually rotate
you can actually rotate
that to see a little bit clearer
this is kind of looking
kind of right on top of it
to see how they are interacting
It's a three dimensional simulation
so it's a very rich way
of thinking about these
And what's exciting for me
it's highly dependent on what the initial
conditions are
and in an earlier version
of Peter's simulation
he did not give
eh...give a net angular momentum
to the system
and so you do not have as
as much of, kind of the planet- satellite
or as much of the disc structures forming
although right here,
there does seem to be a dominant plane
in this scenario
and, what's exciting is, here
we have a binary system
sometimes you restart it
you might not have a binary system
depending on the initial conditions
you might have something that starts
to look like the Milky Way
sometimes you might have something that
looks very different than the Milky Way
and it really gives us clues
of why we see
such diversity, specially in...when
we're looking at galaxies
the structure of galaxies, that is
highly dependent on initial conditions
One can argue that our own solar
system did have some net
initial angular momentum
because the current theory, it was...
-what really canalized nearby supernova,
that sent a shockwave and
allowed the dust that would form
our Solar System to reach a
critical mass and start to
condense into the Sun and the planets
and so, this isn't, in my mind,
a too unrealistic of a scenario
and it's really cool to look at
and it really gives you a sense of thing
you already see a binary star
orbiting around each other
or orbiting around the center of mass
which kind of looks like
around each other
and then this star right over here has
it's own kind of captive planet
that it's just rotating around it
you can see it a little bit clearer
if we had a very, at least
from this perspective, a very close range
we cann zoom in a little bit more
to see it a little bit better
this has a satellite but
then they are also kind of dancing
around each other
So it's a really fascinating, a really
fascinating simulation, I can really
stare at this and play with it
for days
and I encourage you to
play with it, restart it, see how
the initial conditions or
what type of solar systems or
galaxies you might end up with
or wether they form discs,
wether you habe binary systems or not
and if you have planets with satellites
And then, if you are more advanced,
actually play with the code
and see if you can
really change the initial conditions,
the starting velocities of things
the number of particles of things
the distribution of mass
that you start off with,
the angular momentum that
you start off with
and see how that might change
the structure of the universe
that you create, and an anotation
to this video that links directly
to this simulation; and I'll also
put the link inside of the description
So: have fun; I can literally spend hours
with this, it is fascinating, fascinating module
that he's created,
we zoom in and out and I really thank
Peter Collingridge for this
incredible contribution.