Let's say there is a country made up only of this
island and it's sitting in the middle of this
lake. And on that island, there is only this one dude here,
he has one house and some land on which crops
can be grown, but he wants to think more formally
about his economy. He's starts setting up some
institutions that start to resemble what we would see in
more complex economies. So, what he decides to
do is--he's decides to set up a firm.
So let me put the firm right over here...
He decides to create a legal entity called
some firm over here--some corporation--and he's
sitting here--he's the household of exactly one person.
This is him as a household, and he decides to
give multiple factors of production to the firm.
So, he essentially rents out his building, so he
gets capital, he rents out the land to the firm.
He's giving land, and he works for the firm, so he
is giving labor. He is the owner of the firm
and he was the guy who thought of this
entrepreneurial activity, so he is giving this
factor of production, but throws in there
some entrepreneurship.
And in return, the firm will essentially pay rent
for these factors of production. So the firm will
pay him money in exchange for being allowed to
use all of these things. So, for the rent on the
capital--the building itself--let's say that this
in a given year, the firm (which he owns) is going to pay him $1,000 per year.
So this is the building rent--the building lease--is $1,000.
For the land rent, he's also going to get paid another
$1,000 per year and then for his wages--essentially the rent on his labor--he's renting his energy and his time,