two positive integers differ by 60.
The sum of their square roots is the square root of an integer
that is not a perfect square.
What is the maximum possible sum of the two integers?
in the second sentence is a little confusing.
lets take it step by step.
so two possitive integers differ by 60.
So lets say we have a and b.
So we have A and B they are both greater than zero
so they are both integers
and they differ by 60 so
A minus B is equal to 60
or we could add B to both sides and we get A
is equal to b plus 60
they are 60 apart fair enough
now this second sentence
the sum of their square roots so the
sum of their square roots.
squared of A plus squared to B
The sum of their square roots is the square root of an integer
that is not a perfect square.
so its equal to the square of sum integer
so c is an integer c is an integer but its not a
perfect square. square root of c not is not an integer
What is maximum possible sum of the two integers.