What I want to do in this video is to try to get a better understanding of the structure of the Earth,
and we're actually going to think about it in two different ways,
so let me just draw half of the Earth over here.
That's my best shot at drawing a half of a circle.
We're going to think about it in two ways.
On the left side, we're going to think about it as the compositional layers or the chemical layers.
So, over here, we're going to think about the chemical structure or the composition of the layer.
And, on the right hand side, we're going to think
about the mechanical properties of the layer.
And when I say the mechanical properties,
I'm really just saying is that layer a solid, rigid layer,
is it kind of a liquid layer, or is it something in between, a kind of putty-like, non-rigid, solid layer.
So, let's think about it on the chemical or compositional side first,
because to some degree this is simpler.
The outermost layer is the crust.
That's the layer we're sitting on right here, right now,
I'm assuming - assuming you're on the planet.
It is the outermost and it is obviously solid -
we'll think about that when we talk about the mechanical side of things.
And it's also the thinnest layer.
Now, crust is not uniform - there's both oceanic crust and continental crust.
Let me draw the crust on this side as well.
And there's both oceanic crust and continental crust.
So, oceanic crust is thinner crust.
So, let's say that this part right here - let's draw some thicker crust -
we'll call the thicker part continental crust,
which is thicker and less dense than oceanic crust.
So, what I'm doing in this light green color, this is continental.
And then in this more fluorescent green is oceanic crust.
And the oceanic crust is pretty thin, in the order of five to ten kilometers thick.
Now, when I talk about oceanic crust I'm not talking about the oceans, the liquid part, the water,
I'm talking about the rock that kind of holds the water.
The rock underneath the ocean.
So, this is five to ten kilometers thick.
If you were to go to the bottom of the ocean, sit on the rock,
then drill, you would have to drill five to ten kilometers to get through that layer,
this compositional layer.
So, this is five to ten kilometers.
And the continental crust is about ten to seventy kilometers thick.
And obviously they are both rigid, they are both solid rock.
Now below, when you think of composition, what the layers are made up of.
The next layer below that, this is actually the biggest layer of the earth by volume, is the mantle.
So, let me draw it like that.
I always have trouble drawing the right hand side of the circle.
So this is the mantle right over here.
And once again we differentiate it from the crust
because it's composed of different types of rock.
Now, we go even deeper.
Let me give you the depths here.
So, the mantle starts below the crust, right below the continental and oceanic crust,
and it goes about 2,900 kilometers deeper.
So it is much, much, much thicker than the crust.
The crust is on the order of maybe 5 to 70 km thick.
This is much, much thicker.
So, even though I drew the crust fairly thin,
I didn't draw it thin enough relative to how thick I've draw the mantle.
This isn't drawn to scale.
Now you go even deeper than that, you get kind of the densest part of the Earth,
and that is the core.
There's going to be a couple of themes here,
especially when we think of the mechanical properties of the earth,
is that the deeper you get, you're going to get denser elements
and you're going to have more heat and more pressure.
The reason why you're going to have denser elements
Is when the Earth was first forming and it was kind of in its molten state,
the denser elements sunk to the bottom,
and the lighter elements would kind of rise to the top.
They would have this bouyancy because they are less dense than everything around it.
Even the gases would bubble up and form our atmosphere.
So, that's why in general, the densest things are at the center
and the least dense things are on the outside - they're in our atmosphere.
And the core, once again, it's composition is
fundamentally different than the mantle and crust.
We believe that it is mainly metals, in particular iron and nickel.
So that's the structure of the layers of the Earth
from a composition point of view, a chemical point of view.
Now, let's kind of think of the same layers,
but we're going to think more in terms of what's liquid,
what's rigid and solid, and what's in between.
So the outermost rigid layer of the Earth is made up
of the crust, both the continental and oceanic crust,
and the coolest top layer of the mantle.
Let me draw that in pink.
So what I'm drawing in pink is the cool, rigid, solid part of the mantle.
So it is solid rock, part of the mantle is solid rock,
its composition is different from the crust, but they are both rigid.
So if you combine this top most layer of the mantle with the crust,
then you're talking about the lithosphere.
So this is the lithosphere.
And this essentially gets you about, depening on where you are on the surface of the earth,
is 10-200 kilometers thick.
And most of the time, it's closer to the high end of the range.
The 10 is kind of where you have hot spots in the mantle
and it's essentially been able to dissolve part of the lithosphere,
we'll talk about that more when we talk about plate tectonics.
These are actually lithospheric plates, and the lithosphere
is actually moving on top of the lower layers of the mantle.
The lithosphere it is rigid, solid, it's made up of
the crust and the uppermost layer of the mantle.
Now, you go a little bit deeper, the temperatures and pressures increased,
but now the temperatures have increased enough
- you have the same composition as the uppermost, the rigid part of the mantle,
but the temperatures have now gone up enough that it now turns it now into
not quite a liquid, we won't call it a liquid,
it still transmits a certain type of waves that liquids wouldn't transmit.
it's more of like a putty-like texture, it has fluid-like properties,
it can float, it's way more viscous than what we'd associate with most fluids,
so it's not rigid and solid, it can have convection going on in it,
but it's not a liquid
- it still will transmit some types of waves that liquids won't.
This is called the asthenosphere, this kind of jelly, putty layer.
It's like that, because it's so hot that the rock has somewhat melted.
So, this is, this layer right here, is the asthenosphere.
I've seen some spellings that have an 'e' after the a,
I think that's the european spelling.
The aesthenosphere obviously starts right below the lithosphere.
It's what the lithospheric plates, when we are talking about tectonic plates, are riding on top of.
It's kind of the gummy layer that allows the rigid layer
to kind of move, actually move on top.
So it starts below the lithosphere and it ends at around 660 kilometers deep.
So, this right here is 660 kilometers deep.
And then you go even deeper than that,
and now the pressures are so big that even are even higher,
the pressures are so big that the same material can't have fluid motion anymore.
It's essentially been jammed together.
So you can imagine if you have things that are somewhat fluid,
their molecules can kind of slide past each other, maybe very slowly.
But, if you increase the pressure enough, they'll be jammed into each other,
and that's essentially what happens in the next layer of the mantle.
All of these layers of the mantle are made up of the same thing,
it's just a difference of pressure.
So, the next layer of the mantle is called the mesosphere.
Mesosphere.
This is called the mesosphere, but there is also a layer of our atmosphere
right above the stratosphere that's called the mesosphere.
And so, don't get confused here, these are two different mesosphere-s.
And this layer, the pressure is so big, that now we are rigid again.
We are kind of definetely solid now.
None of this debate about a little bit of fluid motion
because the pressure is so big.
Now you go a little bit deeper, you are in the core, the metallic core,
the temperatures are so high, that even though the pressures are high
because we have a compositional change,
we are at pressures where this type of mesospheric rock is rigid,
but metals at this temperature can be fluid,
can actually be liquid.
We actually have a liquid outer core.
The entire core, as far as we know, is made up of
the same stuff, just the outer part of the core,
the temperatures are high enough to melt the metals,
but the pressures aren't so high enough to make them solid.
They're definitely high enough to kind of make more
rocky materials solid, but not the metals.
And then you go even deeper, now the temperature keeps going up,
the pressure is so strong that even the metals are solid.
So, this is the solid, the solid, inner core.
So, when you think about the mechanical properties,
the innermost, and just so you know the total distances we're talking about,
the outer core starts at,
actually, I didn't tell you where the mesosphere -
the mantle ends at about 2900 kilometers deep,
so that's clearly where the mesosphere ends as well,
because the mesosphere is kind of the lower mantle.
This is 2900 kilometers deep.
Then you go even deeper.
Now, you're in the liquid outer core, and that extends
from about 2900 kilometers deep to about 5100 kilometers deep.
So I really should, I frankly should make the liquid core in my drawing a little wider.
So, this depth is about 5100 kilometers deep.
And then obviously, you have the center of the Earth,
and the entire radius of the earth is about 6400 kilometers.
So, hopefully that clarifies things when you hear
people talking about the lithosphere or the mantle,
they're really talking about mechanical versus composition.
And when we talk about mechanical, solid inner core,
liquid outer core, essentially solid mesosphere,
and then you have something, kind of a spongy,
somewhat fluid, not-solid, not-liquid aesthenosphere
that the lithospheric plates can ride on top of,
and then you have your actual rigid, solid lithosphere
made up of the uppermost part of the mantle and the crust.