Solve for x and y.
We have two equations and two unknowns
Negative 3y plus 4x= 11 and y plus 2x = 13
What we could do is try to solve this using- using elimination
Maybe we could add these two equations together
to get some variables to cancel out.
But if we just add y and -3y, those will cancel out.
And if we just add 2x and 4x, THOSE will cancel out
But maybe we can SCALE one of these equations
so that we WILL get some cancellation.
If this y could somehow become a 3y, then 3y and -3y would cancel out.
So the easiest way to t-turn this y into a 3y would be to just
multiply this entire equation so we don't actually change the information in it
To multiply this entire equation by 3.