Now that we set up our equation. Let's see if we can answer some more interesting questions.
This is a warm-up. We are gonna do a little bit of what we did in the last video.
But I will do it with the equations now.
The equations are really just a mathematically representation of the same information that we have up here.
As a starting point, let's think about how much, under this basic plan, it will cost for us to attend 3 sessions in a given month.
We have our equation right over here. Our total cost in that month is going to be equal to 20 plus 8 times the number of session.
The number of sessions is "s". "s" is 3 in this circumstance. So we replace "s" with the 3.
So we get that our cost is 20 + 8 times 3. Or 20 + 24. Or $44. So it's gonna cost us $44.
Now lets do the same under the trial plan
How much is it gonna cost up to attend 3 sessions?
Well, this is more straight forward, our total cost is gonna be equal to 12 times the number of sessions.
The number of sessions is 3.
so it is 12 times 3, so our total cost is going to be $36.
But we could also answer more interesting questions with these equations.
For example, how many sessions can I attend in a month for $54.
When I look at my salary and my budget for health and fitness, this is what I can afford. And based on that I wanna ask.
How many session can I attend with each of these situations?
First let's think about it for the trail plan. How many session can I attend for $54.
Now let's just assume that this is some kind of special yoga studio, where
you can even attend a half session and they will just charge you half the cost, 6 dollars. If you attend a 1/4 of a session they charge you 3 dollars.
so they keep track of exactly what fraction of a session that you attend.
You don't have to attend a whole number of sessions.
You could attend 2 1/2 and they will bill you accordingly.
So with that said, how many session under the trial plan can I attend for $54?
Well, lets think about it this a little bit.
So my cost now is 54. 54 is "c". It's my monthly cost. 54 is equal to 12 times the number of session.
So now I have set this equation. In order to answer this question. I just need to figure the number of session that satisfy it.
Now this is "s" is an unknown variable.
What number of sessions times 12 is equal to 54.
Well you might say, if I could just get "s", just the "s" on the right side here, then I have the answer.
"s" will be equal to some value.
And if I want just an "s" on the right hand side, I divide this by 12.
12s divided by 12 is s. The number of sessions.
But if I have an equal sign, I can't just willy-nilly divide one side by 12 without doing the exact same thing to the other side.
If that is equal to that, in order for them still be equal we have to do the same thing to both sides.
So on the right hand side, I'm left with just an s, and on the left hand side, I have 54 divided by 12.
Let me think about that. 12 goes into 54.
4 times. 4 times 12 is 48.
You are left with a remainder of 6.
So you could say 12 goes into 54. Or you could say 54/12 is equal to 4 and 6/12.
or 4 and a 1/2.
So the number of session that I can attend are 4 1/2.
If I 54 to spend, I can attend 4 1/2 sessions under the trial plan.
If this was yoga studio that said, you can't attend half sessions, then
it would only be 4 sessions, because 5 sessions would get me above my budget.
But I said you can attend fractional sessions, so it is 4 1/2.
Now lets answer the same question for the basic plan.
Under the basic plan how many sessions can I attend for 54 dollars?
Once again this will be our total cost for that months, so we say,
54 is equal to 20 + 8 times the number os sessions.
And once again, I'd like to have just session on the right hand side of this equation.
So I can say session are going to be equal to something.
This is the number of session I can attend.
But I have this 20 here and this 8 here, so i have to think about how I can get rid them.
So the first thing to think about is how can I get rid of this 20 on the right hand side of this equation?
what am I gonna do to the entire equation?
well the simplest thing, I could subtract 20 from the right hand side, but if subtract 20 from the right hand side,
iI also have to subtract from the left hand side to maintain the equality.
And so I'm left with.
on the left hand side: 54 minus 20 gets me 34,
and thats equal to 8s,
so 8s has to equal 34
in order for 8 times the number of session plus 20 to be equal to 54
and you can add 20 both sides to get the original.
So we're almost done, we just need to isolate the s right here and you can imagine that the easiest way
would be to divide the right hand side by 8 but if divide the right hand side by 8,
we have to do the same to the left.
and so what do we for the number of session that we would have to attend?
well, these cancel out, and so you get the number of session is equal to 34/8
34/8 is equal to, lets see.
8 goes into 34 four times with the remainder 2.
so 4 and 2/8.
or it's 4 1/4.
So I can attend 4 1/4 session under the basic plan.
So assuming I can do fractional session, for which one can attend more sessions in?
The basic or the trial plan?
Well for 54 I can attend a slight longer amount of session under the trial plan.