This right here is our derivative intuition module.
It was contributed by Ben Eater, and it is a pretty intresting module.
What is cool about it is it really helps to conceptualize what a derivative is all about.
All it really is [derivatives] is the slope of the tangent line at any point.
So in this exercise over here they have graphed f(x) = 2x^3
So this is 2x^3 over here
and what we need to do is to move these orange dots up and down
so these orange dots right now show a line so when I highlight that orange dot,
you see the line down here become orange.
And right now the dot is on zero as the slope of the line right here is zero
but we see that that line is definitely not the tangent,
the slope at that point is definitely not zero.
So what we need to do is move this so it becomes pretty close,
or as close as we can eye-ball it to the slope of the tangent line.
and so that looks about right, as it looks about right.
It looks pretty close to the slope of the line at that point.
And you can even see while I do it up here, you see d/df of f(x) at -2
So the derivative at f equal to negative 2 what is the derivartive there
that is the slope, so by putting it all the way up here I am saying
that the slope is equal to 24 at that point.
So that is my approximation, eye-balling it like that.
Lets do this point right here. It looks like the slope is decressing
a little bit but it is still very positive
so mayby the slope is around 14 or 15
and then here, once again the slope has decressed but it is still reasonbly positive
the slope looks like it is about 5.
So our slope is drcressing
right over here the slope dose look like it is about zero (0)
it looks like an inflection point actully, so our slope is zero right there.
You can see that the derivative at f(0) is 0 which just means
that this fancy notation to say that the slope of the tangent line / curve at this point is zero
it is flat there, you can see that it realy is flat
and you go over here, and we want to find the derivative at
f(1) and so again it looks like the slope is increasing.
So this interesting, up here the slope was very positive but it was decressing as we went over here
notice how it is getting flatter and flatter
but it goes to zero and now the slope is incressing again
so at this point we want to make a tangent,
and notice that the slope has gone up relative to where we were at one
so that looks like the slope right over there
and we do the slope over there
and if we get pretty close it will actully draw the curve of the derivative
So there you go
and so we didn't find the derivative at evey point in the curve
we found it just at these special points we have the orange dots for
but since we gots the orange dots close enough to the actual derivative
just by eye-balling it to try and find, trying to look at what the slope of the tangent line is.
It says, ok you have done it right and it then drew the whole slope of the derivative
and what the entire derivative is saying, is at any point this is the slope of the tangent line.
So even though you didn't move a dot around at
-0.5 if you go right up here that looks like it is around 2.5.
So this will be a little bit over 1, this looks like that will be the slope of the tangent line right over there.
Or if we went all the way over to -2.25, the slope will be aproximatly
30 right over there, so once you have the curve
you now have the slope of the tangent line
or if you have the slope of the curve at every point we see over here.
So this is just a pretty neat exercise.