Let's see if we can use our example
to understand the 3 types of income statements
and hopefully understanding those income statements
will also help us understand this example.
So I'm gonna start of, we're gonna focus on month 2
and what I've done is I've rewritten some of this
accrual income statement down here
so it really looks like a statement
so this right here is the income statement for month 2
on an accrual basis. And that month, we said we had
$400 of revenue, $200 of expense,
$400 minus $200 gives us $200 of income.
And income statement tells us what happened
over a period of time, what was the activity?
How much revenue, how much expenses, and other things
this is just a super simplified one, without taxes
without interest, without other types of expenses over here.
I also have drawn the balance sheet at the end of month 1
and the balance sheet at the end of month 2.
Or you could also view this balance sheet here
as the balance sheet at the beginning of month 2.
And the main thing to realize is the income statement tells you
what happens over a time period,
while balance sheets are snapshots, or they're pictures
at a given moment.
Snapshots. So this tells us essentially,
what did I have?
The assets are the things that can give me
future benefits. So what do I have,
and the liabilities are things that I have to give
future benefit to, or things that I owe
so this is what I have, this is what I owe,
and then the equity is really what I have to my name
if I net out the liabilities from the assets.
So the beginning of month 2, which is the end of month 1,
I had $100 of cash, no accounts receiveables,
I didn't owe anyone anything,
I didn't owe them money, I didn't owe them services
So $100 minus 0, means I had $100,
that's kind of what the owners of the company
can say they have of value at the beginning of the month.
You fast forward, now at the end of the month 2
I now owe the bank $100,
So I just put this as negative $100 here,
it normally wouldn't be accounted that way
on an actual company's balance sheet, but just to simplify it,
But I have an accounts receivable of $400,
so my total assets now are $300 of assets,
remember, accounts receivables aren't assets,
because someone owes me something,
someone owes me cash in the future.
I still have no liabilities
So you take all of your assets,
minus all of your liabilities,
and now I have $300 in equity.
So you can see
the snapshot at the beginning of the month: $100 in equity
snapshot at the end of the month: $300 in equity.
And so to go from one point to the other,
to go from $100 to $300,
I must have grown in equity by $200,
I must have gotten $200 worth of value from someplace
and that's what the income statement describes.
It describes it right over here
the change in equity,
sometime the change in retained earnings,
or just change in equity,
that is going to be the $200 in net income
that the company got over that time period.
Now there's one thing that you're probably confused by right now
well you know, how do we reconcile everything with the cash
we know that over this period we got $200 in income
on an accrual basis.
But when you look at the cash, we went from $100
positive cash, to negative $100 in cash.
It looks like we lost $200.
So how can we reconcile the fact that we got $200 income?
How can we reconcile that with the fact that
we lost $200 in cash?
And that reconciliation is going to be done
on the cash flow statement, and I'll do that in the next video.