I've drawn an arbitrary triangle right over here
And I've also drawn is three medians
Median EB median FC and median AD
And we know where the three median intersect
at point G right over here we call that the centroid
What I wanna do in this video is prove to you
That centroid is exactly two thirds along the way of each median
Or another way to think about it we can pick any one of
these medians then let's say let's pick EB
What I wanna do is I wanna prove that EG,
EG is equal to two times GB two times GB
So whatever distance this is it's twice this distance there
Or other way to think about it is EG is two thirds along
the way of EB and that logic that I'm using to prove this
You can use for any of the medians to show
That the centroid is exactly two thirds along the way of any median
Or divides it to a segment that's twice as long as the other segment
And to do that let's focus I wanna focus on triangle A B E
Triangle A B E right over here
And I'm gonna draw this median as essentially the way
So let me draw that way I'm gonna try to color code it similarly
So we draw it I'm gonna draw it a little bit flatter than that
So it's like that and then we have the two yellow sides
So it looks something like this
It looks something like that
And then we have the centroid right over here at G
That is our centroid and then we have this magenta line going to A
Let me draw a little bit neater than that
We have that line going to A
And then we have this blue line going to F right over here
We have this blue line going to F
And let me label all the points go back to the orange color
So this is going to be E, this is going to be B, this is going to be A
This is going to be F right over here
And just to make sure we have all the same markings
That little marking there is that marking
These two markings are on this side right over there
And the whole way that I'm gonna prove
That EG is twice as long as GB is
Just to refer the results that we did I think a couple of videos ago
That the medians divide in this triangle to just
Into six smaller triangles that all have equal area
So another way to think about it
Is each of these three smaller triangles have equal layer
These are three of the total of six smaller triangle
So these three all have equal area
So let's think about of this triangle right over here
Let's think about of this triangle, triangle AGB
This is triangle AGB right over there those are same triangles
And let's compare that to triangle
Let's compare it to triangle EAG right over here
Let's compare it to this triangle which is
This triangle right over here on the original drawing
Now they both have the exact same height if you view EG
As their as their base or not I guess their shared base
They don't have the exact same base
This smaller triangle has the base E oh sorry
The smaller orange triangle has GB as its base
The larger blue triangle has EG as its base
But the definitely have the same height or altitude
When you draw it this way
So their height in both cases is this right over here
Now the other thing that we do know
The other thing that we do know
Is that this blue triangle EAG
Has twice the area of the orange triangle how do we know that?
Because it's got two of these triangles in it
So one way to think about it is this orange triangle has area X
You want me to call it A well I already used A
So I'm gonna call it area X
Then each of these blue triangles have area X
Or you could say this entire blue region
This entire blue region has area two X area two X
So if you look at this two blue triangles
We know that one half times base time height is equal to area
So we get one half the base is EG one half
I'll do that in green color
One half EG times height times this yellow height
Is going to be equal to two X
I'm just way I'm just applying the formula for the area of a triangle
One half base times height is equals to area this is our area
Now let's do the same thing for this orange triangle
One half let me scroll a little bit to the right
We have one half GB GB times the yellow height
Times height is going to be equal to X
Is going to be equal to X
Well we can substitute if this is equal to X we can
We can place this entire expression right over here for X
So let's do that we get one half
And you might already see where this is going
But I won't I won't skip any steps here
We get one half time EG times H times H
Is equals to two is equals to two time X
But instead of X I'm gonna write this here
As you can look so two times two times one half times GB
Times this length times the base of the smaller triangle
Times H times H
And now we can just simplify this
We have two times one half is just going to be
It's just going to be one you can divide both sides by H
And we are left with one half EG is equals to GB
Or we could write EG over two is equal
Let me do this in same color since I've gone this far
With the same colors
So we can write we can write on half EG, EG is equal to GB
Is equal to GB and we're done
This is essentially saying that GB is half of EG
GB is half of EG so for example if EG is two
This is going to be one if EG is four this is going to be two
So we've actually proven our result
We'll actually let's go back to
This is the result we wanted to prove to get to there
We just multiply both sides of this equation by two
You multiply thisthe left hand side by two you get EG
You multiply the right hand side by two you get GB
So we've proven the EG is twice GB
And you can apply the same logic to any of the medians
To show that the centroid
Is exactly two thirds along the way of the median.