We're in Tate Britain and we're looking at John Everett Millais's Ophelia.
This is the quintessential Victorian and quintessential Pre-Raphaelite painting.
It is. And the Victorians painted Shakespeare quite a lot and they even painted Ophelia quite a lot.
But this is the painting that everybody remembers.
It's that moment after Hamlet has murdered Ophelia's father,
and she has let herself fall into this river and is letting herself drown.
She goes mad after Hamlet murders her father and allows herself to drown.
And Shakespeare describes the place where that happens.
He describes the flowers and the willow tree.
Millais picks up on that interest in the botanical setting and expands on it.
On the botanical specificity. This is an artist who is really taking Ruskin seriously.
Ruskin advised artists to go into nature with a "singleness of heart, rejecting nothing, selecting nothing, and scorning nothing."
That is that Nature itself has some kind of spiritual power.
Who are artists to mess with God's work?
That's right. But that was the academic tradition,
to take from Nature and improve on it and to idealise it.
That was what Reynolds had advised, that's the foundation of academic tradition.
Millais is completely rejecting that.
He's going into nature and he's trying to be as true to what he sees as possible.
It's interesting, because when we think of painting in plein air,
that is, when we think of painting outside,
we often think of late 19th century, French painting.
We think of the Impressionists, but off course,
the Pre-Raphaelites in England were taking this seriously mid-century.
Millais found a spot that was very much like the one that Shakespeare described.
But it's not as pictoresque as it sounds.
Painting outside is full of frustrations and difficulties.
You have insects, you have weather variations, you have animals,
and Millais speaks about this with a wonderful sense of sarcasm in a letter that he wrote.
Millais wrote:
"I am threatened with a notice to appear before a magistrate
for trespassing in a field and destroying the hay.
I am also in danger of being blown by the wind into the water,
and becoming intimate with the feelings of Ophelia when that lady sank to muddy death."
This is the funniest part, I think.
"There are two swans that not a little add to my misery
by persisting in watching me from the exact spot I wish to paint.
My sudden perilous evolutions on the extreme bank, to persuade them to evacuate their position,
have the effect of entirely deranging my temper,
my pictures, brushes and palets.
Certainly, the painting of a picture under such circumstances,
would be a greater punishment for a murderer than a hanging."
So we have Millais really clearly at the end of his rope, trying to paint this image.
The Pre-Raphaelites often show us images of solitary women,
expressing feelings of longing and frustration and, in this case, madness.
The model for this is the woman who'll become Rossetti's wife,
who was his model and muse, Elizabeth Siddal.
She apparently posed for him in a bathtub they kept warm with some candles underneath.
Although she did get sick as the water did eventually get cold.
I know he was quite proud of the dress he had bought for her to wear.
It was already an antique and was heavily embroidered with silver,
and is beautifully rendered here as it floats.
It almost becomes like the water reeds that we see around.
In fact, this painting was really praised in its day
for being perhaps the most faithful to nature in terms of its botanical accuracy.
We can see clearly not only a large willow tree that has fallen and then has regrown.
It's actually wonderful to look at the way that those upturned roots mimic the pose of Ophelia's arms.
And we see lots of flowers that we can identify very specifically.
And that have symbolic purpose.
We see forget-me-nots and poppies, which are a symbol of death,
and violets, which are a symbol of faithfulness.
In fact, she's got a chain of violets around her neck,
which, I think, comes directly from the Shakespearian play.
The symbolic meaning of all the flowers would have been understood by the Victorian public.
And interestingly, links all the way back to Shakespeare,
who, as you said, is very specific as well about some of the flowers that are mentioned.
Ophelia floats with her palms upturned.
She's not dead yet, her eyes are open and she seems to be floating down the river.
But there are lovely passages when you look closely,
not only at the flowers, but especially in the lower left,
where we see the light moving through those weeds that are growing up in the water.
The intensity of the colors and the specificicity - both of those things, I think,
would have been really new and rather shocking to the Victorian public.
Part of that was achieved because the Pre-Raphaelites rejected the traditional mode of painting,
that is painting on a dark ground.
Instead, they painted on a brilliant white ground and some of that luminosity really comes through.
In addition, some of these artists actually painted not on a dry white ground, but on a ground that was still wet,
which meant that that white was picked up by the colors and really creates this vivid luminessness.
So the Pre-Raphaelites really were revolutionary.
We love them now and they seem very familiar to us,
but they seemed really radical back in the late 1840s and 1850s.