There's a very popular and I thought, good movie, out
based on the play,
which is based on the novel by Victor Hugo,
Les Miserables
and I'm sure I'm mispronouncing it.
It means The Miserable, for who it was not obvious.
And what I want to give is a bit of context
because, in that book/play/movie
there is an attempted revolution, and sometimes
people try to associate it with the French Revolution.
But that is not depicting
the French Revolution that people talk about
when they talk about the French Revolution.
So I thought I would give a little bit of a scaffold
of French history in the late 1700s
and all the way through the mid 1800s.
To give a little bit of context on the matter.
So let's start off in 1789.
1789. That's when you have the French Revolution.
The First French Revolution, you could say.
Or the French Revolution,
which is the French Revolution that people talk about,
when they're talking about the French Revolution.
It was all about deposing Louis 16th
and his wife, Marie Antoinette
This is her body there, I think she just got guillotined.
This is her head, it was a very bloody revolution.
This is the storming of the Bastille. Right over here.
And that starts the beginning
of the First Republic in France.
The First Republic.
So there were all these dreams and aspirations that
France would now be a country of the people,
and not too dissimilar to the United States.
But, revolutions are not so easy or so clean or so fast
and France had to go through several,
of a long period of pain before it could
really establish itself as a real republic.
But let's keep going on... further off in history.
Let me do that in a different color.
Put the timeline in white.
So let's fast forward to 1799.
1799.
This is when Napoleon Bonaparte comes to power.
So when people talk about Napoleon,
they are talking about Napoleon Bonaparte.
We'll see there are other Napoleons
but people just say hey, Napoleon did this or that,
they're talking about Napoleon Bonaparte.
So this is Napoleon comes to power. Napoleon...
And he officially ends the first Republic, in 1804
because he declares himself emperor.
But let's fast forward.
There's many videos on the Khan Academy dealing with
the Napoleonic wars and the French Revolution
but let's fast forward to 1815.
So let me do that in white again.
So you get to 1815.
So that was about, 10 years, and this is about, 16 years.
So this is.. let's put 1815 right over there
1815 is essentially Napoleon faces his Waterloo
which is literally at Waterloo
that's why people talk about "facing your Waterloo".
So that was... he was banished a little bit at Elba
he was able to come back
He had 100, actually 111 days in power
But then he was finally defeated.
And then he was finally put into exile at St. Helena,
where he died.
And 1815, you essentially have
the restoration of the Bourbon monarchy.
So Louis 16th's younger brother
comes to power, and they call him Louis 18th.
So this is Louis the 18th.
Which raises a very good question:
what happened to Louis 17th?
Louis 17th was Louis 16th's son, who died in prison
at the age of 10 in 1795, during the Revolution.
So let's keep...
Or during the Revolutionary period, I guess we could say.
So this right over here, this right over here, let me draw..
this is Napoleon's...
Let me do this in the same color as I did Napoleon, right
So 1799 to 18...
actually 1814 is when Napoleon's reign ended
but he then came back for a little bit,
so I'll draw a little bit of dotted line here
A little dotted line
And then 1814 was the formal restoration
of the Bourbon Monarchy
And then of course Napoleon comes back a bit.
But after Waterloo, it's really firmly, firmly established.
So you have the restoration of the Bourbon Monarchy.
So this is Louis 18th.
And then in 1824, he dies. And he dies childless.
1824. So let's see, it's about 9 years.
I will put this about right over there. 1824.
He dies childless, and so his younger brother,
Charles 10th comes to power.
So then you have Charles 10th
I'll do all the Bourbons in purple.
Charles X.
And this is Charles X right over here.
And so let's go a little bit further off into history.
You fast forward all the way to 1830.
You fast forward to 1830
A lot of discontent.
And now you have the Second French Revolution.
You might say,
ho hey, this must be what Les Miserables is about.
NO. We're not there yet.
Les Mis is not about the 2nd French Revolution,
which is sometimes called the July Revolution.
July Revolution
And this revolution actually did not, it was successful,
but it did not establish a republic at this point.
Instead, it installed.. and this whole time,
there was kind of a liberalization.
The monarchy, even when it was put in power
had a kind of gradual decline in how much power it had.
But after the July Revolution, they put in
Charles X's cousin.
Charles X's cousin, who was the Duke of Orleans.
The Duke of Orleans, who was this guy right over here.
Louis Phillipe the 1st.
So let me write that, so this is Louis Phillipe the 1st
And so you're saying,
Sal, you started off this video talking about Les Mis
and you haven't mentioned Les Mis yet!
Give me a little bit of context.
So now I will give you context.
So if you watched the movie,
it starts off with Jean Valjean
he's at like a shipping place,
where they're repairing ships of some sort.
That was in 1815, after Waterloo.
So it was under Louis 18th's regime.
So that's right over here.
Let me see where the start of the movie
The start of the movie is right... right about there.
And then the real climax of the movie
which is this rebellion,
there's these barricades being set up in Paris,
you have all these young, idealistic folks
were trying to overthrow the government.
This does not happen until 1832.
This is 1832.
I'll do it right over here.
1832.
And what catalyzed it,
there were several things that were catalyzing that
And actually,
most revolutions are catalyzed by just...
economic discontent. If people are rich and happy, and
have jobs and aren't getting sick,
most people won't be in the mood to revolt.
But in 1832, as you can imagine,
the economic situation was not good.
There was also a very nasty outbreak of cholera
and what really catalyzed the events in Les Mis
and they even referred to it in the movie
is the death of this chap right over here.
Jean Maximilien Lamarque
Let me write them down, write the name down
Jean Maximilien...And I'm sure I'm mispronouncing it.
Lamarque
And he dies in June of 1832.
And he was very sympathetic to the plight of the poor
to the plight of the common man.
and he... kind of the average folks
because it said, "Hey, look, he's our guy in government"
and he had kind of an influential role in government.
So when he died, they're like,
"look, we don't have anybody else
kind of in a high position who can speak for us.
Let's use his funeral as a catalyst for revolt."
And you saw that happening in the movie, Les Mis.
So Les Mis, in that climactic moment
that is the June rebellion of 1832.
And it's not, you don't have to
have amazing comprehension of watching movies
to realize that this was unsuccessful.
So this right here, didn't work. Didn't work.
If it did work,
it might have been called the Third French Revolution.
But it was not, it was an unsuccessful revolution,
or unsuccessful rebellion really.
And as Victor Hugo observed it, and that's why
he was able to recount it in so much detail.
The barricading, the young people,
the shooting in the streets, all the rest.
So just as a little bit of review.
When people talk about the French Revolution,
they're usually talking about the
French Revolution 1789, which establishes or
begins to establish the First Republic.
It was a successful revolution.
The second French Revolution,
this is the July Revolution,
this is in 1830, this puts into power Louis Phillipe the 1st,
the person that they're trying to overthrow in Les Mis
And they don't establish the Second Republic after this.
For the Second Republic, we have to go
all the way to the Revolution
we have to go all the way to the Revolution... of
Let me make sure I can scroll properly
Go all the way... let me continue my timeline.
So this is Louis Phillipe 1st
to go 18 years to 1848
where you have the Third French Revolution.
So Third French Revolution
which leads to the popular election of
Napoleon Bonaparte's nephew.
Louis Napoleon Bonaparte.
This guy right over here.
But France is still not done.
It still can't establish itself as a long and lasting republic.
In 1851 this character declares himself emperor.
So 1851, he too declares himself emperor.
And France is not finally free of kings and emperors
until 1870.
So let's do this run all the way to 1870.
Where France essentially loses the Franco-Prussian war
And this character right over here is deposed, and
you have the establishment of the Third French Republic.