(piano playing)
When things move, they tend to hit other things,
and then those things move too.
When I pluck this string, it's shoving back and forth
against the air molecules around it, and they push against other air molecules
although, they are not literally hitting so much as
getting too close for comfort,
until they get to be air molecules in our ear, which
push against some stuff in our ear, and that sends signals
to our brain to say, "Hey! I am getting pushed around here."
"Let's experience this as sound!"
This string is pretty special because it likes to vibrate in
a certain way and at a certain speed.
When you're pushing your little sister on a swing,
you have to get your timing right.
It take her a certain amount of time to complete a swing
and it's the same every time, basically.
If you time your pushes to be the same length of time,
then even gentle pushes make her swing higher and higher
That's amplification.
If you try to push more frequently, you'll just end up
pushing her when she's swinging backwards
instead of going higher, you'll dampen the vibration.
It's the same thing with this string.
It wants to swing at a certain speed, frequency.
If I were to sing that same pitch, the sound waves I'm singing
will push against the string at the right speed to amplify
the vibrations so that that string vibrates, while the other strings don't.
It's called a sympathy vibration.
Here's how our ears work. Firstly we've got this eardrum
that gets pushed around by the sound waves.
And then that pushed against some ear bones that push against
the cochlea, which has fluid in it
and now it's sending waves of fluid instead of waves of air
but what follows is the same concept as the swing thing
The fluid goes down this long tunnel, which has a membrane
called the basilar membrane.
Now, when we have a viola string, the tighter and stiffer
it is, the higher the pitch, which means a faster frequency.
The basilar membrane is stiffer at the beginning of the tunnel
and gradually gets looser so that it vibrates at high
frequencies at the beginning of the cochlea and goes through
the whole spectrum down to low notes at the other end
So when this fluid starts getting pushed around at a
certain frequency, such as middle C, there's a certain
part of the ear that vibrates in sympathy.
The part that's vibrating a lot is gonna push against
another kind of fluid in the other half of the cochlea
and this fluid has hairs in it which get pushed around by the fluid
and they're like, "Hey! I'm middle C and I'm getting pushed
around quite a bit!"
Also, in humans at least, it's not a straight tube,
the cochlea is awesomely spiraled up.
Ok, that's cool, but here's some questions.
You can make the note C on any instrument, and
the ear will be like, "Hey, a C!"
But that C sounds very different depending on whether
I sing it or play it on viola. Why?
And then there's some technicalities in the mathmatics
of swing pushing. It's not exactly true that pushing
with the same frequency as the swing is swinging
is the only way to get the swing to swing.
You could push on just every other swing,
and though the swing wouldn't go quite as high as
if you pushed every time, it would still swing pretty well
In fact, instead of pushing every time or half the time,
you could push once every three swings, or four, and so on
There's a whole series of timings that work, but the
height of the swing, the amplitude, gets smaller.
So in the cochlea, when one frequency goes in, shouldn't
it be that part of it vibrates a lot, but there's another part
that likes to vibrate twice as fast, and the waves push
it every other time and make it vibrate too,
and there's another that likes to vibrate three times
as fast, and four times, and this whole series is
all sending signals to the brain that we somehow
percieve it as a single note?
Would that make sense?
Let's also say we played the frequency that's twice
as fast as this one at the same time
It would vibrate places that the first note already vibrated,
though maybe more strongly.
This overlap, you'd think, would make our brains percieve
these two different frequencies as being almost the same
even though they are very far away
Keep that in mind while we go back to Pythagoras.
You probably know him from the whole Pythagorean theorem thing
but he's also famous for doing this:
He took a string that played some note,
let's call it C. Then, since Pythagoras liked simple proportions,
he wanted to see what note the string would play at
half the length.
So he played half the length and found that the note was
and octave higher. He thought that was pretty neat
So then he tried the next simplest ratio and
played a third of the string.
If the full length was C, then a third the length
would give the note G, an octave and a fifth above.
The next ratio to try was one-fourth of the string
But we can already figure out what note that would be.
If half the string was C an octave up
then half of that would be C another octave up.
and half of that would be another octave higher and so on and so forth.
And then one fifth of the string made the note E
but wait, let's play that again...
it's a C major chord
Ok, so what about one-sixth?
We can figure that one out too using ratios
we already know.
One-sixth is the same as half of one-third
And one third was this G, so one-sixth
is the G an octave up.
Check it out! One-seventh will be a new note
because 7 is prime and Pythagoras found that it was
this B-flat.
Then 8 is two x two x two
so an eighth gives us C three octaves up
And a 9 is a third of a third
So we'd go an octave and a fifth above
this octave and a fifth
and the notes get closer and closer
until we have all the notes on the chromatic scale
and they go into semi-tones, etc.
But let's make one thing clear.
This is not some magical relationship between
mathematical ratios and consonant intervals.
It's that these notes sound good to our ears
because our ears hear them together in every
vibration that reaches the cochlea.
Every single note has the major chord secretly contained
within it.
So that's why certain intervals sound consonant
and other dissonant, and why tonality is like it is
and why cultures that develop music independently
of each other still created similar scales, chords, and tonality
This is called the overtone series, by the way
and because of physics, but I don't really know why
A string half the length vibrates twice as fast,
which, hey! makes this series the same as that series
If this were A 440, meaning that this is a swing that likes to swing
440 times a second, here's A an octave up,
twice the frequency, 880
and here's E at three times the original frequency, 1320
The thing about this series, what with making the string vibrate
with different lengths at different frequencies
is that the string is actually vibrating in all of these
different waves even when you don't hold it down
and producing all of these frequencies
You don't notice the higher ones usually because
the lowest pitch is loudest and subsumes them
but say I were to put my finger in the middle of the string
so that it can't vibrate there, but didn't actually hold the string down there
then this string would be free to vibrate in any way
that doesn't move at that point,
while these other frequencies couldn't vibrate
and if I were to touch it at the one-third point
you'd expect all the overtones not divisible by three
to get dampened, so we'd hear this and all its overtones
The cool part is that the string is pushing around
the air at all these different frequencies
and so the air is pushing our ear at all these different frequencies
and then the basilar membrane is vibrating in
sympathy at all these different frequencies
and your ear puts it together and understands
it as one sound. It says "Hey, we've got some big
vibrations here and pretty strong ones here
and here and there and there
and that pattern is what a viola makes.
It's the difference in the loudness of the overtones
that gives the same note a different timbre
A simple sine wave with a single frequency with
no overtones makes an "oooo" sound, like a flute
while reedy, nasal-sounding instruments have more power
in the higher overtones
When we make different vowel sounds,
we're using our mouth to shape the overtones
coming from our vocal chords
dampening some, while amplifying others
To demonstrate, I recorded myself saying
"oooaaaeee" (singing different vowel sounds on the same pitch)
at 440 Hz
Now I'm going to put it through a low pass filter,
which lets through the frequencies less than A 441
but dampens all the overtones.
Check it out!
(sounds of vowel sounds again, but without higher overtones)
Ok, lets make ourselves an overtone series.
I'm going to have Audacity make a sine wave,
A 220.
Now I'll make another at twice the frequency, 440,
which is A an octave above
Here it is alone.
If we play the two at once, do you think we'll hear
the two separate pitches, or do you think our brain
will say, "hey, two pure frequencies an octave apart?"
"The higher one must be an overtone of the lower one"
"so we're really hearing one note!"
Here it is.
Let's add the next overtone.
3 time 220 gives us 660.
Here they are all at once.
It sounds like a different instrument from the
fundamental sine wave, but the same pitch.
Let's add 880.
And now, 1000.
Oh, that sounds wrong. Alright, 880 plus 220 is 1100
That's better.
We can keep going and now we have all these happy overtones
Zooming in to see the individual sine waves,
I can highlight one little bump here and see
how the first overtone perfectly fits two little bumps
and the next has three, then four and so on.
By the way, knowing that the speed of sound is about
340 meters per second
and seeing that this wave takes about 0.0009 seconds to play
I can multiply those out to find that the distance
between here and here is about 0.3 meters, or one foot
So now all these waves are shown at actual length
So C#, 1100, is about a foot long,
and each octave down is about half the frequency,
or twice the length
That means that the lowest C on a piano,
which is five octaves lower than this C
has a sound wave one foot times 2^5,
or thirty-two feet long!
Ok, now I can play with the timbre of the sound
by playing with how loud the overtones are relative to each other
What your ears are doing right now is pretty complicated
All these sound waves get added up together into a single wave
and if I export this file, we can see what it looks like.
or I suppose you could graph it
Anyway, your speakers or headphones have this little diaphram
in them that pushes the air to make sound waves
To make this shape, it pushed forward fast here,
then does this little wiggly thing
then another big push forward.
A speaker, remember, is not pushing air from itself to your ear
It bumps against the air, which bumps against more air
and so on, until some air bumps into your eardrum,
which moves in the same way as the diaphragm in the speaker did
and that pushed the little bones
that push the cochlea, which pushes the fluid
which, depending on the stiffness of the basilar membrane
at each point, is either going to push the basilar membrane
in such a way that makes it vibrate a lot,
and push the little hairs,
or it pushes with the wrong timing,
just like someone bad at playgrounds.
This sound wave will push in a way that makes
the A 220 part of your ear send off a signal
which is pretty easy to see.
Some frequencies get pushed the wrong direction sometime
but the pushes in the right direction more than make up for it
So now all these different frequencies that we added together
and played are now separated out again.
In the meantime, many other signals are being sent out
from other noise, like the sound of my voice,
and the sound of rain, and traffic,
and noisy neighbors, and the air conditioner and so on
But then our brain is like, "Yo! Look at these-I found a pattern!"
"All these frequencies fit together into a series starting
at this pitch, so I will think of them as one thing"
"And it is a different thing when these frequencies,
which fit the pattern of Vi's voice, and oh boy!
that's a car horn!"
Somehow this all works, and we're still pretty far
from developing technology that can listen to lots of sound
and separate it out into things nearly as well
as our ears and brain can.
Our brains are so good at finding these patterns
that sometimes it find them when they're not there.
Especially if it's subconsciously looking out for it
and you're in a noisy situation
In fact, if the pattern is mostly there,
your brain will fill in the blanks and make you
hear a tone that does not exist.
Here I've got A 220 and its overtones
Now I'm going to mute A 220.
That frequency is not playing at all.
But you hear the pitches A 220 below this A 440
even though A 440 is the lowest frequency playing.
Your brain is like, "Well, we've got all these overtones, so close enough"
Let me mute the highest overtones one by one
It changes the timbre but not the pitch
until we leave only one left
Somehow removing the higher note, you make the
apparent pitch jump up.
And, just for good measure....
but you should try it yourself
So there you have it.
These notes, these notes given to us by simple ratios
of strings by the laws of physics
and how frequencies vibrate in sympathy to each other
by the mathematics of how sine waves add up
these notes are hidden in every spoken word
tucked away in every song
you can hear them in birdsong, bees buzzing,
car horns, crickets, cries of infants...
and most of the time you don't even realize they're there.
There is a symphony contained in the screeching of a halting train,
if only we are open to listen to it
Your ears, perfected over hundreds of millions of years,
capture these frequencies in such exquisite detail
that it's a wonder that we can make sense of it all.
But we do, breaking out the patterns that mathematics dictate
finding order, finding beauty