Find the volume of a sphere with a diameter of 14 centimeters. So if I have a sphere, so this isn't
just a circle. This is a sphere. You can view it as a globe of some kind.
So i'm gonna shad it a little bit so you can tell it's three-dimensional. They're giving us the diameter
so if we go from on side of the sphere straight through the center of it, so we're imagining we can see
through the sphere. And we go straight through the centimeter that distance right over there is 14 centimeters.
Now, to find the volume of a sphere, we prove this or you will see a proof for this later when you learn
calculus, but the formula for the volume of a sphere is volume is equal to 4 thirds pi*r^3.
Where r is the radius of the sphere. So they 've given us the diameter and just like for circles,
the radius of the sphere, the radius of the sphere is half the diameter.
So in this example, our radius is going to be 7 centimeters. In fact, the sphere itself
is the set of all points in three dimensions that is exactly the radius away from the center.
With that out of the way, let's just apply this radius being 7 centimeters to this formular right over
here. So we're going to have a volume is equal to 4 thirds pi*7. cm^3.
And, since it already involves pi, and you can approximate pi with 3.14,
some people even approximate it with 22/7, but we'll actually just get the calculator out
to get the exact value for this volume. So this is going to be...
My volume is going to be 4/3...And then I don't want to just put a pi there because that might interprit it as 4 divided by 3 pi.
So four divided by three times pi times seven to the third power.
In order of operations it will do the exponent first so this should work out.
An the units are going to be in centimeters cubed or cubic centimeters.
So we get 1436, they don't tell us what to round it to so I'll just round it to the nearest tenth.
1436.8 So this is equal to 1436.8 centimeters cubed.
And we're done!