1913 was a banner year for Léger.
It was the year in which he figured out
how to become a Léger,
instead of a follower of Picasso or Braque.
He did a large series of paintings
entitled "Contrast of Form."
Each of these examined the ways in which
these basic primary and secondary colors
could be put together with black and white
in order to make a canvas that, like music,
could be appreciated without having to "read it"
as a certain kind of scene or narrative.
"Contrast of Forms," what does that tell you?
Not a whole lot.
So what he's not telling you, very deliberately,
is that this painting would have been figures.
And you see these kind of mechanical shapes --
almost like manikins or tin men --
that form these vertical stacks --
very much like bodies.
Like any painter at that time,
Léger would have had
training from life to do anatomy.
Now he's trying to put that behind him --
trying to turn what might be a rather calm image
into one that almost seems like a snapshot caught
at an accident moment in mid-motion.
He wants you to look at this painting as a painting.
He leaves so much of that burlap canvas
blank and raw.
Those pigments on it, they feel kind of crusty
and almost like they're put there --
not by a painter with a fine brush --
but somebody applying things
in a much more rugged way --
in a much more hands-on way.
The white is applied almost like chalk --
it's so rough -- to make this picture pop.
An offsetting "contrast" as Léger knew,
to these reds and blues, yellows and greens,
that would have been unthinkable
in painting a mere ten years before this.
I bet you when this painting was put on view in 1913,
most of the viewers would have thought,
"When is the painter going to come along
and turn this sketch into something that's actually
a final product?"