We're on problem 15.
It asks us, if triangle ABC
and triangle XYZ are two
triangles such that-- OK, let
me draw these two triangle.
Triangle ABC, maybe it looks
something like that, and then
we have triangle XYZ,
and we want to prove
that they are similar.
Similar means that they
look the same.
They have a similar shape, but
could be of different sizes.
So essentially all of their
angles are the same or all the
ratios of their sides
of the same.
So XYZ might just be
a smaller version.
Maybe I should have drawn
a bigger one.
It looks like they want
us to prove the
triangles are similar.
They tell us that the ratio of
AB to XY-- let me color that.
They say the ratio of AB
to XY is equal to the
ratio of BC to YZ.
Which of the following would
be sufficient to prove the
triangles are similar?
So there's a couple of times
when you know that a triangle
is similar, is if the ratio of
all the sides are equal.
Think about it, just giving
two sides isn't enough,
because even though I drew them
so that they're similar,
it could look something
like this.
Maybe the ratio here is 2:1.
So maybe AB and XY, maybe
that's a 2:1.
Maybe that's 2 and that's
1 like that.
The ratio is 2:1.
And maybe BC to YZ
is also 2:1.
But there's nothing that tells
us that that can't
open up like this.
It could be like a
2 and a 1 ratio.
Or actually even better, I
don't want to draw them
similar anymore.
I want to draw them
some unsimilar.
Maybe BC comes in like that
maybe YZ goes out like that.
And so just knowing that the
ratio of two of the sides are
the same, that alone doesn't
tell you that you're dealing
with a similar triangle.
These two triangles would
be very different.
These are definitely not
similar triangles.
In fact, all of the angles
would be different.
Now, how do you prove that
something is similar?
Well, actually I attempted this
problem about two minutes
ago and it stumped me, because
I think, if I'm right, that
there's a mistake
in the problem.
In geometry class, they always
teach you that if you know
that the ratio of two of the
sides are equal and that the
angle between them are equal,
then that's sufficient to say
that it's a similar triangle.
Or that you can make the
conclusion of the ratio of AC
to XZ would also be equal.
So that's the answer they're
probably looking for.
That if you have the ratio of
AB to XY, you have the ratio
of BC to YZ, then you want the
angle in between them to say,
OK, these are similar
triangles.
So you'd have to know
that angle B is
congruent to angle Y.
And that's choice B.
I don't argue with the fact that
angle B being congruent
to angle Y is sufficient
to prove that these
triangles are similar.
I just think that some of
these other things are
actually sufficient to prove
the triangles are similar.
They don't teach you the tools
in geometry, but you can even
think about it intuitively.
Once you learn the law of
cosines in trigonometry, which
you're not that far away from
right now, you'll see that any
of the other angles, if you know
the corresponding angles
are congruent, you would be all
set to know that these are
going to be similar triangles.
For example, if you know that
angle C is congruent to angle
Z, and you could even
think about it.
Let's say if you knew that angle
C was congruent to angle
Z, there's no other way to draw
this triangle versus just
having a similar triangle.
So, for example, in this one
right here, this would be
angle C and this would be angle
Z, and clearly, these
two aren't congruent.
If you think about it, when
you say that this angle is
congruent to this angle, you're
constraining the shape
of this line right here.
You're constraining the
direction that it goes in.
If you forced this angle to be
the same as this, let's say
that you said this angle is
equal to that angle, then you
would have to go out in this
direction out there, and then
you would break what you
originally said, that the
ratio of that to
that is equal.
So just think about it in terms
of when you add another
angle, it actually does
constrain the triangle to
being similar.
And the same thing is true,
angle A and angle X.
If you know that angle A is
congruent to angle X, that
also constrains the triangle
to being similar.
The only one that I know
definitely isn't sufficient is
angle X being congruent
to angle Y.
That's useless.
Let's see, angle X congruent
to angle Y.
Yeah, that doesn't help you.
That tells you that this one
is an isosceles triangle
because these two base angles
would be the same, so that
would be the same as that, but
it doesn't tell you anything
about how does this
relate to that.
So even though the answer
they're looking for is
probably B, I would say that A
and C are also sufficient.
Next question.
Question 16.
And send me a note if you think
I'm missing something,
because I thought about
it a little bit.
All right, 16.
In parallelogram FGHI-- let me
draw parallelogram FGHI.
We have one side.
We come down at a
45-degree angle.
We have the other side.
Let's say we go up at
a 45-degree angle.
I can do it from here.
Close enough.
Got my parallelogram.
Parallelogram FGHI.
So that F, that's a G, that's
an H, and that's an I.
Diagonals IG and FH are drawn
and intersect at point M.
So let me draw IG and FH.
OK, these are lines.
Fair enough.
And they intersect at point M.
Which of the following
statements must be true?
OK.
Triangle FGI must be
an obtuse triangle.
And that means that one of the
angles in the triangle is more
than 90 degrees.
I mean, just the way I drew it
here, which is a completely
legitimate way to draw it, all
of these lines are parallel.
We see that that doesn't have
to be the case, because just
the way I drew it, all
these angles are
less than 90 degrees.
So that's definitely
not the case.
Triangle HIG, must be
an acute triangle.
Let's think about
it a little bit.
Let's try to prove it
by contradiction.
Let's say that one
of the sides was
more than 90 degrees.
So this is just the
way I happened to
draw it right here.
But if you think about it, I
could have drawn it like this.
So the way I drew it, HIG
is in an acute triangle.
All of these sides are
less than 90 degrees.
But I could have drawn this
the complete opposite way.
Let me draw it that
way actually.
I'll do it quick and dirty.
So what if I drew
it like this?
What if I drew our parallelogram
like this?
The direction that I drew
it was arbitrary.
So now this is F, G, H and I,
and they're talking about
triangle HIG.
Well, clearly, in this case,
angle H right here, this is an
obtuse angle.
That is greater than
90 degrees.
So HIG would be an
obtuse triangle.
So there's nothing that prevents
us from drawing the
parallelogram like this,
which would make
this an obtuse triangle.
So that triangle does not have
to be an acute triangle, so B
doesn't work.
All right, what else
do they say?
Triangle FMG must be congruent
to triangle HMG.
Well that's congruent.
So that would mean that all
the sides are equal and
everything, and that's
clearly not true.
They share this side right here,
but this side up here
could be a lot longer than that
side, which would make
this side here a lot longer
than that side, so that's
definitely not true.
So, D is probably the answer,
but let's see if
we can prove it.
Triangle GMH must be
congruent to IMF.
So let me do that in two
different colors.
So GMH, that's that one right
there, must be congruent to
IMF, that's that one
right there.
Let's see.
First of all, we know that this
angle and that angle are
going to be congruent.
They are opposite angles or, as
they say, vertical angles.
The reason I don't like using
vertical angles is because
this angle and this angle are
also opposite angles, and to
call them vertical angles is
bizarre because they're not
vertical with each other.
Anyway, that's just my problem
with the notation.
OK, so where were we?
We wanted to prove that
that triangle and that
triangle are congruent.
This angle is definitely equal
to that angle, and know that
this line is parallel
to this line, right?
So we can view each of these
crossing lines as transversals
will between two
parallel lines.
That's a parallel line, that's
a parallel line, so this is a
transversal between two
parallel lines.
Then this angle is going to be
congruent to that angle, and
that's because I think the word
is opposite internal, or
alternate interior angles,
or something like that.
And it makes sense.
You could imagine drawing the
transversal either way and
then the angles would change,
but they are always going to
be congruent.
And by the same argument, this
angle is going to be congruent
to that angle.
So we know that all of the
angles are the same, and now
we have to make some type of
argument that all of the sides
are the same.
Really, if we could just prove
that one of the sides are the
same, then we know that all
of the sides are the same.
Well, we know that it's
a parallelogram.
So in order for all of the
sides to be parallel, the
opposite sides have to
be the same length.
I'll leave you to think
about why that is.
But if all the opposite sides
are the same length, we know
that this side is equivalent
to this side.
So, you know, we could use one
of those geometry postulates
that they-- angle, side,
angle, right?
We haven an angle, a side and an
angle, and an angle, a side
and an angle, and say, OK,
that's enough for us to show
that these are congruent
triangles.
So the answer is D.
Anyway, see you in
the next video.