We're in the British Museum and we are looking
at some of the most famous sculptures
from all of the history,
in fact, perhaps the most famous sculptures.
This is the Pediment 's sculptures
from the East end of the Parthenon
on the Acropolis in Athens.
Created in the 5th century B.C. ,
which was the Classical period of Ancient Greece
The period when Athens is a Democracy
the "Golden Age".
And the Parthenon was its most important monument.
It was a treasury, in fact,
for the new Confederations, in Greece itself,
and so it was a symbol
of wealth, of power, of wisdom.
And, dedicated to the goddess Athena
who was the goddess of this city-state of Athens.
And the goddess of wisdom, and also war
- a warrior goddess -
The sculptures that we are looking at
from the East pediment
and, pediment is that triangular shape
on either end of an ancient greek temple.
Yeah, really a gable
The figures had to be arranged -
it must had been a difficult composition
to fill an elongated triangle.
In fact the figures rise
and you can still see the triangle.
The fact is, though, that
the middle figures are completely missing.
Let's give a quick overview of the narrative
Athena would be born
from the head of her father, Zeus, in the middle.
Then we have series of gods
and goddesses reacting to that.
The 3 figures that survived, on the right side
of the East Pediment
we think it might be Hestia
who would be closest to the middle,
Aphrodite who is reclining on the lap of her mother.
And then to the right of Aphrodite,
we think that that would have been
the goddess of the Moon
leading a chariot to the Moon's setting
On the left side of the pediment
we have the opposite of that.
We have the Sun actually rising
and the god of the Sun actually bringing the Sun
on his chariot into the new day
representing, of course, the birth of Athena.
The thing that is most remarkable to me
is how life like, these are
and how filled with movement
Even though we don't have any heads
except for the one male reclining nude
- which is a severely damaged -
and is thought to probably be Dionysus.
Even without the head, even without the hands
which are often the most expressive part of the body
And despite the fact the bodies themselves
are largely clothed,
the bodies are still incredibly expressive,
in terms of their energy,
in terms of their responsiveness
and in terms of their relationship to each other.
There is a kind of integration of the figures,
that's very complicated compositionally.
So the figure to the left of center
moves away but turns back,
and is interrelated to the figure next to her
who is seated, who is also reacting to her
and to the event in the center.
But then it is kind if more stabilized
by that frontal seated figure
just to the left.
And then the reclining nude
who looks over to left.
So there is a real integration of the whole here,
that's very complex.
The thing that I find so interesting is
this psychological understanding
as well as this anatomical understanding
and simultaneously this respect for,
and love of the beauty of the body.
Now the women are clothed, but
the way that the artist is handling the drapery
in some ways actually defines
the turn of the muscles of the body.
In a sense of revealing more about the body
than the body would itself if it was nude
It is important to remember, I think,
something that we often forget
because we think about sculptures as white
which is that all of this would have been painted
in very bright colors
which would have seemed very strange,
almost garish to us today.
And probably really important
because, of course these would've been much higher
and much further away from the viewer than they are now.
But that paint would have helped viewers far below
to see details in the sculptures.
But there is a kind of nobility
that is very much emblematic of
this high classical moment in Ancient Greece.
And if you look for instance at the figure
that we think is Dionysus.
I mean here is the god of wine, right?
who completely relaxed
and yet there is still this kind of nobility.
Yeah. There is still this kind of balance.
He's a god. Absolutely.
And we know it,
there is no doubt about it when we look at him.
He's divine. We're, we're on mount Olympus.
It's so easy to see why later cultures
later ages would look back to this kind of sculpture
and see this as kind of apex
as a kind of high point of human achievement.
You imagine an entire culture that is somehow
about perfection and transcendence, and beauty
and the heroic, and the noble.
It's like, the art so much embodies those values,
that one imagines them
in the ancient Athanians themselves.