So this diagram over here
I have this big triangle and I have all of these other little triangles inside this big triangle
What I want to do is see if I can figure out the measure of this angle right here
We will call them measure theta
They tell us a few other things
They use this symbol. You might have seen them before
They mean that these are right angles or they have a measure of 90 degrees
So that is a 90 degree angle, a 90 degree angle and that is a 90 degree angle over there
They also tell us this angle over here is 32 degress.
Let's see what we can do
We can solve this in different multiple ways. That's what's really fun about these
There are multiple ways to solve these problems
So this angle is theta, we have theta is adjacent to this angle
Is adjacent to this green angle and if you add them together you're going to get this right angle
So this pink angle theta plus this green angle must be equal to 90 degrees
When you combine them you get a right angle
So you could call this one, its measure is going to be 90 minus theta
And now we have three angles in the triangle and we just have to solve for theta
Cause we know this angle and this angle are going to be equal to 180 degrees
So you have 90 minus theta, plus 90 degrees, plus 32 degrees`
Let me do this in a different color. Plus 32 degrees is going to be equal to 180 degrees
The sum of the measures of the angle inside of a triangle add up to 180 degrees
That's all that we are doing over here
And so lets see is we can simplify this a little bit.
So if we subtract these two guys
90 plus 90 is going to be 180. So you get 180 minus theta plus 32 is equal to 180 degrees
And then we have, what else do we have?
We have 180 on both sides. We can subtract that fromboth sides, so that cancels out
That goes to zero
and it would be negative theta plus 32 degrees is equal to zero
You can add theta to both sides and you get 32 degrees is equal to theta
Or theta is equa to 32 degrees
So it's going to actually be the same measure as this angle right over here
That's one wat to do the problem. There are other ways we could have done the problem
We could have said, and actually there are a ton of ways that we could have done this
We could have looked at this big triangle over here and said
Look if this is 90 degrees over here, this is 32 degrees over here
This angle up here is going to be 180 minus 90 degrees minus 32 degrees
because they all have to add up to 180 degrees
And I just kind of skipped a step there, obviously this.. actually let me not skip a step
Let me call this "x". If we call the measure of that angle "x"
We have "x" plus 90. I'm looking at the biggest triangle in this diagram right here
"X" plus 90 plus 32 is going to be = to 180 degrees
And so is you subtract 90 and 32 from both sides
So if you subtract 90 from both sides you get "x" plus 32 is equal to 90
and then if you subtract 32 from both sides you get "x" is equal to 58 degrees
"X" is = to 58 degrees
Now what else can we figure out?
Now if this angle over here is a right angle
And I'm just re-doing the problem all over again to show you that there are multiple ways to get the
answer
We were given if that is 90 degrees then this angle over here is supplementary to it
and it also has to be 90 degrees. So then we have this angle plus 90 degrees plus this angle
have to equal 180. Maybe we could call that "y"
So "y" plus 58, plus 90 is equal to 180
You can subtract 90 from both sides, this will become 90
Subtract 58 from both sides and you will get "y" is = 32 degrees
Well if "y" is 32 degrees, it is complementary.
It adds up, it's complementary to this angle right over here
Let me do that in a new color
It adds up to 90 degrees
It is complementary to this angle right over here
We can call it "z"
So these two combined are going to add up to 90 degrees.
Or "z" is going to be equal to 58 degrees
And now we are inside the triangle we care about to figure out theta
Theta that we have already figured out earlier in this video
Well this here is 58 degrees
If this angle here is 90 then this angle over here is also going to be 90 because they are supplementary
So you ahve 58 degrees (I wanted to do that in that orange color)
So if you have 58 degrees plus this 90 plus theta
this is going to be equal to 180 degreees
You can subtract 90 from both sides
that becomes 90
Then you add 58 plus theta is = to 90
Subtract 58 from both sides and you get theta is equal to 32 degrees again
I just wanted to do that to show you that there are multiple ways to do this problem
and as long as you are doing things that are logically consistent
and making assumptions that you can make
and then logically deducing step by step
there are multiple ways to get that right answer