we cannot factor out a 4 since 15 is not divisible by 4.
we must factor by grouping. look for 2 numbers whose product equals the product of 4 and -15
their sum needs to be equal to positive 4
the first clue is the product of the numbers is negative, so a and b must have different signs
but a + b is equal to 4
so, the difference of their absolute values must equal 4
let's think about all of the factors of -60
6 band 10 look tantalizing since they are 4 apart
we want them to add to positive 4, so larger number must be positive
so, we want positive 10 and negative 6
now, group first 2 terms
now, group the second 2 terms. both are divisible by 5
factor out a 2y
now, factor out a 5