When we observe the physical world,
we find random fluctuations everywhere.
We can generate truly random numbers
by measuring random fluctuations known as noise.
When we measure this noise, known as sampling,
we can obtain numbers.
For example,
if we measure the electric current of TV static over time,
we'll generate a truly random sequence.
We can visualize this random sequence
by drawing a path that changes direction
according to each number,
known as a random walk.
Notice the lack of pattern at all scales,
at each point in the sequence,
the next move is always unpredictable.
Random processes are said to be nondeterministic,
since they're impossible to determine in advance.
Machines, on the other hand, are deterministic.
Their operation is predictable and repeatable.
In 1946, John von Neumann was involved
in running computations for the military,
specifically involved in the design of the hydrogen bomb.
Using a computer called the ENIAC,
he planned to repeatedly calculate
the approximations of the processes involved in nuclear fusion.
However, this required quick access
to randomly generated numbers
that could be repeated, if needed.
However, the ENIAC had very limited internal memory,
storing long random sequences was not possible.
So, Neumann developed an algorithm
to mechanically simulate
the scrambling aspect of randomness as follows:
First, select a truly random number called the seed,
this number can come from the measurement of noise,
or the current time in milliseconds.
Next, the seed is provided as input to a simple calculation.
Multiply the seed by itself,
and then output the middle of this result.
Then, you use the output as the next seed,
and repeat the process as many times as needed.
This is known as the middle-square's method,
and it's just the first in the long line of
pseudorandom number generators.
The randomness of the sequence is dependent
on the randomness of the initial seed only.
Same seed, same sequence.
So what're the differences between a randomly generated
versus the pseudorandomly generated sequence.
Let's represent each sequence as random walk.
They seem similar, until we speed things up.
The pseudorandom sequence must eventually repeat.
This occurs when the algorithm reaches a seed
it has previously used,
and the cycle repeats.
The length before pseudorandom sequence repeats
is called the period.
The period is strictly limited by the length of the initial seed.
For example, if we use a 2-digit seed,
then an algorithm can produce at most 100 numbers
before reusing a seed, and repeating the cycle.
A 3-digit seed can expand pass a thousand numbers
before repeating its cycle.
And a 4-digit seed can expand pass 10,000 numbers
before repeating.
Though, if we use a seed large enough,
the sequence can expand into trillions and trillions of digits
before repeating.
Though the key difference is important,
when you generate numbers pseudorandomly,
there're many sequences which cannot occur.
For example,
if Alice generates a truly random sequence of 20 shifts,
it's equivalent to a uniform selection
from the stack of all possible sequences of shifts.
This stack contains 26 to the power of 20 pages,
which is astronomical in size.
If we stood at the bottom, and shined the light upwards,
a person at the top would not see the light
for around 200 million years.
Compare this to Alice generating a 20-digit pseudorandom sequence
using a 4-digit random seed.
Now this is equivalent to a uniform selection
from 10,000 possible initial seeds,
meaning she can only generate 10,000 different sequences,
which is a vanishingly small fraction of all possible sequences.
When we move from random to pseudorandom shifts,
we shrink the key space into a much, much smaller seed space.
So for a pseudorandom sequence to be
indistinguishable from a randomly generated sequence,
it must be impractical for a computer
to try all seeds and look for a match.
This leads to an important distinction in computer science
between what's possible versus
what's possible in a reasonable amount of time.
We use the same logic when we buy a bike lock.
We know that anybody can simply try all possible combinations
until they find a match and it opens.
But it would take them days to do so.
So for 8 hours, we assume it's practically safe.
With pseudorandom generators,
the security increases as the length of the seed increases.
If the most powerful computer
would take hundreds of years to run through all seeds,
then we safely can assume it's practically secure,
instead of perfectly secure.
As computers get faster,
the seed size must increase accordingly.
Pseudorandomness frees Alice and Bob from having to
share their entire random shift sequences in advance.
Instead, they shared relatively short random seed,
and expand it into the same random-looking sequence
when needed.
But, what happens
if they can never meet to share this random seed？