Never hurts to get a
bit more practice.
So this is problem number 5
from the Normal Distribution
chapter from ck12.org's
AP Statistics FlexBook.
So they're saying the 2007 AP
Statistics examination scores
were not normally distributed
with a mean of 2.8 and a
standard deviation of 1.34.
They cite some College
Board stuff here.
I didn't copy and paste that.
What is the
approximate z-score?
Remember, z-score is just how
many standard deviations
you are away from the mean.
What is the approximate
z-score that corresponds
to an exam score of 5?
So we really just have to
figure out-- this is a pretty
straightforward problem-- we
just have to figure out how
many standard deviations
is 5 from the mean?
Well, you just take
5 minus 2.8, right?
The mean is 2.8.
Let me be very clear.
Mean is 2.8.
They give us that.
We didn't even have to
calculate it, right?
So the mean is 2.8, so 5
minus 2.8 is equal to 2.2.
So we're 2.2 above the mean,
and if we want that in terms
of standard deviations,
we just divide by our
standard deviation.
Divide by 1.34.
I'll take out the
calculator for this.
So we have 2.2 divided by
1.34 is equal to 1.64.
This is equal to 1.64,
and that's choice c.
So this was actually
very straightforward.
We just had to see how far away
we are from the mean if we get
a score of 5, which hopefully
you will get if you're taking
the AP Statistics exam after
watching these videos, and then
you divide by the standard
deviation to say how many
standard deviations away from
the mean is the score of 5.
It's 1.64.
I think the only tricky thing
here might have been-- you
might have been tempted to pick
choice e, which says the
z-score cannot be calculated
because the distribution
is not normal.
I think the reason why you
might have had that temptation
is because we've been using
z-scores within the context
of a normal distribution.
But a z-score literally just
means how many standard
deviations you are
away from the mean.
It could apply to any
distribution that you can
calculate a mean and a
standard deviation for.
So e is not the correct answer.
A z-score can apply to a
non-normal distribution, so the
answer is c, and I guess that's
a good point of clarification
to get out of the way.
I thought I would do two
problems in this video, just
because that was pretty short.
So problem number 6: The
heights of fifth grade boys in
the United States is
approximately normally
distributed-- that's good to
know-- with a mean height of
143.5, so it's a mean of 143.5
centimeters, and a standard
deviation of about
7.1 centimeters.
Standard deviation
of 7.1 centimeters.
What is the probability that
our randomly chosen fifth
grade boys would be taller
than 157.7 centimeters?
So let's just draw out this
distribution like we've done in
a bunch of problems so far.
They're just asking us one
question, so you can mark this
distribution up a good bit.
Let's say that's our
distribution-- and the
mean here, the mean
they told us is 143.5.
They're asking us taller
than 157.7, so we go in
the upwards directions.
So one standard deviation above
the mean will take us right
there, and we just have to add
7.1 to this number right here.
We're going up by 7.1.
So 143.5 plus 7.1 is what?
150.6.
That's one standard deviation.
If we were to go another
standard deviation,
we go 7.1 more.
What's 7.1 plus 150.6?
It's 157.7, which just
happens to be the exact
number they ask for.
They're asking for heights,
the probability of getting
a height higher than that.
So they want to know what's the
probability that we fall under
this area right here, or
essentially more than two
standard deviations from
the mean, or above two
standard deviations.
We can't count this
left tail right there.
So we can use the
empirical rule.
We can use the empirical rule.
If we do our standard
deviations, to the left that's
one standard deviation,
two standard deviations.
We know what this
whole area is.
Let me pick a different color.
So we know what this area
is, the area within two
standard deviations.
The empirical rule tells us.
Or even better, the 68-95-99.7
rule tells us that this area,
because it's within two
standard deviations, is 95%, or
0.95, or it's 95% of the area
under the normal distribution,
which tells us that what's left
over, this tail that we care
about and this left tail
right here, has to make
up the rest of it, or 5%.
So those two combined have to
be 5%, and these symmetrical.
We've done this before.
This is actually a little
redundant from other
problems we've done.
But if these are combined 5%,
then they're saying that each
of these are 2 and
a half percent.
Each of these are 2
and a half percent.
So to answer their question,
what is the probability that a
randomly chosen fifth grade boy
would be taller than 157.7
centimeters, well, that's
literally just the area under
this right green part.
Maybe I'll do it in
a different color.
This magenta part that I'm
coloring right now, that's
just that area, we just
figured out it's 2.5%.
So there's a 2 and a half
percent chance we randomly find
a fifth grade boy who's taller
than 157.7 centimeters,
assuming this is the mean, the
standard deviation, and we are
dealing with a normal
distribution.