Now that have a basic understanding of what a ratio
is, let's see if we can tackle some more advanced problems.
So, I have a classroom.
It's got fifty-five students in it.
fifty-five students.
And I also know that the ratio of boys to girls, the ratio of
I'll write it this way, boys to girls is four:seven.
What I want to know is, how many girls do I need to add.
So, how many girls need to add, or do I need to add, do I need
to add, for the ratio, for the ratio to become one:two.
one:two.
And this is the ratio of boys to girls.
I'm not switching the ratio on you.
So, right now for every four boys, I have seven girls.
I want to add some girls so that the ratio becomes for
every boy, I have two girls.
So how can you do this?
Well, just going back to the basic ratio video, the first
thing we can do we, know the total number of students.
And we know the ratio.
So maybe it'll help us to figure out the number of boys
and girls we have right now.
So our current ratio is four:seven.
So boys, boys, to girls, right now is equal to four:seven.
That means -- what does that mean?
That means for every, if you add up these two.
For every eleven students there are four boys and seven girls.
There are four boys, four boys and seven girls.
That's what this ratio tells us.
You give me eleven students of this -- you could split
this classroom into a bunch of groups.
And for every group of eleven, you're going to have four boys
and seven girls that's all that tells me.
For every eleven students, four boys and seven girls.
If you split them, every group has the same number
of boys and girls.
Now, how many groups of eleven students there are?
So there are fifty-five students.
We have fifty-five students total.
And we're breaking them into groups of eleven.
And every group will have the same number
of boys and of girls.
So we have eleven groups.
Sorry, if we divide by eleven students per group.
Students per group.
So how many groups of eleven students do we have?
That means we have five groups of eleven students.
five groups of eleven students.
And we've done this drill before.
Every group has four boys and it has seven girls.
So we have five groups.
five groups each of them has four boys, that means we have five
times four, which is equal to twenty boys.
And we have five times seven, we have five groups, five times seven,
each group has seven girls.
Of girls.
So that's equal to thirty-five girls.
And the numbers add up.
twenty plus thirty-five is fifty-five.
And twenty to thirty-five, twenty to thirty-five, is equal to four:seven.
So it all works out.
So that's what we have right now.
Now, we're going to add to girls to the classroom
to change the ratio.
So let's do this.
So right now we have twenty boys.
We have twenty boys.
And we have thirty-five girls.
We just figure that out.
And I'm going to add some girls to the classroom.
So I'm going to add some girls to the classroom And my new
ratio, after I add these g girls to the classroom, my new
ratio is going to be one:two.
one:two.
So I have an equation I have one unknown, I
can just solve for it.
You can almost do this one in your head.
twenty is to what, one is to two as twenty as to what?
You could say, oh, twenty is -- one is one / two of twenty, twenty is one / two of forty.
So you could say, oh, it's forty.
So g would be equal to five.
That's how you would solve it in your head.
If you want to do it algebraically, you
could cross-multiply.
So you get thirty-five plus g times one.
So you get thirty-five plus g is equal to two times twenty.
Is equal to forty, which is essentially what
we did in our head.
We said, hey, this thing has to be equal to forty.
So, if you subtract thirty-five from both sides, you
get g is equal to five.
So if you add five girls to your classroom, you're going
to have forty girls.
So then you'd have forty girls.
And you have twenty boys.
And your ratio is twenty:forty, which is two:four, which is
the same thing is one:two.
And we've done our problem.