The goal of this video is to try to figure out
the antiderivative of ln(x), and is not completly
obvious how to aproach this at first, even if were to I told you
to use integration by parts, you would say:
'Wait, wait. Integration by parts you are looking for
the antiderivative of something that con be expressed
as a product of two functions, it looks like I only have one function'
but it might become a little bit more obvious
i I were to rewright this as the integral of ln(x)
times one dx, now you have the product of two functions
one is a function of x, it actually not dependent of x
it's always gonna be 1, but you could have f(x) = 1
And now it might become more obvious to use integration by parts
Integration by parts tells us that, if we have an integral
that can be veiwed as the product of one function
and the derivative of another function
this is really just the reverse product rule
we've shown that multiple time already, this is gonna
be equal to the product of both functions
f(x) times g(x) minus the antiderivative of
instead of having f and g' we are gonna have
f' and g, so f'(x) times g(x) dx
And we've seen this multiple times so when you
so when you figure it out what should be f and what should be g
for f you want to figure it out something that is easy
to take the derivative of and it simplifies the things, possibly
if you are taking the derivative of it, and for g'(x)
you want to find something where it's easy to take the antiderivative of it
so, a good candidate for f(x) is ln(x)
if you take the derivative of it is 1/x
so lets say that f(x) = ln(x), then f'(x) = 1/x
and lets set g'(x) = 1 that means g(x) could be equal to x
so lets go back right over here so this is going to be equal to
this is going to be equal to f(x) times g(x)
f(x) time g(x) is x ln(x), so g(x) is x and f(x) is ln(x)
I just like writing the x infront of the ln(x)
to avoid ambiguity so this is x ln(x) minus
the antiderivative of f'(x), which is 1/x times g(x) which is x
dx
well what's this gonna be equal to? all we have inside the integral
this is just 1/x time x which is just equal to 1
so this simplifies quite nicely, this is going to end up equaling
x ln(x) minus the antiderivtive of just dx
or the integral of 1 dx is just minus x
and this is just the an antiderivative of this, if we want to
write the entire class of antiderivaives we just have to add plus c here
And we are done! we figured out the antiderivative
of ln(x) and I encourage you to take the derivative of this
for this part you are gonna use the product rule