We're on problem 221
And let's see, they have--is all of that in the denominator?
Well, I guess it is
Let's see, they wrote 1 over--
and I'll write it the way they did it
1 over-- and they have this--
you know, I think it's got to be 1 plus
I think it's 1 plus
The way they wrote it is weird
1 plus 1 over 1 plus 1/3
This looks a lot like another problem that we did
But anyway, I'll do this one
So let's see
If we do 1 plus 1/3, that's 3/3, plus 1/3, so that's 4/3
So then that turns into 4/3, 1, 1 plus, 1 over that
and then you have 1 plus that
And so then this equals 1 plus 1 over 1 plus--
what's 1 over 4/3?
Well, that's the same thing as--
1 divided by 4/3 is the the same thing as 1 times 3/4
and that's equal to 3/4
And what's 1 plus 3/4?
Well, that's 4/4 plus 3/4, right?
4/4 plus-- so that's 7/4
So then that becomes 1 plus 1 over 7/4
which is equal to 1 plus 4/7
and that equals 7/7 plus 4/7 is equal to 11/7
And that's choice D
The way they wrote it was weird
They wrote it like this, 1 plus down here
But I assume that this is what they wanted
what I originally had done
Problem 222
In the rectangular coordinate system above--
well, let me draw it
That's the y-axis, that's the x-axis
y, x
And they have a point out here called point p
and they say that's at 4. x equals 4, y equals 0
In the rectangular coordinate system above
if point r, not shown, lies on the positive y-axis
so it lies someplace over here
and the area of triangle orp , so this is point o
and r is going to be some place on this, is 12
what is the coordinate of the point r?
So the coordinate of the point r, let's just call it--
well the x-value is going to be 0, right?
And this y-value, I don't know, let's call it x
No, let's call it y
That's a better variable name for the y-value
So they essentially want to know what the area of this
triangle right here is
Or actually, they want to know what y is
given that the area of that triangle, they tell us, is 12
The area of this triangle is 12
So what's the area of this triangle?
It's the base times the height times 1/2
The base is 4, right?
This is x is equal to 4
So it's 4 times the height
Well, the height is going to be y, right?
Because the coordinate of r is 0 comma y
So 4 times y times 1/2-- if you don't do the 1/2
you're getting the area of the whole rectangle--
is equal to the area of the triangle is equal to 12
So you get 2y is equal to 12
y is equal to 6
So the coordinate of r is 0 comma 6
And that is choice--
oh, they just ask what is the y-coordinate of point r
So that's 6, and that's choice B
Problem 223
Car A is 20 miles behind car B
So let me see if I can draw that
So this is A, this is B-- and it's 20 miles behind it
I don't know if that's relevant-- which is traveling
in the same direction along the same route as car A
Car A is traveling at a constant speed of 58 miles per hour
so car A is at 58 miles per hour, and car B is
traveling at a constant speed of 50 miles per hour
Fair enough
How many hours will it take for car A to overtake
and drive 8 miles ahead of car B?
So they don't want just car A to catch up
They want car A to catch up and go ahead 8 miles, right?
And drive 8 miles ahead
So another way to think about it is how long will it take
for car A to go 28 miles further than car B?
And the easiest way to think about it is just what their
differential is, right?
Car A is going 8 miles an hour faster than car B
So the relative velocity of A relative to B
is 8 miles an hour
And you could say that, well
I don't want to use fancy notation, but car A
if you're sitting in car B and you looked at car A
you'd say, oh, it's going in my same direction
but I'm stationary and it's going at 8 miles per hour
So the question essentially says if I'm going at 8 miles
per hour, how long does it take to go 28 miles, right?
Because I have to catch up to 20 miles with B
and then I have to go 8 more miles
You could just pretend like you are in car B and you think
that you are stationary
You ignore the fact that the world is speeding behind you
And you just see car A
You say, oh, car A must be moving at 8 miles an hour
in the direction in which my car is pointed
So, anyway, if you have to go 28 miles
and you're going at 8 miles per hour
distance divided by rate is equal to time
That's equal to 3 and 1/2 hours, which is choice E
Next question, 224
For the past n days
the average daily production at a company was 50 units
so for n days, 50 unit per day average
if today's production of 90 units, so we have 90 units
and that raises the average to 55 units per day
what was the value of n?
OK, so the old average would have been n times 50--
and this is kind of obvious --
divided by n is equal to 50, right?
Now, if I want to average in this 55
what happens is I get to n times 50, right?
That's the sum of the n days before
the sum of the total production for the n days before
And what I want to do is I want to have the production
for today, and that is 90, plus 90
and now I'm going to divide by n plus 1 days, right?
And now the average is 55
So we just have to solve this for n
So let's see what we can do
I'll do it in a different color
We get 50n plus 90 is equal to--
multiply both sides by n plus 1-- 55n plus 55
So let's subtract 50n from both sides
You get 90 is equal to 5n plus 55
Subtract 55 from both sides, 55 to 35 is equal to 5n
n is equal to 7
And that's choice E
Problem 225
OK, They write x plus 1 over x minus 1 squared
And they say if x does not equal 0 and x does not equal 1--
and that's good, because if x equaled 1
we'd be dividing by 0 here--
and if x is replaced by 1/x everywhere in the expression above
so x is replaced with 1/x everywhere in the expression above
then the resulting expression is equivalent to--
I don't know, let's just do it
So if we get 1/x-- we're just replacing x with 1/x-- plus 1
over 1/x minus 1 quantity squared
and that equals -- let's see
This is the same thing as 1/x plus x/x, right?
1 is the same thing as x/x
And this 1 is the same thing as x/x, right?
That's an x/x
So then this equals 1 plus x/x over 1 minus x/x
everything squared
And this inside of the brackets
that's the same thing as 1 plus x/x--
instead of being divided by this
we could multiply by the reciprocal-- times x over 1 minus x
I just reciprocated this and multiplied
And this is all still in the squared
Now these x's cancel out, and lo and behold, we get 1 plus x
over 1 minus x squared,which is the same thing as x plus 1--
well, let's think about it. x plus 1 over 1 minus x squared
And see, that's not one of the choices, right?
But let's think about it
1 minus x, that's the same thing as--just let me rewrite it
This is the same thing as x plus 1 divided by--
now this 1 minus x is the same thing as x minus 1
times negative 1, right?
And we're going to square all of this
Well, this over here, this is the same thing as x plus 1
over x minus 1 squared times 1 over negative 1 squared,right?
If you take the square of a product, you could--
this is the same thing as that times 1 over negative 1
So that turns into this, and this, obviously if I'm
squaring another number, this just becomes 1
So I'm left with x plus 1 over x minus 1 squared
And that's exactly what we started off with
and that's choice A
And that's the trick, to realize that
this is just a negative of x minus 1
And you can take a negative 1 out
but we're going to square it anyway
so it's going to turn it back positive
Next question
In choice E, actually, in that one
they tempt you by taking the negative outside
but you can't take the negative outside the square
You're squaring it, so the negative will disappear
Anyway, problem 200
Oh, I'm all out of time
See you in the next video