A lot of people, including myself,
have found the study of World War I
to be a little bit confusing sometimes.
And I think the reason is, the world was very different,
leading up to World War I, than it is today.
The modern world we live in was shaped, to a large degree,
by World War I, and then later [by] World War II.
And just to get a sense of what
our modern world looks like –
and especially what modern Europe looks like –
this is a map of modern Europe.
But the interesting thing about this map is that
instead of being the traditional map that you normally see,
where you just see the country boundaries –
the state boundaries – this has the state boundaries
right here in these little gray lines.
These show where France ends and, say,
Switzerland or Germany or Italy begins.
But overlaying all of that,
we see where the languages are spoken.
So this is actually much more focused on,
[for example], "Where do people speak French?"
"Where do people speak German?"
And the thing that you will notice is – for the most part –
throughout most of Europe, today's boundaries –
the modern boundaries – closely match up
to where languages are spoken.
There are a few areas where there is more of a disconnect
[for example,] Catalan and Spanish.
(And actually, that is leading to some issues.)
But for the most part, in modern Europe,
the linguistic boundaries and
the national boundaries kind of match up.
If we rewind to the world before World War I,
things were very different.
Some of the boundaries we recognize.
We recognize the United Kingdom.
(Well, Ireland has since been carved out.)
But the United Kingdom's boundaries
are not very different now than they were then.
Spain is not that different.
France is not that different.
Italy is not that different.
Germany is a good bit different.
In fact, if you take Germany – or the German Empire –
entering into World War I, or in the early 1900s,
before 1914, between it and the Russian Empire,
they essentially were swallowing up a bunch of
linguistic groups, right over here,
that now have their own independent states.
The other thing that you might notice
is this huge state called "Austria-Hungary" –
often called the "Austro-Hungarian Empire."
And people say, "Well, you know,
I'm familiar with some of these nations
that have the words 'Austria' and 'Hungary' in them.
But what is this Austro-Hungarian Empire?"
And what's interesting about Austria-Hungary
is it really was an empire.
It really was trying to cobble together all of these folks
that spoke all [of these] different [languages] –
[and that consisted of] all [of these] different types of [ethnicity].
This is kind of a zoom-in of the Austro-Hungarian empire
leading into World War I.
And the Austro-Hungarian Empire is probably
the most important empire to focus on if we're trying to
understand how World War I started.
Because leading up to World War I, in 1908,
the Austro-Hungarian Empire
formally annexed Bosnia and Herzegovina.
And that's another confusing thing for many of us,
the fact that 'Bosnia and Herzegovina'
is actually the name of just one country.
It's called "Bosnia and Herzegovina."
Or I guess, for the Austro-Hungarians,
that was, I guess now, one region that they annexed.
And what's interesting about that is
if you look at the linguistic map,
you see that this whole region right over here
[speaks] very similar dialects: Serbian, Croatian and Bosnian.
They're all very linguistically and ethnically connected.
So this whole region right over here
is linguistically and ethnically connected.
And what we'll see is that this desire to connect
ethnic or linguistic backgroundsis what led to a lot of what
people with similar happened in World War I –
or at least was the spark that [ignited] –
people sometimes say –
the powder keg [that was] World War I.
The other thing that was very different –
or the other country or nation or empire that we are
not [very familiar with] today is the "Ottoman Empire."
So on a modern-day map we would see the country of Turkey –
which is kind of on the Anatolian Peninsula.
So this is Turkey right over here.
This is modern-day Turkey.
But entering into World War I, in 1914,
Turkey , essentially, [was formed out of] part of
the remnants of the Ottoman Empire.
So, this right over here is what theOttoman Empire looked like.
This, right over here, is roughly modern-day Turkey.
The Ottoman Empire contained much of modern-day Turkey,
and much of what we now call the 'Middle East.'
including much of what is now Syria, Iraq, Lebanon, Israel,
and some of what is now Saudi Arabia.
This was then part of the dying Ottoman Empire.
At its peak, the Ottoman Empire controlled much of the Muslim world.
It controlled Northern Africa,
as well as all the stuff that you see here –
and even a little bit of Persia,
and actually a good bit of the Balkans,
Southeast Europe, and even Greece at its peak.
Now I'm talking about going hundreds
and hundreds of years back into the past.
So when we enter into World War II,
we have a world where state boundaries don't necessarily
match linguistic boundaries or by ethnic boundaries.
To a large degree, we had these empires that had existed
as we exited out of the 1800s.
And these empires were not just in Europe –
like the Austro-Hungarian Empire –
or not just in the Middle East – like the Ottoman Empire.
Right over here is a kind of an empire map
at around that point in time.
And you see probably the most dominant empire
here is the British Empire.
That's [the area in] pink [here].
That's the United Kingdom.
Great Britain would just be this [island] right over here.
You throw in Ireland, you get the United Kingdom.
Great Britain was in control of
the entire Indian subcontinent (in Asia).
Although nominally, Egypt was somewhat independent,
Great Britain had a huge amount of influence there.
Obviously, places like Canada and Australia
and New Zealand were under the control of,
or part of, the British Empire.
Well, what a lot of people don't realize is that
a significant amount of Africa was also under British control.
And what we have, running up into World War I,
is kind of a race between empires –
a colonization race especially
between the major powers of Europe.
In particular, you have Great Britain – or or the United Kingdom –
that obviously had a vast empire.
"The sun never sets on the British Empire."
And it wasn't ever setting on this empire that we just saw here.
And the German Empire was also startingto flex its muscle and starting to militarize.
And the more that the Germans saw that the British were militarizing,
the more the Germans would want to militarize – and vice versa.
And you just had this arms race.
And they were all trying to build their empires.
So the Germans, they were present in Africa.
You have the French who were present in much of Africa.
And you have to remember all of this in context.
Some of this empire building was, frankly, just about you ego,
and just about spreading someone's influence – spreading [one's] power.
A lot of it was based on kind of ethnic beliefs about civilization.
I guess these were rationalizations to [justify taking] control of other people's resources.
And a lot of it was – we were in a world where access to resources,
in particular access to raw materials – and especially oil –
could, to some degree, define whether a power was a power at all.
And so, with that, I think we have a pretty good basis for [understanding]
the state of affairs as we enter into World War I.