In the last video we saw how blood sugar concentration, or,
glucose concentration in your blood of 80mg/dL
was kind of a normal fasting blood glucose, if you hadn't eaten for eight hours --
or "before a meal," and the fancy word we learned in the last video was 'preprendial.'
What I want to do in this video
--because 80mg/dL really does not make a lot of tangible sense to me,
I do not know exactly how much sugar that is--
what I want to do is try to put this into different units
so that we can better conceptualize how much sugar that might be in our bodies.
So let us just do a little bit of unit analysis over here.
So if we have 80mg/dL--
--that's what we're talking about; that's a normal, fasting blood glucose level--
now let us think about how much that is per liter.
A deciliter is a tenth of a liter.
So if we want to cancel out the units, we want dL in the numerator
so we want to know dL per L, so that "that" and "that" will cancel out.
There are 10 dL's per L.
And so that gives us 80*10 is 800mg per--
--dL's cancel out--
800mg per L. Now if we want that in terms of grams,
we can just multiple to get rid of that 'mg,' so we put in the denominator,
and put 'g' in the numerator. 1g is 1000mg.
So, once again, milligrams cancel out, and you have 800/1000.
So, 800/1000 is 0.8g/L.
And then to make sense to normal human bodies--I looked this up on the internet--
the average human body, I'm assuming--I'm like, 5'9", 150lbs, so I think I'm pretty close to average--
but they said that the average human body has about 5L of blood.
So let us multiple this...0.8g/L * 5L/average human
Obviously a smaller human will have less, and a larger human will have more blood flowing through them...
But this is an average person right over here, so the Liters cancel out,
and so we get 0.8 * 5 = 4, and then we have grams per average human.
4g/human.
And just to get an idea of what 4g are:
1 teaspoon is equal to 4.2g. So 4g is almost a teaspoon.
So, 4g is approximately 1 teaspoon of glucose per human being.
So in your entire bloodstream you have about a teaspoon of sugar that your cells can do whatever your
cells need to do.