Between the ancient Roman world and the modern world
and between the ancient roman emperors and napoleon
the was only one ruler
that controlled most of western europe
and the person that you're referring to is
Charlemagne,
or Charles the Great, or Carolus Magnus
so few fragments of information
this was so long ago
9th century
this is a really long time
On christmas day, in the year 800 exactly
Charlemagne was crowned Emperor by the Pope in Rome
This is a huge deal.
The Roman emperors in ancient world had ruled from Rome
until Constantine moved the empire to Constantinople
where is now his temple.
and so the center of power had shifted to the east.
now in 800, 500 years after constantine
we have an emperor in the west
there's still an emperor in the east
who still had more authority that
people still looked into the emperor in the east
the byzantine empire
So lets think about what happened in western europe
that allowed Charlemagne to become the new emperor
Well the first thing important to understand
the western roman empire basically fell apart
we see specially in a few centuries
is the dissolution of the
institution of the roman empire
the idea of the roman empire hangs on
but its ability to govern comes apart
to understand what happend to roman empire in the west
you have to recognize the pressure
from serious invasions from people
that the Romans thought of as barbarians