One of the most interesting women
in all of Egyptian history.
Began her life as the daughter of a bureaucrat,
but would marry the pharaoh of Egypt.
She would then be demoted upon his death
and would simply be the Queen Mother.
But her son would then elevate her status,
substantially, making her divine, making her a goddes.
So much of that history can bee seen
in this teeny sculpture of Queen Tiye.
There's a clear sense of her nobility,
even though she bagan in a relatively modest way
as a commoner, although of fairly high status.
She looks out and past us here,
and there's no doubt she's a queen.
She is completely unapproachable.
And we may also be getting a sense here
of what she looked like.
There seem to be some individual characteristics.
She seems to be a little bit older.
We can see lines extending below her nose
on either side of her cheek,
and there're some distinctive facial characteristics.
So perhaps we have a little bit of a window into
what she really looked like.
The face and neck are made out of yew wood, this beautiful dark wood.
The eyes are made out of ebony and alabaster
and then there are some other materials as well.
Gold and some of the semi-precious stone,
lapis lazure is visible just under the headdress
that seems to have been chipped away.
That's right, what we're seeing are in fact evidence
of these changes in Tiye's life.
Underneath the headdress, that we see her in now,
would have been a gold headdress that signified her status
as the queen, as the wife of the pharaoh.
And we can also see that in the two gold clips
that we see on her forehead
that are evidence of where that crown would have been worn.
There would have been a cobra placed there,
the insignia of royalty.
That was presumably removed when her husband died,
and she actually fell in status to that of Queen Mother.
But she was so important and so smart,
and her son depended on her so much
that in order to have her be able to actively participate in politics
and the affairs of the Royal Court,
he elevated her status to one of a goddess.
And that's when this headdress would've been added.
This would have been spectacular when it was first made.
Now, it simply looks a little bulbous,
but if you look a little bit to the back right of the skull
you can just make out some brilliant blue faience beads
that catch the light and really shimmer.
That would've covered the entire headdress
and so she would have looked regal and almost celestial,
appropriate to a goddess.
Her headdress extends upward
where we see horns, a solar disc and chief feathers.
Now, that solar disc may refer to the religion
founded by her son Akhenaten.
Akhenaten got rid of Egypt's traditional polytheistic religion
and established a monotheistic religion
centered around Aten who was symbolised by the sun.
The sculpture really does give us a sense of her importance,
her power, her son's respect for her,
and gives us just a little glimpse into the complexity
of Egyptian life at this high station.