We're in Saint Peter's Basilica,
standing in front of Michelangelo's Pieta
I feel very lucky because on this rainy Monday morning,
we're the only ones
and it actually looks quite small
in relationship to the chapel that holds it
but also just especially in relationship to
St. Peters, which is so vast
Of course, this sculpture was made for the cardinal
but then it was placed in the old St. Peters
which was significantly smaller
than this one
and so it would have had a different relationship
to the architecture
what I'm finding interesting is despite the fact
that it's relatively small
and probably about 20 feet away from us
it's still a really intimate image
there really is this extraordinary
relationship that Michelangelo has
constructed between the body of
the dead Christ and his mother
the Virgin Mary, who holds him on her lap
Mary looks very young and beautiful
like her body is
and her lap is sort of enlarged
to carry the body of her dead son
the realism of that dead body
of its weight
one of the most beautiful passages i think
of the sculpture is the way she holds up
his right arm and pulls up that flesh a little bit
and you really feel for a second
first of all that the marble is transformed
by Michelangelo with the flesh
and the weight of that body
through that weight the loss of life
that's so palpable for Mary
it's the complete lack of resistance
that his body offers
and the exertion that she has to extend
in order to hold it
and that contrast
makes for the viewer i think
in a very physical experience looking at this sculpture
his body looks so much like the body
of a real, young man
the rib cage, the abdominal muscles
and yet it's also idealized in the way
in which there's this beautiful turn of his body
across her lap
and for Mary as well
there's this interesting contradiction
in her sweetness and beauty
but also the strength and the scale
that's necessary for her to easily hold him
look how deeply carved that marble is
the drapery
this real love of the turn of the stone
creating this very vivid sense
of light and shadow
the complexity of the surface
against the broad, pure surfaces
of Christ's legs
of his torso, of his arms
Mary tilts her head forward and looks down
at him, his head is thrown back
so there's something between those two necks
for me
And his neck is exposed
to us, incredibly vulnerable
Christ's foot hangs in midair
Mary, her left hand is open
and pointing delicately forward
as if she's still trying to comprehend his death
but I think there's also a way of presenting
Christ's body to the viewer
saying this is the path to salvation
this is God's sacrifice for mankind
MY sacrifice of my son
that makes possible your redemption
there is a kind of rhythm that points to that hand
the drape and the knee point up towards
Christ's knees which in turn,
create a kind of rhythmic bridge to her hand
and to that sense of wondering
this is very clearly an image
that is meant to be contemplated
and the pain and the suffering
that Christ has endured
That Mary's enduring is meant to be contemplated
as a pathway
[whirring] They're polishing the floor!
Okay let's move on!