[intro piano music]
Ok! Bryn and Monica.
We are standing before the New York Kouros.
And that means what, Monica?
"Kouros" means young man in Greek.
Ok. So this is a general term that refers to a sculpture of a young man.
OK. So, a sculpture of a young man.
So we walk up to this
not recognizing it is a portrait of an individual.
No, this is really a type, an idealized male form.
But a man not a god?
Absolutely! These are believed to be grave markers.
And of course, one thing you can't escape
when you walk up to this, it is nude.
Absolutely!
So they are taking off of the clothing
to focus on the ideal, young male form.
So if this was a portrait it might be a little strange
to have the man being naked, right?
And a Kenneth Clark interpretation,
the difference between the naked and the nude,
rather than someone without clothing,
the nude is an ideal form.
Right, focusing on the perfection of the human body.
And a young man, so an expression in a very narrow range
Of a man around twenty years old. Yes.
OK, now the first thing we notice about it,
it's extremely frontal.
It only makes sense from the front.
So it's not meant to be experienced in around. Right.
Only from the front or the back.
Oh yes that's correct!
And an Egyptian posture that is undeniable, right?
The hands kind of locked to the sides,
the stepping forward with the knees locked,
and even the hairdress that looks Egyptian.
Right. And even though he is stepping forward,
that the weight is balanced perfectly over both feet,
just looks as if though he is about to walk somewhere.
So we wouldn't mistake this for an Egyptian statue because of its nudity
and as you've mentioned because of the naturalism of the posture. Correct!
But, nobody is denying that it comes from an Egyptian influence.
Yes, because we see many Egyptians sculptures with this very kind of pose.
OK, so a transitional moment for the Greek statuary
between what's known as the the Geometrical Period,
or the Orientalizing Period, in some vocabularies,
to the Archaic.
So it's the starting of a new period
And it is interesting that terminology, the Archaic Period,
In the historical way anticipating the era of the Classical.
That's right. This sort of idealizes the Classical Period.
They're getting a point for that.
So, maybe more responsibly if we would call this the sixth century,
the period before the Classical...BCE.
And we certainly see the beginning of something here
with life size, a litte less than life size, male nude sculpture.
What distinguishes this from the figures
in the next gallery, the Classical Period?
And while we're getting a personal view of this,
all the crowds are in the Classical section
Because, in the Classical section,
the human forms really correspond much more naturalistically to true life.
The proportions are correct, they are less stiff,
they exist more in the rounds,
they make sense from all sides.
So ideal types but more lifelike. Exactly!
This one is still little patterned and stiff.
Correct! The musculature, well, there's a clear interest by the sculptor
in the underlying forms of the human body.
The bones, the musculature,
they are standardized, they are formalized into geometric shapes.
While in the Classical period,
they're really correspond much more naturalistically
to the way the human body actually looks.
And that design even carries over to the face.
So the face looking a bit like a mask,
even with a bit of that forced smile...
they called it "the archaic smile."
Exactly. And the stylized eyes,
the eyebrows that continue right from the side of the nose.
And, as you've mentioned before,
the hair is well stylized so it's perfectly regular
sort of beaded rods.
So we would expect in the classical period
to see still idealized young male figures,
but we would expect to see them less patterned and abstract.
Right, much more naturalistic!