Dr. Steven Zucker (Dr. S.Z.): We are in the Uffizi and we are looking at Rafael
this is the "Maddona of the Goldfinch" .
Which is a really funny title
Dr Beth Harris (Dr. B.H.): It is a funny title
St. John who we see here on the left is holding out a goldfinch, the bird to the Christ Child
who strokes it's head.
And the Goldfinch is a symbol of the Passion of Christ,
of Christ's suffering. And so we have that idea
that we often have of the foretelling of Christ's terrible future.
Dr S.Z: But at the same time this is a painting of two children and a mother.
And - So it exists on several different planes
because they're childern doing childlike things:
one showing a pet to another, one wanting to touch it
uh, the mother looking down protectively
Dr. B. H: and even a kind of tenderness between the mother and son.
Look at the way that Christ put his foot on his mother's,
so there is that skin-to-skin moment of human contact there,
that's really lovely, but, to me Christ doesn't look like
a child having fun. He looks very much 'all knowing'.
As opposed, if you are looking at the painting from 1300s
Christ would look - instead of looking like a baby, he would look like a little man
in order to indicate his sense of wisdom.
But here I think Rafael communicates that through the elegance of Christ's body.
Look at the way he lifts his arm up,
strokes the Goldfinch, tilts his head back.
He stands in this incredibly elegant 'contrapposto' (counterpose)
that no child would ever stand in.
Dr. S.Z: It's true
Dr.B.H:I mean it's such a pose
Dr S.Z: and it is a beautiful foreshortening of his head, of his face
as he leans back. But then there's a kind of energy and child likeness
that we see in John.
John seems to so engaged, 'Look what I can show you!'
Dr. B.H:and yet it's the symbol, this really potent symbol of Christ's suffering.
Dr S.Z: What so interesting is that unlike in the 1300s, as you mentioned before,
we don't have the Madonna on a throne.
Here the nature itself is the throne, you know?
We have this verdant environment, this beautiful atmospheric perspective
and she sits on a rock.
That is: 'divinity is all around us'.
By the time we get to the late 15th century to the early 16th century,
in the High Renaissance, nature itself has taken on the expression of God.
We don't need, in a sense, those kingly symbols.
Dr B.H: Look at how composed it is, in a way we don't even notice immediately:
We have a pyramid composition with Mary at the top
and St. John and Christ on either side.
And that sense of real stability and balance
that's also so much a part of the High Renaissance.
Dr S.Z: Even as the figures are so engaged with each other, and
this dialog that's taking place between them, there is also that sense, that High Renaissance sense or right
of balance, of perfection of the eternal.
Dr B.H: That interlocking of gestures and glances,
Mary looking down at John, John looking at Christ, Christ looking back at John
all of them inclosed within the pyramid structure of Mary's body,
that unified composition, that brings everythings together
in this really lovely landscape.
Dr S.Z:I'm intrigued by the book.
Mary had been reading, she's kept her place. And, of course, that reminds us
of an earlier scene, 'The Annunciation', when Gabriel interrupts her as she's been piously reading the Bible.
but here she's been reading and now she is interrupted by her charges.
She's doing a little bit of babysitting.