so the first thing we need to do is take our wire
we've already stripped a quarter of an inch of insulation off the end
and we're going to put our spade connector on it
squeeze it tight and make sure that we have that crimped joint
working for us alright, so now we're going to connect that
to the pole in our motor before we do we'll trim it off
looks like we need about 4 inches and we have about a 1/4 inch exposed
and we'll take that 1/4 inch and we'll wrap it around the motor there
the little contact there to the motor
we wanna make sure that we loop it through that connection
and we're gonna take a little bit of solder
and we're gonna solder it to that connection
make sure that wire is held in place
alright, so we did the exact same thing to the other side, connected the motor
to the pole on the switch on the other side the same way so that they're symmetrical
so now we're gonna take another piece
of wire that's about 4 inches long and we're stripping the ends off
of actually two pieces of wire there and we're gonna loop it through
loop one of them through the other motor and crimp it in place
make sure its wrapped around pretty tightly there
and solder it in place so that it stays where it needs to go
and the other side of the wire we're gonna twist with the wire we just cut
twist it together and we're gonna wrap
that in around on the other connection on the motor on the other side
so we'll have another wire there
and so once thats looped through our motor
the contact on our motor we'll solder that in place
okay, so now we can be sure that those two wires that are connected
to our motors are not gonna come loose so we should have 3 extra wires
at this point and we've got a bunch of other parts
still left but we're gonna start to connect our switches
so the first thing we're gonna do is well, we'll do our led switches
and we're gonna just twist together the leads of the two resistors
that we've selected and we'll loop those around
connect them to one of our contacts on our sliding switch
now this is a single pole double throw switch
and we don't really need a double throw switch
we only need a single throw so we went ahead and bent one of the contacts
out of the way 'cause we don't need it so we're gonna solder the resistors down
to one side of the switch and what's important is that you can
if you do use a single pole double throw switch
with the 3 contacts you need to solder to two contacts
and the two contacts you should solder to should
be right next to each other
if you solder to the two outside contacts it wont work appropriately
so we're gonna take the 20 gauge hook up wire that we had connected before and
we're twisting it on to the other contact and this is the hook up wire from
the one that's connected to the positive terminal on the battery there
and now we're gonna get our switch and we're
getting it lined up and we're gonna put some hot glue down there's about
a nickel sized bunch of hot glue that we just put down
and we're holding it in place, the holding of the switch in place.
it takes a while for the hot glue to dry
alright, so now we have our switch in
we're gonna try to route our wire so they're a little bit more out of our way
and that's good. now we're goint to at this point
we're gonna take our other switch and we're gonna connect it but
before we do that we need to put a little bit of solder
on our battery connection in the back here.
and this is going to allow us to take the 3 volts
from our batteries cuz the batteries are connected in series
and drop it down to 1.5 volts
because our motors are gonna run a little slower
on 1.5 volts, so that's good for us.
because they run really fast already
okay so we're crimping that connect our wire on to our
switch and again we just wanna make sure that
the loop on the wire is fits really tightly around
the post on our switch and we're soldering that on place
making sure that it's got a nice good connection and
so this is the other wire, this is the wire
from our motor that we're gonna connect to the
this will be the on/off switch
the previous switch was the i should say
the switch for the leds. and sometimes its hard
to get the wires to stay in place, you can see they're
bouncing around for me there. alright now
that that solder is in place
now my switch has what it needs to do it's job.
alright, so i'm gonna put down a little bit of hot glue
and make sure that switch is held in place
right there, and now we're gonna take the
other end of the wire was a little bit long
i'm gonna strip off just a little bit
and we are going to solder that wire to the
exposed contact on the battery there and then again
that's gonna allow us to run the motors at a
little bit lower speed cuz we're using a lower voltage.
alright, lets see if we can get this to work and
it takes a little bit doing on this and
one thing you gotta be really careful of
is that the if you hold the soldering iron on
that part too long it will overheat the plastic and around
the connections, it's really important you don't do that
i used to i always like to put a little bit of hot glue
on top of that and then when the hot glue hardens
it helps to kepp the wires from pulling out.
in the next video we're gonna make our antennas
and connect 'em to the single pole double throw switches
in the front of the bot so that spout can turn around
when he bumps into something.