f of x is equal to 7x minus 5
g of x is equal to x to the third power plus 4x
and then they ask us to find f times g of x
so the first thing to realize is that this notation, f times g of x,
is just referring to a function that is the product of f of x and g of x
so by definition, this notation just means f of x times g of x
and then we just have to substitute f of x with this definition and g of x with this definition
and then multiply out these algebraic expressions
so f of x is right over there and g of x is right over there
so lets do it
so this is going to be equal to, switch back to the orange color, is going to be equal to f of x which is 7x minus five times g of x
and g of x is x to the third power plus 4x
and you could, if we were multiplying two expressions that each have two terms, you could use FOIL if you like
i don't like using FOIL becuase you might forget what it's even about
FOIL is really just using the distributive property twice
so, for example, you take this expression, whatever you have out here
if you had a 9 out here or an "a" or an "x" or anything, now you have 7x minus 5
if your multipling it times this expression you would multiply this times each term over here
so when you multuply 7x minus 5 times x to the third
you get, and i'll write it this way, you get x to the third times, acutally let me write it the other way
you get 7x minus five times x to the third and then you have plus 7x minus 5 times 4x
and now we can do the distributive property again
we're not normally used to seeing the things we distributed on the right hand side but it's the same exact idea.
we could put x to the third here as well
now when we distribute, you multiply x to the third times 7x and times negative 5
x to the third times 7x is 7x to the fourth power
x to the third times negative 5 is minus 5x to the third
and then you do it over here, you distribute the 4x times 7x is plus 28x squared
4x times negative 5 is minus 20x
and lets see if we can simplify this
we only have one fourth degree term, one third degree term, one second degree term, and one first degree term
so actually you can't simplify this anymore and we're done!
this is the product of those two function definitions
this is f times g of x. it is a new function created by multiplying the other two functions.