What I want to do in this video is tackle a problem that would be considered
pretty difficult for most first year physics students and you frankly probably
wouldn't be expected to solve a problem like this in most
first physics classes or if your in an advanced or honors class, you might
be expected to, or it might be bonus problem but its an interesting type of problem
because what were going to do is launch a projectile
on an incline, so maybe were on a side of hill
so its a hill, let me do it in green.
Were on the side of a hill like this, and lets say we know the inclination of
the hill; the hill's inclination is 30 degrees
off the horizontal
so this is the horizontal right over here. So that is the
inclination of the hill. And then we are going to launch a projectile
at 10 meters per second.
We are going to launch it at 10 meters per second
and the angle with the hill is 15 degrees
so at a 15 degree angle with the hill.
And the reason that this is more difficult than the traditional projectile motion problems is
well we could think about it, the projectile is going to be launched and it is
eventually going to land at some point on the hill. But we can't do the