In this video I want to talk
about what is easily one of the
most fundamental and profound
concepts in statistics and
maybe in all of mathematics.
And that's the central
limit theorem.
And what it tells us is we
could start off with any
distribution that has a
well-defined mean and variance.
And if it has a well-defined
variance, it has a well-defined
standard deviation.
And it can be a continuous
distribution or a discrete one.
I'll draw a discrete one
just because it's easier to
imagine at least for the
purposes of this video.
So let's say I have a
discreet probability
distribution function.
And I want to be very careful
not to make it look anything
close to a normal distribution
because I want to show you the
power of the central
limit theorem.
So let's say I have
a distribution.
Let's say it could take
on values 1 through
6: 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
It's some kind of crazy dice.
It's very likely to get a 1,
let's say it's impossible-- let
me make that a straight line--
you've a very high likelihood
of getting a 1, let's say it's
impossible to get a 2, let's
say it's an OK likelihood
of getting a 3 or a 4.
Let's say it's
impossible get a 5.
And let's say it's very
likely to get a 6 like that.
So that's my probability
distribution function.
If I were to draw a mean, this
is symmetric, so maybe the mean
would be something like that.
The mean would be halfway.
So that would be my
mean right there.
The standard deviation maybe
it would look-- it'd be
that far and that far
above and below the mean.
But that's my
discreet probability
distribution function.
Now what I'm going to do here,
instead of just taking samples
of this random variable that's
described by this probability
distribution function, I'm
going to take samples of it.
But I'm going to average the
samples and then look at those
samples and see the frequency
of the averages that I get.
And when I say average
I mean the mean.
So let's say-- and let me
define something-- let's say my
sample size, and I could put
any number here, but let's say
first off we try a sample
size of n is equal to 4.
And what that means is
I'm going to take 4
samples from this.
So let's say the first
time I take 4 samples.
So my sample sizes is 4.
Let's say I get a 1, let's say
I get another 1, let's say
I get a 3, and I get a 6.
So that right there is my first
sample of sample size 4.
I know the terminology can get
confusing because this is a
sample that's made
up of 4 samples.
But when we talk about the
sample mean and the sampling
distribution of the sample mean
which we're going to talk more
and more about over the next
few videos, normally the sample
refers to the set of samples
from your distribution.
And the sample size tells you
how many you actually took
from your distribution.
But the terminology can be very
confusing because you can
easily view one of
these as a sample.
But we're taking 4
samples from here.
We have a sample size of 4.
And what I'm going to do is
I'm going to average them.
So let's say the mean-- I'm
going to be very careful when I
say average-- the mean of this
first sample of size 4 is what?
1 plus 1 is 2.
2 plus 3 is 5.
5 plus 6 is 11.
11 divided by 4 is 2.75.
That is my first sample mean
for my first sample of size 4.
Let me do another one.
My second sample of size 4.
Let's say that I get a 3, a 4,
let's say I get another 3,
and let's say I get a 1.
I just didn't happen
to get a 6 that time.
And notice I can't
get a 2 or a 5.
That's impossible for
this distribution.
The chance of getting
a 2 or a 5 is zero.
So I can't have any
2's or 5's over here.
So for this second sample of
sample size 4, my sample mean--
so my second sample mean is
going to be 3 plus 4 is 7.
7 plus 3 is 10 plus 1 is 11.
11 divided by 4 once
again is 2.75.
Let me do one more because I
really want to make it clear
what we're doing here.
So I do one more-- actually
we're going to do a gazillion
more, but let me just
do one more in detail.
So let's say my third sample of
sample size 4 I get-- some I'm
going to literally
takes 4 samples.
So my sample is made up of 4
samples from this original
crazy distribution.
Let's say I get a 1,
a 1, a 6 and a 6.
And so my third sample mean is
going to be 1 plus 1 is 2.
2 plus 6 is 8.
8 plus 6 is 14.
14 divided by 4 is 3.5.
And as I find each of these
sample means-- so for each of
my samples of sample size 4 I
figure out a mean-- and as I do
each of them I'm going to plot
it on a frequency distribution.
And this is all going to
amaze you in a few seconds.
So I plot this all on a
frequency distribution.
So I say, OK, on my
first sample my first
sample mean was 2.75.
So I'm plotting the actual
frequency of the sample means
I get for each sample.
So 2.75, I got it one time.
So I'll put a
little plot there.
So that's from that
one right there.
And the next time I
also got a 2.75.
That's a 2.75 there.
So I got it twice.
So I'll plot the
frequency right there.
Then I got a 3.5.
So all the possible values, I
could have a 3, I could have
a 3.25, I could have a 3.5.
So then I had the 3.5 so
I'll plot it right there.
And what I'm going to do
is I'm going to keep
taking these samples.
Maybe I'll take 10,000 of them.
So I'm going to keep
taking these samples.
So I go all the
way to s 10,000.
I just do a bunch of these.
And what it's going to look
like over time is each of these
I'm going to make a dot because
I'm going to have to zoom out.
So if I look at it like this,
over time, it still has all
the values that it might
be able to take on.
You know, 2.75 might be here.
So this first dot is going to
be this one right here is going
to be right there and that
second one is going to be right
there and then that one at 3.5
is going to look right there.
But I'm going to do it
10,000 times so I'm
going to have 10,000.
And let's say as I do
it, I'm going to just
keep plotting them.
I'm just going to keep
plotting the frequencies.
plotting them over and
over and over again.
And what you're going to see
is as I take many, many
samples of size 4.
I'm going to have something
that's going to start
kind of approximating
a normal distribution.
So each of these dots represent
an incidence of a sample mean.
So as I keep adding on this
column right here that means
I kept getting the
sample mean 2.75.
So over time I'm going to have
something that's starting to
approximate a normal
distribution.
And that is a neat thing about
the central limit theorem.
So the central limit-- and this
was the case for-- so in
orange, that's the case
for n is equal to 4.
This was for sample size of 4.
Now if I did the same thing
with a sample size of maybe 20.
So in this case instead of just
taking 4 samples from my
original crazy distribution
every sample I take 20
instances of my random variable
and I average those 20 and then
I plot the sample mean on here.
So in that case, I'm going
to have a distribution
that looks like this.
And we'll discuss
this in more videos.
But it turns out if I were to
plot 10,000 of the sample means
here, I'm going to have
something that-- two things:
it's going to even more closely
approximate a normal
distribution.
And we're going to see in
future videos it's actually
going to have a smaller-- well,
let me be clear-- it's going
to have the same mean.
So that's the mean.
This is going to
have the same mean.
It's going to have a smaller
standard deviation.
So I should plot these
from the bottom because
you kind of stack it.
One you get 1 and then another
instance then another instance.
But this is going to more
and more approach a
normal distribution.
So the reality is-- and this is
what's super cool about the
central limit theorem-- as your
sample size becomes larger,
or you can even say as it
approaches infinity, but you
really don't have to get that
close to infinity to really get
close to a normal distribution.
Even if you have a sample size
of 10 or 20, you're already
getting very close to a
normal distribution.
In fact, about as good an
approximation as we see
in our everyday life.
But what's cool is we can
start with some crazy
distribution, right?
This has nothing to do with
a normal distribution.
But if we have a sample size--
this was n equals 4-- but if we
have a sample size of n equals
10 or n equals 100, and we were
to take 100 of these instead of
4 here and average them and
then plot that average,
the frequency of it.
Then we take 100 again,
average them, take the
mean, plot that again.
And if we were to do that a
bunch of times, in fact, if we
were to do that an infinite
time, we would find--
especially if we had an
infinite sample size-- we
would find a perfect
normal distribution.
That's the crazy thing.
And it doesn't apply just
to taking the sample mean.
Here we took the sample mean
every time but you could have
also taken the sample sum.
The central limit theorem
would have still applied.
But that's what's so
super useful about it.
Because in life there's all
sorts of processes out there,
proteins bumping into each
other, people doing crazy
things, humans interacting
in weird ways.
And you don't know the
probability distribution
functions for any
of those things.
But what the central limit
theorem them tells us is if we
add a bunch of those actions
together, assuming that they
all have the same distribution,
or if we were to take the mean
of all of those actions
together and if we were to plot
the frequency of those means,
we do get a normal
distribution.
And that's frankly why the
normal distribution shows up so
much in statistics and why
frankly it's a very good
approximation for the sum or
the means of a lot
of processes.
Normal distribution.
What I'm going to show you in
the next video is I'm actually
going to show you that
this is a reality.
That as you increase your
sample size, as you increase
your n, and as you take a lot
of sample means, you're going
to have a frequency plot that
looks very, very close to
a normal distribution.