Express d times 4d to the fourth to the one half power as a radical expression.
So the key thing to realise here is that if I take anything
to the one half power by definition, this is the
same thing as taking the principle root
of that anything.
So let's just apply that here we have
4d to the fourth raised to the one half power.
So this part, right over here, let me do it in two different colours,
so I have d right over there,
and the I have 4d to the fourth raised to the one half power
which by definition is the principle root,
of 4d to the fourth and we explore other videos
while this all works out well with exponent properties.
Now we know how to simplify this right here.
We are looking for the principle root of
this is the same thing, this is the same thing as d
times the principle root of 4 times the principle root
of d to the fourth, times the principle root of d to the fourth
The principle root of four, principle root of four is
2, and we have that d out front.
And the principle root of d to the 4th power is the
I should do it as a positive square root of d to the four
That is d squared, and we don't have to put an absolute value here,
because even if d is a negative value,
d squared will still be a positive value.
And if this was a d squared here,
then we would have to think about the absolute value over here.
And then, just to simplify this we have a d times
a 2 times a d squared that's multiply the d's times each other
same base, that become d to the third.
So this becomes 2 times d to the third power.
Now another way you could have done this is
to just straight use the exponent properties.
You could have said that that is the same thing as
d times and inside the parenthesis
If you take the product of things and then raise them
to an exponent, that's the same thing as raising
each of them individually to the exponent
and then taking the product.
So that's the same thing
so I'm gonna rewrite this part right over here
as 4 to the one half power
times d to the fourth to the one half power
and 4 to the one half power, this is literally just
the principle square root of 4 which is 2 and d to the fourth
to the one half power, this is, again
you can use exponent property, if I have something
raised to some power and then I have it raised to
another power, this is the same thing as
that same base raised to the product of these powers
Let me prove it in other videos.
So this right over here, this expression right over here
is going to be equal to d to the 4 times one half power.
What's 4 times one half?
Well that's just 2! So this simplifies once again
d times 2 times d squared, which is 2 d to the 3rd power.