We're in The Hofburg in Vienna in the royal treasury
which is filled with crowns and scepters
Reliquaries and jewells. It's amazing.
and one of the real treasures is an enormous mantle
that was worn during the coronations of the holy Roman emperors
But that's not what this was made for.
This was made in the 12th century in Sicily,
actually in the royal workshops of Roger II
who was a Norman that ruled
and the Normans you might remember actually began as Vikings
as they came down from the North
and they eventually settled in north-western France.
and also at the bottom of Italy and the island of Sicily
and that's where this was made.
So this is a really large cloak
you can see the hasps at the top for where it was worn on the shoulders
and its made of red silk, gold stitchings
and thousands of pearls and enamel plates and jewells
And it's in exceptional condition.
The enamel is made in cloth edge where very fine walls of gold
separate the enamels' themselves as they melt, as they petrify
and what's interesting about this mantle is
if you look at its imagery
even that was made for Christian ruler
It's full of Islamic motives,it was made by Islamic artisans
and we see that in the lion overpowering a camel,
we see it in the caligraphic script along the semicircular bottom
and the tree of life in the centre
and motif almost identical to that in the dome of the rock in Jerusalem
These are motives that come out of the patternbooks that
would have transversed the Islamic world
and recopied over hundreds of years
the robe is clearly meant to symbolize power
Look at the forms of those lions.
They're schematic and not terribly naturalistic
but they evoke a real sense of fierceness in their faces,
and their puffed up chests.
And the camels look so subdued and overpowered.
Those camels are domesticated.
They're actually wearing saddles.
One of the interpretations of this iconography, of this symbolism
is that the lions were actually representing the Normans.
The house of Roger II had as its symbol the lion.
wheras the camel might be a reference to people
that Roger had conquered.
so although this cloth was made in the 12th century
it acquired the legend that it was made for Charlemagne,
for the very first holy Roman emperor for the 9th century
But we know that it's not the case.
because in fact the Kufic inscription of Arabic writing
gives us a specific tape.
This mantle was worked in the most magnificent royal splendor
perfection, might, superiority
approval, prosperity, magnanimity, beauty
the fullfilment of all desires and hopes
felicitous days and nights without cease or change,
with authority, with honour, freedom from harm,
triumph and livelihood in the city of Sicily in the year 528
528 according to the Islamic calendar
dating from the time of Mohamed
this correlated with the 12th century in the western calendar
those plates also have a kind of important iconography that has an Islamic origin.
you'll see the star that's made of intersection of two squares
and going back to the begining of Islam
there was a notion that the Earth was a square
and the heavens were square
here we see those overweight
and so you do have a kind of cosmological reference
and perhaps a reference that Roger himself
ruled over all
There is a clear sense here of
speaking to the owners grandeur
Just imagine, through history those that were crowned holy Roman emperor
wearing this garment, carrying an orb, carrying a sceptre.
The Pope, a huge ensemble of the most powerful people in the West.
It must have been quite a sight to see.