Abstract Expressionism is often divided into two classifications,
one of which is 'action painting' – which is the work typified by Bill De Kooning,
or Jackson Pollock – where you feel the action of the artist on the canvas.
The other side doesn't really have a name.
But you might call it 'still painting,' because, in fact, there's an absence
of gesture, or activity, or angst on the canvas.
Instead, what you have is quiet contemplation –
a mood of deep immersion in color.
In a Rothko painting, you have three or four zones of different thinly washed
layers of color, all interacting with each other in a subtle way –
not like bold contrasts – but instead, of almost swimming into each other,
to get your eye and your brain working optically to almost immerse your
consciousness in these fields that Rothko has created.
They may look simple.
On the other hand, to really figure out how he
created those effects is far more complicated.
And it's not easy to understand what colors are actually
in which layers on the canvas.
The mystery of the whole thing is actually appropriate to Rothko's goals.
He's wanting to make a picture which advertises its own mystery,
it's solitary quality, it's introspective quality.
It's a quality that he felt was reflecting his own state while painting.
And I think it's a quality that he wanted to inspire in the viewers
who were in the space of his paintings.
In the exhibition, we've installed an entire room only of Rothko –
and not only for the reason that we have
many beautiful paintings to present,
but because of this power they
have to create an environment,
you feel the intimacy of the atmosphere
that he has made for you.
The point of Rothko's art is to
provide a universe for viewers
that they don't have in the real world.
There is definitely a spiritual side to what Rothko was doing.
It's not at all an ironic art, or a kind of calculated,
clever, sort of tactical art.
In fact, one of the quotations of Rothko that's repeated often
is, "Silence is so accurate."
What he was really doing was extolling the power
of an abstract language to say so much more
than words could do.
I think when you look at
a painting by Rothko,
you also realize what is
meant by the term 'all over,'
which is often used in regard
to Abstract Expressionist painting.
It's not like there is center point – and the edges, or the corners,
or the sides are of lesser importance than the core.
In fact, the action of the painting – if there is action – is distributed equally
from top to bottom, and from side to side.
And there is no way that you
can complete your experience
of that picture without
letting your eye wander –
or even your body wander – all
over the surface of that canvas.
You end up feeling like you're in a zone with no gravity –
almost that there is not a weight.
Rothko often said that he liked his paintings
to be hung rather low to the floor.
The reason for that is that he really saw these paintings
as something that mattered in terms of the physical presence of the viewer.
The physical presence of the viewer starts with their feet being on the floor.
And he wants the paintings to – not literally begin on the floor –
but as close to that as is reasonably possible,
so that you're almost standing in the painting,
rather than admiring some kind
of separate object on the wall.
Your space is the painting
space – and vice versa.
Like many of the artists in the Abstract Expressionist era,
Rothko did not want his paintings to be framed.
Paintings that were made on easels and then put on frames were understood
to be allusions of another
scene – of an imagined place.
Rothko and his peers did not feel that they were alluding to another space,
or place, or time with what they were making.
What they were making was the reality
that they wanted to present to the viewer.
And for that reason, it didn't need the borderline
of a frame separating its reality from their reality.
What they wanted was the joint
reality of spectator and painting.