So let's get some practice at simplifying polynomials,
especially in the case where we have more than one variable over here
so I have 4x squared y
minus 3x squared minus 2 y
so that entire expression
plus the entire expression
8xy minus 3x squared plus 2x squared y plus 4
So the first thing that jumps out at me
is that I'm just adding this expression to this expression
so to a large degree these parentheses
don't matter, so I can just rewrite it as
4x squared y minus 3x squared minus 2y
plus 8xy minus 3x squared plus 2x squared y plus 4
Now we can try to group similar terms or like terms
So let's think about what we have over here
So this first term we have over here is a 4x squared y
So can I add this to any of the other terms here?
Do we have any other x squared y terms?
Well, sure. This one right over here
is another x squared y term.
If I have 4 of something
in this case I have 4 x squared y -s
and I add 2 x squared y -s to it,
how many x squared y -s do I now have?
Well,4 plus 2: I now have 6 x squared y -s.
Now let's move on to this term.
So I have negative 3 x squared-s.
Do I have any more x squared-s
in this expression right over here?
Well, sure, I have another negative 3 x squared
so if I have negative 3 of something
and then another negative 3
I end up with negative 6 of that thing.
So it's negative 6 x squared.
Now let's think of this negative 2y term.
Are there any other y -s over here?
Well, it doesn't look like there are.
This is xy, this is 4, there are no y -s.
So I can't really add that to anything, so I'll just rewrite it - negative 2y.
And then 8xy. Well, once again, doesn't seem like that can be added to anything else,
so let's just write that over again.
Then finally we just have the constant term plus 4.
And it pretty much looks like we're done.
We have simplified this as much as we can.