In the last video
I talked about how bitcoin transactions are really incorporated
into a global and a publicly accessible ledger of sorts
that we call the transaction block chain.
This work is actually carried out by nodes in the Bitcoin network
that are known as bitcoin miners.
There is a reward for all that effort,
especially since some of the computational heavy lifting is done by these bitcoin miners.
They are basically awarded a certain numer of bitcoins for their efforts.
This happens by the miners effectively constructing
what is called a coinbase transaction.
They basically assign themselves bitcoins within that transaction.
In a sense, bitcoins are effectively generated almost out of thin air during this process.
Of course, if you see something like that, that may raise in your mind the question
of whether there is ever an upper limit to the Bitcoin money supply.
And fortunately the answer...
Maybe not so fortunately, depending on your viewpoint.
...the answer to that question is actually yes.
The Bitcoin system is actually designed so that there can be at most 21 mln bitcoins ever generated.
That's the maximum numer of bitcoins that can ever come up in the system.
Beyond that point, no more new bitcoins will ever be accepted or generated or allowed to be generated.
As a result, nodes from that point onward,
once 21 mln bitcoins have been generated,
will no longer get a reward for complementing the transaction block chain.
The bitcoin miners who do all this effort
are not gonna get guaranteed award for doing that effort.
And keep in mind, that because every transaction in the Bitcoin system is public
and the nodes in the system actually know how many coins have been generated
it's possible to really enforce this limits
on the total numer of bitcoins created.
There are two points I wanna make regarding this particular limit.
First of all, even after it is reached
we will still gonna need to do what bitcoin mining does today.
That involves things like incorporating transactions into transaction blocks
and incorporating these transaction blocks into transaction block chains and so on.
If you think about it, once the 21 mln coin limit is reached
these nodes don't get that automatic reward of bitcoins
for performing this extra effort.
You may be wondering what incentive is there for these nodes
to engage in this additional effort.
I mean, why are they doing this sort of thing
if they are not gonna get bitcoins as the guarantee for doing that work.
At this point the hope is that when we reach the 21 mln bitcoin limit
or as we get closer and closer to it,
the transaction fees will play a more prominent role
in a nodes decision to be a bitcoin mining node.
In particular, the idea here is that we hope the transaction fees will be enough of an incentive
and more and more people will
in general, I think hopefully at this point will be using bitcoins,
so as a result, I think there is an expectation or it's not unreasonable to think
that as more and more people use bitcoins
there will be more and more transactions
and as a result, more and more opportunity to make money out of the transaction fees.
It turns out that in the context of bitcoin mining
a lot of the heavy lifting is in this proof of work piece,
not in being able to incorporate all these transactions into a transaction block.
Even if there is a lot of transactions in a transaction block
it's not that much more effort for the miners to really incorporate those extra transactions.
If they are getting all these extra transaction fees
then that might be a good incentive for them.
It's also worth noting that transaction fees are actually set by the pair in Bitcoin.
The pair is gonna have their honours of setting the fee appropriately,
so that the nodes in the Bitcoin network are incentivised to add that pair's transactions
to their transaction blocks.
Hopefully, that makes some sense.
The second point I wanna make regarding this limit of 21 mln bitcoins
is that really Bitcoin does allow for fractional coins.
We haven't really talked much about that in this video
since I've really implicitly talked only about the idea of coins being these whole entities
like Alice transferring ten coins to Bob
or twenty five coins to Bob.
But it turns out you can actually have coins that are fractional.
In fact, the smallest possible unit in Bitcoin is a very small numer.
It's 0.00000001 bitcoins.
This is one hundred milionth of a bitcoin.
Just as an FYI, this is known as a Satoshi.
This name actually comes from the name Satoshi Nakamoto.
Satoshi Nakamoto is the pseudonim of the inventor of bitcoin.
Nobody actually is sure that there is somebody named Satoshi Nakamoto,
but as far as anybody can tell, the only person who's ever taken credit for the invention of bitcoin
is the Satoshi Nakamoto name.
It's unlikely there is actually a person behind that name
but it's more likely it's some kind of a group or something of that nature.
Aside from that, there are actually a couple of other additional controls that I wanna mention.
They are built in the Bitcoin for keeping the growth of that money supply in check.
First of all, the reward provided to bitcoin miners
actually decreases over time.
If you were aware, when Bitcoin began, which was around January of 2009,
at that time the reward for a bitcoin miner to do their effort was 50 bitcoins.
The way that the reward structure is set up
is that every 210,000 blocks,
so when you get to 210,000th block period,
when 210,000 new blocks are generated,
the reward size actually gets cut in half.
What that means is that once 210,000 blocks are generated
the reward goes from 50 bitcoins to 25 bitcoins,
then from 25 to 12.5 and so on and so forth.
It does take approximately four years to generate 210,000 blocks.
I'll talk a little bit later where this four years numbers come from.
Right now, when I'm recording this video it's May 2013,
the current award is actually no longer 50 bitcoins.
The current award now is 25 bitcoins per mining operation.
It's gonna go down by half in approximately four years
and that's just gonna keep happening until around the year 2140.
In 2140 we will expect that the entire bitcoin supply will have been generated.
So it is unlikely we will be generating bitcoins after 2140.
2140 is the point at which all bitcoins will have been generated.
The last way to limit the generation of bitcoins
is to actually calibrate the difficulty of solving that proof of work protocol at a global level.
I was gonna point out another functionality that Bitcoin has built into it
is that for every 2,016 blocks that are generated
the network basically estimates the time that it took to generate those blocks.
It looks at how long did it take to generate the first of these block
and how lond did it take to generate the last of these blocks
and then measures that amount of time.
If that amount of time
is something significantly bigger than two weeks
then the proof of work protocol will be simplified.
It will be calibrated so that it's easier to generate the blocks.
On the flip side, let's say it took a lot less than two weeks to generate these 2,016 blocks.
In that case, the proof of work will be again calibrated to be made more difficult.
The goal is, we want it to be the case it takes about two weeks to generate 2,016 blocks.
About 14 days to generate 2,016 blocks.
To get a better sense for why that numer is the way it is
you could see that, let's say it takes about two weeks to generate 2,016 blocks.
What that actually will imply is that it takes about ten minutes
before the proof of work is actually solved
and a new transaction block is folded into the overall transaction block chain.
You can actually work out that if it took ten minutes to come up with one new block at the global level
and you multiply that by six to get the numer of blocks generated per hour,
so you get six blocks per hour,
or really six new proofs of work per hour,
which in turn would lead to six new transaction blocks per hour,
you multiply that by 24 hours per day
and you multiply that by 14 days
and you will find that when you multiply these things together
you will get the numer 2,016.
So, you can get the sense where this numer comes from.
I wanna make one last final claryfing remark regarding this proof of work.
Since solving the proof of work requires a bitcoin mining node to come up with the proof string,
which it currently does through some type of excessive search,
as you increase the numer of bitcoin mining nodes on a network,
the proof of work will be solved faster.
I don't mean faster for a particular node,
I mean faster at the level of the entire network.
In other words, it will take less time before at least one node comes up with the solution,
because these nodes are all working on same problem concurrently.
I also wanna mention quickly that even though different bitcoin mining nodes are all validating
either the exactly same set of transactions
or maybe largely overlapping set of transactions,
they are all solving entirely different proof of work protocols when they are doing this sort of thing.
The reason for that is that each node inserts its own coinbase or generational transaction
into the block that it's working on to award itself coins.
This generational or coinbase transaction is unique to each node.
As a result, the challenge string for which each bitcoin mining node
is seeking the corresponding proof of work
will be different for each bitcoin mining node.
Essentially, what you have is that because you have a cryptographic hash function being used in the process
just this one difference, the fact that just this one piece is different
completely randomizes the proof of work problem that results.
That makes it likely that across the entire network
the solutions are likely to be widely distributed
and we can expect that if we have enough nodes
one node will come up with the solution in about ten minutes.
At least one node will do it
and once one node comes up with the solution
everyone else can proceed from that point onward with the new chain.
As you can see, the Bitcoin protocol takes a numer of measures,
implements a numer of mechanisms to both limit the total numer of bitcoins
as well as he ray in which these bitcoins are ultimately generated.