We're in San Lorenzo in Florence in the Old Sacristy
That's a room that is traditionally used when a church
for the priest of fast. That is, to put on the garments
for a religious ritual, But in this case, it was
intended to be a mausoleum for the founder of the
Medici dynasty. Giovanni di Bicci de Medici who is baried here along
with his wife, in the early 1400s when a group of people decided to
rebuild the church that was here and the families contributed money.
Now, it wasn't that they were chipping in. Each was in control of its own
chapel. Giovanni di Bicci de Medici decided to
pay for the building of the Sacristy. He got a bigger space. He got a
bigger space, he paid more money and he hired Brunelleschi. He was smart. We should
say that when you enter the church, the Sacristy is off
the left transept. It is now known as the Old Sacristy.
Because Michaelangelo designed the New Sacristy. But here we are in Brunelleschi's
Old Sacristy which is the epitome of Renaissance architecture
Now, Brunelleschi has done some extraordinary things here. First of all, there is a sense
of solemnity, of calmness, that is in part a
result of the extraordinary sense of geometry here, and order
rationalism, so many of the characteristics that we associate with 15th century
Florentine Renaissaince thinking humanism. So instead of
the mysterious basis of a Gothic church we have
a space built on the fundamental geometric shapes
of the square and the circle and a sense of
clarity. This notion of geometry having a kind of
philosophical importance. And of course, this is a burial
site. And so the idea of the eternal, the idea in fact of resurrection
is crucial here. The room itself is a perfect square.
In fact, one could argue it comes close to being a cube but then it's
surmounted by this beautiful hemispheric dome and one of the ways
which historians understand this is that the circles reference
to the spirituality of the geometry of heaven. If you think about a circle, it has no
beginning and no end. like God. Whereas we inhabit the
much more rectilinear space, the earthly space, the space of gravity.
So how do you get the circle down to the square
that is the room itself? He has done this by borrowing a technique
that we find in Byzantine architecture, thinking about Aya Sofia, which is