We've talked a lot about mirrors, in particular parabolic mirrors that reflect light, but I want to do now is talk about lenses
or talk about what a lens is and think about how they transmit or refract light. So a simple lens that
we've all seen that maybe it's made out of glass or maybe something else is each surface, and I'm going
to focus on convex lenses first, so remember: concave means it opens inward like a cave; convex means
it opens outward. And in a convex lens, it will be symmetric. So one side of the lens will look like
that, and you can view this, and often times the simpler lenses are made this way, it's part of the surface
of a sphere, and its symmetric so it has some center right over here and then you have another surface o
of a sphere that's exactly the same.
So let's think about what's going to happen as light goes through this lens as it is transmitted through
it and maybe gets diffracted by it. So we are assuming this is air out here and this is glass or something
with a higher index of refraction where light travels slower. Imagine that some light that is going parallel
to the principle axis of the lens--this is the principle axis of the lens right here just like we talked
about the principle axis of our parabolic mirrors- but if you imagine light that is going parallel to
that, right when it hits this surface over here (remember the perpendicular at this point is going to
look like this because the lens is actually curved