So we're told that AE is equal to twelve that's this side right over
here and EC is equal to 18 EC is equal to 18
And then they've drawn a bunch of median's here for us
So we know that they are medians
Because when they intersect the opposite side
They're telling us that this length is equal to this length
So that ED is equal to DC CB is equal to BA
AF is equal to F here that F B and D are the mid points
And the G then would be the centroid
Where the medians intersect
And so the first thing they ask us is what is the area of B G C?
So B C G right here that is this triangle right over there
And to figure out that area we just have to remind ourselves
That the three medians of a triangle divide a triangle to
Divide a triangle into six
Six triangles that have equal area
So if we know the area of the entire triangle
And I think we can figure this out
This is a right triangle they're telling us that
AE this entire distance right over here is going to be twelve
So this is going to twelve which I'm gonna space
This entire distance right over here is 18 they tell us that
So the area the area of AEC, AEC is going to be
For the one half times the base which is 18 times a height
Which is 12 which is equals to 9 times 12 which is 108
That's the area of the entire right triangle triangle AEC
If we want the area of BGC
If we lower this little altitude right over here
The ones that are bounded by the medians
Then we just have to divide this by 6
Coz they all have equal area we've that in previous videos
So the area of BGC is equal to the area of AEC
The entire triangle divided by 6 which is 108 divided by 6
which is what it's 60 we get ten and then 48
This would be 18 it would be 18
And that's right coz it would be a 108 is the same as 18 times 6
So we get our first part the area of that right over there is 18
And if we want we can say hey the area of any of these triangles
These the ones that are bounded by the medians
This is gonna be 18, this is gonna be 18
This entire FGE triangle is going to be 18
But we did this first part right over there
Now they ask us what is the length of AG?
So AG is the distance it's the longer part of this median right over
here and to figure out what AG is we just have to remind ourselves
That the centroid, the centroid is
Always two thirds along the way of the median
Or it divides the median into two segments
That have a ratio of 2 to 1
So if we know the entire length of this median
We can just take two thirds of that
And that will give us the length of AG
And lucky for us this is a right triangle and we know that
We know that F and D are the mid points
So for example we know that this AE is 12 that was given
We know that ED is half of this 18
So ED right over here I'm using a new color ED is going to be 9
ED is going to be 9 so then we could just use
A Pythagorean Theorem to figure out what AD is
AD is the hypotenuse of a of this right triangle AD
So we're looking at triangle AED right now
So we know that let me write this down
We know that 12 squared 12 squared plus 9 squared
Plus 9 squared is going to be equal to AD squared
Is going to be equal to AD, AD squared
12 squared is 144, 144 plus 81 plus, plus 81
And so this is going to be equaled to AD squared
So this is what this is 225
So we have 255 is equal to AD squared is equal to AD squared
And 225 you may or may not recognize is 15 squared
So AD, AD is equal to 15
You wan to take the principal root the positive root
Coz we're talking about distances or length of sides
We don't care about the negatives
So AD is equal to 15 so this whole thing right over here
Is going to be equal to 15
And AG is going to be two thirds of AD
AG is equal to two thirds of AD
We've proved that in the previous video
That the centroid is two thirds along the way
Of any of these medians or we could do it for any of the medians
So it's equals to two thirds times 15 which is equal to
Which is equal to 10
So AG right over here, AG right over here is equal to
Is equal to 10 so we did this second part
Now this third part what is the area of F of FGH
So let me let me color it in
FGH so if we knew this length if we knew HG
And if we knew FH we could easily figure out what that area is
And there's actually multiple ways of figuring out
Either one of those things
So one way one way that we can thing about finding what HG is
Is to remind ourselves, is to remind ourselves
That HG is the altitude of either triangle FGE or triangle AFG
And both of them have a base of 6
Both of them have a base of 6
So this is 6 and this is 6 over here
And they have a height equal to GH
And we know what the area is
We know that the area is already equal to 18
So you can say if we just take this triangle up here
So we're talking about the area, area of triangle AFG
So we know it's one half times its base
Which is 6 times its height which is GH times GH
That's as one half base times height
Is equal to the area of this triangle
Which is going to be equal to 18
And so then we just have to tell ourselves
Well this is three times GH is equal to 18
GH if we divide both sides of this by
If both sides of this by 3 GH is equals to 6
So that is one way to do it GH is equals to 6
You could also made a similarity argument
And you could say look this is this triangle up here
Is similar to this larger triangle over here
This is this hypotenuse is two thirds of the length
Of this entire thing
So this is going to be two thirds of this 9
So that's another way that you could've gotten 6 there
But either way we got this length
Now we just have to figure out what FH is
And we could figure out what FH is if we know what AH is
If we know what AH is because we know A to F is 6
So FH is gonna be AH minus AF
So let's figure out what AH is
Well once again we can make a similarity argument
And if you wanna do it formally we see
That both of the larger this this larger triangle
And this smaller triangle both have a 90 degree there
They both have this angle in common
So they have two angles in common
They're definitely similar triangles
And so we know the ratio of H we're gonna do it in orange
We know that the ratio of AH to AE which is 12
Is equal to the ratio of AG which is 10,10 to the ratio of AD
which we already figured out was 15
So one way to think about it is H is gonna be two thirds of 12
We'll we can just work through the math
Just using the similar triangles
So this right hand side over here is just 2 over 3
And so AH multiplying both sides by 12
Is equal to two thirds times 12 which is just if you do it
It is just H so AH here is 8, AH is 8, AF is 6
So FH right over here, FH right over here is gonna be 2
So now we have enough information
to figure out the area of FHG
it's going to be one half let me write over here
it's going to be one half times the base
I'll just use FH as the base here although
Or I could just do it either way I can use well FH as the base
One half times 2 times the height times 6
Which is equal to 6 and we are done
And you could keep going you could figure out the length
Of pretty much all of these segments here
Using some of these techniques
Or any of these areas where going back
We figured out most of them