Write the equation of a line that has a slope of one-third,
and contains the point negative 12, negative 14-thirds.
So the equation of a line we can write as 'y' is equal to...
...'mx' plus 'b'. This is in slope-intercept form,
where 'm' is our slope, and 'b' right over here is our y-intercept.
And they have actually given us our slope.
Our slope, they tell us, is one-third. So we know that 'm' is going to be one-third,
so we know that 'y' is equal to one-third 'x' plus 'b'.
And so now we just have to solve for 'b',
and the way we can solve for 'b' is that we know this line contains the point negative 12, negative 14/3.
So when 'x' is equal to negative 12, 'y' is equal to negative 14/3.
So lets write that down: negative 14/3 is going to be equal to one-third our slope times our 'x' value,
which is negative 12 times negative 12, and then plus 'b'.
So when 'x' is negative 12, we know that 'y' is equal to negative 14/3,
and we also know that the slope is one-third. That's the 'm' in 'mx'+'b'.
So now we can solve for 'b'.
The left hand side negative 14/3 is equal to one-third times negative 12.
One-third times negative 12 is negative 4, so this is negative 4 plus 'b'.
Let me write that plus 'b' in the same colour that I started with.
And now just isolate 'b' on the right hand side, we can add 4 to both sides.
I want to get rid of this negative 4 so lets add 4 to both sides.
So plus 4, plus 4, we are left with, on the right hand side, we are left with just a 'b'.
'b' is equal to...
On the left hand side we have 4.
4 I can re-write because I'm going to have to add 4 to negative 14/3.
So I want a common denominator. 4 is the same thing as 12/3,
So 4 is 12/3, minus 14/3...
...so I just want to be clear: I just re-wrote the 4 as 12/3.
So 12/3 minus 14/3, or negative 14/3 plus 12/3, is going to give us...
...we have the same denominator of 3, so we are going to have 12 minus 14 is negative 2.
So we have -2/3 is equal to 'b'.
So the equation of the line we figured out.
They gave us the slope and now we just figured out the y-intercept using the information right over here.
So the equation of our line is going to be 'y' is equal to one-third 'x'...
...we got the one-third from the problem.
One-third 'x' plus 'b', 'b' is negative two-thirds...
...so I can just write negative 2 over 3.
And we are done.