in our last video, we looked at simple designs of beam and arch bridges.
Now let's move on to the modern edge
Truss bridge
Truss Bridge make use of a large frame, called Truss
It sets on the top or bellow the bridge deck.
In this case, it is on top.
While it may seem that it only adds weight to the deck.
Truss distributes the load through frame,
so the deck does not experience as much of load.
each segment of the Truss experience different loads of
either tension or compression
we apply two equal loads to the deck,
and calculated the loads to each segment
which are shown as percentages of the total load.
you can see that the largest loads are on the end and the top segment.
while the middle segments have none.
remember that, when we do the compression tests,
spoiler alert!
Let's see if this convict will get shot up from this Trust job...
so how do you think the truss will break?
Discuss!
Thanks for coming, Yoda.
I love your work.
As you can see, the outer segments to the Truss are the first to break,
as they are handling the largest part of the load.
The diagram showed the outer and the top segments had the same loads.
But why didn't the top break?
That's because the top pieces are lined along the grain of the wood.
woods are stronger in that direction
Adding the truss allowed the same deck length to hold 32 pounds.
which is 25% stronger than the beam bridge of the same length.
The final type of the bridge we will discuss, is the iconic suspension bridge.
Although the only suspension bridge around us is less than iconic...
But the same principles apply.
Suspension bridges utilize thick steel cables
which support the deck and transfer the loads to the towers and to the anckers at the end of the bridge.
Supporting cables are used to suspend the bridge deck from the main cables.
the main cables and the supporting cables of the bridge are always under tension.
the cables transfer the load to the towers.
which experience compression.
and also to the anckers at the end of the bridge.
in our model, we used wires for the main cables, and supporting cables.
some of the constructions are not ideal, because it is difficult to simulate some of the joining points and anckers on the small scale.
For this test, we need the full cast of characters.
The miss fits. versus, the bike gang!
Oh, there's this crazy guy again! The loss of the crazy guy...
As forces apply, the cables transfer the load out to the towers and to the end.
and the first transportation maintains the integrity of the deck
So even when it does break, it doesn't really launch anyone!
unfortunately.
I really wanted to see the crazy guy get launched.
This bridge supported 32 pounds.
Which is the same as the Truss Bridge.
The Truss and the Suspension bridges were stronger than the long beam bridges
but weaker than the arch bridge
this may have been unexpected
but the real advantage of the truss and suspension bridges
are that they can spend longer distances than the beam and arch bridges