Gina had 2/3 cup of laundry detergent.
She used 1/2 of the detergent on
Friday to wash all of her sheets.
How much detergent
does she have left?
So, we're essentially
going to take half of 2/3,
or 1/2 times 2/3.
So, let's see which of
these choices match up.
So we should be taking 1/2 times 2/3.
Well, here they are taking
2/3 minus 1/2,
so this isn't going to be right.
Here they're going to be taking--
Let's see, 1/3 because 2/3 times 1/2--
This is exactly what we want to do.
We want to take 1/2 of 2/3.
And we multiply the
numerators: 2 times 1 is 2.
We multiply the denominators:
3 times 2 is 6.
You have 2/6--
You could say that 2/6
has either been used up,
or 2/6 is left.
And 2/6 is the exact same thing 1/3,
divide the numerator
and the denominator by 2.
So this looks right.
And so here, 1/6 cup.
Well we know it's not 1/6 cup.
We know it's 1/3 cup.
So here: 1/3 cup, because
2/3 is equal to 1/3 pluss 1/3.
That's right.
So half of 2/3 must be 1/3.
This is exactly right aswell.
These are both completely
reasonable ways to ways to getting
the right answer,
that Gina has 1/3.
She used a third of a
cup of laundry detergent,
and she has a third left.