Let's do a few more examples of finding
the limit of functions as x approaches
infinity or negative infinity.
So here I have this crazy function,
[reads function]
So what's going to happen as x
approaches infinity?
And the key here, like we've seen
in other examples, is just to realize
which terms will dominate.
So for example, in the numerator,
out of these three terms,
the 9x^7 is going to grow much faster
than any of these other terms,
so this is the dominating term
in the numerator, and in the denominator,
3x^7 is going to grow much faster than an x^5 term,
and definitely much faster
than a log base 2 term.
So at infinity, as we get closer and closer to infinity,
this function is going to be roughly equal to
9x^7 over 3x^7, and so we can say,
especially since as we get larger and larger,
as we get closer and closer to infinity,
these two things are going to get
closer and closer to each other,
we can say this limit is going to be
the same thing as this limit,
which is going to be equal to
the limit as x approaches infinity -
well, we can just cancel out the x^7's,
so it's going to be 9/3, or just 3,
which is just going to be 3.
So that is our limit as x approaches infinity
of all of this craziness.
Now let's do the same with this function
over here. Once again crazy function,
we're going to negative infinity,
but the same principles apply.
Which terms dominate as the absolute value
of x gets larger and larger and larger,
as x gets larger in magnitude.
Well in the numerator, it's the 3x^3 term,
in the denominator it's the 6x^4 term,
so this is going to be the same thing as
the limit of 3x^3 over 6x^4
as x approaches negative infinity.
And if we simplify this, this is going to be equal to
the limit as x approaches negative infinity
of 1 over 2x.
And what's this going to be?
Well if the denominator, even though it's
becoming a larger and larger negative number,
it becomes one over
a very, very large negative number,
which is going to get us pretty darn close
to zero, just as one over x as
x approaches negative infinity gets us close to zero.
So this right over here,
the horizontal asymptote in this case
is y is equal to 0,
and I encourage you to graph it,
or try it out with numbers to verify that for yourself.
The key realization here is to
simplify the problem by just thinking
about which terms are going to
dominate the rest.
Now let's think about this one.
What is the limit of this crazy function
as x approaches infinity?
Well once again, what are the dominating terms?
In the numerator it's 4x^4,
in the denominator it's 250x^3,
these are the highest degree terms.
So this is going to be the same thing
as the limit as x approaches infinity
of 4x^4 over 250x^3,
which is going to be the same thing as
the limit of - let's see -
4 - well I could just - this is
going to be the same thing as -
well we could just divide 250 - well
I'll just leave it like this.
It's going to be the limit of 4 over 250
- x^4 divided by x^3 is just x -
times x, as x approaches infinity.
Or, we could even say this is going to be 4/250
times the limit as x approaches infinity of x.
Now what's this?
What's the limit of x as x approaches infinity?
Well it's just going to keep growing forever,
so this is just going to be -
this right over here is just going to be
infinity, and infinity times some number
right over here is going to be infinity,
so the limit as x approaches infinity
of all of this is actually unbounded.
It's infinity.
And a kind of obvious way
of seeing that right from the get-go
is to realize that the numerator
has a fourth degree term,
while the highest degree term in the denominator
is only a third degree term.
So the numerator is going to grow
far faster than the denominator.
So if the numerator is growing far faster
than the denomiator,
you're going to approach infinity in this case.
If the numerator is growing far slower
than the denominator,
if the denominator is growing far faster
than the numerator, like this case,
you are then approaching zero.
So hopefully you find that a little bit useful.