The members of a distinguished committee were choosing a president
and each member gave one vote to one of the
27 candidates. So each member gave one vote to one of the 27 candidates
so it looks like they all got at least one vote
For each candidate, the exact percentage of votes the candidate got
was smaller by at least 1 than the number of votes for that candidate.
Let me underline that. It's kind of a confusing statement.
For each candidate, the exact percentage of votes the candidate got
was smaller by at least one than the number of votes for that candidate.
was smaller by at least one than the number of votes for that candidate
What is the smallest possible number of members of the committe?
So, let's define some variables here. Maybe we can get our heads around this.
let's just say that "m" is equal to the number of members of the committee
members thats equal to members. and lets just think about each candidate
let's say that, we just have 27 candidates but lets just pick some arbitrary candidate "i"
so then "i" can be any number from 1-27.
any integer.
so, candidate "i." This sentence right here, let me write it in blue
since i underlined it in blue. Candidate C sub-"i" equals the number of votes for the "i"-th candidate
Now, let's see if we can do something with what i underlined.
The exact percentage of votes the candidate got was sma-
So lets just, the exact percentage of votes the candidate got would be
The votes he got (or she got) divided by the total number of members
Now, this will give you a decimal
If you want it as a percentage, if you want it as a percentage
you want to multiply it by 100
so times 100 so thats this part
the exact percentage of votes the candidate got
so, thats this right here
was smaller by at least 1 than the number of votes for that candidate
so smaller than- smaller by at least 1
so the number of votes for the candidate is "C" sub-"i"
and its smaller, its not less than or equal to the number of votes they got
its less--
its smaller than or -- its less than or equal to one less than the number of votes they got
at least one less
was smaller by at least one
so we're gonna put the minus 1 here
so this tells us that the percentage of votes that any candidate got
is less than the number of votes they got minus one
which is really what that sentence is saying
which is really the hardest part: understanding what that sentence is saying
Now what is the smallest possible number of members on the committee?
Now think about it, we want to minimize the number of members
So we really want to minimize, the number of votes that each candidate gets.
So let's just think about, the minimum number of votes,
the minimum votes per candidate.
So can we have 0 votes for each candidate?
Well they tell us here, they say each member gave one vote to one of the 27 candidates,
So everyone got at least 1 vote.
So no, we cannot have 0 votes.
Can we have 1 vote per candidate?
It seems fair, that they each got at least 1 vote, but if we look over here,