OK, we're on problem number 16.
Let's see, they drew us something here.
From point A to point B, I have a line.
Then I have another, B to C.
Then I have another, from here to here.
OK, so what are they telling us?
They tell us, this is a 90 degree angle.
Whoops, not what I wanted to do, edit, undo.
I'm using the wrong tool.
So they tell us, this is a 90 degree angle.
this is 90 degree angle.
This is A, this is B, this is C, this is D.
And they say,
the figure above shows the route of Diane's tripŁŹ
from her house to her job.
Diane travels 16 miles from A to B, so this is 16.
15 miles from B to C, so this is 15.
And 4 miles from C to D, so this is 4.
If she were to travel from A to D directly,
how much shorter in miles would the trip be?
So what would be the direct route?
I'm assuming,
they're kind of talking if she could fly.
What would be her direct route?
So that would be this route.
I thought I was using the line tool.
Edit, undo.
I'll do it in a better color anyway.
So this is the direct route, right here.
This is we want to figure out, the distance of this.
So how can we figure out the distances?
And the trick here is to just realize that
this is going to be the hypotenuse of a right triangle
And you might-- seem confusing,
your initial impulse might have been to say this is x
and this is 15 minus x, and all of this fancy stuff.
Or what you could do, is you can say,
well, this side here,
we know what this is, this length.
Whoops.
Let me draw it a little bit better.
That length, what is that length?
this length is going to be the same as this length
right?
If we assume this is a 90 degree angle.
It's going to be 15.
And then what's this length, right here?
it's going to same as this length up here, right?
I just kind of extended a rectangle.
So this length right here is 4.
So what is this entire length?
It's going to be 16 plus 4, so it's 20.
So now, what we're trying to figure out
her straight line distance is nothing but
the hypotenuse of a rectangle-- of a right triangle
where we know the other two sides.
So we can say,
if this is her straight line distance, x,
we could say x squared is equal to 20 squared,
20 squared plus 15 squared.
x squared is equal to--
let's see, this is 400, plus 225, is equal to 625.
And the square root of 625 is 25, so x is equal to 25
So her straight line distance is 25.
And how far was she travelling before?
Let's see, she was going 16 plus 15 plus 4.
So that's 20-- she was going 35, what is that, miles?
Right, miles.
She was going 35 miles,
and if she goes straight, she goes 25 miles.
So she would save 10 miles if she went straight,
if she was able to fly.
So that's choice C.
Next problem.
Problem number 17.
One circle has a radius of 1/2,
and another circle has a radius of 1.
What is the ratio of the area of the larger circle
to the area of the smaller circle?
Let's see, so the area of circle 1, area 1,
is going to be equal to what?
It has a radius of 1/2, right?
So it's pi r squared, is the radius.
So it's pi 1/2 squared.
And what's the area of circle 2?
The area of circle 2, it's pi times its radius.
And its radius is 1.
So 1 squared.
So the ratio of the area of the larger circle
to the smaller circle --
which one is going to be the larger circle?
This one is, because it has a larger radius, right?
It has a radius of 1.
So the ratio of the larger circle
to the smaller circle--
and that might be where you messed up,
if you flipped the two--
the ratio of the larger circle to the smaller circle
is equal to pi times 1, right?
Well that's just pi.
Over pi times 1/2 squared.
Pi's cancel out, so we have, it equals 1 over 1/4.
Or what we could do is
we could multiply the numerator
and the denominator by 4, which equals 4/1.
So the ratio is 4:1, and that's choice D.
Problem 18.
Clear image.
If the sum of the consecutive integers
from minus 22 to x inclusive is 72,
what is the value of x?
So this is the number--
we've actually done a problem very,
very similar to this,
so it shows you that people at the SAT,
they think of a lot of creative problems,
but every now and then, they have to repeat.
So they're saying the sum of the consecutive integers
from minus 22 to x is 72.
So let's think about this, let's draw the sum.
So it's minus 22, plus minus 21, plus minus 20,
right?
Plus-- it keeps going, until it gets to 0-- plus 0.
And then--
and I'm going to go this way,
again, I'm doing that for a reason.
And then you can say, plus 1, plus 2, plus--
you keep going,
and then you'd have plus 20, plus 21, plus 22, plus 23
plus 24, all the way until we get to x, right?
What you need to realize is all the way
from minus 22 to 22, the sum is 0.
And why is that?
Well, look at the way I drew it.
So minus 22--
we're taking the sum of everything, right?
So minus 22 is going to cancel out with positive 22.
You add those together, you get 0.
Minus 21 is going to cancel out with positive 21.
Minus 20 is going to cancel out with positive 20.
And so forth, and so on.
So everything--
so the sum from minus 22 plus, bam, bam,
bam, bam, all the way to plus 22, that equals 0,
right?
So we only get into the positive sum once
we get to 23, right?
So 23 plus 24 plus something, something, something,
is x, right?
And we have to get to 72.
And here we can just eyeball it.
23 plus 24 plus 25, what's that?
Well their average is 24, 24 times 3 is 72.
Or we can just add it up.
So 23 plus 24 is 47, 47 plus 25, it equals 72.
So the last number that we use in this whole range is 25.
So this is x.
That is x.
And all we did is we said-- think about it,
take the sum from minus 22,
all the way to positive 25.
Everything up to negative 22,
from minus 22 to positive 22,
all of those cancel out with each other.
So the sum is just going to be 23 plus 24 plus 25.
That equals 72, so then x is 25.
Next problem-- I'm running out of time,
so I'd better do it in the next video.
See you soon.