Move the orange dot to -2 + 2i.
So we have a complex number here.
It has a real part: -2.
It has an imaginary part of 2 times i.
And what you will see here is we're going to plot it
on this kind of two-dimensional grid.
But these are not traditional coordinate axes.
In our traditional coordinate axes,
you're plotting a real x value versus a real y value.
Here, the horizontal axis –
that's going to represent the real part of our complex number.
And our vertical axis is going to represent the imaginary part.
So in our complex number, our real part is -2.
And then our imaginary part is positive 2.
And so that right over there
in the complex plane is the point -2 + 2i.
Let's do a few more of these.
So 5 + 2i.
Once again, the real part is 5.
Imaginary part is 2
And we're done.
Let's do two more of these.
1 + 5i.
1 – that's the real part – plus 5i right over that 'Im' label.
Alright. Let's do one more of these
4 -4i.
The real part is 4.
Imaginary part is -4.
And we're done.