Based on the data below which student's score improved the most between the mid-term and final exam?
And so they give us this data in terms of a bar graph for each student.We actually have two bars that show the mid-term in blue and then final exam in red.
and they tell us that here,mid-term in blue,and final exam(in red)
-and sometimes this is called a two column bar graph,because for each student here,you have two columns
of data.So if you were to actually look at the data its self,you have the mid-term data and then the final
exam data.Now,they are asking us,"which student's score improved the most
between the mid-term and the final exams?"So,if we look at Jasmin right over here,might as well start with her since she
might as well start with her since she
is the most to the left.It looks like she definitely did improve from the mid-term to the final
It looks like the mid-term,if I had to guess,this looks like about
a,I don't know,looks like she got maybe a 72 or 73 on the mid-term,I'm just guessing.
I don't know the exact number.And looks like on the final she got,I don't know
that looks like maybe a 77 or 78,approximately.So she improved a little bit about
5 points from the mid-term to the final.The way they have given us this information
we don't know the exact numbers, because it isn't super precise
in terms of marking off the bars.
Hopefully it will become obvious when we look through everyone's scores
Lets look at Jeff.
Jeff actually did WORSE from the mid-term to the final exam.
Looks like he got over an 85 on the mid-term,and then on the final
looks like he got,about an 84 or 85.
So he actually went down.
So it is definately not Jeff.he definately did not improve the most
he actually went down.
Next,if you think about Nevin,
it looks like Nevin actually improved about the same ammount
as Jasmin.On both scores-I don't know if Nevin is a boy or a girl's name,
this person on both tests,this person did better than Jasmin.
But looks like the ACTUAL improvement is about the same.
Looks like they went from about an 83 to,I don't know,about an 88.
I am just estimating it,just trying to look at,look at this axis right
over there,and estimating what those scores are.
So Nevin and Jasmin right now, based on the three we have seen
are tied for the lead.
Now lets look at Alejandra.
Now Alejandra-and this is,ok,this jumps out.
She definately improved,DRAMATICALLY,
from the mid-term, to the final exam.
Looks like on the mid-term,she maybe got an 81 or an 82.
So maybe this was an 82 she got on the mid-term,
and then on the final,looks like she got about a 95,a 95 on the final.
So this dramatic improvement.
So right now,Alejandra is the leading contender
for most improved,from the mid-term,to the final.
And then,finally, Marta,
right over here,
looks like,she actually got worse from the mid-term to the final.
She scored in the mid 90's on the mid-term,
and then LOW 90's in the final.
So she is definately not the most improved.
So the winner here is Alejandra.
Alejandra,is the most improved
between the mid-term,and the final exam.