Hello.
We are now gonna do some slope and y intercept problems as well.
y-intercept problems as well.
Let's get started.
So let me make up a problem.
Let's say we have the points two, five.
The other point, let's make that negative three, negative three.
Well, first let's just graph those two points.
I'm going to graph them in yellow.
So two, five.
Let's see that's one two.
One, two, three, four, five.
So two, five is going to be right over there.
OK.
And then let me graph negative three, negative three.
So it's one, two, three.
One, two, three.
So negative three, negative three is right over there.
And then now let me draw a line that will connect them.
That's my new technique.
I draw it in two pieces.
I think that's good enough.
OK.
So let's see if we can at least first figure out the slope of
the line, and then if we have time we'll try to figure
out the y-intercept.
And then we'll know the whole equation for the line.
Let me pick a slightly thinner color, and we'll get started.
So the slope, if you saw the last module that just
introduces how we calculate the slope, that's
just rise over run.
Or, change in y over change in x.
This is y.
So let's just do that real fast.
So let's take this as our starting point.
So change in y could be five-- remember, y is the
second coordinate-- five minus negative three.
And that's this one.
Over-- now you do the change in x-- two minus, this
is also negative three.
Well five minus negative three, that's five plus plus three.
So that equals eight.
And then two minus negative three.
Once again that's two plus plus three, so that equals five.
So we figured out the slope of this equation.
It's eight / five.
And let's see if that makes sense.
Let's figure out what the rise and the run is.
If we were to start at this point right here, let's see how
much we have to rise to get to the same y-coordinate
as the other point.
So let's see.
We're here, and the other point is up here.
So let's figure out what this distance is.
Actually, now is a good time to use the fat.
Oh man, I have a shaky hand.
OK.
Let's figure out what that distance is.
That distance is delta y, which is change in y.
So it's one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight.
That equals eight.
And that makes sense, because if you think about it
what did we just do?
We just took y equals five, which was up here, minus
y equals negative three.
And so obviously we just calculated that distance
just by looking at the two coordinates five minus negative three.
When you do this calculation it actually gives you
this distance right here.
So that's how we figure out how much we have to rise.
So now let's do the run.
Well the run, to go from this point to the other
point, we went this far.
And let's count how far that is.
Well, it's one, two, three, four, five units.
So we can say delta x is equal to five.
And that's exactly what we did. delta y over delta x was equal
to eight / five, or rise over run is equal to eight / five.
And it would have been the same thing if we calculated run here
or if we calculated rise here.
But it's the same thing.
Hope that's making sense to you.
And I hope that also makes sense that if the rise for a
given run becomes more, then the slope of the line is going
to become steeper and it'll become a bigger number.
So let's see what we have so far for the
equation of this line.
So so far we know the equation of this line is equal to, y is
equal to the slope eight / five x plus b.
So we're almost done.
We just have to figure out this b right here.
Now that b, just so you remember, that's
the y-intercept.
And that's where we intersect the y-axis.
And since this graph is pretty neat, we can actually inspect
it and see that, well, it looks like we're intersecting
the y-axis at two.
So my guess is we're going to come up with b equals two.
But let's solve it, just in case we didn't have this
neatly drawn graph here.
So how can we solve for b?
Well, we can substitute values that we know
that work for x and y.
Well either of these points are on that line, so we can
substitute them in for x and y.
So let's use the first one.
OK.
So the y we get five, will equal eight / five times x.
Well, x there is two.
Times two plus b.
Well, now we just get five is equal to sixteen / five plus b.
And then we get b equals-- well five is twenty-five / five, right?
five is twenty-five / five minus sixteen / five equals nine / five.
All right.
See, so I was actually wrong.
When I looked at this graph I said, oh that looks like
almost two, so yeah it's probably going to be two.
But when we actually did it using algebra, when we did it
analytically, we actually saw that b is equal to nine / five.
So it's almost two.
9/5 is 1 and 4/5, or 1.8.
So that's almost two, but it actually turns
out that it's not.
It's at 1.8.
And I can write it down as a decimal.
1.8.
So the final equation for the line, I'm going to try to
squeeze it in at the bottom of this page, it's going to be y
is equal to-- well, we know the slope.
eight / five x.
Now we just add the y-intercept.
Plus nine / five.
There.
We solved it.
Let's do another one.
And so-- that's nine / five.
I don't want to be too repetitive.
Let's do another problem.
Time to do another problem, and let me put that
graph back there again.
There you go.
All right.
I'm going to think of two random numbers again.
Let me try to do this fast, because YouTube puts a
ten minute limit on me.
So let's say I had the points two, negative three.
And I had the point negative four, five.
So two, negative three.
Let's plot that sucker real fast.
So x is two, so it's here.
And the negative three.
One, two, three.
So two, negative three is there.
And negative four, five.
So that's one, two, three, four.
One, two, three, four, five.
I have to count like this because this
graph is unlabeled.
But if we actually were to draw in the coordinates you would
that see this is five, and this is negative four, and so on.
And this is two, and this is negative three.
And now let's just draw a line.
Let's draw it right there with my shaky hand.
OK.
There you go.
Good line.
And another good line.
All right.
So first we need to figure out the slope.
Well we could just do that doing the algebra.
So its slope is just delta-- I'm still using the line tool
again-- delta y over delta x.
Change in y over change in x.
Let's take this y as the first point now.
So we'll say five minus this y, negative three.
Over-- now since we used the five first we have to use the
negative four first as well.
Negative four minus two.
Well five minus negative three, that equals eight.
And negative four minus two, well that equals negative six.
And negative eight / six, well that equals-- they're
both divisible by two.
So that equals minus four / three.
And let's see, does that make sense as the slope?
Well, if we were to go down four from this point.
So if the rise was negative four-- one, two, three, four.
So if we go down-- woops, I'm using white.
So that's why you can't see it.
We go down by four here, and then we go to the right
three, positive three.
We still end up on the line.
So it works.
Looks good to me.
Let's see if I can solve the y-intercept in thirty seconds.
Otherwise, I'll start it on the next module.
So we get y is equal to minus four / three x, plus b.
And actually what we'll do is we'll leave off here, and I'm
going to solve for b-- and you could try to do it on your
own-- in the next installment of this presentation.