So how do we know that there is a core
and that the core is made up of a liquid outer core and a solid inner core?
The answer there comes from the same technique that we saw Mohorovičić used in 1909
to essentially see how the behaviour or when you measure the siesmic waves
or whether you can even measure the siesmic waves,
the different distances from an earthquake.
So if there is an earthquake right here and we are calling that 0 degrees,
let's remember a couple of things here.
Let's remember that P-waves can travel through anything.
They can travel through solids or liquid or air for that matter.
So they can travel through anything.
But S-waves can only - S for secondary, these are the transverse waves -
these can only travel through solids.
So it turns out that if an earthquake happens at 0 degrees
and you have seismograph stations all over the world and these are extremely sensitive
in order to measure earthquakes that are happening thousands of kilometres away.
It turns out that there is something called a S-wave shadow.
You can measure them here, you can measure them here.
They can go all the way over there, they can go over there, you can measure them over here.
You can see you can measure it in all of these points
but then all of a sudden at 105 degrees -
we are measuring 0 degrees here and we are going outwards like that -
suddenly at 105 degrees and further you stop measuring S-waves.
They don't get for some reason. You'd think that the S-waves would get over here.
That they would get over here, maybe a little bit weaker
but they would be able to get all the way over here.
But they just abruptly stop. No more S-waves.
So in this whole area right over here you get no S-waves.
And obviously I could flip this picture over
and you would see a symetric thing on the other side of the globe
all over this area over here you also would not see S-waves.
You would only see them from 105 degrees in this direction and 105 degrees in that direction.
And the only reasonable explanation that we could give
is that there must be some material that an S-wave cannot travel thorugh
that it would have to travel through to get to these points beyond 105 degrees.
And we know that S-waves only travel in solids.
So the assumption there is that at some point beyond 105 degrees
it's hitting liquid.
So that's what tells us that this right here is probably a liquid.
It's hitting some layer that is liquid. So that tells us that there is a core
and that at least the outer part of that core is liquid enough to stop S-waves.
So the S-waves because they only travel in solids
it leads to this S-wave shadow and this tells us that we have a core
and that core at least the outer part is liquid.
We don't know yet whether the inner part is liquid or solid.
Now the next point of it is how do we know that there is an inner core?
We could use P-waves for that.
A P-wave can travel through anything.
But remember, as you get denser material,
in general, for the same type of material
if you get denser material its going to move faster
so its going to refract outwards like we see here,
but if it goes into a liquid in general sound waves or as I should say P-waves
or seismic waves will move slower in liquids.
And so the refraction patterns that we get,
what we do measure from seismograph stations around the world,
is that it looks like the P-waves are kind of doing what we would expect in the mantle,
but then they're getting refracted as if they're going into a slower medium
as they go through the outer core,
and we that right over here,
and then they get refracted again,
to get to some point on the other side.
That is just what you'd expect if it was all liquid.
But if you go to stations as we get further out
it looks like, if you just look at the refraction patterns,
and you can now model that with fancy computers and get all the data points,
but you could say the only way that reality can fit the data we get,
based on when things reach here,
is if the P-waves are being first refracted to the outer core,
but then they're refracted away that they're going through a denser material,
significantly denser material in the inner core,
and then the're just continuing to refract the way you would expect.
So it's really the refraction pattern of the P-waves.
And frankly the fact that there is what we call the P-wave shadow.
The P-wave shadow by itself, all that tells you
is that kind of roughly crazy things are happening someplace in the core,
but the real way we know that we have the inner core that's solid,
as supposed the whole thing being liquid,
is the pattern when and how the P-waves reach essentially the other side of the globe,
based on modelling how waves would travel through different densities and different types of medium
you can say, wow, there's got to be an inner core right over here.
And obviously it's a lot more math that I'm not going into,
but if you'd do that math based on the shadow
and you'd know the speed in that material and all of that things,
that you could figure out the depth at which these transitions occure.
We know that we have an transition from mantle to outer core here,
and then the transition from outer core to core there.
So hopefully that satiates your questions
about how do we know what the composition of the Earth is
without ever having to dig down there.
We've never even got below our crust.