We're in the Musée d'Orsay and we're looking at Rosa Bonheur's
light filled painting called 'Plowing in the Nivernais.'
That refers to both the region and the kind of oxen that are the stars of this canvas.
They are. The human figure that pushes them along is hardly important.
So Rosa Bonheur did some extraordinary things.
She was an incredibly precocious girl.
I think it was at age fourteen that she was actually sketching in the Louvre and actually creating oil paintings.
This was possible because her father was an artist and had really encouraged her.
I think that they were very liberal.
Otherwise she would not have had her enormous artistic talent encouraged.
She might not've ended up a painter at all.
So this was made in 1849 which is just one year after the revolution
and so interesting that an artist now is moving out into the countryside,
away from all of the chaos of the city --
Where the revolution happened--
And we have this incredible image of these oxen turning the soil in the fall to
prepare it for the following year's season and look at the soil itself.
You almost get the sense that here's the strength of France.
The earth looks incredibly rich and fertile. So there is a sense of a kind of nationalistic idea
of the French countryside and that France will survive and indeed thrive.
And those oxen are so powerful and so beautiful and, in a sense, so eternal.
You know, this is a ritual that has gone on long before the politics
of the modern world.
And will continue long after. They come forward in a receding diagonal that moves into our space
so that we have this sense of depth and atmospheric perspective
and sense of weather and the warmth of the sunlight... It's really so particularly and carefully observed
and it reminds me so much that we see of the 1840s and then into the 1850s of this interest
in rural life, of laborers, of the virtues of the countryside.
Yeah, when I look at this, the oxen, those backs are so beautifully aligned, they almost
create their own horizon like the hills beside them and so, in a sense, they are the earth itself.
There is this sense of permanence. I think throughout the 1840s, especially with the kind of industrialization
and growth of the cities that's taking places that there is this real desire to return to
this much more basic truth.
Which resides in nature and the countryside.
And in labor itself but in a kind of simple, very direct kind of labor.
So do you think that Rosa Bonheur is giving us a conservative vision at this moment just after
a very radical revolution of 1848 that brings the working class into power in a significant way?
I think that there are conservative aspects here but it's more complicated than that.
She's breaking too many boundaries. She's emphasizing the importance of landscape,
of animal painting itself, on a scale that is often reserved for history painting.
She's a woman not painting interiors, not painting as an amateur but is painting
at the level of the highest professional. These are radical ideas and I don't think that we can see this
as conservative painting.
And really remarkable accomplishments.