What I want to do in this video is to familiarize ourselves
with the notion of a sequence.
And all sequences is an ordered list of numbers.
So for example, I could have a finite sequence
that means I don't have an infinite number of numbers in it.
Where, let's say I start at one and I keep adding three, so one plus three is four
four plus three is seven, seven plus three is ten.
And let's say I only have these four terms over here
so this one we would call a finite sequence.
I could also have an infinite sequence
so, an example of an infinite sequence
let's say, we start at three and we keep adding four
so, go to three, to seven, to eleven, fifteen.
And you don't always have to add the same thing
we'll explore fancier sequences
one, the sequences where you keep adding the same amount
we call these arithmetic sequences
which we will also, explore in more of a detail.
But to show that this is infinite, to show that we keep this pattern going
on and on and on, I'll put three dots.
This just means we're going to keep going on and on and on so we could call this
an infinite sequence.
Now, there's a bunch of different notations that seem fancy for denoting sequences
but this is all they refer to, but I want to make us comfortable
with how we can denote sequences and also how we can define them.
So we could say, that this right over here
is the sequence, a sub k, for k is going
from one to four, is equal to this right over here.
So when we look at it this way, we can look at each of these as a terms in the sequence
and this right over here would be the first term
we would call that a sub one, this right over here
would be the second term, we call it a sub two, I think you get the picture.
a sub three, this right over here is a sub four.
So this just says all of the a sub k's from k equals one
from our first term all the way to the fourth term.
Now I could also define it by not, explicitly writing the sequence
like this, I could essentially do it using, defining our sequence
as explicitly using a kind of a function notation or something close
to function notation.
So the same exact sequence, I could define it as a sub k
from k equals one to four
with, instead of explicitly writing the numbers here.
I could say a sub k, is equal to some function of k.
So let's see what happens, when k is one we get one
when k is two, we get four, when k is three, we get seven
so see when k is three we added three twice
let me make it clear.
So this was plus three, this right over here was a plus three
this right over here, is a plus three.
So whatever k is, we started at one and we added three
one less than the k term times.
So we could say that this is going to be
equal to one, plus k minus one times three
or maybe I should write three time k minus one, same thing.
Three times k, minus one.
And you can verify that this works
so you can verify that this works.
If k is equal to one, you're gonna get one minus one is zero
and so, a sub one is going to be one, if k is equal to two
you're going to have one plus three which is four.
If k is equal to three, you get three times two plus one is seven
so it works out.
So this is one way to explicitly define our sequence with kind of this function notation.
I want to make it clear, I have essentially defined a function here.
If I wanted more traditional function notation
I could've written a of k, or k is the term that I care about
a of k is equal to one plus three times k minus one.
This is essentially a function where an allowable input
the domain is restricted to positive integers.
Now, how would I denote this business right over here.
Well, I could say this is equal to, and people tend to use a
but I could use the notation b sub k or anything else
but I'll do a again.
A sub k, and here we're going from our first term
so this is a sub one, this is a sub two, all the way to infinity.
Or we could define if we wanted to define an explicitly as a function
we could write the sequence as a sub k, where k starts at the first term
and goes to infinity, with a sub k is equaling, so we're starting at three
and we are adding four, one less time for the second term
we added four once, for the third term we add four twice
for the fourth term we add four three times.
So we're adding four one less than the term that we're at.
So it's going to be plus four times four times k minus one
four times k minus one, so this another way of defining
this infinite sequence.
Now, in both of these cases I defined it as an explicit function
so this right over here is explicit.
This is an explicit function.
And so you might say well what's another way of defining these functions.
Well we can also define it, especially with something like this
Like an arithmetic sequence we can also define it recursively.
And I want to be clear, not every sequence can be defined as either an explicit function
like this or, as a recursive function
but many can, including this which is an arithmetic sequence
where we keep adding the same quantity over and over again.
So how would we do that, well we could also another way of defining this first sequence
we could say a sub k, starting at k equals one, and going to four
with and when you define things recursively, when you define a sequence recursively
you want to define what your first term is with a sub one, equaling one.
And then you can define every other term in the terms of the term before it
and so we could write a of k plus, or let me write it this way
a sub k is equal to the previous term
so this is a sub k minus one, so the given term is equal to the previous term
let me make it clear, this is the previous term, plus the previous term plus
in this case we're adding three every time.
Now how does this make sense, well we're defining what a sub one is
and if someone says, well what happens when k equals two
well they're saying well it's going to be a sub two minus one
so it's going to be a sub one plus three.
Well we know a sub one is one, so it's going to be one plus three, which is four.
Well what about a sub three, well it's going to be a sub two plus three
a sub two we just calculate it as four, you add three it's going to be seven.
This is essentially what we mentally did when I first wrote out the sequence
when I said hey I'm just going to start with one, and I'm just going to add three for every successive term.
So how would we do this one
well once again, we could write this as a sub k, starting at k at the first term
going to infinity with our first term, a sub one is going to be three now
and every successive term a sub k, is going to be the previous term, a sub k minus one plus four.
And once again you start at three, and then if you want the second term
it's going to be the first term plus four, it's going to be three plus four
you get to seven and you keep adding four, so both of these, this right over here is a recursive definition.
We started with kind of a base case, and then every term is defined in terms of the terms before it
or in terms of the function itself, but the function for a different term.