Now on problem number 15.
When it is noon Eastern Standard Time in New York City,
it is 9 am Pacific Standard Time in San Francisco.
Well we know that. There's a three hour difference
between New York and San Francisco.
A plane took off from New York City
at noon Eastern Standard Time.
So it takes off from New York City
at 12 noon Eastern Standard Time.
What time is that in Pacific Standard Time?
Well they're three hours back,
so that's also 9 Pacific Standard Time.
A plane took off in New York City
at 12 noon Eastern Standard Time
and arrived at San Francisco at 4 pm Pacific Standard Time.
So this is am.
And so it goes to SFO,it goes to San Francisco where I live.
I live a little south of San Francisco. But anyway,
so it goes to San Francisco and what time does it get there?
It says 4 pm Pacific Standard Time.
And we know that New York is three hours ahead,
so that's Eastern Standard Time there,
so that's also 7 pm Eastern Standard Time.
I'm an expert at this because I work for a hedge fund
where all we do is schedule a lot of calls
with the company management.
And they happen to, normally,
not be in the same time zone as we are,
so we're pros at scheduling calls across time zones.
So this is like second nature.
I'm enjoying this problem more than most people.
Back to the problem.
If a second plane left San Francisco
at noon Pacific Standard Time--
so at 12 pm Pacific Standard Time, and what is that?
That's also 3 pm Eastern Standard Time-- and took the exact,
same amount of time for the trip, what was the arrival time
Eastern Standard Time in New York City?
So what time is it in Eastern Standard Time?
So the first thing we just have to figure out is
how long does the trip take, and then do the second part.
So how long did this trip take?
This plane left at 12 Eastern and arrived at 7 pm Eastern,
so it took 7 hours. And that was easy,
because we started from 12 and we went to 7, right?
Similarly, if we're going to leave at 3 pm Eastern Time--
because we want to stay in Eastern Time,
because our final answer has to be Eastern Time--
if we leave at 3 pm Eastern Time and take 7 hours,
we're going to get there at 10 pm Eastern Standard Time,
which is choice A.
The trick of this problem is really just staying in one,
consistent time zone the whole time.
You could stay in, maybe,
the Eastern Standard Time the whole time.
Next problem.
It looks like I'll have to draw something.
I'll draw this rectangle.
I'll draw it in yellow.
So let's say this is a rectangle.
And then I'll try my best to draw some of these circles.
We'll just look at the part that's inside of the rectangle,
because I don't feel like erasing all that other stuff.
Well this is not perfect.
These points touch, right?
Actually, let me erase all that other stuff,
because it's distracting.
So I'll erase this.
I'm trying my best to draw neat.
Let me erase all of the rest of the circle just so
it doesn't distract you from what's already drawn there.
Almost done.
Sometimes I feel like that guy who paints pictures on PBS,
because I spend so much time drawing these diagrams.
What's his name, Bob? OK.
So let's see, I was using yellow.
Let me fill that in a little bit. OK.
What are the points that they draw?
They say that that's point Q, point P, point T,
point R, point S.
In rectangle P, Q, R, S above, arcs Q, T
and R, T are quarter circles with centers at P and S. OK.
So these are quarter circles with centers at P and S.
If the radius of each circle is 1--
so the radius is 1, so this is 1, right?
Because this is a radius.
This is the radius of the circle-- this distance is also 1.
What is the area of the shaded region?
So they drew the shaded region as this.
That's the shaded region they did.
So to figure that out we just have to figure out
the area of the larger rectangle,
and then subtract out the areas of these quarter circles.
So what's the area of this larger rectangle?
Well we know its base because this distance is 1,
this distance is 1.
And we know, in general, that this radius is 1.
This distance is 1, and also this distance is 1.
So the entire rectangle is 2 by 1, right?
This is 1. 1 plus 1 is 2, 2 by 1.
So the area of the rectangle-- I'll call that area sub r--
is equal to 2 times 1, which is equal to 2.
Now we just have to figure out
the area of these quarter circles.
So if I had a whole circle with radius 1,
what would its area be?
So it would be area is pi r squared.
And if the radius is 1, the area would is equal to--
well pi times 1 squared is just pi, pi times 1.
So the area would be pi for a full circle, right?
So the area for a quarter circle--
I could do it in this color--
the area of that blue right there,
area of blue would be pi over 4, right?
Because it's a quarter circle, this is pi/4.
And similarly, that one would also be another pi over 4.
So the area of the shaded area
would be the area of the rectangle, which is 2.
You probably can't even see that blue.
The area of the rectangle is 2 minus the area of
each of these quarter circles, minus pi over 4.
And so this would be 2 minus pi over 2, which is choice B.
Next problem.
Looks like more drawing for me.
OK.
So they drew this graph, and I guess I will draw it too,
because the whole point of what I'm doing is trying to
explain to you how to do these problems. Let's see,
so draw my axes x and y.
And then the graph comes in like this.
Then it dips down like this.
And then it goes up like this.
And they give us a couple of points on the graph.
They say that this point here is, 0, 1.
And they say that this point, right there, is 1, 0.
And they say the graph of y equals f of x is shown above.
So this is y is equal to f of x.
Which of the following could be the graph of y
is equal to f of x plus 2?
So if you've done this in class,
this is kind of a traditional shifting problem.
So what you have to realize is, when you take x plus 2--
before when you had, let's say, when x--
let's put it this way.
Before when x and f of-- and y.
Let's do x and y.
When x was equal to 0, y was equal to 1, right?
And when x is equal 1, y is equal to 0.
Now what happens when x and y--
I still want to input 0 into f of x, right?
I still want to input 0 into f of x,
because f of 0 is going to be the same thing.
But if I want to put 0 into f of x,
I have to put a negative 2 in here, right?
Now when x is equal to negative 2,
then this expression here becomes 0, right?
f of negative 2 plus 2 is equal to 0,
so that's equal to the old f of 0.
So then that equals 1.
And if I wanted a 1 here,
I would have to put a minus 1 in for x, right?
Think about it.
If I take a minus 1, and I input it into this expression,
then I get f of 1, right?
If I put minus 1-- my phone is ringing,
it's slightly distracting. But anyway, focus.
I only have 30 seconds left.
But f of minus 1--
Actually, let me continue this into the next thing,
and let me answer my phone.