We're in the British museum and
we're looking at the frieze that went around the Parthenon.
And not exactly on the exterior of the Parthenon...
Inside the porch, basically.
They're carved quite shallow,
and although they would've been painted more brightly,
I still think it would've been a little tough to see.
Essentially what we have is a procession of the citizens of Athens
on the birthday of Athena, patron goddess of Athens
..and it would wind its way through the city
until it actually reach her temple.
Right, the Parthenon.
And inside the Parthenon was a giant sculpture
by Phidias of the goddess Athena.
What we have here then,
is actually not a representation of some mythology
but actually a representation of something
that the Athenians would have lived themselves.
...Yes, and they're putting themselves in the realm of the gods,
because they take part in the procession
looking very ideal and very noble,
and the procession ends with a sacrifice to the gods,
in the presence of the gods and goddesses.
And so in a way the human realm and the divine realm
...that definition dissolves.
Let's take a close look at the procession.
because first of all it's extremely long,
it's on two sides of the building.
The procession actually starts off kind of slowly here
...right, and it gathers momentum and energy.
And we are talking about dozens of horses,
dozens of riders, each one depicted slightly differently.
Horses overlapping horses, overlapping riders.
There is an incredible sense of rhythm and actually movement
I mean all of this is frozen, its stone, right?
Nothing is moving but there is such a complexity
of the hooves of the horses,
of the legs of the horses,
of the legs of the riders...
the anatomy of the horses, the muscles, their veins...
and each one is in a slight,
as you said is in a slightly different position,
but all creating this momentum.
And to my ear, I almost hear, the footfalls of those horses.
The male figures have these wide shoulders and narrow hips,
and beautiful torsos, incredible muscles on their arms
with these very beautiful faces that are very calm.
We see those humans, these Athenians actually controlling the power
and the wildness of nature represented through the horses.
And there's something really wonderful about an animal
that's acting very wild and passionate.
And a human rider just sitting holding its...so nobly,
maybe turning and looking back behind him,
not even worried about that animal that's about to rear up,
but in such control that he can even turn his back on it.
There's something about that that speaks to a kind of nobility and heroism.
So if in fact, the frieze depicts the Panathenaic Procession
and that's generally accepted.
Although there's some other historians that have suggested alternate possibilities.
Then most likely what we are seeing is the folding of the Peplos here
which was actually woven by the Athenians,
It was a great honor
and of course it was ultimately paraded through the city
to drape the statue of the goddess Athena herself
in the temple, the Parthenon.
This group of sculptures would have been directly over the main entrance to the Parthenon
The Parthenon itself could actually be surmounted from any direction.
In order to walk into the main chamber
you would have walked directly under this, and so...
...and you would've looked up at the gods.
These are in lustic condition,
and there's a kind of stillness here
and a more of an isolation to the figures
than these rough and tumble of the horses and the riders
in the procession that I love so much.
But what's really remarkable in these figures
is the treatment of the drapery.
It's almost like there was a sculptor,
who under Phidias' direction,
just loved playing with the patterns of the drapery.
They swirl and move, and gather.
We were looking at three figures here,
who sit facing each other, but one turns away,
and there's one figure here who just..
I've never seen anything...
Ares, the god of war
Is that who it is?
Yeah
It's so human, and so divine at the same time, and even though we
can't see his face, there's a kind of total
confidence and idealism to his body, and the way he holds his body
and the way he moves and he lifts up his knee and leans back
and looks on, and has a sense of
total tranquility, and yet his gesture is so human
There is a kind of complete comfort within his own body
that the sculpture is able to express just exquisitely.
But its remarkable for its variety, for its complexity, for its unity..
...for its understanding of the variety of human experience of motion
of the relationship between animal and man, and man and god
and very much in that way is a mirror, of the way the Greeks saw
themselves and the world.