In the last video we studied a super simplified economy that only sold one good or service.
But now let's think about things a little bit more generally a little bit, you know, more complex economies.
And let's say that in year one economists have determined
that the level of prices of goods and services produced in that economy is a 100.
So they've esencially just multiplied and divided it by right numbers
so that their index that they generate just says that is 100.
And they do this so that they can measure the prices
in other years relative to year one.
So let's say in year two using their index,
they realise that prices are now 110.
Now this is not a simple thing to do.
This would have been a very simple thing to do if there was only one good
or service in the economy, like our last example - apples.
You could have just taken the price of apples that went from 50 cents to 55 cents.
In real world this is not a simple thing to do. You have gazillion goods and services.
Some prices go up, some prices go down.
The quantities of the goods and services change in fact.
They might be goods and services that are offered in year one but don't exist any more in year two
There are goods and services in year two that didn't exist in year one.
But for the sake of this video let's just assume that economists are able to say this
If you call the generell level of prices a 100 in year one
it's now a 110 or in other way that think about there're things of gotten 10 % more expensive.
Now if we assuming that we had we know this relationship it's one again it's an easy thing
to figure out and it actually turns out there is no perfect way to do this
How can we figure out the relationship between real GDP and nominal GDP?
And remember whenever we talk about real GDP so we talk about real GDP in year two
So real GDP in year two.
Whatever you talk about real GDP you're talking about GDP in terms of the prices in some base year.
So in this example we think about real GDP in year two in terms of year one dollars.
So whatever were goods and services that we produced in year two,
we're going to think about, what if they were in the same prices as in year one.
That would give us the real GDP in year two.
So one what we think about it really just a ratio
So the ratio, so let's me write, nominal GDP,
so this is GDP in year two measured in year two dollars,
devided by, I guess we call this as proportion really,
devided by a real GDP in year two and is measured in year one dollars.
Well, that's going to be the same thing as the ratio of the prices between year two and year one.
This is going to be the ratio of, we use the syndicate right over here, 110 to 100.
I want you to sitting thing about this for second.
It's just saying "Look, the same goods, these are measuring the same goods and services
The real GDP is mesauring them in year one prices. The nominal GDP is mesauring them in year two prices.
So things got 10 % more expensive between year one and year two.
The nominal GDP should be 10 % larger than real GDP.
We should have in exactly same ratios.
And now we can manipuliate this thing using any type of algebra that we want.
For example we could say "Well, nominal GDP not that's right nominal now, but this is right a kind of specify that exaclly we're talking about
This is a nominal GDP of year two
So now we could say nominal GDP is equal to we can multiplay boatsides times that's the real GDP.
It's equal to 110 over 100 times the real GDP.
Remember it's real GDP in year two measured in year one dollars.
Or we can measure, we can devide, we can devide boatsides of this equation by this 110 over 100
and then we get nominal GDP in year two devided by 110 is egual to real GDP.
This is nominal GDP in year two.
And writing in this way the kind of feels like you're taking nominal GDP in year two
and prices have increased, there would be the generall increase in the level od prices
that's cold price infaltion. We see that right over here and now we're deflating it
to get real GDP. We're dividing it by the ratio of the prices.
We're dividing it esencially by how much the prices have gone.
I guess that's say the ratio between the year two prices and year one prices.
This quantity right over here is 1.1
So another way you could think we're deflating the nominal GDP in year two
to get the real GDP in year two or getting it in, remember this is in year one prices.
And because od that this number right over here, this number right over here is refered to as the deflator
This is our GDP deflator.
You pick up base year and in this case was year one that base year could be 1985 it could be 2006, and also it could be anything.
Your GDP deflator is going to be relative to that base year.
Well, that base year was a 100, your deflator, was gonna say, how much things are now in this year?
And you can even go backwords in time. Year 0 that deflator might be even 1985 because maybe things are going cheaper.
Or you could actually had prices go down
You could actually had deflation, so maybe in year two your deflator would be 98.
But the reason why it's called the deflator
it's because generally you have infaltion's time goes on
and generally you're going to be defalting your nominal GDP
You're going divideing it by value gradeor than one
It's going to be something over 100 divided by 100, which is your base year to get your real GDP.