What we're going to prove in this video is a couple of fairly
straight forward parallelogram related proofs
And this first one we're gonna say,
"Hey, if we have this parallelogram ABCD,
let's prove that the opposite sides have the same length "
So, prove that AB is equal to DC and that AD is equal to BC
So, let me draw a diagonal here
So, I'm gonna draw a diagonal
And this diagonal, depending on how you view it is intersecting
two sets of parallel lines so you can also consider it
to be a transversal
Actually let me draw a little bit neater than that
I can do a better job
So, nope that's not any better
That is about as good as I can do
So, if we look, view DB, this diagonal DB, we can view it
as a transversal for the parallel lines AB and DC
And if you view it that way, you can pick out that angle ABD
is going to be congruent
So, angle ABD, that's that angle right there is going to be
congruent to angle BDC because they are alternate interior angles
You have a transversal, parallel lines
So, we know that angle ABD is going to be congruent
to angle BDC
Now you can also view this diagonal DB, you can view
this as a transversal of these two parallel lines,
of the other two pair of parallel lines, AD and BC
And if you look at it that way you'll immediately see that angle
DBC, right over here, angle DBC is going to be congruent to angle
ADB for the exact same reason, they are alternate interior angles
of a transversal intersecting these two parallel lines
So, I could write this
This is alternate interior angles are congruent when you have
a transversal intersecting two parallel lines
And we also see that both of these triangles,
triangle ADB and triangle CDB both share the side over here
It's obviously equal to itself
Now, why is this useful
Well, you might realize that we've just shown that both of these
triangles, they have this pink angle and they have this side
in common and then they have the green angle
Pink angle, side in common and then the green angle
So, we've just shown by angle-side-angle that these
two triangles are congruent
So, let me write this down
We have shown that triangle -- I'll go from non-labeled to pink
non-labeled to pink to green -- CBD and this comes out of
angle-side-angle congruency
So, this is from angle-side-angle congruency
Well, what does that do for us
Well, if two triangles are congruent then all of the corresponding
features of the two triangles are going to be congruent
In particular, side DC corresponds to side BA --
side DC on this bottom triangle corresponds to side BA
on the top triangle
So, they need to be congruent
So, DC
So, we get DC is going to be equal to BA and that's
because they are corresponding sides of congruent triangles
So, this is going to be equal to that and by that exact same logic,
AD corresponds to CB
AD is equal to CB and for the exact same reason:
corresponding sides of congruent triangles
And then we're done!
We've proven that opposite sides are congruent
Now, let's go the other way
Let's say that we have some type of a quadrilateral
and we know that the opposite sides are congruent,
can we prove to ourselves that this is a parallelogram
Well, it's kind of the same proof in reverse
So, let's draw a diagonal here,
since we know a lot about triangles
So, let me draw
There we go
That's the hardest part, let's see
Draw at a -- that's pretty good
Alright
So, we obviously know that CB is going to be equal to itself
So, I'll draw it like that
We obviously 'cause that's the same line
And then we have something interesting
We've split this quadrilateral to two triangles: triangle ACB
and triangle DBC
And notice, they have all three sides of these two triangles
are equal to each other
So, we know that by side-side-side that they are congruent
So, we know that triangle, I'm gonna start at A and I'm going
to the one half side, so, ACB is congruent to triangle DBC
and this is by side-side-side congruency
Well, what does that do for us
Well, it tells us all the corresponding angles
are going to be congruent
So, for example, ABC, angle ABC is going to be
you can see ABC -- is going to be congruent to DCB,
angle DCB and you can say by you can say corresponding angles
congruent of congruent triangles
I'm just using some short hand here to save some time
So, ABC is going to be congruent to DCB
So, these two angles are going to be congruent
Well, this is interesting because here you have a long line
and it's intersecting AB and CD and we clearly see that these
things that could be alternate angles, alternate interior angles,
are congruent
And because we have these congruent alternate interior angles
we know that AB must be parallel to CD
So, this must be parallel to that
So, we know that AB is parallel to CD by alternate interior angles
of transversal intersecting parallel lines
Now, we can use that exact same logic
angle ACB is congruent to angle DBC
and we know that by corresponding
angles congruent of congruent triangles
So, we're just saying that this angle is equal to that angle
Well, once again these could be alternate interior angles,
they look like they could be, this is a transversal
and here's two lines here which we're not sure they're parallel
but because the alternate interior angles are congruent
we know that they are parallel
So, this is parallel to that
So, we know that AC is parallel to BD by alternate interior angles
And we're done!
So, what we've done is interesting
We've shown if you have a parallelogram, opposite sides are,
opposite sides have the same length
And if opposite sides have the same length then you have
a parallelogram
And so, we've actually proven it in both directions
And so we can actually make what you call
an if-and-only-if statement
You can say, "If opposite sides are parallel of a quadrilateral "
Or you could say, "Opposite sides of quadrilateral are parallel
if and only if their lengths are equal "
And you can say "if and only if"
So, if they are parallel then you can say their lengths are equal
and only if their lengths are equal are they're parallel
We've prove it in both directions