On a string instrument, the length of a string "l"
varies inversely as the frequency.
So, l = k*1/f.
An 11-inch string has a frequency of 400 cycles per second
So, f = 400 cycles / second
Find the constant of proportionality and
then find the frequency of a 10 inch string
So 11 = k *1/400. So to solve for the constant of proportionality
we will mutiply both sides by 400 cycles / second
so the left hand side becomes 400 * 11 = 4400 cycles*inches/second
4400 cycles*inches/second = k
We can say the length = 4400cycles*inches/second * 1/f
Now we are taking of a situation where l= 10 inches
10 inches = 4400 cycles*inches/second * 1/f
We could mutiply both sides by "f" & we can also divide
both sides by 10 inches.
Left hand side we are left with "f" = frequency
Right hand side we have 4400/10 = 440cycles/second
So when our string is 10 inches long
our frequency has increased to 440 cycles/second
So when our string was 11 inches long f= 400cycles/second
when our string is shorter at 10 inches our
f has increased to 440 cycles/second