ine of the great renessaince spaces
is the Pazzi chapel of Santa Croce
and we are sitting in it, and we're sitting on a bench that lines the wall
because this was originally used as a chapter house
meaning a meeting room for the monks of Santa Croce
so the would have sat right were we're sitting
just of the cloister
which is the traditional place for the chapter house, so we're really looking at
something that is true really renesaince
work of architecture by Brunelleschi although it was completed after
his death and we see all of these
That we come to expect if burleneschi these of petra serena
green, stone that articulates the
elements on the wall but it also articulates the walls themselves
and the dominance of the perfect geometry
so we immediately have sense of rectangles and squares
and circles and semicircles but
my overwhelming feeling of walking here was that
into an ancient Roman tample
a so thisi is very close to a central planned space
it's something like the Pantheon and there is
intenion to the kind of perfect geometry
and centrality that we realy do associate with the ancient world so I think you're right
I think he's been woring very hard to create these
classicism this revival of the
ideas os ancient world, lovely
pluted philaters long walls and the hemispherical
dome with oculars in the centre and windows
piercing it sides of this really lovely
light taht comes into the chapel, the dome on pendentives and
inpendentive triangular spaces
that the dome rests on
we see roundels, terracotta and
this what have been made by Luca de la Robbia who has recently
perfected the ability to fire to the high temperature
what he used what we consider modern glazes
raly is the sesne of a centrally planned space