In the last video we tried to relate what 13.7 billion years really means
by compressing it to ten years, which is still a pretty long time, at least from our perspective.
And we saw that these huge periods of time, everything that's happened
since the United States Declaration of Independence
all gets compressed into just five seconds!
And that's, you know, that's not much when you think about ten years. I mean ten years!
You would wait around a lot, that's a huge amount of time.
So hopefully that put things in perspective a little bit.
What I want to do in this video is kind of do the same thing but
relate the 13.7 billion years if that were a distance
or the length of a timeline how big each of these periods would be.
So just to start off, if the timeline...
I'm recording this in High Definition right now.
There should be 1280 pixels wide, depending on where you're watching it,
so maybe you're watching it on a High-Def TV.
If the timeline was the width of my screen right over here
If the timeline was the width of my screen here
So if that was 13.7 billion years from there
let's say this is the beginning of the universe
and this is our present time
If that was 13.7 billion years the amount of time that humans, modern humans,
the people who look and think like us
the amount of time that we have been on this planet
will not even be a pixel
This little dot I drew is multiple pixels.
The amount of time we have been here would not even be a pixel
In fact a pixal, and that dot I drew is about four pixals, But a pixel
just one little pixal on my screen
would represent eleven million years.
Let me scroll over
It would represent eleven million, eleven million years.
So if this was the timeline the dinosaurs would have been extinct
about six pixels from the end.
So it would be right about...
So six pixels from the end is when the dinosaurs would have gotten extinct and
the amount of time that modern humans are on the planet
wouldn't even register here.
It would be one twentieth of that pixel over there.
In fact if we just expanded that very last pixel...
If we were to expand that very last pixel, I'll do it in yellow,
the very last tiny pixel that you can't see if we were to expand that