Conflict theory is a way of studying society
that focuses on the inequalities
of different groups in society.
It is based on ideas of Karl Marx in the 19th century
who believed a society evolved
through several stages.
The most important which were:
Feudalism, Capitalism and finally Socialism.
19th century Europe was a capitalist society
where rich upper class called "Bourgeoisie"
were minority of the population
and poor lower class
called "Proletariat" were majority.
Now you may think that majority would have
more sway over the society
but it was actually Bourgeoisie
that had the power.
They owned the factories
that produced everything people needed
and they sold what they produced
to earn living.
The Proletariat only had their labour to sell
to make a living and
they were dependent on factory owners to get paid.
But this wasn't just one side of dependence.
The factory owners were also dependent on workers
to work in the factories though they've never admit it
because they would lose some of their power.
There is a significant economic inequality
between factory owners and the workers.
It was this economic inequality that
Marx believed would fuel change in society.