Let's do one more example dealing with displacement, velocity and time. So we have: If Marcia travels
for 1 minute at 5 m/s to the south, how much will she be displaced? And so we know, we know that
that velocity (let me do it this way) we know that velocity is equal to displacement
is equal to displacement divided by time, it's really once again, it is change in time
but we'll just say time, that's implicitly change in time
and if you manipulate this a little bit
you really just multiply both sides by time
you just multiply both sides by the variable 't'
you get displacement, cuz this cancels out...
...you get displacement, and I'll flip this around
I'll write...what's on the righthand side I'll write on the left
so you get displacement is equal to time times velocity
or velocity times time
is equal to velocity times time or velocity times change in time
so over here they're asking for displacement
they're asking us how much did Marcia get displaced
and they're saying that she travels for one minute
so this one minute right over here, this is her time
sometimes you can do that as her change in time
it really is her change in time
whatever...you know...if it said 0 minutes on her stopwatch when she started
at the end it'll say 1 minute
or if it starts at 5 minutes, or maybe it was 3:05 when she started, it'll be 3:06 when she finish
it was really the change in time
once again, I won't write the delta there, just cuz
it keeps it...this is the way you most frequently see it
but I want to tell you that these are the same thing for the purpose of this problem
because sometimes you'll see the delta there
so the one minute, the 't' right over here is one minute...
...one minute...
...at 5 meters per second to the south
this right over here is the velocity
they give us the magnitude, which is 5 meters per second
or you could say that's the speed
and they also give us the direction, to the south
so this right over here
is 5 meters per second to the south
so we might just say, hey if we want displacement
that's just going to be equal to
5 meters per second to the south times 1 minute
the problem here is, when we talk about displacement
we're going to think about a magnitude of how much its moved
so it'll be a distance of some kind, and some direction
we have our direction here, but we don't want any other units there
and if we just multiply this over here
we have a minute over here, but we have seconds in the denominator
you can't just cancel out a minute and a second
so you can't just say you're going to get 5, and have some weird thing here
so in order for it to all work out
you either have to convert the 5 meters per second to meters per minute
or let me phrase it in another way
you have to convert the 5 meters per second to some amount of meters per minute
not 5 meters per minute, it's going to be different
or you convert the 1 minute to seconds
so at least in my mind it's easier to convert 1 minute to seconds
so let's do that
so this is the same thing
1 minute times...
and we want to get rid of the minute, the minute is essentially the numerator right now
we can put this over one
but it's essentially the numerator
so we want to divide by minutes
and we want to multiply by seconds
we want seconds in the numerator
and so what is...how many seconds are there per minute?
you have 60 seconds for every 1 minute
and so you have a minute canceling out with the minutes
and so now you have 5 meters per second to the south times 60 seconds
this is now cool, cuz you now have seconds and seconds
I wrote 'sec' there, but this is also 'sec'
so now you have seconds over seconds, those cancel out
so your displacement is going to be equal to 5 times 60
and then your units left are meters
all the time units have canceled out
and it's meters to the south
and this is equal to...5 times 60 is 300 meters to the south
and we are done, that's how much she has been displaced
if they just wanted the distance, you can say that she traveled 300 meters
just that part, the magnitude of the displacement...
...that is the distance that she traveled