Solve for x, and we have the absolute value of 2x minus 5 is equal to 11.
Now, the big insight you need to have whenever you have an absolute value equation like this
is to remember, if I have the absolute value of a is equal to 11
what do we know about a?
That means that a is either equal to 11
OR, what else could a be?
It could be negative 11.
Because there are two possible a's that are exactly 11 away from zero.
It could be positive 11, or it could be negative 11.
That's the exact same logic you apply to an equation like this.
If the absoulte value of 2x minus 5 is equal to 11
that means that the stuff inside the absolute value sign either equals 11
or the stuff inside the absolute value sign is equal to NEGATIVE 11.
Because if this is equal to 11, the absolute value of 11 is 11,
If this thing over here is equal to negative 11, when you take its absolute value
it'll still be equal to 11.
So, let's write that down - so 2x minus 5 could be equal to 11,
or 2x minus 5 could be equal to negative 11.
In either case its absolute value is 11.
Now, let's just solve each of these equations.
Over here we can add 5 to both sides
of this equation - we get 11 plus 5 is 16, 2x minus 5 plus 5 is just 2x.
2x is equal to 16, divide both sides by 2, we get x is equal to 8.
Now let's do this situation.
2x minus 5 is equal negative 11 - let's add 5 to both sides of this equiation.
On the left hand side we just get 2x because the 5's cancel out.
2x is equal to negative 11 plus 5, that's negative 6.
And we can divide both sides by 2
and we get x is equal to negative 3.
So we've got two solutions, depending on whether this thing in here is equal to 11 or negative 11.
We got x to be equal to 8, in which case 2x minus 5 would be 11,
or we have x is equal to negative 3, in which case 2x minus 5 is equal to negative 11.
Let's verify it.
So, if x is equal to 8, let's show that it satisfies this equation.
So we'd get 2 times 8, minus 5. The absolute value of 2 times 8, minus 5 should be 11.
2 times 8 is 16, minus 5 gives 11.
So the absolute value of 11 is 11, we know that's true.
It all works out.
Now let's try when x is equal to negative 3.
We get the absolute value of 2 times negative 3, minus 5.
should be equal to 11. So what's 2 times negative 3?
2 times negative 3 is negative 6, minus 5 gives negative 11.
The absolute value of negative 11 is 11, so we get 11 is equal to 11,
so they BOTH work.