So one of the main purposes of accounting for anything of making these accounting statements in the first place
is so that you can reflect what's going on in a buisness and that might be for investors, to see how a buisness is doing, or it might be for the managers of a buisness
So they can see where the buisness is doing well, where it's not doing well, or maybe how rescorces should be allocated
So let's se which of these two methods of accouting, the cash method and the accrual method
Give a better indication of what's actually going on in the buisness, and the way I did it in the first two videos, the first column over here
This is the cash basis of accounting and this is the accrual, and let's just look at the income statement
We are assuming a very simple world, were the is no taxes, we have no debt, we have no intrest or things
like that. We just litterally have Revenue and just a simple profit.
And we'll make it more complicated in the future
So this right here you could view as our income statement.
This is our income statement for month one on a Cash basis and a Accurual basis
Now when you look at either basis on month one, it's the same thing so it's not that interesting
But let's go to month two. On the cash basis of accounting it looks like you just lost $200
To a outsider who doesn't know the details of what's actually going on it would seem somthing shady
is going on or it's a money losing buisness.
"Why would I want to invest in this buisness that's losing $200 a month?"
But if you look at the accrual basis it better reflects that you actually did some catering
that month. As a matter of fact, you did a pretty large catering.
So if you recognise the Revenue for the service you actually did that month, that $400
You could say look, I performed services that will earn me $200 in the future
Assuming the customer is good for the money.
And instead of putting that $400 in cash, because you didn't get the cash you can't do that,
We said look, the customer owes us $400, which is still a asset
A asset is anything someone owes you some future benefit.
So the customer is going to give you cash in the future.
Cash is a asset because you can use it to buy stuff and get people to do stuff for you
To get some future benefit.
So both cash and Accounts Receivables are assets.
So in month two I think it's fair that the Accrual method is giving us a better indication
of what's actually going on.
Let's go to month three. When you look at the example, you actually did nothing on month three.
You could have gone on vacation on month three.
There was no catering done.
But on a cash basis it looks like it was your best catering month ever
Because you got $600 inflow in cash.
And you didn't have to spend any expenses because you didn't do any accounting.
But when you look at the Accrual basis it actually reflected what happened.
You had no Revenue and no expenses assosiated with the Revenue.
So once again, to a outsider they'd say maybe you took a break, maybe a vactation,
Or maybe it was just slow time in your buisness.
And you don't recognize these $200 in advance
Because you didn't do anything to get it.
You said: Look. I got this $200. It's a cash advance.
You could even say it's a cash advance from customers.
But I'm not recognizing the Revenue in the month that I got it.
I'm waiting until I actually do the service. So I'm deferring the Revenue.
So you defer it to month four, when you actually perform the service.
On the cash basis it looks like you lost money again.
So hopefully this gives you a idea of why accrual gives a better picture
of what's happening in a buisness.
In the next video, I'll try to reconcile what the Accrual income statement is telling us
and the actual cash.
Because right now it might look a little mysterious.