There's been a lot of talk lately about the fiscal cliff
which sounds very dramatic
and what I want to do in this video is
at least lay out the numbers so that we are all on the same page, and then
in the next few videos
think about the implications
or how the negotiations between the President and the Congress might actually work out.
so the first thing to frame this conversation is
just where the budget is right now
so let me draw a little graph
so let me make this axis right over here represent our budget
now I want to make this as big as possible
so that we can get a little bit of granular detail
on how much the budge might move based on how the negotiations work out
so let's say that this line is roughly 4 trillion dollars long
so that's 4 trillion, and half way would be about 2 trillion
and between 2 and 4, you got 3 trillion
then 1 trillion would be right over here.
1 trillion
then I'm going to do some bar charts to show the different scenarios.
and as I do this, keep in mind the size of the US economy
the US economy is approximately 15.5 trillion dollars
so that is roughly our GDP, depends on which year you're measuring
but that gives us at least a frame of reference for
what chunk of GDP we are talking about when we talk about the federal budget.
So let's start with the 2012 budget.
So in 2012, the US government is spending 3.6 trillion dollars.
So let me make my graph a little more granular
so this would be 3.5
so 3.6 would be right around here.
so let me draw that
and I'll do it in... I'll do this purple color for the expenditures
so this is how much the federal government
spent, or I guess is spending in 2012
so~ just like that
Alright. There we go. So that's expenditures.
Now, you are probably aware,
that we don't have all of the revenue
we didn't bring in 3.6 trillion in taxes,
so this right over here is 3.6 trillion
our revenue that we get through tax revenue and other things is somewhat less
It in 2012 was on the order of 2.5 trillion.
So I'll draw that right over here,
so 2.5 trillion and I'll do it in this green color
So this is how much revenue was brought in,
so let me write this down.
This is 2.5 trillion
Now let's think about how much might get spent under the different scenarios.
So first I'll layout a rough approximation of Obama's budget proposal for 2013.
So Obama in 2013.
So on the spending side,
he sees, or would like to see spending go up by 200 billion
so let's see this,
so on the spending side, we're going to add 200 billion
and in the next few videos, we could talk the pros and cons,
the arguments for and against, something like that
so let me draw that
so relative to the 3.6, we're now at 3.8
so this, you have a spending increase of...
so plus 200 billion, that gets us to 3.8 trillion in total expenditures
If my best estimate of what what the Republicans in Congress would want,
so let's write... let's say Republican-
Republicans in 2013 is that they would actually-
ideally wants spending cuts from these levels
so let's draw that out...
and roughly on the order of about 100 billion
so roughly on the order of 100 billion- and they might want even more than that
but let's just go with that for now.
So that gets us to a budget of 3.5 trillion.
so that's about that right over there
3.5 trillion
so once again, relative to 2012
you're going down by 100 billion (let me make that clear)
you're going- you're subtracting 100 billion
now in the Fiscal Cliff scenario
the Fiscal Cliff scenario, the spending will be similar to the Republican ideal right over here
so let me write this right over here: Fiscal Cliff
Fiscal cliff- we are also spending-
we are cutting on the order of 100 billion in government expenditures
so let's draw that
so at least on the expenditure side-
and these are all very rough
I'm sure that there're Republicans who'd agree and disagree with this
but I'm trying to get my best sense of...
kind of an aggregate view on things
so... the fiscal cliff- we are also cutting spending by 100 billion.
by one- so we are cutting by 100 billion
Now, let's go to the revenue side of things.
In all these scenarios for 2013,
and just to be clear, the fiscal cliff- that's also for 2013
in all of these scenarios, we get the same revenue
from... that we got in 2012- let me draw that
plus we get another 100 billion from the growth in the economy
As the economy grows, and if you're tax rates are completely constant
you're also going to get more more revenue for the federal government
so you get about 100 billion, you get 100 billion from the federal government
so that get's us to 2.6 trillion,
2.6 trillion without changing anything
so let me just shade all of these in really fast
so that takes us to 2.6 trillion
so let's shade that at one end
shade that one end
and then shade that one end.
Now, as you probably heard on the news
Obama would like to extend the Bush tax cuts for the middle class,
and he considers the middle class those who are making less than 250 thousand dollars for a family
but he would like to not extend the bush tax cuts on the ridge and like to actually include a few other tax increases also on the wealthy
and so you would get an increase of revenue, under Obama's plan, of 300 billion
300 billion- and this is once again very rough
there's probably 50, 60 billion that I'm not fully accounting for
but it will give you the rough picture
so this is 300 billion
and what Obama's doing here
or at least in the proposal, as far as I can gleam
none of it is that simple
what they're talking about right over here
is extend the tax cuts for middle class
...for middle class...
which my best reading seems like,
we would lose a little under 200 billion of revenue
but then we keep the tax cuts
or we... we let the tax cuts on the wealthy expire
so that gets us 200 of this
\and there are other tax increases,
and other (mumble) I guess removing loopholes
and whatever else that increases this to 300 billion
So let's compare the deficit
let's compare the deficit, so this gets us to-
in the Obama scenario we end up with 2.9 trillion in revenue
So let's compare what the deficit did from 2012 to Obama's budget plan
So in 2012 you take 3.6 billion and subtract out 2.5 trillion
there's a gap of 1.1 trillion
This is the deficit- this is how much the government has to borrow in 2012
Under Obama's budget, what would be for 2013?
Well, we're spending 3.8 trillion,
we are getting 2.9 trillion
so you have a gap of 900 billion.
900 billion
He- so there is some deficit reduction
although the deficit is still quite large
the deficit reduction is 200 billion
100 billion of that came from economic growth
and then the rest is coming from ... a good chunk of that is coming from increased taxes
or letting- depending on how you view it- either increase taxes on the wealthy
or not letting the tax cuts expire on the wealthy
Now let's think about the Republican situation
Well you have 2.6 trillion in revenue
and you have 3.5 trillion (and let me write this down)
you have 3.5 trillion in expenditure
and once again you have on the order of 900 billion gap
so in terms of deficit reduction, these things look pretty similar
you have a very similar deficit
Obama is increasing spending
and he would argue that he is investing in things that might help stimulate the economy
or invest in America for the future
and then he is making it up by letting the tax cuts on the wealthy expire for the most part
The Republicans want to cut spending
but they're also letting the tax cuts continue
so you essentially have the same level of deficit reduction
Now, I think we are ready to talk about the Fiscal Cliff.
The Fiscal Cliff- we're spending 100 billion less
and then we're also letting all of the tax cuts for, both the wealthy-
those ab- those who are earning at a family level of 250 thousand
and for the middle-class; we're letting them all expire.
And so, we have revenue increase by 400 billion.
So this goes up by 400 billion.
So plus 400 billion
and so that takes us roughly- and once again this is all rough-
to about 3 trillion in revenue, and 3.5 trillion in expenses
and your deficit, under the Fiscal Cliff scenario
the deficit is going to going to be 500 billion dollars
Now you might say, Hey, this is great!
When everyone talks about the deficit, deficit is a scary thing
we're borrowing from the future, and all that
Why are people so afraid of the Fiscal Cliff?
The reality is, is that if you take 500 billion out of the economy
so 100 billion through spending cuts
and then 100- and then 400 billion from tax increases
so the government is deleveraging
but that money is being sucked out of the economy
and you could argue that there's kind of a multiplier effect as well
that that might endanger what is already a very precarious recovery
that the recovery is really just starting to happen
and if we were to suck all of the money out of the economy-
that's what the argument would be-
then that might throw us into another resession
or that might make the recovery that much weaker
in the next few videos, we'll discuss that in a little more depth
see what people are saying the impact might be
and what the argument might be in either case.