We're asked to shade 20% of the square below.
Before doing that, let's just even think about
what percent means.
Let me just rewrite it.
20% is equal to-- I'm just writing it out as a word--
20 percent, which literally means 20 per cent.
- Let me break it out -
which is the same thing as 20 per cent.
And if you're familiar with the word century,
you might already know that cent comes from the Latin
for the word hundred.
This literally means you can take cent,
and that literally means 100.
So this is the same thing as 20 per 100.
20% means you're really going to meet
That means if you want to shade 20%,
if you break up the square into 100 pieces,
we want to shade 20 of them. 20 per 100.
So how many squares have they drawn here?
So if we go horizontally right here, we have 1, 2, 3,
4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10 squares.
If we go vertically, we have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
6, 7, 8, 9, 10.
So this is a 10 by 10 square.
So it has 100 squares here.
Another way to say it is that this larger square-- I guess
that's the square that they're talking about.
This larger square is a broken
up into 100 smaller squares,
so it's already broken
up into the 100.
So if we want to shade 20% of
that, we need to shade 20 of
every 100 squares that
it is broken into.
So with this, we'll just
literally shade in 20 squares.
So let me just do one.
So if I just do one square, just
like that, I have just
shaded 1 per 100
of the squares.
100 out of 100 would
be the whole.
I've shaded one of them.
That one square by itself
would be 1%
of the entire square.
If I were to shade another one,
if I were to shade that
and that, then those two
combined, that's 2% of the
entire square.
It's literally 2 per 100,
where 100 would
be the entire square.
If we wanted to do 20, we do
one, two, three, four-- if we
shade this entire row, that
will be 10%, right?
One, two, three, four, five,
six, seven, eight, nine, ten.
And we want to do 20, so that'll
be one more row.
So I can shade in this whole
other row right here.
And then I would have shaded
in 20 of the 100 squares.
Or another way of thinking about
it, if you take this
larger square, divide it into
100 equal pieces, I've shaded
in 20 per 100, or 20%, of the
entire larger square.
Hopefully, that makes sense.