The goal of this video is to explore some of the concepts or
formulas you might see in the traditional Physics class but
even more importantly to see that they are really just common sense ideas.
So let's just start with a simple example.
Let's say that, and for the sake of this video just so I don't
have to keep saying this is the magnitude of the velocity,
this is the direction of the velocity, et cetera.
Let's just assume that if I have positive number that it means
for example if I have a positive velocity it means that I am
going to the right and let's say if I have a negative number
which we won't see in this video, let's assume that I'm going
to the left and that way I can just write a number down -we're
only operating in one dimension- you know that it is
specifying what the magnitude and the direction.
If I said that the velocity was 5 metres per second that
means 5 metres per second to the right.
If I said it is negative 5 metres per second that means
it's 5 metres per second to the left.
Now let's just say, just for simplicity, let's just say that if we
start with an initial velocity, we start with an initial velocity of
5 meters per second
Once again I am specifying with a magnitude and the direction
because of this convention here.
We know it is to the right
and let's say that we have a constant acceleration
we have a constant acceleration at play
of 2 meters per second per second, or 2 m/s^2
and once again since this is positive, it is, to the right
and let's say that we do this for a duration
so my change in time is...let's say we do this for a duration of 4 s
so s for this video is seconds
So what I want to do is think about how far
how far do we travel?
Well there's two things here.
How far or how fast are we going, after 4 seconds
and how far have we traveled over the course of those 4 seconds
So let's draw ourselves a little bit of a diagram here
so this is my velocity axis
and this over here is my time axis
(let me draw a straighter line than that)
so that is my time axis
This is velocity, that is my velocity right over there
and I'm starting off at 5 m/s
this is 5 m/s right over here
so V_i is equal to 5 m/s
and then every second that goes by, I'm going 2 m/s faster
because it's 2 meters per second per second!
so every second that goes by
so after 1 second...I'm going to go 2 m/s faster...so I'll be at 7
Or another way to think about it
is the slope of this velocity line is my constant acceleration
I have a constant slope here
So it might look something like that
So what has happened after 4 seconds?
so 1...2...3...4...so this is my delta t
So my final velocity is going to be right over there
(I'll write it down here because it's getting in the way of this word velocity)
And so this is V_f, this is my final velocity
and what would it be?
Well I'm starting at 5 m/s, so I'm going to do it both ways...
using the variables and using the concrete numbers
So I'm starting at some initial velocity
the subscript i says i for initial
And then each second that goes by, I'm getting this much faster
So if I want to see how much faster have I gone
I multiply the number of seconds that go by times my acceleration
And once again, this right here
I just wrote the subscript c saying it's a constant acceleration
And so that will tell me how fast I've gone
If I start at this point, and I multiply the duration times my slope
I will get this high, I will get to my final velocity
and just to make it clear with the numbers
These numbers really could be anything
I'm just picking these to make it concrete in your mind
You have 5 m/s plus 4 seconds
(I'm going to do that in yellow)
plus 4 seconds
times our acceleration of 2 m/s^2
And what is this going to be equal to?
You have the seconds cancelling out with one of the seconds down here
You have 4 times, (so let me write it)
So you have 5 meters per second, plus, 4 times 2 is 8
8, this seconds is gone so we're just left with m/s.
or this is the same thing as 13 m/s which is going to be our final velocity.
And i wanna take a pause here (and you can pause here and think about it yourself)
This hopefully should be intuitive
We were starting at going 5 m/s
Every second that goes by, we're going to go 2 m/s faster.
So after 1 second, we'll be at 7 m/s
after 2 seconds we will be at 9 m/s.
After, after 3 seconds we will be at 11 m/s.
And then after 4 seconds we will be at 13 m/s.
So you multiply how much time passed times acceleration, this is how much faster we are going to be going.
We are already going 5 m/s, 5 plus how much faster, 13 m/s
So this right up here is 13 m/s.
So, I'll take a little pause here,hopefully that is intuitive.
And the whole point of that is to show that this formula that you'll often see in many physics books
It's not just something that randomly popped out of air.
It just makes complete common sense.
Now the next thing I want to talk about is what is the total distance we would have traveled?
Now we know from the last video that distance is just the area under this curve right over here.
So it's just the area under this curve.
Oh yea, you see this is kind of a strange shape right here,
how do I calculate its area?
Now we can just use a little simple geometry to break it down into 2 different areas.
That are very easy to calculate the areas.
Or 2 simple shapes, you can break it down into this blue part, this rectangle right over here.
Easy to figure out the area of a rectangle.
And we can break it down into this purple part, this triangle right here.
Easy to figure out the area of a triangle.
And that will be the total distance we traveled.
And even this will hopefully make some intuition.
Because this blue area is how far would we have traveled if we were not accelerating,
If we just went 5 m/s, four 4 seconds.
So if you go 5 m/s times (so this is 1 second, 2 second, 3 second, 4 second)
So you're going from 0 sec.. time 0 from time 4
Your change in time is 4 seconds, so if you go 5 m/s for 4 seconds, you're going to go 20 meters.
This right here is 20 meters. That is the area of this right here.
5 times 4. This .. this.. this.. mag(enta).. I guess purple or magenta area tells you how further than this are you going
because you are accelerating because you kept going faster and faster and faster.
It's pretty easy to calculate this area.
The base here is still 5 cause that's 5 seconds have gone by.
And what is the height here?
The height here is my final velocity minus my initial velocity.
Or it's the change in velocity due to the acceleration.
And the change in velocity due to the acceleration 13 minus 5 is 8.
Or it's this 8 right over here. It is 8 m/s
So this height right over here is 8 m/s.
The base right over here is 5... eh sorry, it's 4 seconds.
That's the time that passed. So what's the area of this triangle?
The area of a triangle is 1/2 times the base which is 4 seconds, times the height.
which is 8 m/s, times 8 m/s.
seconds cancel out, 1/2 times 4 is 2, times 8 is equal to 16 meters.
So the total distance we traveled is 20 plus 16, is 36 meters.
That is the total, or I could say total displacement.
And, once again, it is to the right since it is positive.
This is our displacement.
Now, what I want to do is this exact same calculations, but keep it in variable form and that will give another formula
that many people often memorize, but I want you to understand that it is a completely intuitive formula and it just comes out of the
kind of the logical flow of reasoning that we went through this video.
What is the area? Once again if we use it in the, (if we just think about the variables)
well, the area of this rectangle right here is our initial velocity,
times our change in time
so that's the blue, this is the blue rectangle right over here.
And then, plus, what do have to do?
We have the change in time, once again, we have the change in time.
Times this height, which is our final velocity
minus our initial velocity (these are all vectors)
(well, they're just positive telling us we're going to the right)
and if we just multiply the base times the height, that would give us the area of this entire rectangle.
We have to take it by half because the triangle is only half of that rectangle.
So times 1/2, so this is the area, this is the purple area.
(That's not purple) this is the purple area right over here.
This is the area of this, this is the area of that
And let's simplify this a little bit. Let's factor out a delta t
So if you factor out a delta t, you get delta t times a bunch of stuff.
v sub i, so your initial velocity
We factor this out, plus this stuff. Plus this thing right over here
And we can distribute the 1/2. We factored, we factored the 1/2 (sorry) we factored the delta t's out.
And let's multiply the 1/2 times each of these things.
So it's going to be plus 1/2 times Vf, our final velocity
(That's not the right color, let me actually do it in the right color so that you actually understand what I'm doing.)
So this is the 1/2, so plus 1/2 times our final velocity
minus 1/2 times our initial velocity (I want to do that in blue. Sorry I'm having trouble changing colors today.)
Minus 1/2 times our initial velocity.
And now what does this simplify into?
We have something plus 1/2 times something else, minus 1/2 times that original something
So what is Vi minus 1/2 times Vi
So anything minus half of it, you're just going to have a positive half left.
So these two terms this term and this term will simplify to
1/2 Vi, 1/2 the initial velocity plus 1/2 times the final velocity.
And all of that is being multiplied by our change in time, or the time that has gone by.
And this tells us the distance that we traveled.
Or another way to think about it, let's factor out this 1/2.
You get distance is equal to change in time, times factoring out the 1/2.
Vi plus Vf (No that's not the right color)
So this is interesting, the distance we traveled is equal to 1/2 of the initial velocity plus the final velocity.
So this is really, if you just took this quantity right over here is just the arithmetic.
(I always have trouble saying that word) is the arithmetic mean of these two numbers.
So I'm going to define this as something new. I'm going to call this the average velocity.
But we have to be very careful with this.
This right here is the average velocity.
But the only reason why I can just take the starting velocity and the ending velocity and adding them together and then divide by two
it's actually taking the average of these two things which would be some place over here.
And I take that as the average velocity is because my acceleration is constant
Which is usually an assumption in every introductory physics class, but it's not always the assumption.
But if you do have a constant acceleration like this, you can assume that the average velocity is going to be the average of
the initial velocity and the final velocity. If this was a curve, if the acceleration was changing,
you could not do that. But what's useful about this, is if you want to figure out the distance that was traveled,
you just need to know the initial velocity and the final velocity, average the two,
and then multiply that times the time that goes by.
So in this situation, our final velocity is 13 m/s,
Our initial velocity was 5 m/s. So you have 13 plus 5 is equal to 18.
You divide that by two. Your average velocity is 9 m/s
if you take the average of 13 and 5. And then 9 m/s times 4 seconds gives you 36 meters.
So hopefully that doesn't confuse you. I just wanna show you where some of these things that you'll see in your physics class
Some of these formulas, why you shouldn't memorize them, and they can all be deduced.