Let's look at how to prepare sulfides from thiols.
So, over here on the left I have my Thiol
And to that thiol I'm going to add sodium hydroxide.
And the sodium hydroxide is going to deprotonate the thiol
Which is then going to react with this alkyl halide in the second step of the reaction
to produce this sulfide as my product
Here is my sulfide right here.
This reaction is the analogue of the Williamson ether synthesis
which we've seen in an earlier video
So, in that video we started out with an alcohol
and we reacted our alcohol with as strong base in the first step and an alkyl halide in the second step.
And we formed an ether as our product.
We can go ahead and draw our ether in like that.
So, the thiol is the sulfur analogue to an alcohol
and a sulfide is the sulfur analogue to an ether.
Let's look at the mechanism to make sulfides...
So, if I start with my thiol right here.
I have carbon bonded to sulfur bonded to hydrogen
and two lone pairs of electrons on that sulfur.
And if I think about the difference in electro-negativity between carbon and sulfur
there's actually not much of a difference in terms of numbers.
So, this is not a very polar bond actually.
That's different with what we see from an alcohol.
So, up here if we look at the alcohol, I know that oxygen is a lot more electro-negative than carbon
This oxygen here would get a partial negative
and this carbon on the left (R-) would get a partial positive.
There is much more of an electro-negativity difference in alcohols.
In thiols there's not really that much of a difference
But thiols can still function as nucleophiles
Because these lone pairs of electrons are located further away from the nucleus than the lone pair on the oxygen
because sulfur is a larger atom.
Those electrons (on sulfur) are more polarizable, and so thiols are actually excellent nucleophiles.
If we go back here to our mechanism, we are going to add sodium hydroxide which is a base.
So, we can go ahead and put OH- over here
The hydroxide anion is going to function as a base
and a lone pair of electrons are going to take this proton and leave these protons behind on the sulfur.
Let's go ahead and draw the conjugate base to the thiol.
We now have Carbon bonded to sulfur, and sulfur now has 3 lone pairs of electrons.
Giving it a negative one (-1) formal charge.
This is called a "Thiolate anion". Let me go ahead and write that.
A thiolate anion.
And thiolate anions are very stable.
That negative charge of the sulfur, since sulfur is a large atom
You can spread out that negative charge over a very large area.
So the thiolate anion is relatively stable and that makes thiols more acidic than alcohols.
Alcohols don't have the same type of stabilization, since alcohols are smaller.
So, thiols are actually very acidic and that's why we can use sodium hydroxide here
to deprotonate our thiol to form the thiolate anion.
In the second step we add our alkyl halide
Here's my alkyl halide.
And the alkyl halide does have a polarized bond.
The difference in electronegativity between a halogen and a carbon atom is fairly large.
This halogen is going to get a partial negative charge and this carbon is going to get a partial positive charge.
So, thiols are good nucleophiles.
Thiolate anions are even better nucleophiles.
So, the thiolate anion is going to function as a nucleophile.
The partially positive carbon is going to function as the electrophile
and we're going to get an SN2 type mechanism.
Where our strong nucleophile attacks our electrophile
and kicks these electrons off here, on to the halogen.
And we can go ahead here and form our product. Right?
This is an SN2 type mechanism.
And we end up with the sulfur now bonded to two R groups.
They could obviously be the same R groups or they could be different R groups.
And so, we've formed our sulfide like that.
Let's do an example of the preparation of sulfides.
We're going to start with this one right here.
We start with this molecule and to that thiol we're going to add sodium hydroxide in the first step.
Let's go ahead and write "sodium hydroxide"
Na+ Then OH- like that
And in the second step we're going to add an alkyl halide.
Let's add this as our alkyl halide: Ethyl Bromide.
When I think about the mechanism, I know the first step is an acid/base reaction.
The electrons on the hydroxide anion... so one of these electron pairs here...
Are going to take this proton, that's the acidic proton on my thiol.
Leaving these electrons behind on the sulfur
I can go ahead and draw the resulting thiolate anion.
I can go ahead and draw that. Let me see what we have here.
We have our ring, and then we have our sulfur, and our sulfur now has three lone pairs of electrons around it
Like that.
Thiolate anions are excellent nucleophiles and when I look at my alkyl halide
once again I know the electronegativity difference between bromine and this carbon
is going to give bromine a partial negative charge and this carbon's going to be partially positive.
So, the thiolate anion is going to act as a nucleophile in an SN2 type mechanism
and a lone pair of electrons here are going to attack my electrophile
and we can go ahead and form our product.
Now we have our ring here, which is connected to our sulfur.
And our sulfur now just picked up two more carbons right?
Because these electrons here are going to kick off on to the bromine
and we end up putting an ethyl group on to that sulfur.
so there are two carbons, now, on the sulfur like that.
and the sulfur has two lone pairs of electrons
And so, we've formed our sulfide!
Now, if I were to name this sulfide, it is a lot like naming ethers.
I could use the common way of naming this and treat those as alkyl groups.
If I look on the right this would be an ethyl group
I could go ahead and start naming it.
I could say it's "ethyl". And if I look at the alkyl group on the left side, this is a phenyl group.
So it's ethyl and then phenyl since I'm following the alphabet rule.
E before P.
And then finally, I know it's a sulfide.
So I can just go ahead and finish the nomenclature here by saying, "sulfide" here.
So, "ethyl phenyl sulfide" is the sulfide produced in this analogue of the Williamson ether synthesis.