In the last video we showed that the ratios of the sides of a 30-60-90 triangle are, if we assume the
longest side is X, the hypotenuse is X, then the shortest side is X over 2, and the side in between,
the side that is opposite the 60 degree side is the square root of three times x over 2.
Another way to think of it is if the shortest side is one, and I'll do the shortest side then the medium
side than the longest side. So if the side opposite the 30 degree side is 1 then the side opposite the
60 degree side is the square root of three times that. So it's going to be square root of three and then
the hypotenuse is going to be twice that. In the last video we started with x and we said that the 30
degree side is X over 2, but if the 30 degree side is one, then it is going to twice that so this is
going to be 2. This right here is the side opposite the 30 degree side, opposite the 60 degree side,
and then the hypotenuse, opposite the 90 degree side.
And so in general, if you see and triangle that has those ratios, you say hey, that's a 30-60-90 triangle.
Or if you see a triangle that you know is a 30-60-90 triangle you cold say, Hey!, I know how to figure out
out one of the sides, based on this ratio right over here, and just as an example:
If you see a triangle that looks like this, where the sides are 2, 2 square root 3, and 4.
Once again the ratio of 2 to 2 square root of 3 is 1 to square root of 3.
The ratio of 2:4, is the same thing as 1:2, this right here must be a 30-60-90 triangle.
What I want to introduce you to in this video is another important type of triangle that shows up alot
in geometry, and a lot in trigonometry. And this is a 45-45-90 triangle.
Or another way to think about it is, if I have a right triangle that is also isosceles
,so a right triangle that is also isosceles.
You obviosly can't have a right triangle that is equilateral,
because an equilateral triangle has all, all of their angles have to be 60 degrees.
But you can have a right angle, you can have a right triangle that is isosceles.
An isosceles, let me write this, this is a right isosceles, i-sos-ce-les triangle.
And, if it's isosceles that means 2 of the sides are equal.
So, these are the 2 sides that are equal.
And then if the 2 sides are equal we have proved to ourselves, that the base angles are equal.
If we call the measure of these base angles X, now we know that X+X+90
have to be equal to 180. X plus X plus 90, need to be equal to 180.
Or if we subtract 90 from both sides, you get X plus X is equal to 90.
Or 2X is equal to 90, OR if you divide both sides by 2, you get X is equal to 45 degrees.
So a right isosceles triangle can also be called, and this is the more typical name for it:
It can also be called a 45-45-90 triangle.
And what i want to do with this video, is to come up with the ratios for the sides
of a 45-45-90 triangle, just like we did for a 30-60-90 triangle.
And this one is actually more straight forward.
Because in a 45-45-90 triangle, if we call each of, if we call one of
the legs X, the other leg is also going to be X.
and then we can use the pythagorean theorem to figure out the length
of the hypotenuse.
So the length of the hypotenuse, let's call that C.
So we get, X squared + X squared, that's the square of both of the legs.
so when we sum those up that's going to have to be equal to C squared.
This is just straight out of the pythagorean theorem.
So we get 2X squared is equal to C squared, C squared.
We can take the principle root of both sides of that.
I want to change it to yellow, and it's not letting me,, ok.
Ok, to C squared, now let's take the principle root of both sides of that.
Principle root of both sides.
The left hand side, you get, principle root of 2 is just square root of 2.
And then principle root of X squared is just going to be X.
So you're going to have X times the square root of 2 is equal to, C.
So if you have a right isosceles triangle, whatever the two legs are,
they're gonna have the same length, that's why it's isosceles.
The hypotenuse is going to be square root of 2 times that.
So C is equal to, X times the square root of 2.
So for example, if you have a triangle that looks like this.
Let me draw it in a slightly different way.
It's good to have to orient ourselves in different ways everytime.
So if we see a triangle that is a 90 degree, 45, and 45 like this,
And you really jst have to know two of these angles to know what the other one
is going to be.
And if i told you that this side right over here is 3.
Actually, I don't even have to tell you that this other side is going to be 3.
This is an isosceles triangle, so the two legs are going to be the same.
And you wont even have to apply the pythagorean theorem if you know this,
And this is a good one to know,
That the hypotenuse here, the side opposite the 90 degree side,
is just going to be the square root of 2 times the length of either of the legs.
So its going to be 3 times the square root of 2.
So the ratio of the sides and the hypotenuse, in a 45-45-90 triangle,
or a right isosceles triangle.
The ratio of the sides are: one of the legs can be 1,
then the other leg is going to have the same measure, the same length.
And then the hypotenuse is going to be the square root of 2 times either of those.
One to one to square root of two.
So this is 45-45-90, let me write, this is 45-45-90.
That's the ratios. And just as a review, if you have a 30-60-90
the ratios were one to square root of three to two.
And now we will apply this in a bunch of problems.