Now I'll start to do some interesting problems
and one of these thing
that you'll find in probablity is that
you can always do a way more interesting problem
so now I'm going to think about:
I'm going to take a fair coin
and I'm going to
flip it 3 times
and I want to find the probability of
atleast one head.
At leats one head out of the 3 flips.
So the easiest way
to think about this is
how many equaly likely possibilities there are.
And in the last video, we saw
that If we flip a coin 3 times, there's 8 possibilities.
For the first flip,
there's 2 possibilities.
Second flip, there's 2 more possibilities.
And in the 3rd flip, there are 2 possibilities.
So 2x2x2 -
there are 8 equally likely possibilites.
If I'm flipping a coin 3 times.
Now, how many of those possibilities
have atleast one head?
Well we drew all of the possibilities over here
so we just have to count-
How many of these have atleast one head?
So thats one, two, three, four, five, six, seven.
So seven of these have atleast one head in them.
And this last one does not.
So seven of the eight have atleast one head.
Now your probably thinking-
Okay Sal, we're able to do it
by writing out all of the possibilites.
But it would be really hard If I said
Atleat one head out of you know, 20 flips.
this time we had 12 because I had only 3 flips.
So let me make it clear-
this isn't 3 flips. In 3 flips.
This would have been a lot harder to do...
And a lot more time consuming to do,
if I had 20 flips.
Is there some short-cut here?
Is there some other way to think about it?
And you couldn't, just do it in some simple way.
You can't just say: Oh! Probability of heads x probability of heads.
Because if you got heads the first time
now you dont have to get heads anymore.
Or you could get heads again,
but you don't have to.
So it becomes a little bit more complicated.
But there is an easy way to think about it.
Where you could use this methodology
right over here:
your going to acually see this on a lot of exams
where they actually make it seem
like a harder problem,
but if you just think about it in the right way,
it all of a sudden, becomes simpler!
One way to think abou it is-
the probability of atleast 1 head in 3 flips
is the same thing as
the probability of not getting all tails.
Right?
If we got all tails,
then we dont have atleast 1 head.
So these 2 things are equivalent.
The probability of getting atleast one head
in 3 flips, is the same thing as
the probability of not getting all tails, in 3 flips.
So whats the probability of not getting all tails?
Well, thats going to be
(1- the probability of getting all tails).
And since its 3 flips, its the probability of tails,
tails, and tails.
Because, any of the other situations
are going to have atleast 1 head in them.
And thats all of the other possibilities.
This is the only other left-over possibility.
If you add them together,
your going to get 1.
Let me write it this way.
The probability.. (let me wrie it in a new color, just so you see where its coming from).
The probability of not getting all tails
+ the probability of all tails.
Well, this is essentially exhausted. This is all the possible circumstances.
So your chances of getting either 'not all tails' or 'all tails',
and this is mutual exclusives. So we can add them.
So the probability of (let me write it this way)...
The probability of 'not alll tails' or
(just to be clear of what we are doing,
..or the 'probability of all tails' is going to be equal to 1.