We know how to take derivatives of
functions. If I apply the derivative operator to
X^2, I get 2X.
Now if I also apply the derivative operator to
X^2+1, I also get 2X.
If I apply the derivative operator to X^2
X^2+pi, I also get 2X. The derivative of X^2
is 2X, the derivative with respect to X of pi of a constant
is just 0. The derivative with respect to X of 1
is just a constant, is just 0.
So once again, this is just going to be equal to 2X.
In general, the derivative with respect to x of X^2
plus any constant, any constant, is going to be
equal to 2X. The derivative of X^2 with respect to X is 2X
Derivative of a constant with respect to X, a constant does not change
with respect to X, so it's just equal
to 0. So you have, you take the derivative, you apply the derivative operator
to any of these expressions, and you get 2X.
Now let's go the other way around. Let's think about the antiderivative.
Anti-derivative. And one way of
thinking about it, it's the, it's the,
we're doing the opposite of the derivative operator.
The derivative operator, you get an expression,
and you find find this derivative.
Now what we want to do, is, given some expression,
we want to find
what it could be the derivative of.
What it could be the derivative of.
So if someone were to tell you,
were to give you 2X.
If someone were to say, 2X
So if someone were to ask you: what is
what is 2X
the derivative - derivative -
of? They're essentially asking you for
the antiderivative!
And so you could say: well, 2X is
the derivative of X^2.
2X is the derivative of X^2.
But you could say: 2X is the derivative of X^2 plus 1.
You could also say that 2X is the derivative of X^2 plus pi.
I think you get the general idea.
So if you wanted to write it in the most general sense.
you would write:
that 2X is the derivative of X^2
plus some constant.
So this is what you would consider
the antiderivative of 2X.
Now that's all nice, but this is kind of
clumsy to have to write the sentence like this
so lets come up with some kind of notation
for the antiderivative.
And the convention here is to use
kind of a strange-looking notation.
Is to use a
a big, elongated, S-looking thing like that
and the dx around the function
you're trying to take the antiderivative
of. So in this case, it would look something like this.
This is just
saying: this is equal to the antiderivative of 2x.
And the antiderivative of 2X, we have already seen,
is X^2, is X^2 plus C.
Now, you might be saying:
Why do we use this type
of crazy notation?
It will become more obvious when we
study the definitive integral, and areas under curves,
and taking sums of
rectangles, in order to approximate the area of the curve.
Here, it really should just be viewed as a notation for
antiderivatives.
And, this notation right over here,
this whole expression, is called:
the indefinite integral.
The indefinite...indefinite...
indefinite integral of 2X
which is another way of just saying:
the antiderivative of
2X.