Let's talk about exactly how flu causes so much damage
to ourselves and why it makes us feel
so lousy whenever we get the flu.
And I start up with drawing the flu virus here.
This is our influenza virus,INFLUENZA VIRUS.
And we have on influenza a couple of features
that we have to remember.
So you know, on the out side there is a sort of envelope.
And what's on the inside of this envelope
are 8 bits of RNA, 8 pieces of RNA.
And so this RNA is important to remember
because in the human cell in our cells, I'm going to draw one of our cells right here,
we have instead of RNA we have DNA, remember.
And so this is our nucleus.
And on the inside of the nucleus is our DNA.
So this is our DNA over here.
So the virus has RNA and we have DNA.
In the outside of the human cell, I should have been labelling this over here, this is HUMAN CELL.
The outside of the human cell has something called
SIALIC ACID
There are these little strings over here. They are coming of
and I'm drawing them far larger than they are in real life.
They're not nearly this big.
But there are these little, tiny little things called sialic acid.
And this sialic acid becomes very important in understanding how the influenza virus
gets into and out of our cells
So the outside, remember, of the influenza virus there were couple of proteins
And I'm gonna draw one of these proteins here.
I'm gonna make it look like a hand.
So this is a little hand and this protein is called HEMAGGLUTININ
In fact previously I called the H protein and you can call that if you want.
But the full name is hemagglutenin.
And what hemagglutenin does is that it actually holds onto sialic acid.
In fact that's an easy way to remember, right, because H and H go together
It holds sialic acid.
That becomes very important because that allows it the first step towards getting into the cell
That is another protein on the outside here.
I'm gonna make it look like a pair of scissors.
Because it will kind of remind us what this one does.
And this is called neurominidase.This one is called neurominidase.
And I'm gonna pass on explaining what it does just for the moment.
I'll tell you a little bit what it does.
So then the first step to get into the cell is for hemagglutinin to hold on sialic acid.
And than there are few other small molecular steps that happen,
important ones but I'm gonna suffice to say gets inside.
And once the influenza virus gets inside,
these are RNA segments they're let loose.
So these segments are gonna start making their way towards the nucleus.
So once they get into the nucleus they are in the same kind of area that DNA is.
And what they do is remarkable.
They basically take over.
These little RNA start making many copies of themselves.
And what they want to do is make our human cell into a factory.
They want to make a factory and this factory is gonna make little proteins, viroproteins.
And it's gonna make viral RNA.
And what it's not gonna do the one thing that cell is no longer gonna to be very good at doing
is its normal job.
So the human cell of course had some job to do
and it's not gonna have the resources or the time to do it
because it's basically been taken over by this viral RNA.
So what happens then is that the viral RNA is basically turned into a factory and
what it wants to do is make more and more copies of it selves.
Let me just show you what that would look like.
Here is a daughter cell, lets say it goes over here.
And I'm gonna clean this up a little bit, just to make sure that we're looking at a nice and neat picture.
Let's say something like this.
So this is our daughter cell on the other side.
And these cells are gonna try to make their way out of the human cell, right?
Because now they're a package, they are ready to go.
And where these suppose they wanna go next?
Where they gonna wanna find their own human cell to invade.
Because they wanna to continue this process.
We've got more human cells over here down below.
We've got maybe let's say one human cell up here.
So we've got new targets for this virus.
And this virus is going to seek out these targets and try to make its way inside
again using its hemagglutinin.
But before it can do that it's gotta break loose, right?
Because it's still attached to that sialic acid.
It's here where neurominidase comes in.
And neurominidase it basically, it nicks.
And there is with the N is helpful for remembering it.
It nicks or cuts sialic acid.
It's if a nicker cut that sialic acid it can break free.
As I remember the two proteins as hemagglutinin holds sialic acid to enter the cell
that is on entry and the neuraminidase is gonna nick the sialic acid
and that important for exiting the cell.
But we still haven't answered the question : how does all this cause our symptoms?
or what happens is as these cells get turned into factories
they start dying or getting damaged.
And all their content start leaking out.
So all these contents from the cell start leaking out and as they do they create inflammation.
Let me bring a little bit up the canvas.
If you have an inflammation, let's say that inflammation is happening in your nose
well you might say : well I have a runny nose or a stuffy nose.
Or if that inflammation is happening in your throat you might say: well I have a sore throat, might hurt.
And if it's happening in your lungs you might have a cough.
So one of those respiratory symptoms, remember that we've got two categories,
All other respiratory symptoms, I'm gonna shorten it as RESP.
Those are gonna be explained by inflammation or at least a part of inflammation.
And remember there are also constitutional symptoms, right?
With constitutional symptoms, those were things like having a fever or having fatigue.
And the reason for that is that your immune system is going wild and crazy
when you have influenza.
It's gonna be attracted to all of those chemicals, we call these cytokines that were being released .
And it's gonna to be attracted to the fact that you've got actual virus particles in the area,
you know that is being infected.
So that strong immune system is going to create some of your symptoms.
It's actually gonna rave up your temperature.
You'll start having a fever, chills.
And because your energy is spent on this attack
you're going to be fatigued.
you're going to be fighting off the virus so you going to be fatigued,
you might have the body aches.
So lot of these kinds of symptoms you get as result of a strong immune response.