If a doctor's concerned if a patient has diabetes or is at risk for diabetes
they might suggest an A1C test to be performed
What I want to do in this video is to explore what A1C even means
and also how that actually relates to diabetes
or the main side effect of diabetes, which is having high blood sugar, or "hyperglycemia"
So to do that, let's think about red blood cells
and I know what you're thinking: what is this to do with diabetes?
we'll get there in a little bit
So red blood cells are the main oxygen carriers in our blood
they kind of look like these lozenges
and inside a red blood cells
you have hundreds and millions of haemoglobin molecules, or haemoglobin proteins
So let me draw some haemoglobin proteins
Actually we have, the number I found is, 200-300 million per red blood cell
and then we have tens of trillions of red blood cells, so we have a lot of haemoglobins in us
and haemoglobin is what makes red blood cells red
When haemoglobin is bound to oxygen, it has a red colour
This right here, each of those are haemoglobin proteins
Now, it turns out, a haemoglobin, let me draw a bigger version of it... haemoglobin
If it has some glucose around, so let me draw some glucose floating around near the haemoglobin
If it has some glucose around, there's some chance
it's not a high probability, but there's some chance
that the haemoglobin and the glucose bump into each other
at just the right way that they'll bind to each other
And so you'll have this situation where you have glucose bound to the haemoglobin
Now this haemoglobin with the glucose bound to it, is called "glycated haemoglobin"
I wrote "glycated" in green, 'cause I'm using green for the glucose
Another name for glycated haemoglobin, or haemoglobin that has some glucose bound to it
is "haemoglobin A1C"
And now I can imagine things are starting to click in your brain
When you're measuring your A1C level, that's a test of the percentage of your haemoglobin that is haemoglobin A1C
So you take a blood test, they're measuring relative to the total amount of haemoglobin
what percentage of that is haemoglobin A1C
And a normal range of that, so if just have normal blood sugar for a reasonable amount of time
you're going to have a haemoglobin A1C level in kind of a 4-6% range
And people are still kind of trying to tighten up this range
and it doesn't completely correlate tightly with the blood sugar
Well, it does correlate, but still, people of the same blood sugar can still have fairly different A1C levels
But 4-6% is considered normal
And if you have higher, higher than 7 or 8%
so greater than 7 or 8%, so if you have like an A1C level of 9 or 10%, that's high
So you can imagine this is kind of a proxy for how much glucose you have in your bloodstream
because the more glucose you have in your bloodstream
the higher the probability that that glucose is going to react with the actual haemoglobin
so you're going to have a higher percentage of haemoglobin A1C
And the other reason why this is useful is kind of, well I guess you can see on the first pass
it's useful because not one of these snapshots that test
everything we've talked about so far, with respect to diabetes
is taking your blood sugar at any one point in time
and we know that your blood sugar changes through out the day
changes depending on how active you are
changes depending on what you might have just eaten
so when you do blood sugar, you're just getting a sample
you don't know where the blood sugar is through out the day, unless you just kept sampling
which can get pretty annoying, you know, keep pricking your needle
With A1C, this starts to become a measure of how much glucose you've had in your blood
over a longer period of time
And in general kind of uses for a measure for the last few months
because the red blood cells and the haemoglobin in them
they have a life span of about 120 days
That obviously doesn't mean all of your haemoglobin gets produced on one day and all dies 120 days later
you have some red blood cells and haemoglobin that might be a few seconds old
and then you have some that might be approaching 120 days old
so on average they're going to be around 60 days old, or about 2 months old
So on measuring this percentage, you're definitely not getting the percentage of anything older than 120 days
and on average you're seeing things that are from about 2 months old
So the higher this percentage, this is saying:
Wow, this is, you know, my average haemoglobin molecule in my body is only maybe 60 days old at this point
And already 7-8% of them have already been glycated
which is an indicator that I probably have more blood sugar than a normal person
In normal situation, only 4-6% of my haemoglobin would get glycated
so hopefully that explains what A1C is
But I do want to say, and I said in the beginning of the video, that I'm not a doctor
and even amongst doctors, the A1C test, or the A1C measurement
there's some debate about how useful it is, what it's measuring
or kind of how far back it actually is a good view at kind of your glucose levels
And also, as I've mentioned, two people with the exact same blood sugar could have different A1C levels
depending on other things: how old they are, whether they have some other type of medical condition