In the last video, we saw that despite the fact that Italy was an original member of the Tripple Alliance
It was a very awkward relationship. You fast forward
to the beginning of WW1, Italy tried to stay neutral
arguing that the Triple Alliance was being on the offensive
as opposed to the defense.
And then as we mentioned in early 1915, in the Spring to 1915, it signs
the secret Treaty of London with the Allies.
Then in May, it actually declares war on Austria-Hungary.
It actually wouldn't formally declare war on
Germany until 1916. So that lays the setting for the
actual combat along the Italian/ Austro-Hungarian border
that they share right over here. So this next map
that I'm going to show you is essentially a zoom in of this part of this map.
So that's this map, right over here.
So we can start in 1915
we already saw that in May, Italy declares war.
Italy declares war on Austria. They don't declare on Germany until the next year.
1915- Declares war on Austria
The first combat happens in June, happens in June
With the first battle on the Isonzo river. I'm sure I'm mispronouncing it.
The Isonzo River contours the then border between
Italy and the Austro-Hungarian Empire.
So it goes right along, right along this area right over here.
It's actually a very mountainous region, and as we'll see
the Italian Front involved many, many battles along the Isonzo River, in fact 12 battles in all.
In June 1915 was the first battle.
First battle on the Isonzo river.
And these continue into 1916.
These continue into 1916, we get all the way into the 5th Battle of the Isonzo River.
So let me draw that arrow a little bit longer.
So these continue all the way into 1916
And these essentially end up in a stalemate. A lot of people die in these battles,
it's incredibly difficult terrain, it favors the defending forces.
and so nothing really happens to the border here.
So far in all the offenses the Italians have taken
nothing really happened. Then as we get into
May of 16, So May of 1916
The Austro-Hungarians decided to go on the offensive.
and they go on the offensive in this part of the border, right over here.
And their offensive is called the Battle of Asiago.
They are able to get as far as Asiago, so battle of Asiago
But once again, even though they were able to claim some ground,
they weren't able to keep the ground, they were kind of spreading their troops out.
They weren't able to maintain their supply lines.
So by the end of that battle, the Italians had reclaimed that territory
and the actual front had not moved dramatically.
So really the first two years of the conflict ended up in a bit of a stalemate.
In fact it continues, we pick up in 1916 with the 6th Battle on the Isonzo River
and in these battles on the Isonzo River continue into 1917.
So let me show you, these are the battles on the Isonzo River, these continue all they way into 1917.
Now, as we enter into 1917, several interesting things are happening.
One as you might remember, on the eastern front,
in 1917, the Russians are starting to fall apart.
They are starting to have revolutions at home, they are losing on the Eastern front.
This allows the Germans to redeploy some troops
also at this point, Italy is formally at war with the Germans,
so as we get to October, October of 1917
The Austro-Hungarians are able to get reinforced by the Germans.
And it was just in time, because frankly by the 11th Battle of the Isonzo River,
so we get to the 11th battle, in kind of late 1917
11th or kind of the fall. 11th Isonzo Battle, the Austro-Hungarians aren't quite sure
wether they can handle a 12th battle on the Isonzo River
So the Germans show up essentially, just in time
And in October of 1917, along with the Austro-Hungarians, the Germans launch their own offensive
on the Isonzo River, and this one is actually the first dramatic
movement along the Italian front.
And this is often called the Battle of Caporetto.
Which is right over here, but as you can imagine
It is right along the border between these too, between these too
states, and its along the Isonzo river, so this is also referred to as the 12th Battle of the Isonzo River.
12th Battle of the Isonzo River
And this one is a very successful offensive.
They focus their troops near Caporetto, at this point of the front
They are able to break the Italian Front and push deep into Italian Territory.
So through October and early November, they are able to over the next several weeks,
this is in October of 1917, they are able to push the Italians all the way back, all the way back
to behind the Piave River, you may not be able to read it, that says the Piave River.
So they are able to push the Italians back, roughly back to this boundary right over here.
And so this takes into 1918
1918, now at this point the Germans are planning their last ditch spring offensive
They say hey look Astro-Hungarians, it looks like this war is kind of taken
we are going to leave this front to you guys, you guys should be able to do the
knockout blow on the Italians right now.
We are going to go return to the Western Front, to take care of the Allies.
Especially because if we don't do it sooner or later, the Americans will reinforce the Western Front.
So the Germans, the Germans
redeploy to the Western Front, redeploy
and essentially leave the Austro-Hungarians to
try to essentially take out the Italians. So in June of 1918
The Austro-Hungarians attempt their final, what they hope is their final offensive
and it is along this boundary along the Piave River.
Unfortunately for the Austro-Hungarians, and fortunately for the Italians.
The Austro-Hungarians did not plan that assault well.
Instead of doing a point offensive, like they did with the Germans in the Battle of Cappereto
where they were able to break the trenches, break the lines. Here was less planed
less coordinated, it was more spread out along the entire line.
On top of everything, the Italians got word of the exact time and date that the battle was going to start.
It was literally going to start at 3:00 AM on June 15.
The Italians decide that if the battle is going to start at 3:00 AM on June 15,
that means that all of their soldiers are going to be in the trenches, ready to assault, ready to attack
at 3:00 AM on June 15, so they started lobbing artillery into these densely packed trenches, knowing that it was likely to hit a lot of people
because there were a lot of people waiting in the trenches for offensive.
So even before the battle began, they were able to inflict a lot of carnage on the soon to be invading Austro-Hungarians.
The invasion itself was a bit of a debacle, when they were able to get on top of the Piave River, it isolated their troops.
The Italians were able to take advantage of that, and kind of those troops that were isolated on the south bank of the Piave River
they were able to take care of them.
And they were able to push the Austro-Hungarians back and they suffered huge losses, the Austro-Hungarian army was incredibly weakened
And some people believe that the Italians could have done and immediate counter offensive and taken the Austro-Hungarians out.
The Italians on the other hand, were still licking their wounds from the battle of Caperetto, and they decided to wait their chance and regroup a bit.
And so they wait, until October of 1918, you have a very weakened Austro-Hungarian army, and this is
when the Italians do their decisive offensive of the Italian Front.
The Battle of Vittorio Veneto. Vittorio Veneto is right over here
so Vittorio, Vittorio Veneto, and once again I apologize to all of the Italians out there for my mispronunciations.
But this is essentially able to break the back of the Austro-Hungarians, The Italians are able to pour through
They are able to take out the Austrians. The Austrians were already weakened. They are starting to have internal strife.
The empire is starting to fall apart.
And so by November, November, the Austro-Hungarian Empire, essentially surrenders.
And not just with the Italians, but surrenders relative to the Allies.
Which is essentially the end of the Italian Front of WW1.