In the years during the First World War,
this art movement called 'Dada' began.
How do you spell that?
That is D-a-d-a.
It is really a nonsense word.
The idea was to create a kind of anti-art.
To kind of challenge what art was.
The world was in flames,
the war was raging across Europe
and artists didn't want to have any part of it.
They wanted to show how absurd and how dangerous
the world had gotten.
And one of the artists who was a Dada artist
His name was Marcel Duchamp.
He had to create what we call 'Ready-Mades'
or what he called Ready-Mades.
Some of them were 'Assisted Ready-Mades'
where he would take two objects that existed in the world
and put them together,
and some objects were just pure Ready-Mades.
And one of my favorites is called
"In Advance of a Broken Arm"
and we're looking at it on the left here.
And you had to explicitly tell me
that it was the one on the left.
Yes I did! (he laughs)
So, just to make this clear, this is
In Advance of a Broken Arm.
That's exactly right.
And you had to point that out
because we have a very similar piece
on the right side here
which I just got off of Amazon,
which is a snow shovel.
- And really they're not much different at all, are they?
No, they both seem like snow shovels.
They are both snow shovels,
except Duchamp has taken his out of the garage
or out of the hardware store
and relocated it, sort of reframed it
and said, "No, this is a Ready-Made."...
..." This is something to look at..."
"...and understand within an aesthetic sphere."
I'm thinking what I think many people are thinking,
Okay, he did that, and it seems
like what he did was a very cynical act.
Which was, like, "here's art for you, all you jokers!"
"I'm going to go buy a snow shovel..."
"...and stick it in a museum and --"
I don't know, I feel like he's like laughing at people.
I think that there is definitely cynicism here,
and I think that this is
very much related to the objectives of Dada
which was to undermine the way in which we valued art,
the way in which we understood art,
saying that the world had become a place of chaos
and a kind of dangerous chaos, and
the artist wanted in some ways
have nothing to do with that any longer.
So how can I most undermine
and in a sense destroy the way
in which we had defined art?
To create a kind of anti-art?
I think that's exactly right.
And was he like the first person?
Because you know we just talked about Warhol,
and we said, if now someone took a piece of advertising
and stuck it in a museum
it would feel very derivative,
but Warhol did that a while after Duchamp.
So to some degree
it feels like now Warhal is derivative,
because Duchamp, --
you know, Warhol had to actually do some work,
he like actually painted a soup can,
but this guy, I mean, he's way ahead of his time,
he literally just bought a snow shovel
and showed up.
Duchamp would say however,
that finding a perfect Ready-Made
wasn't an easy thing.
He went on a hunt
and most objects did not suit his definition
of what a perfect Ready-Made would be.
You know he has created a kind of narrative here.
I mean, what do you think of
when you put that snow shovel together with the title?
To me, it looks like a parody.
In Advance of a Broken Arm...
Yeah, he went and bought a snow shovel
and he called it In Advance of a Broken Arm,
which is a very, kind of fancy-sounding title,
which makes you think a little bit,
but yeah, I , er, yeah
(they giggle)
So I think you're absolutely right,
I think it's impossible,
And here's the even more absurd part:
we're looking at a photograph,
not even of the original In Advance of a Broken Arm,
but a later snow shovel
he replaced the original with
after the first had been lost,
perhaps to a snow storm!
O yeah here we read:
"August 1964,"
"Fourth version after lost original of November 1915"
So I guess --
Well, can you even have an original?
Well exactly, because there's probably
a hundred of those originals.
So, let's play this out for a moment.
Imagine that this came up to auction
and it went to Sotheby's or Christie's,
it went to one of the big auction houses
and it's a Duchamp,
this important example of Dada.
And the auction is going to start
at some very high numbers right?
It's going to start at 2 million dollars.
Is that really what this might go for?
Er, these are priceless objects.
Except that somebody could walk into Home Depot
or go onto Amazon
or in their grandfather's barn or something
And imagine they could get
past the guard at Christie's
and walk into the showroom
with their own snow shovel
and there would be no difference, physically,
between the snow shovel
that is up on the podium
that is for sale, for auction,
and that is reaching this astronomical figure
versus the snow shovel
that's worth 29,99.
So that's a fascinating question,
because they are physically identical snow shovels
and one was touched by Duchamp
and placed in a museum
and another 1,000 were not
and because of that,
this one could go for millions.
You started off by saying
"is Duchamp being cynical"?
I think in some ways he really is.
He is trying to make, in a sense,
the apparatus of the art market transparent,
he is trying to force us to grapple with
"how do we define what art is?"
and how it's important.
And maybe that our values are misplaced
in some way.
But he is also pointing toward something else
which is that art is not necessarily
in the 20th century,
located in the practice of its making,
located in the proficiency of the artist
and their brush work,
but it is located in the symbolic language
that art can invoke.
In the way that art
can transform the way
that we see the world.
So...
I am actually becoming a bit of a fan
of Duchamp.
But I think there is...
O and I'm also thinking of becoming
an avant-garde artist.
I want to do an art installation
called "Breath Of Air".
Which is: I will go to that location
that little part of volume
and I will just exhale, right there.
And I will put a little plaque or something
saying "Salman has exhaled at this point"
That would push thinking at art.
Art that doesn't even exist!
You know what?
You missed your moment.
Because art was made like that
in the 1970's and 80's.
Someone has allready done that?
Someone has allready created art that doesn't exist?
- Or, art that exists as a performative act.
O, yeah, but...
yeah.
This is a difficult one.
I'm er,
I mean...
yeah.
(they laugh)
This is about as tough as it gets.
What is your take on it?
I mean, In Advance of a Broken Arm.
It does...
I, I agree with everything you said
that, like, he introduced this,
he is challenging people's notion of art,
challenging the art market,
challenging all of these
but in my mind it seems
in a very cynical way.
That 'I'm going to put a very mundane object on there,
make people bid on it
and think of it as art,
but...
What do you make of this name
"Advance of a Broken Arm"?
And that it gets a special showcase
and the fact that it costs the same
as a 5 dollar snow shovel from Home Depot?
You know, when we think about poetry for example
we don't worry about the cost of the typeface
we think about
where that poetry brings us
emotionally and intellectually.
It transforms us, it changes us.
And so, it is interesting that in the visual arts
we are still so tied to the handicraft.
Duchamp is really distancing art
from the handicraft
and making it a purely conceptual process.
So he is really forcing that issue
I think in an important way.
That has really challenged the 20th century
and made contemporary art possible.
That is interesting
So what you are saying is that
he is -- like poetry
Poetry is really about the idea of poetry
someone can copy and paste that
and we can all share that poetry
there is no physical words there
And he kind of did the same
It's the idea
thats why he was able to take another shovel
and do it again and again.
But still... We say that but
at the same time, the art market
does not necessarily view it that way.
They view this shovel as somehow being holy
versus the other shovel
that was made at the same assembly line
that is nowhere near as holy.
I think that is exactly right
and in some ways, Duchamp failed.
In some ways, I think the avarice
of the art market has prevailed
despite his attempt to undermine it.
We still would auction it at a very high price
we still differentiate the 2 shovels
and we would still value one
over the other
In a sence we heroicise the object
that is somehow connected
to the conceptual
even though I think Duchamp
was really focussed on
seperating those things.
And what about--
just going back to the name
I mean I can kind of buy
some of this
in that he is challenging what is art
and this idea
of putting focus on something like this,
but at the same time it seems like
the title is a little bit uppity.
Why didn't he just call it 'Snow Shovel'?
Or just 'blank'?
Why did he have to say
"In Advance of a Broken Arm"?
I will not pretend to know
what his motivations were
but I think that the cynicism we spoke of before
is exactly his point here.
Some of my students have said
they can imagine someone slipped on the ice
and broke their arm.
Oh, I could imagine,
you could call this 'In Advance of a Cherry Pie"
I can imagine that after working a long day
shoveling snow I will go eat a cherry pie.
I think that notion of absurdity
was central to Duchamp's practice
and what he was interested in.
I think he wanted us to bump up against
the absurdity of that title
and to be challenged by it.
Fascinating.