When you buy a US treasury security, you are essentially giving a loan
to the US Federal Government
This is an example here
I have a US treasure security here
it says that the owner of this piece of paper here will be paid $1000 in one year
so, if you buy this from the Treasury, maybe from somewhere else
let's just say that the government is issuing them right now
let's say you buy it for, you buy it for $950 and the government will
will give you this security right over here
now fast forward 1 year you're holding this security
and what'll happen?
so you know that stuff is written there
what'll happen a year later?
Well it's written on the security and I simplified it just for the example
it says the holder of this security will get $1000
so at this point, the US government has to give you $1000
so you look at just the money flow, it's pretty clear that you're just lending the money
you give them $950 now, and then a year later, they'll give you $1000
and if you want to put this in terms that you normally associate with borrowing money
in terms of how much interest that you'll get
well, you lent $950 and you got back $1000
So, let's think about it this way
Let's get the calculator out
So, 1000 divided by 950 is equal to 1.053, or 105.3% of your money back
This is 105.3% of money lent
of money given to the government
or another to think about it is
you got a 5.3% interest or you lent your money out at an annual interest of 5.3%
you got your money back, plus you got 5.3% after one year
So, you could imagine, of all sudden many people want to buy this government security.
Now the price goes up, instead of 950 dollars, imagine it is now 980 dollars. What is the implicit yield that
the person get on it
we'll get the calculator back on here
so, you paid in 980, instead of 950. Then a year later
when you get the 1000 dollars back, there'll be 102% of your money
So, in that situation there will be 102% of your money
so, at the 950 dollar price, you're essentially lending the government money at 5.3%
And 980 dollars, you are lending the government money at 2%.
And I'm doing this just to show you a point
When the price of the treasury security goes up, as happened in this case
the yield, or the interest, that you are getting on your loan goes down
in either situation, you're going to get your 1000 dollars back.
if you're lending 950 and get 1000 dollars back, you'll get 5.3 %
So this is what people are talking about when they say
treasury prices go up, if treasury prices go up
then the yields go down
So, there's more demand for the treasury, the interest on the treasury will go down
In the next video we'll talk about how this might change for treasuries of different maturity dates