So we've got the equation x^2 + y^2 = 1,
I guess we could call it a relationship.
And if we were to graph all the points x and y that satisfy this relationship
we get a unit circle like this.
And what I'm curious about in this video is
how we can figure out the slope of the tangent line
at any point of this unit circle.
And what immediately might be jumping out in your brain
is well, a circle defined this way, this isn't a function
it's not y explicitly defined as a function of x
for any x value you actually have 2 possible y's
that satisfy this relationship right over here.
So you might be tempted to maybe split this up
into two separate functions of x.
You could say y is equal to the positive square root of 1-x^2
and you could say y is equal to the negative square root of 1-x^2
take the derivatives of each of these separately
and you would be able to find the derivative
for any x, or the derivative of the slope
of the tangent line at any point.
But what I want to do in this video,
is literally leverage the chain rule
to take the derivative implicitly
so that I don't have to explicitly define y as a function of x either way.
And the way we do that is literally just apply
the derivative operator to both sides of this equation
and then apply what we know about the chain rule.
Because we're not explicitly defining y as a function of x
and explicitly getting y = f'(x)
they call this,
which is really just an application of the chain rule,
we call it implicit differentiation - Implicit Differentiation.
And what I want you to keep in the back of your mind
the entire time, is it is just an application of the chain rule.