Whenever people talk about investing
the terms risk and reward tend to come up a lot
and they usually tend to come up
together, somehow implying that the more risk you take the more reward
that you might be able to get, and that's
actually what it is implying.
But what I want to do in this video
is give a little bit of an introduction to that
or a little bit context, a little bit more structure
on how do you think about risk and reward.
So let's say that we have $1,000
and we want to figure out what we can do with this $1,000
well, one option is we could just put it into a savings account
so here is one option,
so we could put it into a savings account
and in this situation our reward, I'll start with the reward first,
is we'll get, I don't know, 1% in interest per year
1% annual interest, so after a year we'll have roughly $1,010
we got 1% on our $1,000. So we get a little bit of reward
what's our risk?
So the risk here, I'll write risk in a different color
what is the risk here?
We'll if I'm putting it into a saving account
and assuming I'm putting it into and FDIC insured savings account
let me put that over here,
if you do open a savings account it should be FDIC insured,
that means that it means it's being insured by the federal reserve
which means that if for whatever reason that bank were to fail
above, below some limit, the Fed will insure your money
so even if the bank fails, and it loses all of it's money and everything
you'll still get your deposit back.
So if you're investing, and you're putting money in an FDIC insured savings account
your risk is essentially 0. You are guaranteed to get that $1,000 back
regardless of what happens to that bank,
so you have very little risk there.
But you might say, look, this is a good risk
but I feel I can get more than 1% on my money
let me think about the other place that I could invest it.
Well you could, and obviously I'm not going to be exhaustive on all of the different
investment options, I just want to give you a sense of risk and reward,
you could say well maybe I could lend the money
to a very reputable company, so let me say
Lend Money to Reputable Company.
And maybe this company has, you know,
a ton, billions and billions of dollars in assets,
it's been around for hundreds of years,
it generates cash on a regular basis,
there's really very few circumstances in which you could imagine
that this company would not be able to pay off it's debt.
and you lend money to a reputable company by essentially buying their bonds.
When you buy a company's bonds, you are lending money to that company,
so that's just the way you should think about it.
So the reward here, if you lend your money to this company
they will pay you 6% in annual interest on your $1,000
So, 6% on the first $1,000, on the first year,
you'd get $60, this is 6 times more than what you were getting
in the savings account. What's the risk here?
Well, it's not 0 anymore, it's not FDIC insured,
the Federal Reserve is not saying they'll either
give the money if the bank goes out of business,
or they'll print the money if they don't even have it,
here the risk is that the business defaults on the loan.
So the Business Defaults on the Loan.
So the company itself might go bankrupt,
if it goes bankrupt, then all the people that the company owes money to
will go after that company's assets.
But maybe you are low on the pecking order,
maybe the company doesn't have enough assets to pay everyone back
so there is some risk, any business could go out of business
you never know what might happen,
but since this is a very reputable company
and as we said it has a lot of assets, it has a very
stable business, it does good in boom times
and recessions, this is a low risk of business default,
so I'll write low risk right over here
because we're assuming it is a reputable company
that has a lot of assets and all the rest.
Now lets say that even that 6%, you know
it's alright, but you feel like you could get more,
you could do better, so let's say that you have a friend
who is a, let's say he's just starting his career as a
doctor, so he has a nice stable job,
so he's just starting his career as a doctor
so stable income
he's making $200,000 a year,
but he's just out of medical school
and he figures he wants to buy a house
and so he's trying to find people, so he's just starting
he wants to find people who can help him with the downpayment
on the house. So here, your reward,
and he says anyone who is willing to lend to me
I will give them 8% annual interest on their money
annual interest, and it looks pretty good,
stable income, it's only $1,000, he's not buying
an outlandishly expensive house, he's buying a $200,000 house
on which he wants to put $40,000 downpayment,
seems well within his means to pay it,
but there is always some risk, there is always some risk
that he doesn't pay.
Who knows? Hopefully this doesn't happen,
maybe something happens to him himself,
maybe he's not able to work as a doctor, maybe
something happens to his health,
maybe he has some type of addictive personality
and he likes to drink away
all of his money, or he likes to gamble it away
and that's why he needs loans to begin with,
so there is some risk, so there's a risk he doesn't pay
but by all indications he looks like a pretty safe character,
but it's definitely riskier than this company
because you have no assets to go after if he doesn't pay
companies can't randomly be hit buy a bus,
a human being can,
so there are, companies for the most part
cannot become alcoholics, a human can.
Who knows? We don't know. But there are definitely
more risks associated with this individual doctor
who does not have assets you can go after.
But maybe this is also not enough reward,
you're like, you know, I heard that I can do even better
I can do better than this in the stock market
so, you look at another option, so let's say you invest
invest the market.
Invest in Stock Market. And you're just going to invest
in a bunch of, a broad portfolio, kind of investing in the market as a whole,
the reward here would be the expected return of the market.
So you look at historical results in the market, and you say, hey look
it goes up and down every year, but over long periods
of time it looks like people and
this isn't the exact number, but it looks like people have
average, approximately 10% per year.
So that looks pretty good, but what's the risk?
Well the risk is is that, this expectation is
just based on historical, what the historical returns of the market were,
there are huge periods of time in the market
I'm talking 10, 20, 30 years, where the market
is flat, where the market could even go down,
people, in any given year, the market could go down in the double digits,
or, you know, 30% 40%, even really bad year,
that we really don't, you really aren't sure
whether you're going to get your 10% per year.
So I would say the risk here is volatility,
and volatility just means we go up and down,
it jumps up and down,
it's not going to be a constant upward trend
like your savings account will be,
volatility, and you have a good chance you could actually
lose the money that you're investing,
it could go down in any year, in any month
in any 5 years, in any 10 years, so once again
it seems like a kind of risky thing,
and you could very easily lose everything,
and let's say that even 10% isn't enough for you
You say, hey, I want to look at things that maybe I could get
even a better return.
So you have a, your brother in law, who's been out of work
for a little bit.
Let me write the brother in law over here,
your brother in law has been out of work
for a little bit, and he says that all he needs
to start his new guaranteed money-making
scheme, is $1,000 so he can buy the equipment
so he can start it up in his garage, and the reward
and there's multiple ways we could setup the reward,
we could make it so that he borrows the money from you
we could make it so that you own part of the business
so let's say the reward is you get a 50% stake in the business
50% stake in business
and let's say that your brother in law is right
and this becomes a million dollar business
so this is a very, very, very high reward,
if what you're brother in law is telling is correct
but what's the risk?
Well the risk here is obviously that he's not correct
and that he squanders all of your money,
so lose everything,
and not only could you lose the monetary money you put in
it could also ruin your relationship
with your brother in law, and maybe your spouse,
so risk relationships, maybe I should put your risk family
family happiness.
Once your brother in law loses all your money
it won't be so easy at thanksgiving
anymore to have a civil conversation.
So in general, the overlying, you know I probably did more of these scenarios
than I needed to, but I think you see the general trend
the more risk that you take in general
the more of a reward you should expect to get
or the more reward you're expecting to get
there's probably some risk there,
and if there's something that looks like it's really safe
with really high reward, one of those 2 things
are probably not true. So if we were to plot all of these
and I haven't really quantified, I haven't kind of given you a way
of measuring risk, in future videos we can think about that
and academics have thought about ways of measuring risk
so that's risk and reward, if you plot it all over here,
so the savings account, it's zero risk, so this is the savings account over here,
and your reward is 1%. So this is 1% right over here.
The lending to a reputable company, it's a little
bit higher risk, so this is this one right over here,
it's a little bit higher risk, and your reward is 6%
so let's say this is 6% right over here.
So it's a little bit high risk,
I'm just saying risk is increasing.
If you lend to the doctor, so let me pick another color here that I haven't used
if you lend to the doctor, once again, risk is a little bit higher
than lending to that company, or the saving account
once again a little bit higher reward, a little bit higher reward,
you now have an 8% reward. Investing in the stock market
now let me pick a color I haven't used yet
investing in the stock market, once again,
higher risk, but also higher reward,
maybe 10% per year. That's 10% right over there.
Your brother in law, super high risk
probably off the charts over here,
but also super high rewards, so maybe it might be
like that.
But the general idea is the more risk the more reward.