Farming as we now associate the word has been around for about 7 to 10 thousand years and..
when we think of farming we imagine a farmer planting seeds and later harvesting the crops
or maybe having cattle that they can allow to graze
and using that cattle later either for meat or milk or wool.
But there's actually a different type of farming that predates
this association with what we can call traditional form of farming.
And it predates it by several tens of thousands of years
and we believe it started with the original inhabitants of Australia.
And what they did is, and this is why we call it farming,
because if you think about farming in the most general sense
is really humans using technology to manipulate their environment
so it becomes more suitable for humans
and more suitable for things that humans might want to eat
or get milk from or ... or whatever.
And this type of farming is called firestick farming.
And I think you can already imagine what it might involve.
It involves using fire which is really a form of technology
or can be a form of technology,
using fire to make the environment more suitable for human activity.
And so what the original Australians did, the indigenous Australians,
or sometimes we refer to them as the Aboriginal Australians.
If you're wondering where the word Aboriginal comes from,
you might recognise some parts of it:
original - you know what that means, the first things
the things that were there from the beginning,
and then you have "ab", which is Latin for "from".
So this is literally "from the beginning",
so when we say Aboriginal Australians we're really
kind of saying that they were there from the beginning.
And so what they would do is that we believe if you go back 50-60,000 years
before the first Aboriginal Australians settled Australia,
Australia had much more forest. It still has forest,
this is a modern picture of an Australian forest,
but what they did is that they set up controlled burns.
And what these controlled burns did is that
they cleared away a lot of forest,
they cleared away a lot of the brush that's at the bottom over here,
and it made it much more suitable for grassland to develop.
And the reason why they liked grassland -
so let's make a little cycle here of what they did.
So they have controlled burns, controlled fires
those controlled fires helped promote grassland
and then once you have grassland that made the environment
more suitable for animals that the original human settlers could essentially live off of,
that they could hunt, that they could potentially eat their meat,
for example things like ... kangaroos
and these supported the human population
which obviously would then do the controlled burns.
And you see here we could have started off with something like this,
someone provides a controlled burn,
and they were actually pretty scientifical about how they did it.
They wouldn't just go with the end of summer
when everything was hot and ready to just blow up
and to start a fire that they couldn't control.
They would often do these is seasons knowing that
they had a certain level of moisture in the air, it wasn't too hot
and to a large degree by doing these controlled burns,
not only did it provide an environment
that was suitable for things like kangaroos
some type of thing that humans could eat,
but it also prevented major fires.
And you still see forest rangers doing this type of thing.
There is some reason to believe that what the original Australians did
on some level was more nuanced and more fine too
than even what we do in a modern sense of controlled burns.
So these controlled fires also prevented major, uncontrollable fires.
Because what happens if you don't have these controlled fires,
then you have brush building up year after year after year,
you have stuff building up,
and then when the fires do occure, they're not going to occure,
they're less likely, the uncontrollable fires
are less likely to start during the winter
when the air is cool, when there might be some moisture,
they're more likely to ocure in the dry seasons.
So you have all this stuff built up, and then when the fire does happen,
it happens in the driest season and then when it happens
with all the stuff built up in the driest season
it just becomes uncontrollable.
One of the several by-products of this firestick farming
we believe is a lot of the grassland in Australia now
might have been more forested befor even when the first European settlers
came in the late 1700s, they were kind of surprised
when they went into what is now Sydney Harbour
and they said:'Wow, look at all the grassland here,
it almost looks like a park space!'
And then they would like their sheep graze there
and they were surprised, because they have driven out the original inhabitants,
and then they were surprised when forest just started to grow up in that grassland.
It was because the original Australians were actually controlling that forest growth
to make it more inhabitable for things like kangaroos
and then when the English settlers came
they started to have their sheep grazing in those grasslands.
And also it was responsible for the disappearance,
we think of many major, or better mega-fauna.
So really large animal that inhabited Australia for millions of years
until humans showed up. And this is one of them, if you just to need to look at them.
This is called Diprotodon optatum, or the giant wombat.
And there are fossils of the giant wombat around 40-50,000 years ago,
but they disappeared with humans showing up.
And there're multiple ways we can think about why they disappeared.
They might have, and this is probably the case,
they might have been more dependent on the forest habitat,
or this was a more favorable habitat for them than the grasslands,
maybe because they ate leaves that were higher up.
Or another thing is once the forest habitat goes away
they were actually also easier to hunt down,
or either way to think about it they might have just been hunted by humans.
But we do see with humans coming to the Australian continent
you start to see the disappearance, and this is not the only one,
there were several major species of megafauna,
of super-large animals that disappeared at that time period.