I'm actually gonna take a step back, clear out some of these stuff,
You've understood the first half of how this process of atherosclerosis happens,
and we're gonna finish off the second half.
So all of the action is still gonna happen in the tunica intima.
So they're much --is gonna stay the same.
And so far we've talked about macrophages,
and we talked about how they form foam cells,
and they --they eat up all the fats,
then form this kind of lake of fat.
And so, let me --let me leave it there,
so that's where the picture's out so far.
And now, let's talk about what happens after that.
So, the next step, step five, is
basically what happen with smooth muscle cells.
smooth muscle cells.
We haven't talked about them so far.
they (..) or they dance over --let's write dance~ over to tunica intima.
So really, again, everything is happening in the tunica intima.
Right, you can see that.
That's all the action is.
So when I say they dance over them,
I'm being a little bit silly,
but basically what happen is that these red smooth muscle cells,
these are the smooth muscle cells,
smooth muscle.
They are gonna start migrating.
They're gonna start migrating or moving.
And they're gonna start migrating into the space,
maybe that one will go over there,
maybe this one go over here, perhaps this one.
And why these start kind of migrating is that,
you know, there's a lot of actions going on,
the macrophages are there, you got the LDL in that lake of fat.
And a lot of chemicals are being released by these cells.
And so they sense that something's happening.
So they can move over there.
What they begin to do is make a fibrous cap.
That's step six.
So they make a fibrous cap --actually let me
--let me write who makes it.
So it's very clear: smooth muscle cells, S-N-C.
Smooth muscle cells make a fibrous cap.
And what a fibrous cap is? It's--
Think about when you're really young and you're playing,
and you know, you never really pay attention in fellow a lot,
you might've come home with skinned knees.
And I (..) my mom always remarks on that.
And those skinned knees turned into scab, right?
And so these smooth muscle cells made fibrous caps.
Basiclally, think of it as a scab.
A scab that formed over this lake of fat.
So I've been drawing for you this yellow lake of fat,
and now, these smooth muscle cells, they coming and say,
"well, you know, we've gotta make a cap over this thing".
Let me erase again, and draw for you what that might look like.
So, let's say that this lake is getting bigger
This lake over time is ...