if we were to buy the stock for 50 dollars
so this is a situation where we're buying the stock
we're clearly putting 50 dollars up front
and if the stock moved up
to 80 dollars and we were perfectly able to call the top
and sell it for that 80 dollars
we would make a 30 dollar profit
off of a 50 dollar initial investment
so that's a 60 percent gain
that's a 60% gain
on our upront capital
now on the other side if the stock were to go down
to 20 dollars we would lose 30 dollars
of our 50 dollar upfront investment
so it would be a 60% loss
so in the buying the stock
based on the scenario that I painted
we could lose 60% or we could lose 60%
and in terms of the potential upside you can gain
an unlimited amount because the stock can just really go to any possible value
and int terms of loss, when you buy a stock,
the most you can lose is 100%
now let's think about the scenario with the call option
To buy the call option it only costs us 5 dollars
so we only had to put 5 dollars up front
and in this scenario where the stock went up to 80 dollars
we figured out we could profit 15 dollars net of the price of the option
so on a base of a 5 dollars investment
we were able to get 15 dollars of profit
so we got a 300% gain
we were able to get a 300% gain
on the other hand, if the stock went down,
we had no reason to actually excersize our option
so we essentially just lost all the money in the option
We lost 100%
and what I want to show here is that
the option gave us leverage
it gave us leverage
and the term comes from physics
because a lever will give you mechanical leverage
it can allow you to exert more force than you otherwise could
by using that simple tool
and a call option is giving you financial leverage
You're essentially making the same bet
but you're multiplying your potenital gain
or your potenital loss
the stock in the good scenario, you made 60%
but in the call option in the good scenario, you make 300%
we multiplied, we multiplied out gain
But on the downside with the stock we lost 60%
but with the call option we lost 100%
so once again, we multiplied our loss
here it looks like our numbers are still favorable,
because our loss multiplication wasn't as much as our gain multiplication,
but this is really based on some of the numbers I chose
but the important thing to realize is
that if you're dealing with an option
it's the same bet
the bet that the company will go up
you're just putting leverage on your bet,
multiplying your gains or losses