Let's think about the market for plastic bags
and I'm picking this market in particular
because there might be some costs
associated with plastic bags
that aren't captured
when you‘re only looking at it
from the point of view of the suppliers or the consumers
so right over here you have a demand curve
that's really the demand
coming from the supermarkets
so this is the demand curve
you could also view it as marginal benefit
So that very first bag that gets produced
the supermarket gets a lot of marginal benefit
they really wanna get that bag
because then they can give it to the people
who that shop at the supermarket
and they can carry their bags home
But then each equivalent bag after that
the marginal benefit get lower and lower and lower
And this green curve over here
we've seen this multiple times
that is our supply curve
which we can also think of it
as our marginal cost curve
to produce that very first bag
The opportunity cost for that very first bag
looks like about a penny per bag
and then it gets higher and higher and higher
to produce more and more bags
And we have an equilibrium price
and an equilibrium quantity
our equilibrium quantity looks like it's about
3 and a half million bags
We have an equilibrium price
of about 2 cents per bag
if this were all of the costs
and all of the benefits
then this area, right over here
would show the aggregate total benefit
that the ecosystem here
the suppliers and the consumers
or the supermarkets or their consumers in this case
are getting from this transaction
marginal benefit higher the marginal costs
This whole area is our total surplus
we've seen that multiple times
But now let's think about that added costs
that plastic bags have
that are not factored into the costs and the prices
or the costs and the benefits right over here
Plastic bags have a negative externality!
There is a cost associated
So this is negative
because there is a cost associated with plastic bags
that is not being borne by
either, in this situation
that is not being factored
into the marginal cost curve
you can also have positive externality
which are the benefits
Maybe we'll be talking about the market for trees
and the society benefits
when more plants or more trees
are being planted or whatever
and let's just say that negative externality
that's coming from obvious things, you know
these bags are going to littered
they're going to be on the side of the highway
the city has to clean them up
there is an environmental risks due to them
animals might eat them and choke on them
and turtles might drown, you know whatever else
because they're choking on plastic bags and whatever else
and so they hire some experts
this is not an easy thing to do
But it's determined that
the negative externality of these plastic bags
is 2 cents per bag
Another way to think of it
the cost to to society and the environment
above and beyond the marginal cost to the producers
is 2 cents per bag
Now, given that
if we assume this statement right over here
It's not an easy thing to come up with this number
but if we assumed that this number is true
What then, is the optimal amount of bags to purchase
And what are we actually doing if we
or what is the optimal amount of bags to produce
and what are we doing
when we do produce this much?
And to think about that
let's create a new curve
this is the supplier's marginal cost
Let's create another curve
that is the supplier plus the society's marginal cost
So that first bag, the supplier
opportunity cost is about a penny
but for society its costing another 2 cents
So, supplier plus society
is costing almost 3 cents
So, we can plot another curve
which we can view as
the supplier plus society marginal cost
So, now we can think of things
in terms of total benefit or total net benefit
I guess that's happening
That very first bag
the supermarket that buys it
is getting that over 5 cents of benefit
but now if you think about
the net benefit to society
it's not this whole height
all the way down to a penny
it's only this part right over here
it's only the difference between 5 and 3
is the marginal net benefit
If you take the marginal benefit
and you subtract out of the total marginal costs
including the externalities
so the next bag
the total cost gets a little higher
and the marginal benefit gets a little bit lower
And you keep
it makes sense for society
will keep getting benefit from this
if you think of the entire ecosystem
will keep getting benefit
until we hit this other equilibrium point over here
And once we get past this equilibrium point
now we think holistically
when we think of the environment
and the government and all of that
Now, all of a sudden
the marginal cost of each incremental unit
is higher than the marginal benefit
So, if we were to produce beyond that
Now we're incurring costs
now we're essentially eating out
all of the benefit
that we would have gotten
if we were to produce all the way
to our old equilibrium point over here
way more in the way of this area
the purple area is more than the yellow area
We're now getting a negative total benefit to society
or you could say a negative total surplus
and we haven't visualized it this way in the past
It's unusual for us
to see a dead weight loss
on this side of the equilibrium point
but you could also view it that way
So, this right over here
is negative surplus
So what you really want holistically
if you are the benevolent emperor of the society
and you really wanna factor in
all of the costs and the benefits of the plastic bags
the ideal thing
if you wanna optimize the benefits for society
you would want the equilibrium price to be around here
that looks like about 3.50
and the equilibrium quantity
would be around 1.8 million
and you would not want all of this excess quantity
that is taking away
that is less efficient for society