We're all used to the traditional operators like addition and subtraction
and multiplication and division, and we've seen there's multiple ways to represent this
but what we are going to do in this video is a little bit of fun.
We are actually going to define our own operators.
And what's neat about this it kind of shows how broad
mathematics can be. And in a more practical sense it is something
that you actually might see on some standardized test.
And the reason why they do that is so that you can appreciate
that these are not the only operators out there, plus
exponentiation and all those, that in mathematics you can define whole
new set of operators. Let's just do that. So let me just define x diamond
x diamond y and I'm going to define that as
I'm just gonna define that as 5x minus y. So you
could view this kind of defining a function
but we are defining it using an operator
so if i have x diamond y by definition we've defined
this operator, that means that's going to be equal to 5x minus y.
So given that definition, what would-what would
7 diamond 11 be?
Well, you just go to the definition. 7 diamond 11
for instead of a x we have 7, so it's going to be
5 times 7. Just let me do 5 times 7 minus, and instead
of a y, we have an 11.
So one way to think about it is every--in our definition
every place you saw a x you can replace with 7
and every place you saw y, you replace with 11.
So you have minus 11 over here. So this is the 7
This 7 is this 7
and this 11--this 11 is this 11 right over here.
And then we just evaluate that. So 5 times 7 is 35,
So this is equal to 35, minus 11, which is equal to 24
So 7 star--or not, this isn't a star--7 diamond 11 is equal to 24.
We can define other things.
We can define something crazy like--let me define
a--well I mentioned a star, let me use a star
a star-- a -- write it this way
a star b--let's say that is the same thing as-- I don't know
a over a plus b. So it's the same idea
What would,
5 star --5 star 6 be?
Well you go back to the definition. By definition
every place you see a you would now replace with 5
every time you'd see b, you'd now replace with 6
this is going to be equal to 5 over 5 plus 6
a plus b
a is 5, b is 6
over 5 plus 6
so this would be 5/11
5/11. And then you can compound them.
We haven't defined and order of operations for these particular
operations we just have defined.
So we are going to be careful to use parentheses
when we do, when we put some of these together.
But you could do something like, something interesting
like -1 diamond--negative 1 diamond 0 star--0 star 5
and once again we just focus on parentheses, because
that is the only thing that is telling us what to start on first
because we haven't, we haven't figured out
we haven't defined whether diamond takes precedence over
star or star takes precedence over diamond.
The way we have that thing saying hey, you do multiplication before you do addition
we haven't defined it for those operations.
But that's what parentheses help us do.
So we want to evaluate the parentheses first.
0 star 5, that is 0, because so now this you can zero as the a
and the 5 as the b
this is going to be 0 over 0 plus 5. Over 0 plus 5.
which is just going to be 0. So this is just goes to 0.
So this whole expression simplifies to negative 1 diamond
this diamond right over here
diamond 0. And now we go to the definition of the
diamond operator. Well that's five times first, the first number
in our operator. The first term we are giving the operator
I guess you can think of it that way.
So 5 times that, so that will be 5 times negative 1
x is negative 1
minus y. Well y here is the zero. Minus 0
So 5 times negative 1. 5 times negative 1 is negative 5
And you will see and the idea is just to make you feel comfortable
defining new operators like this, and not feel being daunted
if you all of a sudden see a diamond. And they are
defined the diamond for you
and you are like you never saw a diamond. They are actually defining it for you
So you shouldn't say I never saw a diamond.
You'll just say, oh well they have defined diamond for me
this is how I use that operator. And sometimes you'll see even wackier things.
You'll see things like, let me draw
So they'll define. So this is, I don't know if you'd even consider this as an operator.
By definiton, if somebody writes a symbol like this
and they put an a b c--let me write this way
a, b, c, d. They'll say this is the same thing as
ad minus b, all of that over c.
And once again, this is just a definition.
They have this weird symbolic way of representing these variables
but they are just defining how (do) you evaluate this crazy expression.
And so if someone were to give you, say evaluate this diamond
evaluate this diamond--let me evaluate the diamond
so evaluate the diamond where in my little sections of the diamond I have a
negative 1, a five, a three and a two. And we would just use the definition of how we evaluate the diamond.
And we'd say every time we see an a, we say that's negative 1
so we have negative 1 times d, well d. Well d is whatever is in the bottom right section of this
diamond or this kite. So d is going to be 2. Let me write this this way.
This is a.
This is b.
This is c.
and this is d.
So this is going to be negative 1
times 2, minus b
Well b is 5
minus five
all of that over c,
which is 3.
So this is going to be equal to negative 2
minus 5. So that is negative 7. Negative 7 over 3.
And you can go crazy like this. And it might be a fun thing actually
if you have some spare time.
Define your own operators and see how creative you can be with those operators.