Most of us are familiar with the "=" sign.
From our earliest days of arithmetic you might have seen something like
1+1=2
Now, a lot of people might think when they see something like this
that somehow "=" means "give me the answer"
"1+1" is a problem,
"=" means "give me the answer",
and one plus one is two
That's not what "=" actually means
"=" is actually just trying to compare two quantities.
When I write
1+1=2
,
that literally means that what I have on the left-hand side of the equal sign is the exact same quantity as what I have in the right-hand side of the equal sign.
I could have just as easily had written
2=1+1
These two things are equal.
I could have written
2=2
This is a completely true statement,
these two things are equal.
I could have written
1+1=1+1
1+1-1=3-2
These are both equal quantities!
What I have here on the left-hand side,
this is 1
One plus one minus one is one
And this, right over here is one.
These are both equal quantities.
Now, I will introduce you to other ways of comparing numbers.
The equal sign is when I have the exact same quantity on both sides.
Now, think about what we can do when we have different quantities on both sides.
So, let's say I have the number 3 and I have the number 1, and I want to compare them.
So, clearly, 3 and 1 are not equal.
In fact, I can make that statement with the "not equal" (≠) sign.
So, I can say 3≠1 (3 does not equal 1)
But let's say I want to figure out which one is larger and which one is smaller.
So, if I want to have some symbol where I can compare them,
where I can tell, where I can state which of these is larger.
and the symbol for doing that is the ">" symbol.
(The "greater than" symbol)
This would be literally read as
"3 is greater than 1"
(3 is a larger quantity)
And if you have trouble remembering what this means "greater than...",
the larger quantity is on the opening.
I guess if you could view this as some type of an arrow,