We are asked what time is it?
So we first want to look at the hour hand which is the shorter hand here and see where it is pointing.
And it is pointing right at Seven, so we have just crossed the seventh hour.
So the hour is Seven.
and then we look at the minute hand, which is the longer hand.
and this minute hand is pointing straight up, right at 12. So this means...
..when you think of the minutes,..That's zero minutes past the hour. Each number represents five more minutes.
So this is right at 7 'o' clock.
Let's check our answers and do a few more of these..
Where is the hour hand?
This hour hand, you might say, hey, this looks closer to eight, than it is to seven.
But the key is to realize that it has passed seven, and hasn't gotten quite to eight yet.
So, we are still in the seventh hour. So the hour is seven.
Notice that these hands go in a clock-wise direction.
So just past seven hasn't gotten to eight yet.
So the hour is seven and when we want to think about the minutes, remember...
.. we started at the top of the clock, that's zero minutes past the hour.
and then we can count by fives all the way to where the minute hand is.
So, Zero, Five, Ten, Fifteen, Twenty,
Twenty-Five, Thirty, Thirty-Five, Forty,
Forty-five. We are forty-five minutes past the hour.
So it's Seven - Forty Five.
Let's do a couple more. So where is the hour hand?
Well, its between the one and the two but the key is..
to realize that it was going clock wise, it has passed the one and..
.. it is about to get to two. So it is still in the first hour.
So the hour is still one. And then the minutes...
we just have to count from Zero by Fives.
So Zero, Five, Ten, Fifteen,..
.. Twenty, Twenty-Five, Thirty, Thirty Five, Forty, Forty Five.. It is One-Forty Five PM..
Let's do one more
So here once again, the hour hand is between one and two.
So it's past one but hasn't gotten to two yet.
So we are still in the first hour. And then the minutes...
.. Well we start at 12, that's zero minutes past the hour.
Zero, Five, Ten, Fifteen.
So it is One - Fifteen.
Let's do even one more.
So this one, the hour hand is exactly at two.
and the minute hand is exactly at twelve.
That means we are zero minutes past the hour.