I've talked a lot about precision and the inclinations I have not told you "why" this is happening...I am not going to go into the physics of it. That is a little bit
beyond the discussion over here...but its a byproduct of the earth and sun's interactions with the Earth
And with the fact that the earth is not a perfect sphere... So this is my little drawing of Earth. And let me put() the pole
in here...North pole && South pole...It actually turns out that Earth...is fat'r than it is taller. So
if you where to measure Earth's diameter along the equator, it's diameter along the equator -> it is
43 kilometers (approximately 27 miles) longer. than if ( you were to measure it's diamter from Pole ->
to pole. and the fact that Earth has the "equatorial bulge" it's not a perfect sphere...Once again I
will not go into the math here...;)
1/8 symmetric (sorry) of the Earth...that interaction between the Earth the pull() of that causes these
long term cycles...this this this actual precision...I* guess are less ...and as we will see in the next
video, these arent the only types of changes we have...the elipse...Earth's orbit actual rotates over
time...two interactions with earth's orbit...and once again...it's one of those things that happens over
thousands and thousands of years...So all of these changes More fat than it is tall those interactions
between the gravity of the Earth of the Moon && Earth's orbit as a whole changes because of interactions