PROBLEM: Construct a line perpendicular to the given line.
So, if I can pick two arbitrary points on this line –
and if I can make a line that is always
equidistant from those two points,
then that line will be perpendicular –
– and actually it will be a perpendicular bisector
of the segment formed by those two points.
Now they don't care whether we're bisecting anything.
But they do care about it being perpendicular.
So let's do this.
So I'm going to draw a circle with my compass.
And so let's just pick that point right over there.
I can adjust the radius if I like.
But I might as well –
Well, I'll just leave it right over there.
Now let me draw another circle.
And this time, I'm going to center it where
the first circle intersects with my line.
And then I'm going to adjust the radius
to overlap with the first dot.
And now, where these two circles intersect,
those are points that are equidistant
from both of these centers that I just constructed.
So let me draw a line that connects those two.
And that line is going to be perpendicular
to our original line.