Let's now account for the same series of events
but instead of doing it on a cash basis
let's do it on an accrual basis. And the whole idea
with accrual accounting, is to match your revenues and expenses
to when you actually perform the service,
so it actual captures a business activity,
as opposed to just capturing when cash changes hands.
So let's see what that actually means.
So in month 1 you cater an even where the cost to you was $100
The customer pays you $200 for your services
And what I'll do, I'll do the accrual accounting right here
So this kind of the cash income statement,
let's do the accrual accounting income statement.
So you actually provided the service of catering,
you got $200 for your services, so I'll put $200
in for revenue.
And the expenses associated with that service
that you provided in month 1 is $100.
And so your profit is $100.
So at least for month 1, the cash basis and the accrual basis of accounting
look exactly the same. And once again
you have $100 in cash. Now let's go to month 2:
You cater an event where the cost to you was $200
You and the customer agree that they can pay you $400
the next month. So now it get's interesting,
because you performed the catering that month
and the catering you performed that month is
worth $400. So in the accrual basis of accounting,
you would say that you earned $400 of revenue in this month.
Even though the customer did not pay you,
they did not give you the cash.
The way that you account for that,
is on your balance sheet, you say that you are
essentially owed $400, so this accounts receivable
this is essential stuff that other people owe you,
you need to receive this from other people,
but it's an asset, other people have an obligation to you
So you have accounts receivable of $400
When they pay you the $400, it goes from accounts receivable to
cash. And then the cost to you was $200.
So the cost to you was $200. So here all of a sudden,
you performed the service,
the revenues and expenses for that service
are in that month, and now your profit here
shows $200, so it is actually a better reflection
of what you did that month.
Now, the reality is you didn't get the cash forward,
and you had to spend $200 of cash out of your pocket,
so you're still, just like the cash accounting,
you're still going to have negative $100 in cash.
Now let's go to month 3.
You get $400 from the customer the previous month.
Now, with cash basis, you would have added that to your revenue,
but here, we already accounted for it in the accounts receivable,
we already took that revenue.
But because you've got the $400 in cash, it's going to
disappear from receivables, and then go into cash,
cause you actually got it.
You get $400 from the customer in the previous month.
You also get $200 in advance from a customer that you have to cater for next month
So you did no catering in month 3,
and because you did no catering in month 3,
you have 0 revenue in month 3, and then you also have 0 expenses,
the way that you account for the $400 that you got,
is that your accounts receivables goes to 0,
and that goes to cash, so the negative $100
you add $400 to it, so it becomes positive $300.
And the way that you account for this $200 in advance
from a customer, is you call that deferred revenue.
You got the cash there, so we went from negative $100
added $400 to $300 and you had another $200 in cash,
so that gives us $500 in cash again,
but we didn't earn any revenue,
that $200, that was a kind of cash advance,
so we put that right over here in deferred revenue,
that's revenue that we're deferring to a future period,
in the future we will earn, this is now a liability
because we were obligated to earn that revenue.
And then in month 4 we actually earned the revenue.
So in month 4, we can actually put it in our income statement
at $200, and then we had $100 of expenses,
so that we have this $100 right over here.
And so in month 4 we earned $100,
and once again, $100 went away from our cash balance,
so we still have $400.
So whether you do the cash basis or accrual basis
you have the same exact amount of cash,
what's more interesting is how the profit
relates in each of the periods,
and I'll talk about that in a little more depth
in the next video.