Let's have some practice adding and subtracting negative numbers. So the first example
that I want to look at is 2-3.
So right now I am just subtracting a positive number from another positive
number but you might already see that I am subtracting a larger number from a smaller
number so I probably or definitely will end up with a negative number.
Let's just think about this a little bit and I am going to do it with the number line.
So there's my number line right over there. Now this is 0
This is 1. This is 2 This is negative 1 this is Negative 2. We could view this as starting
at 2 so this is 2 right over here and were going to subtract
3 from that 2 so we are going to move 3 to the left on the number line. so were going to move 3 to the left.
1, 2, 3, and that gets us to negative 1.
so it's equal to negative 1. Now let's mix it up a little bit more.
Let's imagine what would happen if we had negative 2 minus 3
So this was positive 2 minus 3. Now let's think about negative 2 minus 3.
So once again lets draw our number line and I will put 0 over here.
So this is 0, this is 1, this is negative 1, negative 2, negative 3, negative 4, negative 5, negative 6 and I could keep going
but were starting at negative 2, starting at negative 2 and then were subtracting 3 again so once again we are going to move 3 to the left.