[music playing]
&gt;&gt;: We're looking at a work by
Robert Smithson, and it dates to
1970, and it's called
"The Spiral Jetty."
This is a photograph showing it.
It must have been taken from a
helicopter, and it's what you
call a work of environmental
art or land art.
It's essentially a bunch of dirt
and rubble that has been pushed
out into the spiral form into a
lake, into this salt lake in
Utah.
&gt;&gt;: It exists in this one place
and this one time.
Could we say it is site
specific?
&gt;&gt;: Right, exactly.
We call it site specific.
One of the things that Smithson
wanted to emphasize was a kind
of a distinction between, you
know, the site of the work of
art, and the traditional site of
the work, which would be a
gallery or a museum or private
home and kind of breaking down
barriers, saying, is a work of
art only to be contained by
museum or can we also
find it elsewhere?
And so he is part of a larger
movement of artists who are
specifically locating or
situating their work in the
land, and oftentimes the works
have these very, very large
proportions.
Like this juts out 1500
feet into the water.
&gt;&gt;: And can you walk through it?
&gt;&gt;: You can usually walk on it.
Well, not necessarily.
It depends on the height
of the water itself.
So sometimes it is submerged.
So this photograph shows that
there are some people out on the
jetty.
&gt;&gt;: Yeah, I see.
&gt;&gt;: But it has been slightly
covered by water.
Sometimes it's lower or higher.
It depends on the depth of the
water in Utah at the time, and
it's very a salty lake.
So it's a work that really is
certainly part of the
environment, but also interacts
and changes the environment in
important ways.
So you could also maybe
categorize it under the category
of process art because it is
something that is forever
changing.
You know, he had one idea of it,
but then there are things that
act upon it and will change it
for, you know, for as long as it
is there.
&gt;&gt;: It is made of things that
are so durable, though.
One gets a sense of
existing beyond human life.
&gt;&gt;: Right.
And it has such a
basic shape as well.
He is interested in some ancient
examples of prehistoric land
art, mounds that have been found
in America and elsewhere, and it
is sort of inspired by that
somewhat abstract quality of a
lot of those.
The idea that your vision of it
right now as you see it as a
totality.
When you are in it of course,
you are only experiencing it,
and it is a very, very
different way
of seeing partial
aspects of it.
&gt;&gt;: What interests me is
that you can go into it
and walk through it.
&gt;&gt;: Right, usually you are not
supposed to touch the art.
&gt;&gt;: No, right.
I like that idea of touching it
and being inside it.
&gt;&gt;: He liked it, too.
Yeah, and --
&gt;&gt;: -- it is fun.
It makes it fun.
&gt;&gt;: Yeah, and he had to use a
lot of construction tools,
massive trucks to drive the
rubble down and also to employ a
lot of people.
So it really destabilizes our
idea that the artist is an
individual, a single person who
is the mastermind.
Of course he did come up with
the scheme, but he never could
have realized this alone.
&gt;&gt;: Right.
&gt;&gt;: And that is such an
important idea now.
Things can be made by groups of
people, by factories, people
that the artist can employ.
&gt;&gt;: Right.
And maybe he is going back also
to what he thinks ancient art
was like, that it was not done
by a single genius artist but
rather was a communal thing and
then was sort of left open
for everyone to interact with.