We finished off the last video in the Hadean Eon.
It was named for Hades or the ancient greek Underworld
Hades is also the name of the guy who ran the ancient greek underworld
Zeus's older brother and it was an appropriate name,
although the idea, the ancient greek notion of the underworld
isn't exactly the modern notion of hell, but it was a
hellish environment, you had all this lava flowing around
and things impacting the earth from space. As far as
we can tell right now it was completely inhospitable
to life. And to make matters worse, even though the
earth started to cool down a little bit, maybe the crust
became a little bit more solid, maybe the collisions
started to happen less and less as we started to go
a few hundred million years fast forward after
Theia ran into the early earth and formed the moon
There is something like the "Late heavy bombardment"
and right now the consensus is that life - whatever we
are descended from - would have had to come about after
the late heavier bombardment, because this was a time when
so many things from outer space were hitting earth,
it was so violent, that it might have killed off any
kind of primitive, self replicating organisms or molecules
that might have existed before it. And I won't go into
the physics of the late heavy bombardment.
What we believe of what happened, because Uranus and
Neptune, so this is the sun right here, That is the sun.
This is the asteroid belt. That's outside the orbit of the
inner rocky planets. But Urans and Neptune,
their Orbits moved outward. What that caused is
gravitationally it caused a lot of the asteroids of the
asteroid belt to move inward and started impacting
the inner planets, and earth was one the inner planets.
And also impacted the moon. It also obvious on the moon
The moon doesn't have an atmosphere to smooth over the
impacts. The consensus is that only after the late heavy
bombardment was Earth kindof ready for life.
We believe that the first life formed 3.824 billion
years ago. Remember, G for Giga, 4 billions years ago.
When we're talking about life in this period, we're not
talking about squirrels or panda bears. We're talking about
extremely simple life forms. Prokaryotes.
Let me give you a little primer on that.
We're talking about Prokaryotes. I'll compare them
to Eukaryotes.
Prokaryotes are for the most part unicellular organisms
that have no nuclei. They also don't have any membrane
bound organelles, or what we would call parts of the cells
that would perform specific functions, like Mitochondria
So their DNA is just floating around.
Let me draw this character's DNA.
So it's just floating around ,just like that.
Prokaryote literrally means : "Before kernel" or
"Before Nucleus"
Eukaryotes DO have a nucleus with all their DNA.
So this is their nuclear membrane with the nuclear
DNA floating inside it
It also has other membrane bound organelles, Mitochondria
is kindof the most famous of them
Mitochondria, we think is basically one prokaryote
crawling into the membrane of another and becoming stuck
and they both becoming a symbiotic organism with each other
So at this time we're still talking Prokaryotes at this stage.
This shows our current understanding of where things
branched off from, at this point of the tree
is some common ancestor to prokaryotes and eukaryotes
prokaryotes right over here
the bacteria and archeae
and here is the eucaryotes
and this first living thing we think might have been
some self replicating molecules, maybe a little bit more
organized membrane, DNA and RNA became
the method of passing information from one generation to the next
It is still an open question what that first life is
or how you even define that first life
Based on the makeup of DNA molecules of the current
organisms, this is how the think the tree of life came about
We have one common ancestor, then the Archeae and Prokaryotes
have a common Ancestor, it's different from the Bacteria
this is an example of Bacteria, Ecoli
We think that the earliest lifeforms we anaerobes
these did not need oxygen and for the most part
found oxygen poisonous and the earliest
lifeforms probably also did not perform photosynthesis
They might have gotten their energy from other sources
Chemically probably in that extremely volatile
environment that they were in
Lets forward to a major event, these are big time scales
we are talking about here
This is a big timescale, we're talking about 800 million
years, humans and chimpanzees have ony
diverged 5 million years ago
From ancient greece to now we're talking about only
2,500 years ! You multiply that by 1,000 you get
2,5 million years.
And this is 800 million years !
These are extremely huge periods of time.
That's why we call them Eons.
The dividing line between the Hadean Eon and the
Archean Eon is a bit fuzzy.
Most people place it at about 3.8 Billion years ago.
It's about the earliest rocks we can observe.
We have rocks from about that time.
So there are 2 things, Rocks have survived and that is
also when we think life has started. So now we are in the
the Archean Eon.
But there is still none to little oxygen in the Environment
If you went to the earth at this time it would have looked
something like this, a reddish sky. You would have had
nitrogen and methane and carbondioxide in the atmosphere
There would still have been a lot of volcanic activity
This right here, these are pictures of stromatolites
These are formed from Bacteria that are bringing in
sediment particles, and over time these things get
built up.
The most important even in the Archean Eon in my opinion
, we believe this happened about 3.5 billion years ago
Prokaryotes, or especially bacteria evolving to use the
energy from the sun
To actually do photosynthesis
The side effect from this was the production of oxygen
And at first this oxygen didn't really accumulate in the atmosphere
because there was a lot of dissolved iron in the oceans
All of the life for the next billion years all occured
in the oceans. There was no ozone layer.
The land was being irradiated, a completely inhospitable
environment for life.
The first oxygen that got produced, instead of being
released into the atmosphere instead bonded with the
iron that was dissolved in the ocean
Once a lot of that iron was oxidized later on and the
oxygen did get released into the atmosphere it had
a cataclysmic effect.
Especially on the anaerobic life that existed until then.
It was neccessary though for us to happen later on.
Still a few billions years though before things start
flopping around on the land. See you at the next video.