So we have matrix D and matrix B and they ask, is DB defined?
Is the product D times B defined?
D times B is going to be defined, is if--
Let me make this very clear.
This is how I think about it.
Let me copy and paste it, so I can do this on my scratch pad.
To answer that question--
Let me get out my scratch pad over here.
Let me paste the question right here.
Let's think about these 2 matrices.
First, we have matix D.
I'll do it as a nice bold D here.
It has three rows and three columns.
It is a three by three matrix.
Then you want to multiply that times matix B.
Matrix B is a two by two matrix.
The only way that we know to define matrix multiplication
is if these middle two numbers are the same.
If the number of columns D has is equal to
the number of rows B has.
In this case they clearly do not equal each other,
so matrix multiplication is not defined here.
Let's go back there and say no, no DB is not defined.
Let's do a few more of these examples.
We have a two by one-- We could view this as a two by one matrix,
or we could view this as a column vector.
This is another two by one matrix, or column vector.
Is C plus B defined?
Matrix addition is defined if both matrices have the exact same dimensions,
and these two matrices do have the exact same dimensions.
The reason why is because with matrix addition
you just add every corresponding term.
With the sum the top--
It will actually be 4+0 over -2+0,
which is still going to be the same thing as this up here.
But what their asking is just to find absolutely
that these both are two by one matrices.
So yes it is defined.
Let's do one more.
Once again their asking us is the product A times E defined?
Here you have a two by two matrix.
Let me copy and paste this so we can make
sure we know what we are talking about.
Let's get my scratch pad out.
This top matrix right over here, matrix A,
is a two by two matrix.
Matrix E-- Were gonna multiply it times matrix E,
which has one row and two columns.
In this scenario, once again, the number of columns
matrix A has is two and the number of rows matrix E has is one.
This will not be defined.
These two things have to be the same for them to be defined.
Now, what is interesting is, if you did it the other way around--
If you took E times A-- Let's check if this would be defined.
Matrix E is one by two, one row by two columns.
Matrix A is a two by two, two rows and two columns.
This would have been defined.
Matrix E has two columns which is exactly
the same number of rows that matrix A has.
This really hits home that the order matters when you multiply matrices.
For the sake of this question, is AE defined, no it isn't.
We can check our answer, no it isn't.