As we've already seen, the end of fighting in World War I
or I guess we have the end of world war one in 1918
and so in 1919, it's time to talk about the terms for peace
and this happens at the paris peace conference
And at this conference, you have all the parties of all the major warring parties
but the terms of peace are dictated by the winners.
and the major powers among the winners are led by these gentlemen over here
This is prime minster Lloyd George of the UK, Vittorio Orlando
of Italy, George Clemenceau of France, President Woodrow wilson of the United States,
and they come to the Paris Peace conference
with very different outlooks of what the peace should look like
We already learned about President Wilson's 14 points. It was very idealistic.
It talked about making the world safe for democracy, how people should determine their own fate,
how we should have the self determination
the end of empires, free trade, creating a league of nations,
so that you can avoid things like world war I again.
The European side was not quite as idealistic, especially the french. As you can
imagine, the french- The us lost a lot of soldiers in World War 1 but the french lost a significant fraction
of their adult males in world war one. the ugly western front was fought in their country
So they were much more eager to make germany pay for what
-for what it's done. So the terms of the treaty with Germany
the treaty of Versailles, and the treaty of Versailles, it's important
to note is only one of several treaties that came out of the paris
peace conferece. It tends to get the most attention because it was
the treaty with germany and many people blame it for
being part of the cause of world war 2. it so humiliated germany that it was so unnacceptable