Keeping in mind how much salt you should be taking if you're on a low-sodium diet,
I'm just gonna write that here: "Low sodium diet".
I was thinking, of all the food that I typically like to consume
and where that fits in the amount that I'm allowed in a given day.
If I'm on a low sodium diet the amount was about 1500mg of sodium per day.
This is sodium – not salt, remember.
If I go through a few foods that'll be fun to figure out how much sodium is in these foods.
Let's start out with something I had not too long ago:
I was recently on a road trip and I stopped off on the side of the road
and I picked up one of my favourite little snacks which was a large carton of fries.
I had some fries and they were delicious.
These are large fries.
I actually love to eat fries with ketchup,
so I had 5 ketchup packets, so this is one food item.
Another food item I've had many many times,
especially when I’m in a big rush and I don't have time to go out and get a proper lunch,
I'll sit down and grab a cup of noodles.
I'll grab a cup of noodles and if you had these,
they are dehadrated noodles that are in here.
If you like me you'll love them.
This is a cup of noodles.
This was another item that I thought would be good to look at.
The next item or the last item is similar to the cup of noodles.
It's another cup of noodles but the kind that you might take when you're sick.
Whenever I'm sick one of the things I always reach for is a pot of water.
I like to boil up the water and cook a block of noodles inside of it.
Put the flavoring packet there and these are dehydrated noodles.
I like to eat those, so these are my dehydrated noodles in a pot of water.
I call that a block of noodles and I usually eat one whole block at a time with the flavoring.
I've gotta a few things here: block of noodles, cup of noodles and also my large fries with ketchup.
I know my limit is 1500mg in a day,
so how far along do these things get me?
One by one, let me just tell you the answer.
The large fries with packets of ketchup – 5 packets, is about 900mg of sodium.
The cup of noodles is about 1200mg of sodium.
You can see I'm going up-up-up, so my block of noodles is actually 1600mg of sodium.
This one puts me over the amount that I'm allowed in a whole day
and that is usually what I would have just for lunch.
It's an immense amount of sodium, tonnes of sodium and it got me thinking:
how in the world, and I'm not actually on a low sodium diet, but if I was...
How in the world would I be able to do it?
I was browsing the Internet and I came across a website which I'm gonna share with you.
It's from the Mayo Clinic.
I don't want to say this is the only website,
there'are tonnes of great websites out there,
but this one website actually got me thinking.
What I thought is, why don't I figure out what kind of food I could actually get?
If I was on a low sodium diet, what would make sense?
I picked out a few things from there
that I thought would be tasty.
They have one thing that's a roasted salmon – this is my salmon.
If I eat a roasted salmon with all of oil and chives, the amount of sodium is 60mg.
Not bad, right?
Let's say I wanna eat that with some potatoes – I've got some roasted potatoes over here
which I love, so does my dad.
These roasted potatoes get me 7mg of sodium.
Potatoes are great, salmon is great but I like my vegetables.
What if I get some asparagus in there?
Some roasted asparagus and other recipe for mushrooms with a roasted asparagus.
This meal is looking better and better and if I get some asparagus with the mushrooms
that's an additional 11mg of sodium, so that's pretty reasonable.
Since since I'm doing so well
I was tempted to go to their 'Dessert menu' and I grabbed one of the recipies for apple pie.
Apple pie is an American favourite, certainly one of my favourites.
I love to make apple pie and that gets me about 16mg of sodium.
If I'm totaling all of this up, I've got 60+7+11+16.
That total comes to...
94mg of sodium.
It's 94mg of sodium is well within my limit of 1500mg of sodium per day.
This is one place you can go to get some good food recommendations.
As I said there are many many others as well.