Find the probability of rolling doubles on two six-sided dice numbered from 1 to 6.
So when they're talking about rolling doubles they're just saying if I roll the two dice I get the same number on the top of both.
So for example, a 1 and a 1; that's doubles.
Two and a two, that is doubles. A three and a three, a four and a four, a five and a five, a six and a six.
All of those are instances of doubles. So the event in question is rolling doubles on two six-sided dice numbered from 1 to 6.
So let's think about all of the possible outcomes. Or another way to think about it, let's think about the sample space here.
So what can we roll on the first die? So let me write this as die number 1. What are the possible rolls?
Well they're numbered from 1 to 6: it's a six sided die.
So I can get a one, a two, a three, a four, a five, or a six.
Now let's think about the second die. So die number 2.
Well exact same thing. I can get a one, a two, a three, a four, a five, or a six.
Now, given these possible outcomes for each of the die, we can now think of the outcomes for both die.
So for example, in this, in this... (Let me draw a grid here just to make it a little bit neater. Draw a line there, and then a line right over there...)
Let me draw actually, several of these just so we can really just do this a little bit clearer.
Let me draw a full grid. All right.
And then the vertical lines.
Only a few more left. There we go.
Now, all this top row, these are the outcomes where I roll a one on the first die.
So I roll a one on the first die. These are all of those outcomes.
And this would be a one on the second die, but I'll fill that in later.
These are all the outcomes where I roll a two on the first die.
This is where I roll a three on the first die.
Four... I think you get the idea (on the first die). And then a five on the first die...
Then this last row is all the outcomes where I roll a six on the first die.
Now, we can go through the columns, and this first column is where we roll a one on the second die.
This is where we roll a two on the second die.
Here's where we roll a three on the second die.
Here's where we have a four.
And then here's where we roll a five on the second die.
(Filling this in... Whoops..) This last column is where we roll a six on the second die.
Now every one of these represents a possible outcome. This outcome is where we roll a one on the first die and a one on the second die.
This outcome is where we roll a three on the first die and a two on the second die. This outcome is where we roll a four on the first die and a five on the second die.
And you can see here there are thirty-six possible outcomes: Six times six possible outcomes.
Now with this out of the way, how many of these outcomes satisfy our criteria... Satisfy the criteria of rolling doubles on two six-sided die?
How many of these outcomes are essentially described by our event?
Well, we see them right here. Doubles, that's rolling a one and a one, a two and a two, a three and a three, a four and a four, a five and a five, and a six and a six.
So we have one, two, three, four, five, six events that satisfy this event (or the outcomes that are consistent with this event)...
Now given that, let's answer our question. What is the probability of rolling doubles on two six-sided die numbered from 1 to 6?
Well the probability is going to be equal to the number of outcomes that satisfy our criteria, or the number of outcomes for this event.
... Which are six (we just figured that out) over the total number of outcomes... Over the size of our sample space.
So this right over here, we have thirty-six total outcomes.
So we have thirty-six outcomes, and if you simplify this, six over thirty-six is the same thing as 1/6.
So the probability of rolling doubles on two six-sided die numbered from 1 to 6 is 1/6.