So you're me and you're in math class
--triangles, triangles, triangles--
I don't know--the teacher keeps saying words?
And you're supposed to be doing something with trigon
whatever those are.
But you're bored and--triangles, triangles, triangles, triangles
Sure you could draw your triangles separately, but then they get lonely.
They're happiest when snuggled up together into a triangle party. Everybody knows triangles love parties!
Sometimes they get together into these triangle conga lines.
And if you keep adding new triangles on the same side
it gets all curvy and spirally
or you can alternate and it goes sorta straight
In fact, since all the sides of the triangle are supposed to be straight lines
and since they are all lying on top of the previous straight line
then this whole line would have to be straight
if we were actually triangles
since it's not
it's proved that these aren't quite triangles
maybe they've been partying a little too hard
But hey!
At least you're not doing math.
Speaking of which,
the teacher is still going on about types of trigots,
and you're supposed to be taking notes,
but you're more interested in types of triangles
which you already know about.
There are fat triangles
pointy triangles
perfect triangles
cheese slice triangles
which are a kind of pointy triangle,
but are symmetric like a slice of cheese, or cake.
Super pointy triangles are fun to stack into triangle stacks.
You could pull all the points facing one direction,
but the stacks start to wobble too much towards that direction
so it's good to put some facing the other direction before you go too far.
You'll notice pretty quickly that the skinnier the triangle
the less wobble it adds to the stack.
To compensate for a big wobble
you could put just one not so skinny triangle that's pointing the other way.
Or maybe you want to wobble
because you have to navigate you triangle stack around your notes
in which case you can even alternate back and forth.
as long as you make the triangles point towards where you want to go a little less skinny.
The easy part about triangle stacks
is that there's really only one part of the triangle
that's important as far as the stack is concerned
and that's the pointy point.
The other two angles can be fat and skinny
or skinny and fat
or both the same if it's a cheese slice
and it doesn't change the rest of the stack
unless the top angle is really wide
because then you'll get two skinny points
and which side should you continue to stack on?
Both?
Also, instead of thinking fat and skinny
you should probably create code words
that won't set off your teacher's mind reading alarms
for non-math related thoughts.
So you'd pick two words off the board:
obtuse and acute
Which by sheer coincidence, I'm sure, just happen to mean fat angle and skinny angle.
Of course,
those are also kinds of triangles
which doesn't make much sense
because the obtuser one angle of a triangle is,
the more acute the other two get
Yet, if you make an acute triangle with the same perimeter,
it has more area
which seems like an obtuseish quality
and then, can you still call an obtuse equilateral triangle a cheese or cake slice triangle?
because these look more like common .
Point is,
triangle terminology is tricky.
But at least you're not paying attention to the stuff the teacher is saying
about trigonometric functions.
You'd rather think about the functions of triangles
and you already know some of those.
There are sines and cosines,
but enough of this tangent. :))
The thing to pay attention to is what affects you triangle how.
If you start drawing the next triangle on your triangle stack this way
by this point you already know what the full triangle will have to be
because you just continue this edge until it meets this invisible line
and then fill the rest in.
In fact, you can make an entire triangle stack
just by piling on triangle parts and adding the points later to see what happens.
There are some possible problems though.
If you start a triangle like this,
you can see that's it's never going to close
no matter how far you extend the lines.
Since this triangle isn't real, let's call it a bermuda triangle.
This happens when two angles together are already more than 180 degrees.
And since all the angles in a triangle add up to 180
which by the way you can test by ripping one up and putting the three points into a line
this means that if these are two 120 degree angles of a triangle.
The third angle is off somewhere being negative 60.
Of course you'd have no problem being a bermuda triangle on a sphere
where angles always add up to more than 180.
Just the third point might be off in Australia.
Which is fine, unless you're afraid your triangle will get eaten by sea monsters.
Anyway, second triangles into a curve is nice
and you probably want to make your spiral
but if you're not careful, it will crash into itself
so you'd better think about your angles.
Though, if you do just right instead of a crash disaster
you'd get a wreath thing or you can get a different triangle circle by starting with a polygon
extending the sides in one direction
and then triangleing around it to get this sort of apeture shape
and then you should probably add more
triangles, triangles, triangles, triangles.
One last game.
Start with some sort of asterisk
then go around and triangle it up
shade out from the obtusest angles and it'll look pretty neat.
You can then extend it with another layer of triangles
and another
and if you shade the inner parts of each triangle
it's guaranteed to be an awesome triangle party.
And there's lots of other kinds of triangle parties just waiting to happen.
Ah, the triangle.
So simple, yet so beautiful.
The essence of two-dimensionality.
The fundamental object of euclidean geometry.
The three points that define a plane.
You can have your fancy, complex shapes
they're just made up of triangles.
Triangles
dissect a square into triangles
make symmetric arrangements
some reminiscent of spherical and hyperbolic geometry
triangles branch into binary fractal tree
numbers increasing exponential with each iteration to infinity.
Triangles
with the right proportion being a golden spiral of perfect right, isoceles triangles
put equilateral triangles on the middle third on the outside edges of equilateral triangles
to infinity and get a snowflake with a boundary of a koch curve
an infinitely long perimeter
continuous yet nowhere differentiable
with a fractional dimension of log 4 over log 3
And uh-oh,
teacher's walking around
better pretend to be doing math!