Let's now use our understanding of some of the operations on sets to get some blood flowing to our brains.
I've defined some sets here, and just to make things interesting, I haven't only put numbers in these sets.
I've also put some colours and some little yellow stars here.
What I want you to figure out is, what would this set be?
This crazy thing that involves relative complements, intersections, unions, absolute complements.
I encourage you to pause it and try to figure out what this set would be.
Let's give it a shot. The key here is really to break it down.
Work on the stuff in the parentheses first
just as you would do if you were trying to parse a traditional mathematical statement
and then it should hopefully make a little bit of sense.
A good place to start is to try to figure out what is the relative complement of C in B (B\C)
or another way of thinking about it is what is B minus C,
what is B if you take out all the stuff with C in it?
Let me write this down:
The relative complement of C in B, or you could call this B minus C
this is all the stuff in B with all the stuff in C taken out of it.
Let's think about what this would be.
B has a 0, does C has a 0? No, so we don't have to take out the 0.
B has a 17, does C have a 17? Yes it does, so we take out the 17.
B has a 3 but C has a 3 so we take that out.
B has a "blue", C doesn't not have a "blue", so we leave the blue in.
B has a gold star but C also has a gold star so we take the gold star out.
The relative complement of C in B is just the set of 0 and this "blue" written in blue.
Now it gets interesting.
We're going to take the absolute complement of that.
The absolute complement of this business (B\C) is going to be the set of all things in our universe
that are neither a 0 or a blue.
That's the only way I can describe it right now, I haven't really defined the universe well.
We already see that our universe definitely contains some integers
it contains some colours, it contains some stars
so this is all I can really say: it's the set of all things that are neither a 0 or a blue.
So far we've figured out all of this stuff.
Now we want to find the intersection of A and this business.
It's going to be A intersected with the absolute complement of the relative complement of C in B.
This is going to be the intersection of the set A and the set of all things in the universe
that are neither a 0 or a blue.
It's essentially the things that satisfy both of these things.
It has to be in set A, and it has to be in the set of all things in the universe that are neither a 0 or a blue.
Let's think about what this is.
The number 3 is in the set A and it's in the set of all things in the universe that are neither a 0 or a blue
so let's throw a 3 in there.
The number 7 is in A and in the set of all things in the universe that are neither a 0 or a blue
so let's put a 7 there.
-5 also meets that constraint.
A 0 does not meet that constraint.
A 0 is in A but it's not in the set of all things in the universe that are neither 0 or blue because it is a 0
so we're not going to throw a 0 in there.
Then a 13 is in A and it's in the set of all things in the universe that are neither a 0 or a blue
so we could throw a 13 in there.
We've simplified things a good bit, all of this crazy business has simplified to this set right over here.
Now we want to find the relative complement of this business in A.
I'll just actually write out the set. I'll write out both of them so we can really visualize them both right over here.
A is 3, 7, -5, 0 and 13, and relative complement with all of this business which we figured was a 3, 7, -5 and 13.
So essentially, start with this set (the first one) and take out all the things that are in this set (the second one).
This is going to be equal to:
We're going to take out a 3, 7, -5, and 13 out of the set
so we're just left with a set that contains a 0.
So all of this business right over here has simplified to a set that only contains 0.
Now let's think about what B intersect C is.
These are all of the things that are in both B and C.
This is going to be:
0 is not in both of them.
17 is in both of them, so we'll throw a 17 there.
The number is 3 in both of them.
Blue is not in both of them.
The star is in both of them.
That's B intersect C.
We're essentially going to take the union of this crazy thing, which ended up just being a set with a 0 in it
we're going to take the union of that with B intersect C
and, we deserve a drumroll now, this is all going to be equal to, when we combine these two sets
it's going to be a set with a 0, 17, 3, and our gold star.
And we are done!