The number 36 is 3 times as large as 12. Write this comparison as a multiplication equation.
So they're saying the number 36 (I'll type "36") is equal to 3 times 12.
And I used this little star thing (asterick "*")... let's see, if I put an "x" there, would that have worked as well?
No, they would have viewed that as 3x.
So... to get this little star thing (asterick) which is normally how you would show multiplication on a computer...
You have to press "shift" and the number "8". And it also shows up on a numeric keypad.
By doing that I was able to show multiplication.
So this can be read as, "36 is equal to 3 times 12". Or "36 is 3 times as large as 12".
So let's check our answer. Got it right! Let's do a couple more of these...
We can compare 4 and 20 using addition by saying that 20 is 16 more than 4.
Fair enough, that's right.
We could also compare 4 and 20 using multiplication.
Fill in the blank correctly to compare the numbers 4 and 20 using multiplication.
So they're saying "20 is (blank) times as large as 4".
Well we know that 4 times 5 is 20. Or that 5 times 4 is 20.
So 20 is 5 times as large as 4. If I take 4 five times, I'll get to 20.
(So let me check my answer... there you go.)
Let's do one more...
The number 6 is 3 times as large as 2.
Write this comparison as a multiplication equation.
We could write that 6 is equal to 2 (and then I press "shift" and the number "8" to get that "times" symbol... that little asterick snowflake looking thing...)
2 times 3. So I could write it like that, or I could write "2 times 3 is equal to 6." Either of those would be completely valid things to say.
So here I'm saying 6 is... Well... I could say... I'd like to say it this way:
"3 times as large as 2." I think that's a little more fun.
So this is exactly: "6 is 3 times as large as 2."
And we're done.