Let's see if we can write 0.36 as a fraction.
There are several ways of doing it. The way I like to do it is to say, well,
0.36, this is the same thing as 36 hundredths. Or, one way to think about it is,
This is in the hundredths place..
This is in the tenths place, or you could view this as 30 hundredths. You can view this as 3 tenths or 30 hundredths.
So we could say that this is the same thing as 36 hundredths or this is equal to "36 over 100."
We've already expressed it as a fraction, but now we can actually simplify it, because both 36 and 100 have some common factors.
They are both divisible by 4, so if we could divide the numerator by 4, and the denominator by 4 (we're doing the same thing to both, so we're not changing the value of the fraction),
36 divided by 4 is 9. And then 100 divided by 4 is 25.
And now these two characters don't seem to share any other common factors,
so we've written it in simplified form. And we're done.