Newton's first law tells us that an object at rest will stay at rest
and an object with a constant velocity will keep having that constant velocity
unless it's affected by some type of net force
or you actually could say an object with constant velocity will stay having a constant velocity
unless it's affected by net force
because really this takes into consideration the situation where an object is at rest
you could just have a situation where the constant velocity is zero
So Newton's first law, you're gonna have your constant velocity it could be zero,
it's going to stay being that constant velocity unless it's affected, unless there's some net force
that acts on it, so that leads to the natural question:
How does a net force affect the constant velocity? or how does it affect the state of an object?
And that's what Newton's second law gives us.
So Newton's second law of motion.
And this one is maybe the most famous, they're all kind of famous
actually, I won't pick favorites here, but this one gives us the famous formula
Force is equal to Mass times Acceleration
And acceleration is a vector quantity and force is a vector quantity
and what it tells us, because we're saying okay, if you apply force
it might change that constant velocity
but how does it change that constant velocity?
We'll say I have a brick right here, and it is floating in space
Newton's second law tells us, and it's pretty nice for us that the laws of the universe,
or at least in the classical sense, before Einstein showed up,
the laws of the universe actually dealt with pretty simple mathematics
what it tells us is if you apply a net force on this side of the object
and we talk about net force because if you apply two forces that cancel out,
and have zero net force, then the object won't change it's constant velocity
if you have a net force applied to one side of this object,
then you're going to have a net acceleration going in the same direction
and what Newton's second law of motion tells us is that acceleration
is proportional to the force applied, or the force applied is proportional to that acceleration
and the constant of proportionality or to figure out what you have to multiply
the acceleration by to get the force, or what you have to divide the force by to get the acceleration
is called mass, that is an object's mass.
and I'll make a whole video on this, you should not confuse mass with weight
and I'll make a whole video on the difference between mass and weight
mass is a measure of how much stuff there is, now that we'll see in the future
there are other things that we don't normally consider "stuff" that does start to have mass
but for our classical or at least a first year physics course, you can really just imagine how much
"stuff" there is. Weight, as we'll see in a future video, is how much that stuff is being pulled down
by the force of gravity, so weight is a force, mass is telling you how much stuff there is.
And this is really neat that this formula is so simple, because, maybe we could have lived in a universe
where force is equal to mass squared times the square root of acceleration
which would have made all of our math much more complicated
but it's nice, it's just this constant proportionality over here
it's just this nice simple expression
and just to get our feet wet a little bit with the computations involved
in force, mass, and acceleration, let's say that I have a force
and the unit of force is a appropriately called the Newton.
So let's say I have a force of 10 Newtons, and just to be clear, a newton is the same thing
this is the same thing as 10 kilogram meters per second squared
and that's good that a Newton's the same thing as kilogram meters per second squared, because
that's exactly what you get on this side of the formula
so let's say I have a force of 10 Newtons
and is acting on a mass
let's say that the mass is 2 kilograms,
and I wanna know the acceleration.
... I wanna know the acceleration.
and once again in this video, these are vector quantities
If I have a positive value here, we're going to make the assumption that
we are going to the right.
if I had a negative value, then it would be going to the left.
So implicitly, I'm giving you not only the magnitude of the force,
but I'm also giving you the direction.
I'm saying it is "to the right", because it is positive.
So what would be the acceleration?
We just use F=m*a.
You have, on the left hand side, 10 N,
I could write 10 N here or I could write 10 kg m/s^2, and that
is going to be equal to the mass, which is 2 kg,
times the acceleration.
And then to solve for the acceleration,
you just divide both sides by 2kg.
So let's divide by 2 kg, let's divide the right...
or let me do it this way...
let's divide the right by 2 kg
that cancels out,
the 10 and the 2, 10 divide by 2, is...
lemme just... 10 divide by 2 is 5, and you have
kg cancelling with kg,
your left hand side, you get 5 m/s^2
and that's equal to your acceleration.
Now, just for fun, what happens if I double that force?
Well then I have... 20 N,
Oh well, I'll actually work it out
I have 20 kg m/s^2
is equal to ... I need to color code this...
2 kg times the acceleration,
divide both sides by 2kg,
and what do we get? Cancels out,
20 divided by 2, is 10, kg cancel with kg,
and so we have the acceleration, in this situation,
is is 10 m/s^2... is equal to the acceleration.
So, when we double the force, we went from 10 N to 20 N
the acceleration doubled. It went from 5 m/s^2
and to 10 m/s^2. So we see that they are
directly proportional, and the mass is that
how proportional they are. So you could imagine, what happens if
we doubled the mass. If we doubled the mass, and
let's say in this situation, it was 20 N, then we won't be dividing
by 2 kg anymore, we would be dividing by 4 kg.
and so then we would have 20 divided by 4, which would be 5 m/s^2
So if you make the mass larger, if you doubled
it, your acceleration would be half as much.
So the larger the mass you have, the more force you need to accelerate it.