Here we are on problem number 8.
The total daily profit, p in dollars, from producing and
selling x units of a certain product is given by the
function p of x.
So the profit as a function of x is equal to 17x minus 10x
plus b where b is a constant.
If 300 units were produced and sold yesterday for a profit of
$1,900, what is the value of b?
So we know that p of 300-- 300 units-- the profit when we did
300 units is $1,900. And we want to figure out b.
So what is p of 300? So let's put 300 in here.
We know it also equals 1,900 but let's put it here.
So it's 17 times 300 minus 10 times 300 plus b.
I just put 300 in for x.
So we're trying to find the profit for 300
and we know already that equals 1,900.
So what's 17 times 300? 17 times 3 is 51.
Let's add those two 0s.
Minus-- and what's 10 times 300,that's 3,000--
3,000 plus b is equal to 1,900.
And then we get 5,100 minus 3,000 minus b is equal to 1,900.
What's 5,100 minus 3,000? 2,100.
And 2,100 minus b is equal to 1,900.
Minus b is equal to, subtract 2,100 from both sides,
and you get minus 200. b is equal to 200.
And that is choice E.
Next problem. Problem number 9.
I will switch colors.
The number that results when an integer is multiplied by
itself cannot end in which of the following digits?
Interesting.
Well, what's a number when it's multiplied by itself?
That's like squaring a number.
So let's kind of study what all the perfect squares look like
So when I square 1, I get 1. When I square 2 I get 4.
When I square 3 I get 9. Square 4 I get 16.
5 is 25. 6 is 36. 7 is 49. 8 is 64.
So let's look at the numbers that it can be.
OK, we could go 9 is 81.
Looks like it can be a 1, a 4, a 9-- and we could keep going
1, 4, 9, a 6, a 5, and actually if we went to, 8 is 64
so it's a 4. 9 is-- oh we already did that--
and then 10 is a 0, right? It can also end in a 0.
The choices, A, sure a number can end in 1.
We just figured that out.
Choice B, sure a number can end in 4.
Choice C, sure a number can end in 5. Thus 25 as an example.
Choice D, a number can end in 6.
Choice E, well none of the numbers we looked at end in an 8.
And it seems like there's a bit of a pattern here,
that it tends to be just a set-- a subset-- of these numbers.
And also we know that the other choices-- choices A through D
we can figure out perfect squares that end in those numbers.
So we know that the answer is E. Next problem.
Problem number 10. A bag contains only
red marbles,blue marbles, and yellow marbles.
The probability of randomly selecting a red marble from
this bag is 1/4.
So I can say the probability of red is equal to 1/4.
The probability of randomly selecting a blue marble is 1/6.
Which of the following could be the total number of marbles
in the bag? Fascinating.
So what we need to do is we need to essentially figure out
the ratio of red to blue to yellow marbles.
So first of all,
what's the probability of getting a yellow marble?
The probability of getting a yellow marble is going to be
1 minus these, right?
So probability of yellow is going to be 1 minus 1/6 minus 1/4
Let's see, we could put all of that over 12.
12 minus 2/12 minus 3/12--3/12 is 1/4.
So that equals-- what's 12 minus 10? That equals 7/12.
So the probability I get a yellow marble is 7/12.
So that means for every 7 marbles--
so let's write it all is a denominator of 12.
That makes it actually a lot easier.
1/6 is the same thing as 2/12.
And 1/4 is the same thing as 3/12.
And they all add up to 12/12.
So for every 3 red marbles,
there are 2 blue marbles and there are 7 yellow marbles.
The ratio of red to blue to yellow is equal to 3:2:7.
And we know we can only get this type of a ratio when
there's a total of 12 marbles, right?
There has to be at least 12 marbles
or any multiple of 12 marbles, right?
If there's exactly 2 blue marbles,
then there'll be 3 red and 7 yellow.
And there has to be at least 2 of the blue marbles.
So any multiple of 12 marbles will work for
this type of ratio.
So if we look at the choices, which of the following
could be the total number of marbles in the bag?
So out of all those choices,
which of them are a multiple of 12? Well, choice A isn't.
10 isn't a multiple of 12. Choice C isn't. 18, 20, 30.
Well 12 is a multiple of 12,so choice B is our answer.
And we just figured out.
If there were 3 red, 2 blue and 7 yellow,
then we get the correct probabilities.
The key is just to try to figure out what the probability of
getting a yellow is and then realizing the ratios
between the two. Next problem. Problem 11.
When the sum of a list of prices is divided by the
average of the prices the result is k. What does k represent?
So if I take the sum divided by the average.
So let's say I'm taking the sum of three numbers.
So let's say, n1 plus n2 plus n3.
I could do it n times, but just for simplicity.
And I'm dividing that by the average. What's the average?
It's n1 plus n2 plus n3 divided by 3, right?
And if you divide by a fraction,
that's the same thing as multiplying by the reciprocal.
So that's n1 plus n2 plus n3 times 3 over n1 plus n2 plus n3.
So this cancels out, and all we're left with is 3,
which is the number of numbers we had.
And you could have done this with 16 or 20 or whatever.
I mean you could have said n1 plus n2 plus da, da, da, da, da
Where I have, let's say, n sub-- let's say I have m digits--
and then divide that by n1 plus n2 plus blah, blah, blah
n over m. Sub m digits. And say, well I'm dividing by m.
This would have also simplified to m digits.
When you do what they said in the problem,
the result is just the number of prices that you are summing.
So that is choice D, the number of prices.
And it works out
because this sum and this sum will cancel out. Next problem.
Let's see how fast-- if I can fit this one in.
So I have a drawing. It looks like this.
Let's see, triangle, triangle,triangle, triangle,
and then dotted lines,dotted lines,dotted lines,dotted lines.
It says, if the area of the square in the figure above is 81
so they're saying this is a square, and if the area is 81
then we know that this side is 9 and this side is 9. Right?
This is 9 times 9.
And the perimeter of each of the four triangles is 30.
So the perimeter is 30 of each of those.
What is the perimeter of the figure outlined by
the solid line? well think about it.
The perimeter of the solid line, that would be this.
That's what we want to figure out.
Well wouldn't that just be the perimeter of the
four triangles,and then we want to subtract out this side,
this side, this side and this side, right?
The perimeter of the red part is the perimeter of each of
the triangles-- added up, all four of them--
minus the perimeter of the square inside.
So the perimeter of the four triangles is 30 times 4,
minus the perimeter of this,which is minus 27.
No whoops, minus 36. So it's 120 minus 36 and that is--