Guglielmo Marconi's first radio transmissions in 1894
have spread into space for over 100 years
at the speed of light. They passed Sirius in 1903,
Vega in 1919, and
Regulus in 1971. That signal has already
passed over 1,000 stars. Anyone orbiting one of
those stars, with a really good receiver, could detect Marconi's
signal and know that we are here. Radio waves
are the longest, and contain the least energy, of any electromagnetic wave.
While visible light is measured in minute fractions
of an inch, radio waves vary from about 19 centimeters,
about the length of a water bottle, to waves the length of cars,
ships, mountains, all the way up to monstrous waves longer than
the diameter of our planet. Heinrich Hertz discovered radio waves
in 1888. The first commercial radio station
went on the air in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, on November 2, 1920.
Then in 1932, a major discovery
by Karl Jansky at Bell Labs revealed that stars and other objects
in space radiated radio waves! Radio astronomy was born.
However, scientists need giant antennas to detect
weak, long-wavelength, radio waves from space.
The enormous Arecibo radio dish antenna measures
305 meters in diameter, over three football fields.
Scientists can link the signals from an array of separate radio antennas to
focus on tiny slices of distant space. Such arrays act as
a single immense collector. This giant New Mexico array
uses 27 parabolic dish antennas shaped into a giant "Y"
with each arm capable of stretching for 13 miles!
Scientists have even spread these linked antennas across the globe.
One of the largest stretches from Hawaii to the Virgin Islands
and acts like such a powerful telephoto lens that a baseball sitting
on the moon would fill its entire field of view.
Many of the greatest astronomical discoveries have been made using radio waves.
Pulsars, the existence of giant clouds of superheated
plasma, which are among the largest objects in the Universe,
and even quasars, such as this one over 10 billion light years away,
were all discovered using radio waves.
Radio waves also provide more local information. Astronomical objects
that have a magnetic field usually produce radio waves
such as our Sun. Thus, NASA's STEREO satellite is able to
monitor bursts of radio waves from the Sun's corona.
WAVE sensors on the WIND spacecraft record the radio waves
emitted by a planet's ionosphere, such as the bursts from Jupiter whose
wavelength measures about fifteen meters. Radio waves
fill the space around us to bring entertainment, communications,
and key scientific information. We can't hear these radio waves.
When you tune your radio to your favorite station,
the radio receives these electromagnetic radio waves and then vibrates a speaker
to create the sound waves we hear. We may not be able to tap our
toes to the cosmic radio transmissions, but we certainly discovered
much about our Universe's grand cosmic dance
by listening to them.
our satellites, and other electronics here on Earth.
Other NASA instruments monitor the changes in other aspects
of the Earth's climate system, such as clouds, aerosol particles,
or surface reflectivity, and scientists are examining their many
interactons with the energy budget. A portion of solar radiation
from the Sun that is just beyond the visible spectrum is referred to
as near-infrared. Scientists can study how this radiation
reflects off the Earth's surface to understand changes in land cover
such as growth of cities or changes in vegetation. Our eyes
perceive a leaf as green because wavelengths in the green region
of the visible light spectrum are reflected while other visible wavelengths
are absorbed. Yet, the chlorophyll and the cell structure of the
leaf are also reflecting near-infrared light, light we cannot see.
This reflected near-infrared radiation can be
sensed by satellites, allowing scientists to study vegetation from space.
Using these data, scientists can identify some
types of trees, can examine the health of forests, and can even
monitor the health of vegetation such as forests infested with pine beetles
or crops affected by drought. Studying the emission and
reflection of infrared waves helps us to understand the Earth's system
and its energy budget. Near-infrared data can also help scientists
study land cover such as changes in snow, ice,
forests, urbanization, and agriculture.
Scientists are beginning to unlock the mysteries of cooler objects across
the Universe such as planets, cool stars, nebulae,
and much more using infrared waves.
,00:00:00.00