So let's revisit the scenario where everyone is trying to
exit Country B's currency, and convert it back into Country A.
We saw in the last video that if just left to its own devices, if this were to happen,
if a lot of B's were wanted to be converted into Currency A,
and because everyone is converting- everyone is afraid to convert into B now,
because they think for whatever reason that B, Country B is in bad shape,
then you have this imbalance and if you left to its own devices,
the Country B's currency would become devalued.
you would need more, more B's to trade for an A.
(For an A.)
which is just another way to say B's currency, B's value,
would go down. And that would be a bad thing, especially if it's a pretty steep decline.
Maybe it's a country that needs to import fuel from the rest of the world,
Maybe they need to import food from the rest of the world,
and if their currency were to devalue dramatically,
then imports could become very, very, very expensive.
And so people in that country might have to pay double for gas,
and double for basic necessities, like food and whatever else.
And so we played out a scenario where the central bank of Country B
actively tries to intervene to keep this from happening, to keep the exchange rate
stable.
So what they do is, they could use, (they could use), reserves
(and I'll do some blue for Country B,)
so they could use reserves for- of A,
that they have accumulated during better times,
And they take those reserves,
so these are reserves that they accumulated in better times,
or in previous videos, depending how you want to view them,
and they try to balance out the supply with A's with the supply of B's
by selling, (by selling), their reserves and buying B's.
So one way to think of it they're adding supply of A's,
and they're also adding supply- they're also adding demand for B's.
They're going to sell the reserves of A,
and buy their own currency. And that would work,
as long as they have reserves, they're going to be able to
stabilize things, so that this situation doesn't happen.
But the problem was, and we talked about at the end of the last video,
is that they can run out here. It's not like they can print
another country's currencies forever.
Or they can't print it at all; they had to accumulate this.
This isn't their own currency, so they have a
finite amount of this, they could eventually run out.
And what is often the case is,
currency speculators see this and begin to smell blood.
They see, "Okay, look, people are trying to exit this currency,
it would devalue if it was left to its own devices,
but the central bank of Country B is trying to keep it devaluing
by depleting its finite reserves of currency A.
And so what currency speculators will start to do is,
"Well, I can go into Country B, and I can borrow B's,
(so I could literally go to a bank in country B and borrow, I could borrow some of the B currency),
and then I can go into the exchange markets, and try to convert it into A's."
(and try to convert it into A's.)
And just off of when looking at this superficially,
what- what's that going to do?
Well, this is going to make the situation even worse for the central bank.
Because now you have people actively,
that even hold B's before they're going to be borrowing B's,
and converting them into A's.
So it's going to create an even larger supply of B's,
and even more demand for the finite number of A's that are willing to go this way.
And why is the speculator doing this?
Well think about the two situations for them.