We have the equation -16= (x/4) + 2
and we need to solve for X.
So we really just need to isolate the X variable on one side of this equation;
and the best way to do that is first to isolate it -- isolate this whole X/4 term from all the other terms.
So in order to do that, let's get rid of this 2; and the best way to get rid of that 2 is to subtract it.
But if we want to subtract it from the right hand side, we also have to subtract it from the left hand side:
because, this is an equation.
If "this" is equal to "that," anything we do to "that," we also have to do to "this."
So let's subtract 2 from both sides.
So you subtract 2 from the right... subtract 2 from the left... and we get, on the left hand side:
-16 - 2 = -18, and then that is equal to x over 4 (X/4) -- x over 4
and then we have +2 -2, which is just going to be zero, so we don't even have to write that. I could write just a "+0", but I think that is just a little unnecessary.
And so we have -18 = X/4.
... and our whole goal here is to isolate the X... to solve for the "X"
and the best way we could do that is we have X/4 over here -- If we multiply that by 4, we're just going to have an "X".
So we can multiply that by 4,
But once again, this is an equation, Anything you do on the right hand side you have to do to the left hand side, and vice versa.
So if we multiply the right hand side by 4. we also have to multiply the left hand side by 4.
So we get 4 * (-18) = (X/4) * 4, the (X/4) * 4 ... that cancels out ... you divide something by 4 and multiply by 4, you're just going to be left with an "X".
And on the other side... 4 X (-18) ... well let's see that's 40... well, let's just write it out. ... so 18 X 4 ... if we were to multiply 18 X 4 ... 4 X 8 = 32, 4 X 1 = 4, plus 1 is 72 -- but this is (-18) X 4, so it's (-72).
So X = -72.
And if we want to check it, we could just substitue it back into that original equation, so let's do that, let's substitute...
Let's substitute this ... into the original equation
so the original equation was -16 = ... instead of writing X, I'm going to write -72 ... = (-72 /4) + 2 ... let's see if this is actually true...
So, this right hand side simplifies to -72/4 ... we already know, that that is (-18) so this is equal to ... (-18) + 2 ... this is what the equation becomes...
and then the right hand side, (-18)+2, that's (-16)
so it all comes out true.
This right hand side, when x= (-72) does indeed equals -16.