Let say that you started off with three apples
and then I were to give you another seven apples.
So my question to you,
and this might be very obvious
is how many apples do you now have?
and l'll give you a second to think about that
Well, this is fairly basic:
you add 3 apples,
now I'm going to give you 7 more
you now have 3 plus 7
you now have 10 apples.
But let say I wanna do the same type of thinking
but I'm too lazy to write the word apples
Let say that instead of writing the word "apples",
I just use the letter "a".
and I say... let say...
and this is, say, a different scenario...
you start off with 4 apples
and to that I add another 2 apples.
How many apples do you now have?
And instead of writing "apples",
I'm just going to write "a's" here.
So, how many of these "a's" do you now have?
And once again,
I'll to give you a few seconds to think about that.
Well, this also might be a little bit of common sense for you
if you had four of these apples,
whatever these a's represented,
if you have 4 of them and then you add 2 more of them
you're now going to have 6 of these apples.
But once again,
we started off assuming that "a's" represent apples
but they could have represented anything
If you have 4 of whatever "a" represents
and then you have another 2 of whatever "a" represents,
you'll now have 6 of whatever "a" represents.
Or if you just think of it as if I have 4 "a's"
and then I add another 2 "a's",
I'm going to have 6 "a's".
You can think of 4 "a's" as a + a + a + a.
And if to that I add another 2 "a's".
So + a + a. That's 2 "a's" right over there.
How many a's do I now have?
Well that's 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
I now have 6 "a's".
So thinking of it that way, let's get a little bit more abstract.
Let say that I have 5 "x's", whatever "x" represents.
"x" could be some number...
So I have 5 of whatever that number is
and from that I subtract 2 of whatever that number is.
What would this evaluate to?
How many of these "x's" will I now have.
So it's essentially "5x - 2x" is going to be what times "x".
And once again, I'll give you a few seconds to think about it.
Well, if I have 5 of something
and I subtract 2 of those away,
I'm going to have 3 of that something left.
So this is going to be equal to 3x.
5x - 2x is equal to 3x.
And if you really think about what that means.
5 "x's" are just: x + x + x + x + x.
And then we're going to take away 2 of those "x's".
We're going to take away 2 "x's".
So take away one "x", take away 2 "x's".
You are left... you are going to be left with 3 "x's".