So say you're Arthur Stone and
you're showing your hexaflexagon to your friend Tuckerman
and you already blow his mind by showing him it has 3 sides.
Orange, yellow, pink. orange, yellow, pink.
but now you're about to extra-super-blow his mind
by showing him there is even more colors
and he's like, 'wow! Where did the blue side come from?'
but you're having trouble of finding all six. Like,
you know that there is a green side somewhere, but where is it?
you're like, "OK Tuckerman, I found the green side"
It's right in....here. Hmm.
Anyway Tuckerman immediately decided that he needs to discover the fastest way to get to all the colors
which he called "The Tuckerman Traverse"
so you and Tuckerman are working on that
And there's hexaflexagons all over the lunch table and then
another student is curious about what you're doing and wants to join your committee.
His name is Richard Feynman.
So stop being Arthur Stone and start being Brian Tuckerman.
So you're Tuckerman and you teach Feynman how to make a hexahexaflexagon by first
folding a strip of 18 triangles with a 19th for gluing.
You and Stone have just figured out how to number the faces
by dissecting a perfect specimen.
You number them 1-2-3-1-2-3-1-2-3-1-2-3
Glue! on one side. Flip it, and:
Glue! 4-4-5-5-6-6-4-4-5-5-6-6-4-4-5-5-6-6 on the other.
You coil it around so that you get 1s and 2s and 3s on the outside, like:
1-2-2-3-3-1-1-2-2-3-3
And then fold THAT around into a hexaflexagon so that all the 2s are on the front.
And then flip it and glue the two "GLUE" parts together, so that all 3s are on the back.
Feynman has some trouble flexing it but you show him how to pinch two triangles together and then
push in the opposite side.
He somehow still does it wrong and ends up backwards, flexing in reverse.
Now he's all intrigued about all the flexing possibilities and you're like
"Let me show you the Tuckerman Traverse!"
But Feynman, being Feyynman, is like "We must create a diagram!"
and Tuckerman is like "Really, it's not that hard-"
"NO! Diagram!"
So you're Feynman and you've already seen you can cycle from 1 to 2 to 3,
So you write that down with arrows and stuff.
Or you can go backwards. But from 1, 2, 3 you can also flex the other way, in which
1 goes to 6, or 2 to 5, or 3 to 4. And if you did 1 to 6, once you're at 6 you can only flex 1 way because the other doesn't work
You HAVE to go to 3. Or backwards, back to 1.
But then you notice that if you go to 3 you can only flex one way and the other
is un-open-up-able but before when you're on 3 you can go either to 1 or 4
but now you can only go to 1.
And you can go backwards to 6 but not backwards to 2.
Which means that this 3 isn't the same 3 as the first 3. Somehow, it's just the same color,
but in a different "state".
You show that to your friend, John Tukey, and he's like:
"Oh, yeah, that makes sense."
And he draws a star in the middle of your 3 and sits back as if that explained everything.
So you're like "whatever."
and flip it back around to get to the other 3 and check it - the star turns into a...not star.
And from this alternate 3 there's this 1-6-3 loop that connects to the main loop at 1,
which is the same 1 as 1 has always been.
But there's a different 1 off of the main 2 in the 2-5-1 loop.
And, of course, everything looks different when you flip it over,
And these 3s are also different because they have different numbers on their other side.
But you complete a diagram of possibilities, which allows you to find the optimal Tuckerman's Traverse.
You also diagram the original trihexaflexagon, which is pretty simple.
The Flexagon Committee approves of your diagram and decides to call them "Feynman Diagrams".
Everything is going great - until 1941. Because suddenly there's important war stuff to do and flexagons are largely forgotten.
Okay, now fast-forward 15 years and be Martin Gardner. You're an amateur magician,
and you're hanging out at your friend's place, talking about magician stuff.
Anyway, your friend shows you something you've never seen before - a big flexagon he's made out of cloth.
And you're thinking "Hey, this is awesome! maybe other people would like to know about this "flexagon" thing."
So you write an article for Scientific American and since you've lended yourself a gig
writing a regular column about recreational mathematics called "Mathematical Games",
And it's a HUGE success, and it gets hundreds of comments - I mean, letters,
And there's nothing else like your column.
And all the cool people are inspired by you and you're pretty much THE reason why people
know about things like Tangrams and Conway's Game of Life and the works of M. C. Escher,
and other things like that.
Now fast forward 50 years and say you're me and the generation of people inspired by Martin Gardner
are now inspiring you, so he's your math inspiration grandfather.
And now you yourself are in the business of mathematically inspiring people and you want them to be aware of their
math inspiration heritage.
Okay, now say you are....you.
If you think Hexaflexagons are cool that is just column No. 1,
And I invite you to joining with the hundreds of people who celebrate Martin Gardner's birthday every October 21st.
This year there will be hexaflexagon parties in homes and schools all over the world and if you want to attend
our host one, check the description.
I'm celebrating by making these videos, and also, I just like the image of flexagons everywhere.
Floating around lunch tables, falling out of your pockets,
Stuck in your head cushions. I like to keep some ready to deploy out of my wallet, or tiny yellow purse,
in case of a flexagon emergency.
And then there's more recent innovations in flexagon technology and all the cool ways to color them, and
other stuff, but that will have to wait until next time.