Welcome to the presentation on more advanced ratio problems.
Let's get started with some problems.
So let's say that I have a class, and then-- oh the pen is
messed up --OK, so in the class the total number of
students is fifty-seven.
And I would also tell you that the ratio of girls
to boys is equal to four:fifteen.
So now this the interesting part, so far it
doesn't look to tough.
My question is how many boys need to leave the room, so how
many boys need to leave for the ratio of girls to
boys to be four:eleven.
This is fascinating.
So, a good place to start is just to figure out how many
girls and how many boys there are in this classroom.
And we already learned how to do that in the introduction
to ratio problems.
We know that the girls plus the boys is equal to fifty-seven, right,
because there are fifty-seven kids in the room.
And we also know, just multiplying-- taking this
equation --and multiplying both sides by b, we also know that
the girls are equal to four / fifteen times the boys, right?
And then we can just substitute that back into this equation,
and then we get four / fifteenb plus b is equal to fifty-seven, is the same thing
as nineteen / fifteenb is equal to fifty-seven.
Let me clean this up a little bit.
That's separate, and then let me go here.
And we say b is equal to fifty-seven-- oh, woops --it's actually fifty-seven
times fifteen all of that over nineteen, right?
I just multiply both sides by fifteen / nineteen.
So fifty-seven divided by nineteen is three.
So b is equal to forty-five.
And we know there're a total of fifty-seven kids in the class-- g plus
b is fifty-seven --so we know that there are twelve girls, right?
fifty-seven minus forty-five.
Good.
So now we know that the current boys and girls
are forty-five boys and twelve girls.
So let's write that down.
So there's twelve girls and forty-five boys.
Now, the question says, how many boys need to leave for
the ratio of girls to boys equals four four:eleven?
So this is the number of girls right now, twelve,
this is the number boys.
Let's say x is a number of boys that need to leave the room.
So if x boys leave the room the new ratio will be twelve girls to
the forty-five boys minus the x boys that leave, right?
If that confuses you, sit and look at that for a second.
We start off with twelve girls and forty-five boys in the room.
And we're saying x boys are going to leave, so the new
ratio is going to be twelve:forty-five minus x.
And we know from this part of the problem that that new
ratio is going to equal four:eleven.
There, we just set up a equation with one unknown
and we can solve for x.
I hope that doesn't confuse you much.
All we did is we figured out how many boys, how many
girls are in the room now.
We said x is the number boys that need to leave.
And we said the new ratio is going to be girls to the new
number of boys, which is forty-five minus x, and that's going to
be equal to the new ratio.
So let's solve for x.
Well, twelve times eleven is what that's one hundred and thirty-two.
one hundred and thirty-two is equal to four times forty-five, one hundred and sixty, one hundred and eighty, minus fourx.
And then if you solve for x, I think you know how to do this
right now, and we can say minus fourx is equal to minus forty-eight.
x is equal to twelve.
There we solved it.
So we say that if twelve boys left the room, the new ratio of
girls to boys would be four:eleven.
And does that make sense?
Well if twelve boys left the room, then the new ratio of girls to
boys would be twelve:thirty-three, right?
Because forty-five minus twelve is thirty-three.
And that's the same thing as if you divide the
top and bottom by three.
That's four:eleven.
So there, we got it right.
So what looked like a very hard problem actually wasn't so bad
when you just sit down and work through the algebra.
Let's do another problem.
Let's say --this thing sometimes malfunctions --OK,
let's say that the ratio of apples to bananas in a
basket is equal to five:nineteen.
And when we add twenty-three bananas the ratio of apples to bananas--
and actually let's write it right now, we now have twenty-three
bananas more --is equal to ten:sixty-one.
So the question is, what is the total amount of
fruit in the basket?
Amount of fruit-- --ah, that's so messy --after
adding the bananas.
So I actually gave you a hint just when I wrote
down initial problem.
We're saying the ratio of a to b-- so let a equal the number
of apples, and b equal the number bananas --so the ratio
of apples to bananas equals five:nineteen.
When I add twenty-three bananas, now the new ratio's going to be the
number of apples to b plus twenty-three.
The new ratio is ten:sixty-one.
So how do we solve this?
Well, once again we have two equations and two unknowns.
We know that-- I guess let's take this equation first,
because it's a little more complicated --we know if we
cross multiply that sixty-onea is equal to tenb plus two hundred and thirty and if we
divide both sides by sixty-one, we know that a is equal to
ten / sixty-oneb plus two hundred and thirty / sixty-one.
Right?
And we could take this equation and multiply both sides by b
and we could say that a is equal to five / nineteenb.
Right?
Well both of these are equal to a so we could set them
equal to each other.
And you get five / nineteenb is equal to ten / sixty-oneb plus two hundred and thirty times sixty-one.
And we solve for b.
While this might seem complicated to you at first,
but it's just a basic linear equation.
And for the sake of time, because I only have two minutes
left in this youtube.
I'm just going to solve for b, and you get b is equal to thirty-eight.
if b is equal to thirty-eight, we know that the initial ratio is five:nineteen.
So that's pretty easy.
We just say a is equal to five / nineteen times thirty-eight is equal to ten.
So the initial number of apples was ten, the initial number
bananas is thirty-eight, right?
So initially we started off with forty-eight pieces of fruit, and
then we're going to add twenty-three more pieces of fruit, right?
And forty-three plus twenty-eight, that's what, seventy-one pieces of fruit.
So, let me review real quick what we said.
We said the ratio of apples to bananas is five:nineteen.
That's a is the number of apples, b is the
number of bananas.
When I add twenty-three bananas, I now have b plus twenty-three bananas, the
new ratio of apples to total number bananas is ten:sixty-one.
And I just used both of these equations.
Two equations and two unknowns.
Solved for a, and then substituted, and
I solved for b.
Nothing fancy here.
I know there's a lot of fractions here, but if you
just work through this, the fractions actually work out.
And I was able to solve for a and b.
Add the twenty-three pieces and I got seventy-one total pieces of fruit.
I think you're now ready to try some of the more
difficult ratio problems.
Have fun!