We're asked to prove that if the orthocenter and centroid
Of a given triangle are the same point
Then the triangle is equilateral
So I have a triangle over here and we're going to assume
That its orthocenter and its centroid are the same point
And just so to review the orthocenter is the point where
The three altitude of a triangle intersect
And the centroid is the point where the three medians
So we can do it is we could assume
these three lines right over here
that these are both altitude and median
And that this point right over here
is both the orthocenter and the centroid
So if we assume that these lines are altitudes
And that tells us that they are perpendicular to the opposite sides
So that is a 90 degree angles those are both 90 degree angles
These are both 90 degree angles
And the fact that it's a centroid means
That each of these lines bisect the opposite side
So it tells us that this length is equal to length
That this length let me just use a different color
This length is equal to that length
And it tells us that this length this length is equal to that length
And you might also say
Well gee each of these line are also then the perpendicular
Bisectors of each of the sides
So not only is this the orthocenter in the centroid
It is also the circumcenter of this triangle right over here
For that out of the way we kind of
Marked up everything that we can assume given that
This is an orthrocenter and a center
Although the other things other properties of this
Especially centroids that we know
But now let's prove that this has to be an equilateral triangle
So the first thing that you might see
And let me label some letters here
So we can refer to things a little bit better
So let's call that A B C D E and F
And we could label in the centroid right over here G
So the first thing let's look at triangle AFG
And triangle this is E and triangle EFG
So let's compare triangle AF triangle AFG
Let's compare that to triangle EFG triangle EFG
So they definitely have one side
Side EF is congruent to side AF these are both the same
And we have angle EFG as the same as angle AFG
They're both 90 degrees
And then they both clearly share the side FG
They both share this side right over here
So they have a congruent side an angle
A corresponding angle in between in another congruent side
And they're all so congruent side congruent corresponding angle
And another congruent corresponding side
So by side angle side these two characters
Are going to be congruent by side angle side congruency
Now can you make the exact same argument
We can make the exact same argument to say
That all of these pairs that have the kind of share this
That both have these, these 90 degree angles next to each other
Are going to be congruent
Triangle we can by the same exact argument
We can see triangle EDG triangle EDG
Is going to be congruent to triangle CDG
Triangle CDG same exact thing side angle
And then we have a side right over here
And then we can use the exact same argument
For this one right over here triangle C looks like an A
Triangle CBG is congruent to triangle ABG
So that by itself is interesting
But we know that if two triangles are congruent
All of their corresponding sides and angles
Are going to be congruent
So for example if we know
That the measure of this angle is blue
The corresponding angle on this triangle
Is also going to have the same measure
I'll just make it with that same blue angle
And we know if this angle right over here is magenta
The corresponding angle on triangle AFG
Is also going to have that same measure
And I'll just mark it with that magenta again
Now we also know from our properties of vertical angles
That whatever an angle measure of AFG is
DGC is going to have the same measure
Because they are vertical angles
But we know whatever angle measure this is
This triangle, triangle CDG is congruent to triangle EDG
So corresponding angles have to be congruent
So this angle is this magenta measure
Then this angle also has to be the magenta measure
And then once again you can see vertical angles
That this is magenta then this is also gonna have
That same measure
And if this has a measure then
That is also going to have that same measure
So by using a little bit of argument of congruent triangles
Corresponding angles are going to be congruent
And vertical angles we can see that all of these inner angles
Right over here are gonna have to be the same measure
They're all and I'm using that with this little magenta arc
Right over there
Now all of these triangles if we split this triangle in two
They all have a 90 degree angle they all have a magenta arc
So whatever's left over is going to be
180 minus 90 minus magenta
Or it's really 90 minus this magenta angle right over here
And that's what this blue angle must be
This blue angle is essentially 90 minus the magenta angle
The blue angle is 90 minus the magenta angle
And so that blue angle must be the third angle for all of these
So once again this blue angle is going to be
90 minus magenta angle
Or a 180 minus magenta minus the 90
So that's gonna be the blue angle
If you, essentially what we're saying is
If you know two angles of a triangle
that forces with the other triangle
What the other triangle is going to be
We already know that all 6 of these triangles
Have two angles in common
The 90 degree angle and the magenta angle
So they all the third angle must be the same as well
And we're specifying that with this blue angle
This blue angle right over here
And now we see if we're to look at angle
If we we're to look at angle E EAC
So angle EAC we see that that's just two of these blue angles
That is congruent to angle ACE, ACE
Which just two of those blue angles
Which is congruent to angles CEA, angles CEA
Which is once again just two of those blue angles
So we have a triangle here where the three angles
In that triangle all are congruent
So it is an equilateral triangle
It is a 60 degree we've proven before
If all three of your angles are the same
The lengths of all three sides are the same as well