We’re in the Sistine Chapel in the Vatican,
which has tremendous importance to Catholicism.
This is where the Pope will lead Mass.
But perhaps most famously,
this is the room that the College of Cardinals
uses to decide the next pope.
And every surface of this space is decorated –
from the beautiful mosaics on the floor –
the walls are painted with frescoes
by early Renaissance artists.
The wall behind the altar was painted
by Michelangelo later in his life.
And then, of course, the ceiling.
And everybody is looking up.
Their necks are craned.
And of course, it’s magnificent.
We’re here in the late afternoon on a day in early July.
The light is diffuse,
and it makes those frescoed figures feel so dimensional.
They feel like sculpture.
And you can imagine what it was like
when it was unveiled.
how revolutionary
Well, he was first and foremost a sculptor.
And it wasn’t actually until the very recent cleaning,
that we knew his brilliance as a colorist.
But, for him, lying and drawing
Trying carving
Figures out of paint
And you have this extraordinary ability
to render both strength and elegance, simultaneously.
They have a massiveness and a presence that is charismatic.
But there’s also a sense of elegance and ideal beauty.
So let’s describe what we’re looking at.
Okay.
Probably the most important are the series of nine scenes
that move across the central []
And those are framed
by a painted architectural framework that looks real.
It doesn’t look like paint.
, to create or in the universe
And then we move through to the creation of Adam –
well the separation of the sexe if the creation of the ifs
And the creation of god’s most perfect creatures –
human beings.
Innocence the separation of good and evil
Man and woman disobeying God,
causing the expulsion of Adam
, the creation of Eve from the garden of Eden.
Scenes of noah
So these are all scenes from the first book of the Bible –
the Book of Genesis
And it’s so interesting.
Because this is a Catholic Church
We don’t see images of Christ.
And Christ is present in other ways.
Not only does the disobedience of Adam and Eve
make the coming of Christ necessary,
But when we look on either side of those central scenes ,
we see the prophets and the cybils
who predicted the coming of a savior for mankind.
The image of the Libyan Cybil
Spectacularly beautiful as
So ‘Cybils’ are these ancient pagan soothsayers
who can foresee the future,
and according to the Catholic tradition,
foretell the coming of Christ/
But Look at the Libyans Cybil.
Look at the elegance
The way that her to toe just reaches down
and touches the ground
But it seems as if she is the process of moving,
and possibly of standing
There is a presence and drama
Especially.
She twists her body in an almost impossible way.
And we can say Michelangelo
has articulated every muscle in the back.
And, in fact, we know that he used a male model
I’m so taken with the color here.
We spoke only of line, of cultural form.
But after the dramatic cleaning of the Sistine chapel
those original colors, their brilliancy, came out.
She, of course, is reaching back.
And, presumably, that’s a book of prophecy that she holds.
There’s a look of confidence and knowing on her face.
The absolute clarity with which
she knows the Christ will come.
Sitting on the architecthual framework
on the four corner of all of the central scenes
are male nude figures that we refer to as ignudi.
I think this is Important because Michelangelo
To create levels of reality
And so, for example, the Libyan cybil
Seated amongst the architecture.
And then set next to her are bronze figures.
And then in the []
Amongst the architecture
As you mentioned, other scenes that seem to
And then relief sculptures
And then seated above those, the ignudi.
And it’s so clear we’re at this moment
at the rediscovery of ancient Greek and Roman sculpture.
And Michelangelo is Rome. He’s in the Vatican.
This is the High Renaissance.
It’s so interesting to compare
on the ceiling
, with the far darker and more pessimistic view that
Michelangelo will paint later on the back wall –
The Last Judgment.
There is a big difference between 1512
When he begins last judgment.
The Protestant Reformation has begun.
And the Church is under attack.
Michelangelo’s world had been shattered.
But when you look at the ceiling, you see instead,
all of the optimism,
all of the intellectual and emotional power
that characterizes the High Renaissance,
in all of its newfound appreciation for the ancient world.
This was a moment of incredible promise.
And all of that, shining through these figures.
And let’s not forget that just a few doors away,
simultaneously Raphael is painting frescoes
in the Papal Palace.
So what a moment in Rome.