Let’s say we we've been hanging out in scenario E for a bunch of days.
On average we've been catching one rabbit, but gathering 280 berries.
We were, I guess, in a berry mood, so this is scenario E right over here.
But now all of a sudden we are in a mood for more proteins.
So let me write down: we are in scenario E
and we are in the mood for more protein.
And so we want to think about what are the trade-offs.
If we try to catch more rabbits
So what I want to do, I want to say,
if I want to catch one more rabbit,
what am I going to have to give up.
So if I catch one more rabbit,
so I go from one rabbit, on average, to two rabbits a day,
so I am going from scenario E to scenario D,
what am I going to give up?
So this is plus one over here.
Well, I am going to give up forty berries
and you can see visually right here.
If I try to get one more rabbit,
I can't go into this impossible, this unattainable part right over here.
I have to stay on the production possibilities frontier,
sometimes abbreviated as PPF
or I guess the acronym for it, I should say, is PPF.
But if I want one more rabbit,
the production possibilities frontier drops off
and I will have to give up forty fruits.
So one more rabbit means that I have a cost.
So I have to give up, on average, forty berries
and the technical term for what I have just described is
the opportunity cost of going after one more rabbit is giving up forty berries.
So let me write this down.
The opportunity cost of one more rabbit
and this is particular to scenario E, as we will see,
is going to change depending on what scenario we are in,
at least for this example.
So the opportunity cost of one more rabbit is 40 berries.
Assuming we are in scenario E.
One more rabbit, I have to give up 40 berries.
And another term, when we talk about the opportunity cost,
of going after, of producing, I guess we could say
the opportunity cost of producing one more rabbit here.
When we talk about the opportunity cost of producing one more unit
is sometimes called the marginal cost.
So this, right over here, you can also view as the marginal cost.
In this context of this video our costs are in terms of
the thing that I am giving up, the opportunity that I am giving up.
In other scenarios, we will see sometimes
the marginal cost be given in actual monetary units, like dollars of whatever else.
what was the cost of producing that extra unit, that extra widget right over there
let‘s make sure we understand opportunity cost
so that's, when we are sitting in scenario E, the opportunity cost
of one more rabbit
but whats the opportunity cost, lets say we are tired of eating meat
we are sitting in scenario E and we want to become vegetarians all together
so we want to go to scenario F
essentially not eat any rabbits and eat as much fruit as possible
so another thing that you could ask in scenario E
is the opportunity cost of
and just to make the numbers easier
I am going to say, opportunity cost of 20 more berries
is, well I am going to give up a rabbit
so over here what we are doing is, we are saying
OK, I want to increase my berries by 20, but to do that I have to decrease my rabbits by one
so the opportunity cost, assuming we are in scenario E
the opportunity cost of 20 more berries is one rabbit
now this, right over here, is not a marginal cost
cause I am talking about the cost of 20 more units
not just one
if I want to write this as a marginal cost of one more berry
then I could just say, well 20 berries is one rabbit
you could say, you could essentially divide both sides by 20
so one more berry
and I will assume for those who want to get more technical, its somewhat linear right over here
one more berry, if we divide both sides by 20
is 1/20 of a rabbit
so if I go for one extra berry, sitting in scenario E
on average, I am going to get 1/20 less of a rabbit
and when I phrase it this way, it is being phrased as a marginal cost
now, for those who want to get a little technical
this is a curve, right over here, so it might not be exactly this
we can't just, well, I don't want to get too technical
for the sake of this one right over here, this is a safe way to think about it
the opportunity cost of 20 more berries is one rabbit
but if we assume that it's somewhat linear right over here
its not so curved, it's somewhat of a line between those two points
then the opportunity cost of 1 berry is 1/20 of a rabbit
or the marginal cost of an extra berry is 1/20 of a rabbit
and we could do it at different points on this curve
and I actually encourage you to do, based on the data that we have
in this table that we constructed in the last video, and maybe this curve
think about what the opportunity cost is in the different scenarios
if you're in scenario B, and if you want an extra rabbit
how much is that going to cost you in terms of berries
or if you want more berries, what is that going to cost you in terms of rabbits?