We divide x to the third plus five x minus four by x minus x, Actually I think this is supposed to be
x squared, let me correct it. So we are gonna to divide, x to the third plus five x minus four by x squared
minus x plus 1 and just to see the different ways we can rewrite this, we could rewrite this as , x to
the third plus five x minus four divided by x squared minus x plus 1
or may be the best way to write in this circumstance is we are going to write algebric long division
is to write it as x squared minus x plus one
divided into x to the third plus
and actually I am going to leave some blank spaces we dont have an x degree an x squared term
but I am gonna leave some space for it just so that we can align everything in the proper space
when we actually do the division
so, x to the third plus nothing to the x squared power plus five x minus four
so we have a place for the third power, the second power, the first power
and the zero'th power, so now lets do a little bit of algebraic long division
lets look at the highest degree term,
x squared goes into the x to the third, how many times?
Well it goes into it x times, x to the third divided by x squared
is equal to x to the three minus two which is equal to x to the one
which is equal to x, so it goes x times
I will write the x right over here and we multiply x times this entire thing
x times, x square is x to the third,
x times, negative x is negative x squared,
x times one is , positive x
and now we want to subtract this whole expression from that whole expression
and thats the same thing as adding the opposite or
multiplying each of these terms by negative one and adding into these terms
so lets do that
so we have negative x to the third,
negative one times negative x squared is positive x squared