I thought I would do few examples using the angle bisector theorem.
So, in the first triangle right over here, we are given that this side has length three;
this side has length six and this little dotted line here,
this is clearly the angle bisector because they are telling us this angle is congruent
to that angle right over there and
than they tell us the length of just this part of this side right over
here is 2. So from here to here is 2 and that this length
is x. let's figure out what x is. So the angle bisector theorem
tells us that the ratio of 3 to 2 is going to be equal to
6 to x. So we can just solve for x.
so 3 to 2 is going to be equal to 6.
to x and than once again you can cross multiply
or you multiply both sides by 2 and x. kind of
gives you the same result. If you cross multiply, you get 3x
3x equal to, 2 times 3 is 12.
x is equal to, divide both sides by 3, x is equal to
4. So in this case, x is equal to 4.
and this is kind of interesting, because we just realized now that this side, this entire side
right over here is going to be equal to 6. So even thought, it doesn't look that way
based on the way, its drawn. This is actually an isosceles triangle.
It has a six and a six and the base right over here is 3.
kind of, kind of interesting. Over here, we are given that this length
is 5; this length is 7; this entire side is
10 and than we have this angle bisector, right over there
We have to figure out just this part of the triangle between this point
We call this point 'A' and this point right over here
find the length of line AB right over here. So once again
angle bisector theorem. The ratio of 5 to this
Let me do this in a new color, the ratio of 5
to x is going to be equal to ratio of 7
to this distance, right over here
and what is that distance? So if the whole is 10, and this is
x, than this distance right over here is going to be 10 -x
So the ratio of 5 to x, is equal to 7
over 10 minus x, and we can cross multiply
Multiply 5 times 10 minus x is 50 minus
is 5x and than 7 times x is equal to 7x
minus 5x and than x times 7 is equal to
7x. Add 5x to both sides of the equation. You get
50 is equal to 12x
divide both sides by 12 and we get 50
over 12 is equal to x
So we can reduce this, let's see if you divide numerator and denominator by 2
You get. This is the same thing as 25 over
6, which is the same thing if you want to write as mix number as
4. 24 over 6 is 4
and than you have one sixth left over, so 4 and one sixth
this length right over here is going. Oh Sorry, this length over
here x is 4 and one sixth and than
this length over here is going to be 10 minus 4 and one sixth
What is that? 5 and 5 sixth