Let's learn a little bit about fluids
so - you probably have some notion of what a fluid is,
but let's talk about it in the physics sense or
maybe even in the chemistry sense
depending on what context you are watching this video-
So a fluid is anything that takes the shape of it's container
for example if I had a glass sphere
Let's say I completely fill this glass sphere with water
I was going to say we were in a zero gravity environment,
but you really don't need that
let's say that every cubic centimeter
or cubic meter of this glass sphere is filled with water
and let's say it's not of glass, let's say it's a rubber sphere
if I were to change the shape of that sphere
but not change the volume
If I were to change the shape of the sphere so
it looks like this now
the water would just change its shape
with the container
in this case I have green water
and the same is also true if that was oxygen
if that was just some gas, right?
It would fill the container and in this situation
it would also fill the the newly shaped container.
So a fluid, in general, takes the shape of the container.
I just gave you two examples of fluids:
You have liquids
and you have gases. Those are two types
of fluid. Both of those things take the shape of their container.
What's the difference between a liquid and a gas, then?
Well, a gas is compressible,
which means that I could actually decrease
the volume of this container
and the gas would just become denser within the container.
So you can think of it as...
if I blew air into a balloon, you could squeeze
that balloon a little bit. There's air in there.
I mean at somepoint the pressure might get high
enough to pop the balloon, but you can squeeze it.
While a liquid is incompressible.
And how do I know a liquid is incompressible?
Well, imagine the same balloon filled with water-
completely filled with water.
If you squeeze on that balloon from every side
let's say i have this ballon and it's is filled with water.
If you squeezed on this balloon
from every side, you would not be able to
change the volume of this balloon. No matter what you
do you will not be able to change the volume of this ballon.
No matter how much force or pressure you put
from any side on it.
If this was filled with gas- magenta ballon for gas-
you actually could decrease the volume by just increasing
the pressure on all sides of the balloon
you could acutally squeeze it and make the entire
volume smaller. So that's the difference between
a liquid and a gas: gas is compressible, liquid isn't.
we'll learn later that you can
actually turn a liquid into a gas, and a gas into a liquid
and a liquid into a solid, we'll learn all about that
later, but this is a pretty good working definition
so let's use that and now we're going to actually just focus on
the liquids to see if we can learn a little bit about liquid motion
or maybe even fluid motion in general. Let me draw something else
So let's say i had a situation, say I had this
weird shaped object that tends so show up in a lot
of physics books, which i'll draw. This weird
shaped container which is relatively narrow here
and it goes, and kind of U-turns and turns into a much larger opening
Let's say that the area of this opening is A1
and the area of this opening is A2.
This one is bigger.
And let's fill this thing with some liquid
which will be blue.
So that's my liquid.
Let's fill it with some liquid....
Let me see if this tool...
There you go! Look at that!
I've filled it with liquid, so quickly.
Alright.
And this is liquid, this is not just a fluid, and what's the important thing
about liquid? It's incompressible. So let's take what we
know about force actually about work and see
if we can come up with any rules about force and pressure with liquids at the center of it.
so what do we know about work? Work is force times distance.
We can also kind of view this as the energy put into the system.
I'll write down here.
So, work is equal to force times distance.
and we learned in the mechanical advantage etc.
that the work in is equal to work out
right?
the force times the distance you put into a system
is equal to the force times the distance you put out of it.
and you migh want to review the work chapter for that
but that's just the law of conservation of energy
because work in is just the energy that you're putting into a system
it's measured in joules
and work out is just the energy that comes out of a system.
And that's just saying that no energy is destroyed or created.
It just turns into different forms.
So, let's just use this stuff here:
the force times distance in is equal to
force times distance out.
Force in times distance in
is equal to force out times distance out.
Allright, so let's say that
I pressed with some force
on this entire surface.
So lets' say I have a piston
let's say I have a magenta piston right here
and I push down on this magenta piston
So, I pushed down on this
with a force of F1
and let's say I push it a distance of D1
That's it's initial position
and that's it's final position
I'll do it in ...
(the harder part of this video is picking the colors)
So let's say after I've pushed it
the piston goes this far.
So this is the distance that I pushed it.
This is D1.
The water is here
and I pushed the water down D1 meters, right ?
So, in this situation, my work is
F1 times D1, right ?
But let me ask a question:
how much water did I displace?
How much total water did I displace?
Well, this volume, right?
I took this entire volume
and pushed it down.
So, what's the volume right there,
that I displaced?
The volume there is going to be...
The volume displaced
has to equal this distance
(this is like a cylinder of liquid)
so this distance times this area, right?
... times the area of the container at that point.
I will assume that it is constant at that point
and that it changes just after that.
So, it equals area 1 times distance 1, right?
We also know that liquid has to go some place.
What do we know about liquids?
You can't compress it.
You can't change it's total volume.
So all of that volume is going to
have to go some place else.
This is where the liquid was.
The liquid is going to rise some level.
Let's say it gets to this level.
This is it's new level.
It's going to change some distance here.
And how do you know what distance that is going to be?
Well, the volume that it changes here
has to go some place.
That's going to push on that,
that's all going to push
That liquid has to go some place
essentially, it's going to end up
it might not be the exact same molecules
but that might displace some liquid here
that is going to displace some liquid here
here, and here, and here, and here
all the way until the liquid up here
gets displaced and gets pushed upward.
So the volume that you're pushing down here
is the same volume that goes up right here.
And so, what's the change in volume?
How much volume did you push up here?
Well, this volume here is going to be
the distance 2 times this larger area.
So we could say:
volume 2 is going to be equal to
the distance 2 times this larger area.
And we know that this liquid is incompressible,
so this volume has to be the same as this volume, right?
So we know that these two quantities
are equal to each other.
So area 1 times distance 1
(this area times this distance)
is going to be equal to
this area times this distance
(area 2 times distance 2).
So, let's see what we can do:
We know this: the force in times distance in
in equal to the force out times the distance out
Let's take this equation...
(I'm gonna switch back to green
so we don't lose track of things)
... and divide both sides by...
(let's just rewrite it)
So, let's say I rewrote each input force...
Actually, I'm much out of time
so I'll continue this into the next video.
See you soon.