(music)
And we’ve entered the church and in the
back corner to the right of the altar is the version
ended up as the tomb of Pope Julius the Second
with the figure by Michelangelo of Moses
And that accounts for the real popularity of this
church now, there is a lot of people here and
they are all here or virtually all here
to see the Michelangelo
And not the relics of Saint Peter’s chains
which probably would of drawn much
more interest just a few hundred years ago
And for the main sake of the church that’s right
but I’m not sure that Michelangelo would
have been entirely satisfied with
what he made here because this is actually
really a fraction of what he originally expected this tomb to be
He made very grandiose designs for the tomb of
Pope Julius the Second, so Pope Julius the second
commissioned Michelangelo to design and sculpt figures
for the tomb; this might seem kind of weird for us
Today we have someone plan their own tomb and as elaborately
it seems kind of Egyptian does it?
It does but you know that rulers did that
they commissioned their tomb all the better to ensure
that their memories and their
achievements lived on in prosperity
Let’s take a look at this sculpture, he’s towering
He is towering, I think he is 8 feet sitting down
so one can only imagine how tall he would be standing up
He is wearing classical garb, he has a massive head
and you just can’t overstate the muscularity
and the sense of power of this figure
He’s frighteningly powerful you can see these bulging muscles
in his arms, he’s a seated figure and yet there’s nothing relaxed about him
he’s filled with power and energy
And in fact as I look at it I really see this figure in
transition so many of Michelangelo’s figures are
and he is seated but he is in my mind at least about to stand
Yeah he does look like he’s pushed his left leg back in order to prepare to rise
And it seems to me that he is rising in anger, under his right arm
you can see the two tablets of the law
The Ten Commandments
One can imagine that he is about to rise and throw them down
on the ground to shatter them, in his anger
He’s come from back down the mountain from his audience
with god and he’s received the laws and he sees
the Israelites who’s left behind have had reverted from the
monotheism that he is preaching, to a polytheism
worshipping the golden calf
And it’s his anger and his fury that I think that
Michelangelo is capturing so beautifully
It does appear to be staring at something with a lot of (intensity) intensity
the figure seems almost alive, the way he pulls his leg
back, his left arm comes in front of his body, his right hand pulls
his beard, his head turns to the left
Not a part of his body that’s not in motion (not engaged)
And that’s right and actually really supporting the
complexity of composition of the sculpture as a whole
Right and that’s something that I think about
that is just something typical of the high renaissance
is that kind of new, complexity of the human body
You can think about it in the early renaissance
artists just sort of figuring out contrapposto (Yeah and)
For the first time since the ancient Greeks and Romans
and here we have something so much so much more complicated
It’s almost a seated contrapposto, but even in the beard
even in the expression which gives energy and velocity and
and just the kind of extraordinary movement through the figure and
contrast areas of really deep carving, creating very rich shadows
this very dramatic of alternations between
the dark and the light, between textures, all of which I
think energizes this figure
It’s too bad that Michelangelo had many other responsibilities
and was unable to complete all of the figures that he
intended for the tomb of Pope Julius the Second but the ones
that he started and the one that he finished
Moses and the other ones that he started like the slaves for the
tomb are just amongst his masterpieces
It is breath taking
(music)