We're on problem 71.
And they ask us, which fraction is equivalent to this
thing, 3x over 5 divided by x plus 4 over x plus 2?
Now the best way to do this, let's simplify the denominator
first. So that's equal to 3x over 5.
All of that over --let's find a common denominator.
The common denominator is 4.
So if we have a common denominator of 4, x/4 is of
course x/4.
x/2 is the same thing as 2x over 4.
So plus 3x over 4.
2x over 4 is the same thing as x/2.
And now if you divide by a certain fraction, that's the
same thing as multiplying by its inverse.
So this is going to be equal to 3x over 5 times the inverse
of this, times 4 over x plus 2x.
Let's see what we could do.
Well we could factor out an x here.
So this becomes x times 1 plus 2.
Actually, 1 plus 2 is 3.
I should have said x plus 2x is equal to 3x.
I should have done.
That's silly, I shouldn't have done that.