What causes water droplets to bounce
when they hit a surface?
What determines whether a surface is
hydrophobic or hydrophilic? And what does
it mean when a surface is superhydrophobic?
It all comes down to surface tension.
Surface tension or surface energy is a
tensile or contractile force.
it's given in unison mutants commuter
which is for screen at length
ordeal for me to squared disparaging per
unit area
service in japan acts like a stretch
elastic membrane kind of like a belated
because surface tension is is
contractile force each section of the
blue is pulling on each other resisting
change in cinci
what causes service and jane
it's caused by the attractive oracle he
supports a speech in water molecules
if we look at a poll of likely the
molecules that are inside the poor are
experiencing cohesive forces with
neighboring molecules
they're completely surrounded by other
molecules
and are enjoying their interactions
the interactive slower the energy seed
of these molecules
these are happy molecules
molecules on the surface of the four are
only surrounded by half the number of
other molecules so they only experience
half the amount of cohesive interactions
these are unhappy models
they read a high-ranking dc-ten
molecules inside the poor
to minimize the number of unhappy
molecules
but with a justice shape to expose the
smallest possible surface area
that's why water droplets hysterical and
why in space
lots of water all city departments peers
but what about water droplets resting on
the surface
what determines whether they will be dot
the role of or spread out completely
when a water drop of complexes service
it takes a cheap of hysterical cap
before have we learned that all liquids
have service energy
actually every single surface-to-surface
energy
a sentence can be thought of as the
interface between two phases
before when we're talking about the
surface tension of the liquid
you were talking about the service and
she between a liquid and air
there's also the service and he
retrieved solid in their
and a certain sense into liquid and
solid
if the congress and the equilibrium
content angle
we can do a force balance on the line of
contact with the surface
we want to balance of forces in the
extraction
we have the surface and he became solid
and a prayer
the service angie we can sell it and
they put in the opposite direction andy
excluded at the same percentage in tune
with the nba_ prayer
rearranging gives this which is the
answer is
once relationships at the continental
that a droplet links of the service is
related to all of the service and cheese
if the equilibrium continental is
greater than ninety degrees the surfaces
hydrophobic
on the other hand at the continental is
less than ninety degrees the services
hydrophilic
intercontinental is bigger than a
hundred fifty degrees
the surface is defined as being super
hydrophobic
water drum set of super hydrophobic
services will follow up
if the continental is less than five
degrees
the surface is defined as being super
hydrophilic
large on the set of super hydrophilic
services will spread out completely
this is useful for anti file coatings
advanced services super hydrophilic any
water that contact the surface will form
a thin film instead of performing
droplets on the surface
so what makes a surface super
hydrophobic person for hydrophilic
there to mean factors and press the
surface chemistry
the service can see determines whether
the service has slowed or high surface
seventy
which then determines whether the
services hydrophobic or hydrophilic
generally speaking surfaces with the
both surface energies are hydrophobic
and services with high energies are
hydrophilic
thinks i just have fun and other classic
several energy out things such as metals
have high energies
the second factors service rep
in general surface roughness will make a
hydrophobic surface even more
hydrophobic anna hydrophilic surface
even more hydrophilic
scientists have been trying to determine
what kind of trainee structures mexicans
is super hydrophobic person who had to
fill it
they've been looking and exams need
chairs such as the lunacy to obtain the
special properties
they're two different states have water
drop it can be and when it comes in some
rough surface
to go over these two different miles
we'll cult favorite evite equilibrium
continental
which is the continental for and ideal
facts are fixed
mccarthy to start the apparent contact
angle which is the content and go on a
rough surface
these two miles were developed by wenzel
and by calcium baxter and they shall
have service records can affect the
water droplets contact angle
the first state that a water droplet npm
when a context of surfaces the wenzel
state
in this state there are no air bubbles
underneath the droplet and the droplet
is incomplete contact with the surface
the drop to actually sticks very well to
the surface and it's called attend
droplet
in the wenzel model
the surface roughness is quantified by
our which is the real surface area
divided by the projected service area
since every surface has some sort of
roughness
because no surface it's completely
smooth at the molecular level
we can assume that are is greater than
one
the wenzel mock states that could save
data star is eager to our tenth
co-signed att_
inspire is greater than one the cosine
of data star is greater than the
co-signer dat
this is a very important statement
let's look at what happens when fear he
is less than ninety degrees
if they take he is forty five degrees
nra_'s nonpoint too
we can calculate the value of the estar
it is starting to have to be thirty two
degrees
so twenty-eight years that's in ninety
degrees we can see that data star is
less than petey
now with the devil happens twenty-eight
years greater than ninety degrees
if in fact the value of the akita
hundred thirty five degrees
an article to one point two
we can calculate that the start
is equal to
under forty eight degrees
now we can see that ada star is greater
than the egg
so when the services hydrophilic
data star is smaller than dating e
month surfaces hydrophobic
a two-star is bigger than payday
this equation shows that roughness will
make a hydrophobic surface even more
hydrophobic
and hydrophilic surfaces even more
hydrophilic
in the chocolate is in the kasi back
sixty
the water drama actually sits on top of
tiny air bubbles
in this state
water droplets will bounce a roll off
this is useful for water repellent and
self-cleaning surfaces
a service can be self-cleaning because
any water droplets that contact it will
grow up
picking up a meter along the way
generally speaking that kasi baxter's
the occurs for a very very rough
services
a special form of the kasi baxter model
just update a star is dependent on the
percent of solid anything contact the
droplet
as is valued approaches zero or in other
words if the tropics sitting mostly on
the air pockets
because an faa_ test our approach is
negative one and data star approaches a
hundred eighty degrees
so to summarize
how water drop it behaves in a complex a
solid is dependent on service energies a
conflict angle describes whether the
surfaces hydrophobic or hydrophilic
surface roughness can also cause
surfaces to become super hydrophobic or
super hydrophilic as shown by the wenzel
or kasi faster model
apologetic love how hydrophobicity can
be useful is how the namic decir de
tocqueville its water to drink
this field listened and then a desert in
africa
the beetle has a very special back where
they are a little hydrophilic islands
that are surrounded by hydrophobic areas
tiny farm droplets can collect on the
hydrophilic islands and grow too large a
droplet
once the troubles are large enough
the droplets rolled down the beatles
back and collected to drink
a