[intro music]
It's a hot day in Rome, but you know,
the ancient Romans had figured out how to stay cool.
We're in a room that reconstructs a room in the villa of Livia.
Livia was the wife of the emperor Augustus.
There is a lovely summer house, a resort of sorts,
And in the villa, there was one room
that was partially undergrond, dug into the rock,
which meant they would stay much cooler in summer.
And we can really appreciate that today!
But the sense of coolness would come not only
from the actual temperature, but also
from the decoration. From the very cool colours that this room is painted in.
What the artist did was paint an amazing illusion
of a landscape, a garden, as though the walls
were not walls at all, but views out
beyond the fence, beyond the wall.
There's trees, and bushes, and fruits, and plants, and birds
It's as if the walls have dissolved and
this is a great example of the second style of Roman wall painting
The first style was characterised by an attempt to re-create
in paint and stucco, the marble walls stuff of decorated Greek palaces
A kind of faux marble or kind of trompe-l'oeil.
Exactly. Now here, instead of the illusion of marble,
the artist has created an illusion of nature.
And nature is spread out all around us
and it's not a menacing nature it's a beautiful cultivated nature
It's full of playful birds,
there is fruit in the trees,
there are blossoms everywhere,
and there is light! The artist used atmospheric perspective
so that the trees and leaves that are closest
are surrendered more crisply than the vegetation in the background.
The only real architecture that's represented is,
as you mentioned, a straw fence perhaps
or something that looks a bit more substantial
in a kind of pink gray.
The artist has used that outer wall
in order to create a subtle rendering of perspective.
You can see that as the wall reaches out in a couple of places
to enclose trees that are just on the border.
We see poppies, roses, irises, pomegranates, quince,
so there is a real sense of variety in the plants,
and the flowers, in the fruits and in the birds that we see.
The positions of the birds: some with their wings stretched back, some sitting quietly
some in the sky... There is a real search for the variety of nature.
My favorite part is this one tree, that is framed
by this pinkish gray wall.
The branches move in exactly the haphazard way that a tree grows,
and there are places where we see light on the leaves and branches
and other places where the leaves are in shadow
It seems as if actually there is a breeze that's come up
and it has blown some leaves over so we seeing more silvery underside
and we get the darker shadows of the tops of the leaves.
So there is a real sense of the momentary and
of this being a breezy, beautiful day.
You can almost hear the leaves rustling in the wind.
I think my favorite plant is probably the acanthus that grows up around a pine
on one of the short sides of the room.
The other element I find most interesting is
that in this open-air space there is perched precariously
on that outer wall, a bird cage.
Throughout this entire room, there are paintings of birds that are free
and flying through the open sky
but here, we have a bird in a cage,
which reminds me that as I stand in this room, although these walls have dissolved, I am still inside a room.
[end music plays]