In the last video we saw that choice A is true. Now lets see if B, C, and D are also true. So choice B they're telling us that the argument, let me rewrite it over here in another color.
That choice B, the argument of z - z^1 is equal to the argument of z- z^2. Now lets think about this
a little bit. We already did some work we simplified what (z - z^1) is equal to. It's equal to T times
Z^2 - Z^1. So this is equivalent to saying that the argument of T times Z^2 minus Z^1, I'm just leveraging
some of the algebra that we already did. Because this thing is the same thing as what's inside of the
absolute value sign which is the same thing as this thing over here. So the argument in T time Z^2 minus
z^1 is equal to, so I'm just rewriting statement B. Statement B is saying that this should be equal to
the argument of... now what's (z minus z^2? z minus z^2 we've figured out was this thing right over here.
Actually it's this thing right over here. It's equal to this thing right over here. And we could rewrite
this thing as being equal to... I'm running out of real estate here. But we could rewrite this thing
right here as being equal to 1 minus T, I'm just factoring out the (1 minus t) times (z^1 minus z^2). (z^1
minus z^2). Or, so we could get it in the same form here let's multiply this times -1 and this times -1
So I'm multiplying by -1 twice so I'm not changing the number. So this is going to be equal to, or the
statement is claiming this is equal to the argument of T minus 1. Let me write it a little bit neater
than that. So the claim is that this should be equal to the argument of (t minus 1) times (z^2 minus z^1).
So lets think about this and just remember all I did is I multiplied this by negative one and this by
negative one if I multiply 2 things by negative one it's equivalent to multiplying by negative one twice.
Which is just multiplying it by one so I was able to swap both of these. So, is this true? Is it true
that the argument of T times (z^2 minus z^1), is it true that that's the same thing as the argument of
t minus 1 times (z^2 minus z^1). So let's think about this a little bit. Let's draw an Argand Diagram.
Here... that's the imaginary axis, this is the real axis. And, let's draw the vectored Z^2 minus Z^1
so let's say that this here is the vector and lets draw the vector Z^2 minus Z^1
now what would T times Z^2 minus Z^1 look like? Well T, we learned, is between zero and 1. So, it's going
to be a scaled down version of Z^2 minus Z^1. So this right here, so who knows what it is? This right
here would be T times Z^2 minus Z^1. Now what would T minus 1 times Z^2 minus Z^1 look like? Well T minus
1 if you remember T is between zero and 1. So T is less than 1. So T minus one, this right here is going
to be a negative number. It's going to be a negative number. So we're going to be scaling it by a negative
number. So we're going to be scaling Z^2 minus Z^1 by a negative number. So this thing right over here.
(t-1) times (z^2 minus z^1) is going to look like this. This is (t minus 1) times (z^2 minus z^1). Now
the arguments are just the angles between each of these numbers and the real axis so the argument for
this thing right over here is going to be this angle is going to be 5 right over so I could call that
5. But what's the argument for this thing? It's going to be that plus pi or plus 180 degrees. We have
to go all the way around. So they are not the same angle. Whatever number this is, right over here,
this number is going to be plus pi, or you can even go minus pi. But they're definitely not
going to be the same angle. So we can cross out, choice B as an option. Now that we're in this mode
let's see if we can tackle choice D because it looks very similar. And then I'll probably do
choice C in the next video because I don't want to spend too much time in each video. So what is choice
D telling us? Let me write it down here. Choice D is telling us... so we don't know, we have to see
if it's true that the Argument of (z minus z^1) is equal to the argument of (z^2 minus z^1)
So let's think a little bit about this right now. So, once again, we've already figured out what (z minus
z^1) is equal to. It's equal to this business over here. So this statement is equivalent
to the statement that the argument of (z minus z^1) which is (t times z^2 minus z^1) leveraging the algebra
from the last video. (t time z^2 minus z^1). Is this equal to the argument of (z^2 minus z^1)? Well once
again let's draw our Argand Diagram. Actually we could leverage the same Argand Diagram in green. We
have (z^2 minus z^1) its argument would be this angle right over here. It would be this angle five. This
is (z^2 minus z^1) That's that angle. (t times z^2 minus z^1) is just going to be the scaled down version
of it what we have in orange. Now clearly T is positive so it's not pointing in another direction
this is just a scaled down version of this. This vector and this vector, or this complex number
and this complex number are going to point in the same direction. So their angles are the same. This
orange vector is this here or this orange complex number is this right over here. This is
(t times z^2 minus z^1) and the green one, just to be clear is (z^2 minus z^1) is that. They're clearly
in the same direction, they clearly have the same argument. So choice D is another correct choice.
Now I'm going to leave you there. In the next video we're going to see if choice C works.