[music]
Dr. Steven Zucker: We're in the National Gallery in London
and we're looking at a really rare painting
--a painting by Duccio
--there are very few in the world
--this is a virgin child with saints
--it's got at the top of it a little teeny
image of King David
Dr. Beth Harris: From the Old Testament
Dr. Zucker: And he's surround by Old Testament prophets
who are identified with their scrolls
Dr. Harris: It's sort of standard iconography
--so you have the prophets who foretell
the coming of Christ
--and then below here we have a triptych
so that when the wings are open
--Mary and Christ are revealed
--so it's kind of wonderful in that
you have the prophets at the top
--who are always there with King David
--and then when the triptych is open the revealing
of the truth of their prophecy comes to be
--and King David was thought to be or understood to be
an ancestor of Christ
Dr. Zucker: And is wearing a blue that relates
directly to the blue that Mary wears
--there is a kind of intimacy here
that is absolutely revolutionary and is the foundation
of the Renaissance later
--look at the way the Christ child looks up
really adoringly at his mother
Dr. Harris: Sort of grabs hold of her vail
to sort of make sure he sees her face
Dr. Zucker: And look at the delicacy
of that vail--I think that's one of the most
beautiful areas of this painting
--the way in which he gathers her vail in one hand
and pulls on it with the other
--and creates this very soft kind of arc
between them--this bridge between them
--Duccio is a Sienese artist
and certainly Duccio's work is characterized
by the sensitivity to the decorative
both in the subtlety of color but also in form
--a kind of interest in the decorative
for its own sake
--and I think you really see that in the way
that Christ pulls at the inner garment
around Mary's neck and creates
a series of really beautiful and rhythmic folds
Dr. Harris: Ya--and playful lines and curves
that carry down around the golden hem
of Christ's garment and Mary's garment
Dr. Zucker: You see it also in the rendering
of St. Aurea whose a rare saint
to shown in paintings of this time
-- I think of any time
-- And St. Dominic on the left as well
-- both of those saints are so direct
that they seem to be almost stepping out of the picture plane
--there's a sense of truthfulness--of veracity almost
that seems so precocious for this moment
Dr. Harris: I think when we look overall
at the painting--at this little altar piece
that would have been a private altar piece
for private devotion that someone could carry around
if they moved and wanted to have the ability
to worship and pray
--so it's important to remember that
this is an aid in prayer
--but when we look at it there is a real sense
of the physical presence of the saints on either side
and of that emotion connection
with Mary and her physical presence
--so we are seeing the beginnings
of this change to the Renaissance
Dr. Zucker: It's so interesting that Duccio
is creating these connections which will lay
foundation for the Renaissance
which will come a century later
--but at the same time this is so firmly rooted
also in the medieval tradition
and we're never very far from that
--not only do we have these broad gold
fields which are really representation
of the divine light of heaven
--there's no rational relationship
between the figures in terms of scale
--and then of course there's that strong
byzantine influence still in the elongation
of the nose--look at Mary--of her fingers
--even as Duccio begins to explore the possibility
of creating a more intimate
and I think emotionally charged rendering
[music]