Welcome to this presentation on logarithm properties.
Now this is going to be a very hands-on presentation.
If you don't believe that one of these properties are true
and you want them proved, I've made three or four videos
that actually prove these properties.
But what I'm going to do is I'm going to show the properties and then show you how they can be used.
It's going to be little more hands-on.
So let's just do a little bit of a review of just what a logarithm is.
So if I say that "a"... oh that's not the right...
Let's see.
I want to change-- There you go.
Let's say I say that a-- Let me start over.
a to the b is equal to c.
So if we-- a to the b power is equal to c.
So another way to write this exact same relationship instead
of writing the exponent, is to write it as a logarithm.
So we can say that the logarithm base a of
c is equal to b.
So this are essentially saying the same thing, they just have different kind of results.
In one, you know a and b and you're kind of getting c.
That's what exponentiation does for you.
And the second one, you know a and you know that when
you raise it to some power you get c.
And then you figure out what b is.
So they're the exact same relationship, just stated
in a different way.
Now I will introduce you to some interesting
logarithm properties.
And they actually just fall out of this relationship and
the regular exponent rules.
So the first is that the logarithm-- Let me do
a more cheerful color.
The logarithm, let's say, of any base-- So let's just call
the base-- Let's say b for base.
Logarithm base b of a plus logarithm base b of c-- and
this only works if we have the same bases.
So that's important to remember.
That equals the logarithm of base b of a times c.
Now what does this mean and how can we use it?
Or let's just even try it out with some,
well I don't know, examples.
So this is saying that-- I'll switch to another color.
Let's make mauve my-- Mauve-- I don't know.
I never know how to say that properly.
Let's make that my example color.
So let's say logarithm of base two of-- I don't know --of eight
plus logarithm base two of-- I don't know let's say --thirty-two.
So, in theory, this should equal, if we believe this
property, this should equal logarithm base two of what?
Well we say eight times thirty-two.
So eight times thirty-two is two hundred and forty plus sixteen, two hundred and fifty-six.
Well let's see if that's true.
Just trying out this number and this is really isn't a proof.
But it'll give you a little bit of an intuition, I think, for
what's going on around you.
So log-- So this is-- We just used our property.
This little property that I presented to you.
And let's just see if it works out.
So log base two of eight.
two to what power is equal to eight?
Well two to the third power is equal to eight, right?
So this term right here, that equals three, right?
Log base two of eight is equal to three.
two to what power is equal to thirty-two?
Let's see.
two to the fourth power is sixteen.
two to the fifth power is thirty-two.
So this right here is two to the-- This is five, right?
And two to the what power is equal to two hundred and fifty-six?
Well if you're a computer science major, you'll
know that immediately.
That a bite can have two hundred and fifty-six values in it.
So it's two to the eighth power.
But if you don't know that, you could multiply it out yourself.
But this is eight.
And I'm not doing it just because I knew that three
plus five is equal to eight.
I'm doing this independently.
So this is equal to eight.
But it does turn out that three plus five is equal to eight.
This may seem like magic to you or it may seem obvious.
And for those of you who it might seem a little obvious,
you're probably thinking, well two to the third times two to the
fifth is equal to two to the three plus five, right?
This is just an exponent rule.
What do they call this?
The additive exponent prop-- I don't know.
I don't know the names of things.
And that equals two to eight, two to the eighth.
And that's exactly what we did here, right?
On this side, we had two the third times two to fifth essentially,
and on this side you have them added to each other.
And what makes the logarithms interesting is and why-- It's
a little confusing at first.
And you can watch the proofs if you really want kind of
a rigorous-- my proofs aren't rigorous.
But if you want kind of a better explanation
of how this works.
But this should hopefully give you an tuition for why this
property holds, right?
Because when you multiply two numbers of the
same base, right?
Two exponential expressions of the same base, you
can add their exponents.
Similarly, when you have the log of two numbers multiplied
by each other, that's equivalent to the log of each
of the numbers added to each other.
This is the same property.
If you don't believe me, watch the proof videos.
So let's do a-- Let me show you another log property.
It's pretty much the same one.
I almost view them the same.
So this is log base b of a minus log base b of c
is equal to log base b of-- well I ran out.
I'm running out of space --a divided by c.
That says a divided by c.
And we can, once again, try it out with some numbers.
I use two a lot just because two is an easy number to
figure out the powers.
But let's use a different number.
Let's say log base three of-- I don't know --log base three of--
well you know, let's make it interesting --log base three of
one / nine minus log base three of eighty-one.
So this property tells us-- This is the same thing as--
Well I'm ending up with a big number.
Log base three of one / nine divided by eighty-one.
So that's the same thing as one / nine times one / eighty-one.
I used two large numbers for my example, but
we'll move forward.
So let's see.
nine times eight is seven hundred and twenty, right?
nine times-- Right.
nine times eight is seven hundred and twenty.
So this is one / seven hundred and twenty-nine.
So this is log base three over one / seven hundred and twenty-nine.
So what-- What does-- three to what power is equal to one / nine?
Well three squared is equal to nine, right?
So three-- So we know that if three squared is equal to nine, then we
know that three to the negative two is equal to one / nine, right?
The negative just inverts it.
So this is equal to negative two, right?
And then minus-- three to what power is equal eighty-one?
three to the third power is twenty-seven.
So three to the fourth power.
So we have minus two minus four is equal to-- Well, we could
do it a couple of ways.
Minus two minus four is equal to minus six.
And now we just have to confirm that three to the minus sixth
power is equal to one / seven hundred and twenty-nine.
So that's my question.
Is three to the minus sixth power, is that equal to seven-- one / seven hundred and twenty-nine?
Well that's the same thing as saying three to sixth power is
equal to seven hundred and twenty-nine, because that's all the negative exponent
does is inverts it.
Let's see.
We could multiply that out, but that should be the case.
Because, well, we could look here.
But let's see.
three to the third power-- This would be three to the third power
times three to the third power is equal to twenty-seven times twenty-seven.
That looks pretty close.
You can confirm it with a calculator if you
don't believe me.
Anyway, that's all the time I have in this video.
In the next video, I'll introduce you to the last
two logarithm properties.
And, if we have time, maybe I'll do examples with
the leftover time.
I'll see you soon.