PROBLEM: "The government created the following
stem-and-leaf plot showing the number of turtles
at each major zoo in the country.
How many zoos have fewer than 46 turtles?"
So what the stem-and-leaf plot does
is it gives us the first digit in each number –
(So essentially, you could call this the 10's place.)
– and then these numbers represent the 1's place.
So there is only 1 zoo that had 4 turtles.
So you could view this as (0 × 10) + (4 × 1) –
– or 4 turtles.
So looking at this row –
in the 10's place – there's a 1.
So we would interpret this number 1 here
as a 10 + 1, or 11.
This is a 14.
This right over here would be a 16.
That's a 16.
And so forth, and so on.
This would be 17 – then 18.
On this row, this is 23. This is 23. This is 26 –
because we have a 2 in our tens place right over here.
This is the first digit.
So let's answer the question,
"How many zoos have fewer than 46 turtles?"
Well, there are no zoos that had 40 or more turtles.
So let's review.
This row shows zoos that had 30-something turtles.
These had 20-something turtles.
These had a number in the teens.
This had a single-digit number of turtles (fewer than 10).
So the answer is literally
as many zoos as we have listed here.
So, [COUNTING] 1 – 2 – 3 – 4 – 5 – 6 – 7 – 8 – 9 –
10 – 11 – 12 – 13 – 14 – 15 – 16 – 17.
17 zoos have fewer than 46 turtles.
Let's do another one.
PROBLEM: "The buyer for a chain of supermarkets
created the following stem-and-leaf plot showing
the number of coconuts at each of the stores:"
"What was the smallest number of coconuts
at any one grocery store?"
So the buyer for a chain of supermarkets created
the following stem-and-leaf plot
showing the number of coconuts at each of the stores.
At any one (1) grocery store, the smallest number –
well that's this one right over here.
Remember it's not 2.
We have our tens place right over here.
It's a 1.
So this number right over here represents
12 coconuts at that store.
So we'll put 12 right over here.
Let's try another one.
"A statistician for a chain of department stores
created the following stem-and-leaf plot
showing the number of watches at each of the stores:"
"How many department stores have exactly 7 watches?"
Well, that's only this one right over here: 0 | 7 watches.
This one and that one are not 7.
This is representing 17,
because it's in the row with 1 at the beginning.
This right over here represents 27,
because its in the row with the 2 at the beginning.
So there's only one store that has exactly 7 watches.
Let's do one more.
This is kind of fun.
"A zookeeper created the following stem-and-leaf plot
showing the number of tigers
at each major zoo in the country:"
"How many zoos have more than 24 tigers?"
So, we can ignore the 0s and the teens.
And we get in the 20s.
This is 25.
So that meets the criterion.
And then you go to 28 – 29.
So all of these in the 30s,
and all of these right over here.
This 3 | 0 , this doesn't mean 0 tigers.
This is 30 tigers. This is 40 tigers.
So we count 1 – 2 – 3 – 4 – 5 – 6 – 7 – 8 – 9.
9 zoos have more than 24 tigers.
9 zoos.
And we're done!