Monica and Brian here in the Upper Egypt Galleries of the University
Of Pennsylvania, Museum of Archeology and Anthropology.
And we're looking here at a larger than life sculpture of Ramses II
who was a pharaoh in the New Kingdom of Ancient Egypt.
Right in the center of the gallery it really dominates the space
and seems to draw everybody in to its universe.
Absolutely, and that's really what its function is.
Really everything about this sculpture is about showing power
and we'll talk a little bit about that today,
about how that works.
This would be a representation of a kind
that you would find in all different shapes and sizes, is that right?
I don't know about shapes, but certainly sizes
from life-size to larger than life size
to colossal, 20 feet and more tall.
So where would this one fit in a sense of scale values?
I think (...) there are other depictions of Ramses
for instance there are colossal representations of Ramses at his large temple in Abu Simbel in Upper Egypt.
And so speaking of temples, that's where this sculpture like this, and
in fact this very sculpture was placed in a temple dedicated to Ramses.
Ok, so in terms of function, this is not a display of power for the people.
No, because really common people wouldn't even be allowed into
the innermost chambers of the temple.
The priests would come and they would bring offerings to the representation of a pharaoh
in fact there's even a little dip in the sculpture itself in front of his feet as you can see right here,
and that's where some of those offerings would have been placed by the priests.
That's fascinating because you don't often think of these as functional sculptures.
You think of them as being, you know, kind of something to be revered.
That's right. It sort of has a dual in that sense.
I mean, although we can't deny clearly the very overt displays of power
and conventional displays of power that this sculpture shows.
For instance, things that we would expect to see in any representation of a great pharaoh:
the linen head cloth, the snake Uraeus there at the top of his forehead,
what's missing now, the inset false beard,
that's also conventional show of pharaonic power.
And all this on top of an idealized body, right, so a heroic body type particular to the pharaoh.
That's right, so besides just the trappings of power,
the trapping of imperial power, we also have a kind of convention of showing the body type in a powerful way.
The musculature, the hands placed firmly and flatly on the thighs as well.
And this particular piece has some challenges to it.
In addition to being pretty badly beaten up.
Yes, it's clearly been damaged, broken into parts over time and reassembled,
but you might notice something a little strange about his head.
Yeah, it's a little tiny and when you come into the gallery you see this remarkable presence
and as you get closer to it, you can't help but feel that the head is a little bit too small.
Why is his head too small, right.
And the reason for that is that it's believed actually
because of the style of the lower part of the body,
that this sculpture was originally from the Middle Kingdom,
that it actually was not at first meant to be a representation of Ramses.
Okay. So, it's repurposed.
Exactly, later when he came to power then the head was resculptured to create a likeness of Ramses.
And so of course by the subtractive method that would make the head a bit smaller.
Wow, so the same head of the previous pharaoh, I guess by logical extension, a less powerful pharaoh,
That's right, or someone who was succeeded by Ramses.
And he's whittled down to look like Ramses.
That's remarkable. Exactly, right.
It's pretty beat up, it's pretty broken.
Yes, it sustained some heavy damage, and the waist is cut clean through, the neck as well.
So, that fact that it's quartzite I'm guessing that's not as hard of a stone as we're used to seeing.
Right, a diorite is really the preferred hard stone in Ancient Egyptian sculpture,
but actually, one of the advantages of the quartzite in this case
is that because it's more porous, it retains some of the original pigment.
I think important to remember, and it's very easy to forget
that all of this ancient sculpture would have been painted,
stones such as diorite which is so hard and so dense,
that paint has flaked off over the thousands of years since it was painted.
But with more porous stones you can see that they retained some of the pigment.
We have some kind of reddish tone to the skin and that's also an Egyptian convention,
to show male figures with a kind of reddish skin tone.
And we can also see the stripes that had been painted in the linen head cloth as well.
Marvellous. I did not notice the color before you just pointed that out.
Now I can kind of see the yellow and blue, is it? Or the black and yellow.
It's probably the yellow and blue.
If you think about a King Tut's, cover of the coffin, it's yellow and blue, right.
The gold and the lapis, I think.
You've changed the way I look at this sculpture now. That's remarkable.
So the compactness of the forms would be the body, the arms close to the body
and the stone between the torso and the arm is still there.
Absolutely right, his arm's not sculpted free from the body,
it all perhaps just a in little bit that's broken away and that's in fact of course why it's broken away.
Right, so his forearms are missing, but you can see the hands resting comfortably on the lap
which would suggest no projecting parts, right, nothing to break off.
Exactly.
So the body type we mentioned is a heroic body type which we would expect to see of a pharaoh,
but it, well is it similar or different than we're used to seeing in Greco-Roman art,
in terms of, say, naturalism, in terms of a natural body?
I think it's really quite different, don't you?
I mean, we have this very strong and muscular body type,
but does it look really the way human body looks in all of its naturalism?
I think at first glances people think so.
I think they do, but if we look closely,
the way the upper arm connects to the shoulders,
somewhat awkward this very thick shins
with their big muscles and this sharp ridge of a shinbone.
So a body type that's particular to the pharaoh
you can imagine if we had all the pharaohs lined up we would see a consistency in there.
That's right. Where really the most important thing is showing
how strong and immovable and permanent the power of this pharaoh is
rather than showing the way his shins and his toes actually looked.
Right. But a consistency of the way he's represented,
so it's always recognized that's a pharaoh.
So that, together with the trappings of his power, really, those things work together to show that.
So the permanence that we talked about before of the stone keeping the forms compact,
would work especially in the context of the tomb to keep things ...
Yes, absolutely because that ties in perfectly with the Egyptian belief in the afterlife,
in this kind of eternal presence or existence of the Ka or the soul of the deceased.
The long now.
That's right.
And the recognizable features work in a political (...) for people to recognize this particular pharaoh,
but then also work in a tomb, so the Ka can recognize the pharaoh.
That's right, because the Ka goes off and wanders around to the underworld, here and there,
but it always needs to come back and needs to recognize its home.
Now, I wanted to say something before we end about the sheer number of images on here,
the sheer kind of weight of the iconography.
Yes, I think it's important to remember or to distinguish between
the image of the pharaoh himself and these other images that we see carved around the throne.
There's a difference between visual images and text, and because that difference is very clear in our culture,
images are pictures and text are letters.
It can be easy for us to forget that these pictures, these hieroglyphs are not pictures, this is text
and they're not to be interpreted as iconography here, that a bird here doesn't necessarily mean a bird.
A bird is a part of this word, it's text.
So, almost like an illuminated manuscript.
That's right, where the image is separate from the text
and the text is not meant to be appreciated as an esthetic visual experience.
So you get two different kinds of looking.
That's right.
So the iconography on the image itself is still enough to keep people entertained,
the bull's Tail, the Uraeus you mentioned, the headdress,
any other symbols of unity that we would be accustomed to seeing
are Old Kingdom statues...
Yes, some things carry through, the pleated kilt, the bull's Tail itself
which we haven't actually mentioned before which here actually appears to hang between
the pharaoh's legs in the front we're meant to imagine that it's coming down from his back.
That's also those kinds of symbols carried through throughout all three major periods of Egyptian art.
So an expert could come and identify this maybe rather quickly as New Kingdom,
but for non-Egyptologists there's a consistency of imagery form Old Kingdom to New Kingdom,
that's really quite startling. Absolutely.