we are at the british museum, standing in front of
the holy thorn reliquary, which was commissioned
by John, Duke of Berry in 1390s in Paris
and this is quite a piece of work.
it´s exquisite and there is an awful lot of detail here.
We´ve just started right from the bottom of it up.
We got the city in gold
and it´s a four cornered city
it represents the four corners of the world
and there is an angel at each corner
blowing a trumpet, and around that
we have this green hill, with four tombs,
with people are rising out of that and looking out.
above that we´ve got the central panel
which is surrounded by rubies and pearls
and lots of gold, and there are twelve figurines
who are the twelve apostles picked out in an armor in gold
surrounding the central panel.and right
in the centre, we have Christ sitting in majesty,
with his feet on the globe. And above that
at the very top, we've got the Father,
and then there are these two saphires. They are the only two saphires in the whole piece.
One is at the very very top above God the Father
and the other one is i the middle of
this window , where the Christ figure is sitting
and this is 2 inch long piece of wood jotting up
into Christ and Cchrist is sitting on a rainbow
and right above Christ there are these two little angels holding a tiny tiny cramapones above his head
what and that is connected to this spike coming out of where the saphire is.
It is supposedly one of the thorns that came from
the crown of thorns.
We will see it at the reliquary here.
The idea of reliquary in the middle ages
is really important because it was these physical objects
which were sometimes body parts of saints.
in this case it is a thorn from the crown of thorns
these objects were used as focussors of spiritual contemplation
well we're really looking here where relics began
because Christ died on a cross and he rouse into heaven. So,
he left nothing behind. So all the relics that are connected to Christ
are things like the crown of thorns or pieces of the true cross
that are material memory, and of course we have no way of proving
whether this was in fact a thorn, from the crown of thorn
worn by christ when he was crucified.
No. But that wasn't the point. The idea was you believed in these objects
and so we insisted to pray in the presence of these objects
was to give extra power and special access
to heaven. Christ and the Passion of all this happened within the Roman Empire.
The crown of thorn was discovered by Constantine´s mother,
the Empress Helena. He went on pilgrimage,
and she found the crown of thorns and the true cross as well.
these were taken by Constantinople and it´s said the Bizantine empire had all
of the power which of course this is what made the rest of the world
extremely jealous of the power that Constantinople had and thats why they came
and sacked Constantinople and thats when these things got taken away
Tis reliquary started with one of the french kings
Louise the ninth, who as he saw it rescued the crown and brought it to paris
and then the gratest gift that he could give to anyone,
would be to take one of the thorns and make a gift of it.
and thats what he did here. it is spiritual but
its so circulous to control because if
someone gives you a gift of something thats
so close to christ that is ever placeable, so here we thought
John, Duke de Pari, who s is one of the french Dukes
and its such an important gift for both religious and political reasons
and he has made this incredible case to House
this one relic. and you see the story of the last Judgement
its not whats going on here.these angels at the bottom are trumpeting
to wake people up to see the dead rising out of their coffins
from the four corners of the earth.and in the centre there is the scene of christ enthroned.
and its important for the relicary because with the out of all this gold and saphires and pearls
and all this paraphernilia around it , how do you know about it.
you know what it is by casing a hole set and keep out.the time will have itswell for this is not an audience
who is litereate. what you mostly got is the story being told by the object itself
and people would have been to church and heard these stories
the stories of the last judgement and christ enthroned. it is like a picture book
for an audience looking at this at the time
regardlessof all that gold back and any of those roles
the most valuable object is this entire piece is not one
bit of thorn that has to swab the blood of christ upon it
there is so much tiny tiny detail in the way
that everything is made in the hair, in the beards,
the carving of the leaves. if you look at the two nailing fingers of christ feet
the way that their carving has been picked out
and the individual fingers that you can see and the praying hands
it is a really nice combination of both.an object of faith and a beautiful object of craftsmanship.