This is a papyrus book of the dead
which will be on display in the exhibition:
“Journey Through the Afterlife: Ancient Egyptian Book of the Dead”
Before it goes on display
the old Victorian paper backing needs to be removed.
So Bridget places the papyrus in a fume hood
and applies strips of paper to protect the front.
The papyrus is faced down and wetted on the table
with tracing paper mapping the delicate areas of the papyrus at hand.
Both conservatives peel off the top backings.
The last backing needs to be picked off with tweezers.
The back of the paper coming off is brown
because it previously was painted to blend in with the papyrus.
Whilst the conservatives continue to take off the backing,
they ensure the papyrus is moist by spraying water on it.
Picking off the backing took over two hours,
so to save you time we sped up the process.
Once the old backing is removed,
a fine, high quality lining is put on to support it.
The newly line papyrus is dried between blotting paper,
under glass and weights and lies there for several weeks.
When Helen and Bridget are confident the newly lined papyrus is dried,
they remove the facing that was put on to provide temporary protection.
Once this is done they examine the result
and are pleased with the new lining on the papyrus.
They will soon get going with the rest of the conservation work that is needed
on the papyri featuring at the next major exhibition.