What I want to do in this video is write the algebraic expressions
that represent the same thing that these statements are saying.
So this first statement, they say "The sum of -7 and the quantity 8 times x,"
So the sum, the sum...so we're going to have an addition here...of -7...
of -7...
...and the quantity 8 times x...
...so the quantity 8 times x. Well that's just 8x...
(So I can just write 8x over there)
So it is -7+8x,
or you could view this as the sum of -7 and the quantity 8 times x.
Let's do the next one!
Take the quantity -3 times x,
so take the quantity -3 times x,
and then add 1...and then add 1...
So the quantity -3 times x, we can write that as -3x,
and then we need to add 1 to that.
So that's going to be plus...plus 1.
Now this one: -6 plus...-6 plus...
so we can write -6 plus something
The product of -1 and x.
So the product of -1 and x...that's just going to be -1x.
-1x which is the same thing as -x.
So we can write this as -6 plus -x, or we can just write this...
this is the exact same thing as
-6-x.
And we are done!