In September 2012 the British Museum's most famous natural mummy
was taken out of the building for the first time in over a hundred years.
One of the Museum's oldest humans was about to be examined with the newest technology.
An the results would be a revelation.
Gebelein man is one of a small group,
6 or 7 bodies of this kind which are in the British Museum.
All of these came from the site of Gebelein in the 1890s.
Gebelein man himself was put on display staight away.
He's always attracted tremendous attention.
We're about to take Gebelein man to the Cromwell Hospital to have him CT-scanned
and we hope to find a lot more about his past biology, his past health,
how old he was when he died,
to get a better understanding of what it was liked to live and die in Predynastic Egypt.
His preservation is entirely due to natural processes.
We would call a body like this a natural mummy.
This is the area where you can see the scapula.
And there's a dent in it.
In the medial border.
And I'm not sure what's happening here.
That'd be and area maybe to have a closer look.
I won't have to talk to him. I won't have to ask him questions
and won't have to give him injections
and also hopefully he won't be clastrophobic.
As far as I'm aware
predynsatic mummies have never been CT-scanned before.
Is it possible to look at the left scapula?
We found out that most of his bones appear to have just fused.
The head of his humerus and the head of his femur,
both of which suggest he's just finished growing
and he's probably and he's probably died between the ages of 18 and 21.
In the more traditional Egyptian mummy,
all the internal organs have been taken out during embalming,
sometimes put back in after they were preserved,
but you will not ever see the brain because they didn't keep that.
In the case of Gebelein man
we would hope to see all these organs preserved just by drying.
We have teams excavating in Egypt and in Northern Sudan
every year for months at a time
excavating both the towns people lived in
and also the places they burried their dead.
There's a real focus at the moment into trying to investigate
what life was like for the ordinary Egyptians.
This looks structural to me, see the way there's a line there?
So much of the study of Ancient Egypt has been
about the temples and the tombs of kings,
and the golden masks you have on the burrials of pharaoh and so on,
but that really was a very small part of the population,
maybe less than 1%.
What about all the ordinary people, the farmers that lived along the Nile,
what was their health like, what was their life like?
A month later, the British Museum team has come to the Natural History Museum
to see the first results of the scans of Gebelein man.
Thanks very much for coming everyone.
This was a little tête-à-tête,
a sort of a scientist to scientist sort of thing,
but it's sort of xxx a little bit which is great
and I'm very pleased that you could all make it here.
Ground-breaking real-time visualization technology developed in Sweden
is now installed on a new authopsy table
which can be used by the public.
If we actually took a slice from this direction,
now look down inside the body and see a lot of the soft tissue.
Well, I think this will be a fantastic tool to bring it to the galleries.
Our visitors will be able to explore this mummy
who's been known in our gallery for over a century.
And as we all learn at school,
the Egyptians took the brain out through the nose
as part for that articifial mumification process.
So this fantastic tool which is like a virtual surgeon's knife
taking away the dome of the skull
and then the ability to see inside
and the preservation of the brain that's over 5 thousand years old?
Six thousand.
Based on the way he's been treated, he should date to about 3600 B.C.
maybe 3700, so ... he's old.
And it's so neat to apply this new technology to something just his old.
And to get these results to see potentially
what he might what he might have eaten
on his last day.
It's really very exciting.
But what did happen on Gebelein man's last day?
He was young and robust, so what or who killed him?
The skeleton and soft tissue now revealed with digital technology
provide evidence for how this man died thousands of years ago.
A lot of the ribs have been broken all down kind of a line.
You can see that the one below this area is quite interesting.
In fact you've got fragments which are still floating in soft tissue.
His shoulder bone had a big indentation in it,
so the rib immediately below also looks like it's been punctured,
shattered into fragments which have emebeded themselves into the muscle tissue
and they're still embeded there today.
The fracure pattern suggests that this was just done when the bone was fresh.
All o which points to him being stabbed in the back.
It's very likely that what we've had on display in the galleries
for many, many years was the victim of a murder.
And it's only now
that we're trully finding out
who this person was.