What I want you to attempt to do is
given an arbitrary list—
I made a particular example of an arbitrary list right here—
write a function that sorts that arbitrary list.
So maybe you call your function my_sort()
You can call it whatever.
What I want is,
after I call my_sort() on a list,
that the list itself gets resorted.
So I don't want my_sort() to return a copy of the list.
I want, after I call my_sort() on "a",
if I then refer to "a"—
let's say I do print(a),
if I do print(a)—
then that will literally return a sorted version of "a".
Or I should say, it will return "a"
but now "a" itself is sorted,
the list that "a" is referring to is now sorted.
So it would now look like this,
"a" would now look like [1, 2, 3, 5, 7, 8].
And you might say,
wait Sal, that's very easy.
There is already a sort function in Python.
You literally can call a.sort()
and that will sort "a" in place
just the way I've asked you to do.
And when I say in place I'm saying
it's actually going to work on the actual list.
It's not going to create a copy of the list that is sorted.
It's actually going to work in place on that actual list.
And a.sort() does this but I don't want you to use that.
So let's cross this off.
The whole point of this is to learn, you know,
just kind of try our best to write our own sorting function.
And what you're going to see,
and hopefully you appreciate
as we go deeper and deeper into this,
there's ['re] many many many many ways to sort things.
And sorting is really a good way
to think about how good a function—
and we'll start talking about algorithms—
how good a process is or how fast a process is,
or how efficient a process is at doing something.
So I'll leave you there.
Try to sort this.
In the next video,
I'll try to outline an algorithm,
which is really a process for doing something.
I'll outline an algorithm,
that's kind of an intuitive way to sort things.
It's not the most efficient way to sort things.
And then after that I'll my best to hand it—
I'll try my best—
try at actually writing that algorithm in a python program.