Let's see if we can write twelve point nine eight as a mixed number.
So, the first thing you might want to realize here is that this is the exact same thing
as twelve plus zero point nine eight.
And this simplifies it, because then we just have to write it as twelve and some fraction that's the same
thing as zero point nine eight. So, if we can write zero point nine eight as a fraction
then we can, we're essentially, we're almost done!
So let's see if we can do that.
So, this nine right over here is in the tenths place.
I'll just write it like that. Tenths place. And this right over here is in the hundredths place.
It's in the hundredths place. So you can view zero point nine eight two different ways.
You can view it as nine tenths. Nine tenths.
That's this part over here, nine tenths plus plus eight hundredths, plus eight hundredths.
And if you want to find a common denominator that would be the same thing as ninety over one hundred
plus eight over one hundred. Plus eight over one hundred, which is equal to ninety-eight over one hundred.
Equal to ninety-eight over one hundred. And so, zero point nine eight is ninety-eight hundredths.
And another way you could have said that is, "Look, this space over here is in the hundredths place. And so this is ninety-eight hundreds, or ninety-eight hundredths."
So, you could have skipped this right over here. So, if we wanted to write this as a mixed number,
we could just write it as twelve and, instead of zero point nine eight, twelve and ninety-eight hundredths.
Now, we haven't reduced this to lowest terms. So, let's se if we can simplify this.
Ninety-eight is divisible by two, and so is a hundred. So, lets divide both of them
by two. They have that common factor. So, we can divide both of them by two.
And so, this is the same thing as twelve and ninety-eight divided by two is nine is forty-nine.
A hundred divided by two is fifty. And I think that's about as far as we can do.
Forty-nine's factors, it's divisible by seven, but fifty isn't.
So we've put it in lowest terms. So, twelve point nine eight can be written as a mixed number,
twelve and forty-nine fiftieths.