Adolf Hitler got his start in the military during World War I.
He's a dispatch runner on the Western Front;
he actually gets fairly decorated.
And, by most accounts, this is where he finds meaning.
He finds meaning in being part of the military;
he finds meaning in, frankly, the war itself.
But, then, in 1918, we, of course, have the end of the war.
Well, first you have the abdication of the Kaiser;
you have a Republican government,
people who want to form a republic take control,
and then they sign an armistice with the Allies in November.
And this is not well received by Hitler.
And frankly, it's not well received by many in the military.
From their point of view, they somewhat delusionally believed
that Germany would have won World War I,
if they weren't stabbed in the back by these "November Criminals,"
by the folks who had taken over after the Kaiser.
So you have this whole "stabbed in the back" theory.
. . . "stab in the back" . . .
by those who had taken over and signed the armistice.
And this wasn't just believed by folks like Hitler.
This was believed even by very senior people in the military.
This right over here is General Ludendorf, one of two people -
the other gentleman, Hindenberg -
who are in charge of the entire German military.
He believed in the "stab in the back" theory.
He thought that they would have won if they didn't sign the armistice,
if these "November Criminals" - these people who had taken control of the government -
did not sign this with the Allies.
And then you go to 1919.
From the point of view of people like Hitler,
things only got worse.
You have the Treaty of Versailles,
that applied all the war guilt to the Germans.
You have these huge reparations that would even be paid in resources.
You have the former German Empire.
A significant amount of its territory is given over to the Allies,
or to form new states.
Then you also have the establishment - the formal establishment -
of the Weimar Republic. It's called the Weimar Republic
because the new German constitution is drafted in the town of . . .
is drafted in the town of Weimar.
And it sets it up as a parliamentary democracy -
that's why we now call it - that's why it's called a republic.
But it's a little bit bizarre of a parliamentary democracy.
It actually gave a good bit of power to a directly elected president
that had a reasonable amount of power, especially in emergencies,
and that would become relevant later on,
when Hitler actually comes to power over a decade later.
But then in 1919, Hitler was still looking, you know,
he was very upset about the war ending;
he stays part of the military.
And part of the military, he's assigned to start infiltrating,
or spying on the German Workers Party.
So, "spy on -" and the acronym in German is the DAP.
But the English translation would be the German Workers Party.
But he actually gets quite impressed by the German Workers Party,
which is really ultra-nationalist.
And when we talk about ultra-nationalist,
it's all about German race superiority,
it's in line with this whole idea that they would have won the war
if they weren't stabbed in the back,
and it's also anti-communist . . .
"anti-communist . . . "
it's anti-capitalist, and it's anti- ethnic minorities and in particular, anti-Jewish.
And all of these ideas, Hitler found very impressive.
And just to be clear, you know, a lot of times when people talk about ultra-nationalist groups,
they often will call them as ultra right-wing. "ultra-right-wing."
And this bears some clarification.
Because the right wing is also often viewed as very capitalist.
But ultranationalists really put the nation,
and kind of the race that they view as indicative of the nation,
above all other concerns.
So yes, they were anti-communist,
they were anti-distribution of wealth - you know,
communists believe in no classes, as little private property as possible,
the German Workers Party didn't believe in that.
They were anti that.
But they were also anti unfettered capitalism,
especially capitalism that might get in the way of the nation's interests.
But, he becomes very impressed with them,
and he actually joins. He actually joins, as the 55th member.
So you can imagine, this is a very - at this point -
is a very, very small party.
But, then we fast-forward to 1920.
By 1920, the party leadership has taken note of Hitler.
They find that - they actually notice him when he's arguing with people,
and that other people are listening.
He's actually a really great orator.
And so they allow him to give more and more talks,
he has more and more authority.
And in order for the party to have more of an appeal,
especially to nationalists in general, they change their name.
They add to German Workers Party, they add
the "Nationalist Socialist.". . . "Nationalist Socialist German Workers Party."
DAP, German Workers Party, or the "NSDAP."
And if you pronounce "Nationalist" in German,
it sounds something like - and I'm going to butcher it right now -
"Nazionalist"- and so if you were going to shorten it,
they called themselves the "Nazis."
"They called themselves the Nazis . . . "
and Hitler actually designed the logo for the Nazis,
which included this symbol right over here, the swastika.
And the swastika is worth talking about,
because it is really this bizarre corruption of a very ancient symbol.
The - Hitler and the Nazis created this entire mythology
around the Germans being the descendants of the Aryans,
or being the purest example of the Aryans.
And the Aryans are the superior race that's responsible for all of civilization's advancement.
It was a delusion, because frankly, there was an ancient Aryan race,
but the best - the most indicative descendants of them
are frankly the Persians, or the Indians.
And actually, the swastika symbol here,
you might actually even see it at a Hindu temple.
It does not mean all of what we associated with Nazism now.
It actually is an ancient Hindu symbol of auspiciousness, of good luck,
but the Nazis usurped it.
But for them, this was a very important idea,
to create this mythology around race superiority,
and to even have a symbol like this,
as opposed to, say, something like a cross that's a religious symbol,
anyone can have a belief in say, Christianity,
and say "Hey, I'm a Christian,"
but the swastika, at least in Hitler's mind and the Nazis' mind,
was a racial symbol.
So it represented their superior race.
And obviously, if their race was superior,
a lot of what they considered the "ills" of Germany
were caused by being infiltrated with what they considered less pure races,
like Jews, and also infiltrated with less pure ideas, like the ideas of communism.
But Hitler gets more and more recognition with the party,
party membership continues to grow,
and by 1921, you have a - you have some disagreements in the party
some people threaten to splinter off,
and when Hitler says, "Hey look, if this is gonna happen, I'm gonna leave the party,"
they realize that he has so much value to the party
that the party would just dissolve if Hitler leaves.
And so they make him the chairman.
Hitler takes control. "Hitler is the chairman of the Nazi party. . . chairman."
And by this point, Hitler is well known or,
he's becoming more and more well known on the speaking circuit,
and we now have several thousand members of the Nazi Party.
Although it's still a fairly small group.
But then things start to get a lot worse in Weimar Germany.
You start having hyperinflation.
The government keeps printing more and more currency,
a lot of it in order - the economy's weak,
it's trying to pay reparations . . .
and so what you have here, this is actually one of the most famous cases of hyperinflation in world history.
You see the value of their currency,
it devalues from 1919 to 1923,
not by a factor of a thousand or a million or a billion,
but nearly a trillion!
So the currency becomes, frankly, worthless.
Then in 1922 - or, this - the hyperinflation is happening this entire time,
and you can see it accelerates through 1922 and then 1923,
but then in 1922 you have Mussolini comes to power in Italy,
and he comes to power through his March on -
"March on Rome." And Mussolini is a Fascist.
That's where the word comes from.
He's a member of the Fascist Party.
And the Fascists' ideas were very similar to the Nazis'.
It was all about extreme nationalism,
all about racial superiority, a very strong government.
And this is - Hitler finds quite inspiring.
You have the Weimar Republic is having difficulty, economic difficulty.
You have many other groups, including the Communists,
attempt their own coup détats. They fail.
But things are getting less and less stable.
Then you fast-forward to 1923.
The inflation is getting super bad,
about as bad as inflation can get.
The currency is worthless.
The economy is going into a tailspin.
And on top of that, because Germany can't pay the reparations to France any more,
France occupies the Ruhr.
So the Ruhr region is occupied - "occupied by France."
And you might remember from the terms of the Treaty of Versailles,
the Sahr region was already being occupied,
and all that coal was being shipped out to France.
The Ruhr region was another significant region of coal and steel production,
and now the French are fully occupying this,
they're forcing a lot of the civilians out of the region,
they're forcing a lot of the workers to work in the mines and the factories,
and then they're shipping all of that supply out to France.
So, this adds further -it further debilitates the economy,
but it's a huge humiliation.
The Treaty of Versailles, in the minds of Germans,
especially the minds of nationalists,
was bad enough, but now you have this huge humiliation by the French.
And this isn't just amongst the nationalists.
The general German population is getting very, very, very, very upset about this.
And so, this gives a lot of fuel to extreme nationalist groups like the Nazis.
So this fuels the Nazis, and based on the estimates I've seen,
entering into the year, they're starting to have in excess of 10,000 members,
starting to be several tens of thousands, and by -
as we get into the later part of the year,
we're approaching, I've seen estimates of,
40,000 to 55,000 members of the Nazi Party
And that's just formal members, and then on top of that
you might have non-members who are growing increasingly sympathetic.
And so what we'll see in the next video
at the end of 1923, Hitler sees this as his chance.
He's inspired by Mussolini, the economy's in a tailspin,
the Germans have been further humiliated by the French,
and they're starting to get - the Nazis in particular are starting to get quite popular.