Let's say I have a bag and in that bag I am going to put some green cubes
and in particular I am going to put 8 green cubes.
I am also going to put some spheres in that bag.
Let's say I am going to put 9 spheres and these are the green spheres
I am also going to put yellow cubes in that bag
Some yellow cubes. I am going to put 5 of those.
And I am also going to put some yellow spheres in this bag.
Yellow spheres. Let's say I will put in 7 of those.
I must take them all in this bag. And I am going to shake this bag and
then I am going to pour them out and I am going to look
at the first object that falls out of that bag.
What I want to think about in this video is:
What are the probabilities of getting different types of objects?
So for example what is the probability,
what is the probability of getting a cube?
A cube of any, of any color.
What is the probability of getting a cube?
Well to think about that, we should think about what -
Or this is one way to think about it. -
What are all of the equally likely possibilities that might pop out of the bag?
Well we have 8 plus 9 is 17, 17 plus 5 is 22.
22 + 7 is 29. So we have 29 objects. There are 29 objects in the bag.
Did I do that right? This is 14, yep, 29 objects.
So let's draw all of the possible objects.
And I will do this in, I will present this in this big area.
I will represent it as this big area right over here.
So these are all the possible objects.
There are 29 possible objects.
So there is 29 equal possibilities, for the outcome
of my experiment of seeing what pops out of that bag.
Assuming that it is equally likely for a cube or a sphere to pop out of that bag first.
And how many of them meet our constrain of being a cube?
Well I have 8 green cubes and I have 5 yellow cubes.
So there are a total of 13 cubes.
So let me draw that set of cubes.
So there is 13 cubes.
Let's draw it like this.
There are 13, 13 cubes.
This right here is the set of cubes.
And I am not drawing it exact, I am approximating.
This represents the set of all the cubes.
So the probability of getting a cube,
is the number of events that meet our criteria,
so there is 13 possible cubes that have an equal likely chance of popping out.
Over all of the possible equally likely events, which are 29.
That includes the cubes and the spheres.
Now let's ask a different question.
What is the probability of getting a yellow?
A yellow object. Either a cube or a sphere.
So once again, how many things meet our conditions here?
Well we have 5 plus 7; there is 12 yellows objects in the bag.
So we have 29 equally likely possibilities.
I will do that in the same color.
We have 29 equally likely possibilities, and of those,
12 meet our criteria. So let's, so let me draw 12 right over here.
I will do my best attempt. So that it looks something like...
A set of yellow objects, there are 12.
There are 12 objects that are yellow.
So the 12 that meet our conditions are 12 over all the possibilities, 29.
So probability of getting a cube is 13 over 29.
The probability of getting a yellow 12 29ths.
Now let's have something a little bit more interesting.
What is the probability...
What is the probability of getting a yellow cube?
So I will put in yellow. So we care about the color now.
So this thing is yellow.
What is the probability of getting a, as my son would say lellow,
What is the probability of getting a yellow cube?
Well, there is 29 equally likely possibilities.
There is 29 equally likely possibilities.
And of those 29 equally likely possibilities, 5 of those are yellow cubes.
Or lellow cubes.
5 of them. So the probability is 5 29ths.
And where would we see that on this Venn diagram that I have drawn?
And this Venn diagram, this is just a way to visualize the different probabilities.
And they become interesting when you start thinking about where sets overlap.
Or even where they don't overlap.
So here we are thinking about things that are members of the set yellow,
So there in this set, and they are cubes.
So this area right over here. That is the overlap of these two sets.
So this area right over here.
This represents things that are both yellow and a cube.
Because they are inside both circles.
So this right over here. Let me write it over here.
So there is 5 objects that are both yellow and,
yellow and cubes.
Now let's ask, and this is probably the most interesting thing to ask,
What is the probability,
What is the probability of getting something that is yellow or...
that is yellow or a cube?
A cube of any color.
The probability of getting something that is yellow or a cube of any color.
Well we still know that de denominator is going to be 29,
these are all of the equally likely possibilities that might jump out of the bag.
But what are the possibilities that meet our conditions?
Well, one way to think about it,
one way to think about it, is:
Well, probably, there is 12 things that would meet the yellow condition.
So that would be this entire circle right over here,
12 things that meet the yellow condition.
So this right over here is 12.
This is the number of yellow. That is 12.
And then to that, we can't just add the number of cubes.
Because if add the number of cubes,
we have already counted these 5.
With these 5 are counted as part of these 12.
One way to think about it is,
There are 7 yellow objects that are not cubes,
those are the spheres.
There are 5 yellow objects that are cubes.
And then, there are 8 cubes that are not yellow.
That is one way to think about it.
So when we counted these 12, the number of yellow,
we counted all of this.
So we can't just add the number of cubes to it,
because then we would count this middle part again.
So then we have to essentially count cubes,
the number of cubes, which is 13,
13, the number of cubes. Number of cubes.
Number of cubes.
I will have to subtract out, this middle section right over here.
Let me do this.
So, subtract out the middle section right over here.
So minus 5.
So this is the number, the number of yellow cubes.
It feels weird to write the word yellow in green.
The number of yellow cubes.
Or another way to think about it,
Or we can just do this math right here.
12 plus 13 minus 5 is what? It is... It is 20.
Did I do this right? 12 minus.... Yep it is 20.
So that is one way, you just get this is equal to 20 over 29.
But the more interesting thing than, even than the answer of the probability of getting that,
is expressing this in terms of the other probabilities
that we figured out earlier in the video.
So let's think about this a little bit.
We can rewrite this fraction right over here,
We can rewrite this as: 12/29, plus 13/29, minus 5/29.
And this was the number of yellow over the total possibilities.
So this right over here was the probability of getting a yellow.
And this right over here was the number of cubes over the total possibilities.
So this is plus the probability of getting, of getting a cube.
The probability of getting a cube.
And this right over here was the number of yellow cubes over the total possibilities.
So this right over here was
minus the probability of yellow and, and a cube.
And I can write it that way.
The probability of yellow, alright, yellow in yellow,
yellow and, yellow and getting a cube.
Yellow and getting a cube.
So, and what we have just here,
and you can play with the numbers,
the numbers I just used as an example right here.
To make things a little more concrete.
But you can see this is a generalisable thing.
If we have the probability of one condition or a number of conditions.
Let me rewrite it.
The probability, and I will just write a little bit more generally here.
This gives us an interesting idea.
The probability of getting one condition,
of an object being a member of set A, or, or a member of set B,
is equal to the probability that it is a member of set A,
plus the probability that it is a member of set B,
minus the probability that it is a member of both.
This is a really useful result,
and I think it is sometimes called like the addition rule of probability.
But I want to show you it is a completely common sense thing.
The reason why you can't just add these two probabilities,
is because they might have some overlap,
there is a probability of getting both.
And if you just added both of these,
you would be double counting that overlap.
Which we have already seen earlier in this video.
So you have to subtract one version of the overlap out,
so you are not double counting it.
And I will throw one other idea.
Sometimes you have possibilities that have no overlap.
So let's say this is a set of all possibilities.
This is the set of all possibilities.
And let's say this is the set that meets condition A.
And let's, this is, let me do this in a different color.
And let's say this is the set that meets condition B.
So in this situation there is no overlap.
There is no way; nothing is a member of both set A and B.
So in this situation, the probability of A and B is 0.
There is no overlap.
And these type of conditions, or these two events,
are called mutually exclusive.
Mutually Exclusive.
So if events are mutually exclusive that means
that they both cannot happen at the same time.
It is... There is no event that meets both of these conditions.
And if things are mutually exclusive,
then you can't say the probability of A or B is a probability of A plus B.
Because this thing is zero.
But if things are not mutually exclusive,
you would have to subtract out the overlap.
And the easiest, probably the best to think about it,
is to just always realize that you have to subtract out the overlap,
and obviously if something is mutually exclusive,
The probability of getting A and B is going to be 0.
Let's say I have a bag and in that bag I am going to put some green cubes