The first step to understanding the disease that we call asthma is to understand how air enters and leaves the lungs in both healthy individuals and individuals that are suffering from asthma.So lets just review that.
You might already know that air enters the lungs via the mouth and nose.That's the first step.
And the it passes through a set of tubes.
The main one, that enters the lungs is called the trachea.I'll write it over here.
And the trachea then branches to two mainstem bronchi.I'll write that down here.
And the those bronchi branch further to bronchioles.And those bronchioles are really big players in the disease that we call asthma.
So remember that name because it is very important when we're talking about asthma.
These are the bronchioles.
Cause this is where all the action is when we're exploring asthma
Okey, now this is also a very important point.The trachea is held open by rings of cartilage.
And you can actually feel those rings of cartilage if you rub your hand gently across the front of your throat.
You'll feel kind some of breaches and those are rings of cartilage that hold both the trachea and the mainstem bronchi
These rings of cartilage holds these tubes basically at a constant size or a constant diameter so that these guys don't change much in size.
Now, the bronchioles don't have that reinforcement and they are actually designed to change size according to the needs of the person breathing in and out.
So let's look at how that happens
If i draw the lungs of this person in here and i'm gonna draw them a bit bigger than they actually would be.
And the lungs are actually surrounded by something called a pleural sack.
And the pleural sack is not really a sack, it's a potential space so that means it could be filled with something,
but it's actually in a healthy person just two membranes that are folded in on themselves and those membranes have a little bit of fluid inside of them.
So only in bad situations like for example if a person gets stabbed or if they get in an car accident and the break a rib
and that perforates this pleural cavity,that's when this potential space could become a real space.
The function of the pleural cavity is to kind of reduce friction between the rib cage.
And the rib cage is made out of bones that protect the lungs.
I'll just draw a few of them in here.
I'm not drawing these all the way around, they actually do come all the way around and join at the sternum
in the mid-line, at least the upper ribs do
There are some floating ribs down below but we'll just draw them in half way
so we can see what's going on in the lungs
And the pleural cavity reduces the friction as the lungs move back and forth
across these ribs.But what the pleural cavity does is, it keeps the
lungs tightly opposed or snugly fitting up against the rib cage
while still allowing them to move freely back and forth.
So let's now look at what causes for example a person to draw air into tjeir lungs.
And we'll start by looking at inhalation at rest.
So when you're quietly sitting on your sofa there's a very important
dome-shaped muscle.And the pleural cavity also keeps the ribs tightly in contact
or tightly in a position with this muscle called the diaphragm
And this muscle is in its relaxed form a dome-shaped muscle and at rest when we wanna
draw air into our lungs, this muscle contracts.
And it doesn't become flat, it just becomes less dome-shaped.
And because it becomes less dome-shaped so it moves down from its original position
the result is that the volume of the thoracic cavity increases
And when the volume increases in a space the pressure decreases
kind of like a vacuum
and the result is that air is going to enter the mouth and pass through these tubes
to enter the lungs in order to equalize the pressure on the outside
the atmospheric pressure
with the pressure on the inside of the lungs
That's inhalation at rest.
And we're using a muscle called the
diaphragm
What about when we're doing physical activity
So I'll just write exercise here
Now, during exercise we need to recrute other muscles
to help us get air in faster
And the muscles that we use to do that are called
external intercostals.
As the name would suggest they attach on the external surface of the ribs in between
the ribs and they pull the rib cage upward and outward
These are the external intercostals
So, again by doing this they basically pull the rib cage up and out and
they help increase the volume of the thoracic cavity
thereby draw even more air in to equalize the pressure on the inside and the outside
Another set of muscles that are used during exercise
are the muscles of the neck.
So we have a bone called the clavicle, you might know it as the collarbone
and the clavicle is actually attached to the head by muscles
sternocleidomastoid is one of them, but we'll just write muscles of the neck
And the muscles of the neck
When they contract what they do is they pull the clavicle upward
and that also helps to increase the volume and get more air in
to this thoracic cavity
So let's now look at what happens when we want to exhale
So this is an interesting thing
Exhalation at rest, when you're sitting on that sofa and you've just
without even thinking about you've taken a breath in