This video here is a
groundbreaking video
for multiple reasons.
One, I'm going to introduce you
to the variance of a sample,
which is interesting
it in its own right.
And I'm attempting to
record this video in HD.
And hopefully you can see
it bigger and clearer
than ever before.
But we'll see how
all of that goes.
So this is a bit of an
experiment, so bear with me.
But so, just before we go into
the variance of a sample, I
think it's instructive to
review the variance
of a population.
And we can compare
their formulas.
The variance of a population--
And it's this greek
letter sigma.
Lowercase sigma squared.
That means variance.
I know it's weird that
a variable already
has a square in it.
You're not squaring
the variable.
This is the variable.
Sigma squared mean variance.
Actually, let me
write that down.
That equals variance.
And that is equal to-- You
take each data point-- And
we'll call them x sub i.
You take each data of point,
find out how far it is from the
mean of the population, you
square it, and then you take
the average of all of those.
So you take the average,
you sum them all up.
You go from i is equal to 1.
So from the first point, all
the way to the nth point.
And then, to average,
you sum them all up and
then you divide by n.
So the variance is the average
of these squared distances
of each point from the mean.
And just to give you the
intuition again, it essentially
says, on average, roughly how
far away are each of the
points from the middle.
That's the best way to
think about the variance.
Now what if we're
dealing-- This was for
a population, right?
And we said if we wanted to
figure out the variance of
men's heights in the country,
it'd be very hard to
figure out the variance
for the population.
You would have to go and,
essentially, measure
everyone's height.
250 million people.
Or what if it's for some
population where it's just
completely impossible to
have the data or some
random variable.
And we'll go more
into that later.
So a lot of times you actually
want to estimate this variance
by taking the variance
of a sample.
Same way that you could never
get the mean of a population,
but maybe you want to estimate
it by getting the
mean of a sample.
And we learned that
in that first video.
If this is-- If that's
the whole population.
That's millions of data points,
or even data points in the
future that you'll never be
able to get because it's
a random variable.
So this is the population.
You might just want to estimate
things by looking at a sample.
And this is actually what
most of inferential
statistics is all about.
Figuring out descriptive
statistics about the sample
and make inferences
about the population.
Let me try this drug on 100
people and if it seems to have
statistically significant
results, this drug will
probably work on the
population as a whole.
So that's what it's all about.
So it's really important to
understand this notion of a
sample versus a population.
And being able to find
statistics on a sample that,
for the most part, can describe
the population or help us
estimate, they call it,
parameters for the population.
So what's the mean of a-- Let
me rewrite these definitions.
What's the mean
of a population?
I'll do that purple.
Purple for population.
The mean of a population.
You just take each of the data
points in the population, x i.
You sum them up.
You start with the first data
point and you go all the
way to the nth data point.
And you divide by n.
You sum them all up
and divide by n.
That's the mean.
So then you plug it
into this formula.
And you can see how far each
point is from that central
point, from that mean.
And you get the variance.
Now what happens if we
do it for a sample?
Well, if we want to estimate
the mean of a population by
somehow calculating a mean for
a sample, the best thing I can
think of-- And really these are
kind of engineered formulas.
These are human beings saying,
well what is the best
way to sample it?
Well all we can do is really
take an average of our sample.
And that's the sample mean.
And we learned in the first
video that that notation--
The formula is almost
identical of this.
It's just the
notation's different.
Instead of writing mu, you
write x with a line over it.
Sample mean is equal to-- Once
again, you take each of the
data points now in the sample,
not in the whole population.
You sum them up from the
first one and then to
the nth one, right?
They're saying that there are
n data points in this sample.
And then you divide it by the
number of data points you have.
Fair enough.
It's really the same formula.
The way I took the mean of a
population, I said, well, if I
just have a sample, let me just
take the mean the same way.
And it's probably a good
estimate of the mean
of the population.
Now it gets interesting when
we talk about variance.
So your natural reaction is
OK, I have this sample.
If I want to estimate the
variance of the population, why
don't I just apply this same
formula essentially
to the sample?
So I could say-- And this is
actually a sample variance.
They use the formula s squared.
So sigma is kind of the greek
letter equivalent of s.
So now when we're dealing
with the sample, we
just write the s there.
So this is sample variance.
Let me write that down.
Sample variance.
This is-- So we might just say,
well maybe a good way to take
the sample variance is
do it the same way.
Let's take the distance of each
of the points in the sample.
Find out how far it is
from our sample mean.
Here we used the population
mean, but now we'll just use
the sample mean because
that's all we can have.
We don't know what the
population mean is
without looking at the
whole population.
Take the square of that.
That makes it positive and
it has other properties,
which we'll go over later.
And then take the average of
all of these squared distances.
So you take it from--
You sum them all up.
And there's n of them
to some up, right?
Lowercase n.
And you divide by lowercase n.
And you say, well this
is a good estimate.
Well whatever this variance is,
that might be a good estimate
for the population whole.
Actually this is what some
people often refer to when they
talk about sample variance.
And sometimes it'll actually
be referred to as this.
They'll put a little
lowercase n there.
And the reason why they do that
is because we divided by n.
And you say, Sal what's
the problem here?
And the problem-- And I'll give
you the intuition because this
is actually something that
used to boggle my mind.
And I'm still frankly
struggling with the
intuition behind it.
Well I have the intuition, but
more of kind of rigorously
proving it to myself that
this is definitely the case.
But think about this.
If I have a bunch of
numbers, and I'll draw
a number line here.
If I draw a number line here--
So let's say you know that--
And let's say I have a bunch
of numbers in my population.
So let's say-- I'm just going
to randomly put a bunch
numbers in my population.
And the ones to the right
are bigger than the
ones to the left.
And if I were to take a sample
of them, maybe I take--
The sample, it's random.
You actually want to
take a random sample.
You don't want to be
skewed in any way.
So maybe I take this one,
this one, this one,
and that one, right?
And then if I were to take the
mean of that number, that
number, that number,
that number.
It will be someplace
in the middle.
It might be someplace
over there.
And then if I wanted to figure
out the sample variance using
this formula, I'd say OK this
distance squared plus this
distance squared plus that
distance squared and
average them all out.
And then I would
get this number.
And that probably would be a
pretty good approximation for
the variance of this
entire population.
The population of the mean
is probably going to
be-- I don't know.
It might be pretty
close to this.
If we actually took all of the
data points and averaged them,
maybe they're like
here someplace.
And then if you figure out the
variance, it probably would be
pretty close to the average of
all of these lines, right?
All of the sample variance
distances, right?
Fair enough.
So you say, hey Sal.
This looks pretty good now.
But there's one little catch.
What if-- There's always a
probability that instead of
picking these kind of fairly
well-distributed numbers in my
sample, what if I happen to
pick this number, this number,
and that number as my-- and
let's say that number
as my sample?
Well whatever your sample
is, your sample mean is
always going to be in
the middle of it, right?
So in this case, your sample
mean might be right here.
So all of these numbers, you
might say OK this number is not
too far from that number, that
number's not too far, and then
that number's not too far.
So your sample variance, when
you do it this way, might
turn out a little bit low.
Because all of these numbers,
they're pretty-- they're,
almost by definition, going to
be pretty close to the
mean of each other.
But in this case, your sample
is kind of skewed and the
actual mean of the population
is out here someplace.
So the actual variance of the
sample, if you had actually
known the mean-- I know this
is all a little confusing.
If you had actually known
the mean, you would
have said oh wow.
You would have found these
distances, which would
have been a lot more.
The whole point of what I'm
saying is, when you take a
sample, there's some chance
that your sample mean is pretty
close to the population
mean, right?
Maybe your sample mean is
here and your population
mean is here.
And then this formula will
probably work out pretty well,
at least given your sample data
points and figuring out
what the variance is.
But there's a reasonable chance
that your sample mean-- Your
sample is always going to be
within your data sample, right?
It's always going to be the
center of your data sample.
But it's completely possible
that the population mean is
outside of your data sample.
It might have just been you
just happen to pick ones
that don't contain the
actual population mean.
And then this sample variance
calculated this way will
actually underestimate the
actual population
variance, right?
Because they're always going to
be closer to their own mean
than they are to the
population mean.
And if you're understanding,
frankly, even like 10%
of this, you are a very
advanced statistics student.
But I'm saying all of this to
just give you, hopefully, some
intuition to realize that this
will often underestimate.
This formula will often
underestimate the actual
population variance.
And there's a formula, and
this is actually proven more
rigorously than I will do it,
that is considered to be a
better, or they'll call it an
unbiased, estimate of the
population variance.
Or the unbiased
sample variance.
And sometimes it's just denoted
by the s squared again.
Sometimes it's denoted by
this s n minus 1 squared.
And I'll show you why.
It's almost the same thing.
You take each of the data
points, figure out how far they
are from the sample mean.
You square them.
And then you take the average
of those squared, except
for one slight difference.
i equals 1 to i equals n.
Instead of dividing by n,
you divide by a slightly
smaller number.
You divide by n minus 1.
So when you divide my n minus
1 instead of dividing by
n, you're going to get a
slightly larger number here.
And it turns out that
this is actually a
much better estimate.
And one day I'm going to write
a computer program to at least
prove it to myself
experimentally that this is a
better estimate of the
population variance.
And you would calculate
it the same way.
You just divide by n minus 1.
The other way to think about
it-- And actually, no.
I'm all out of time.
I'll leave you there now.
And then in the next video,
we'll do a couple of
calculations just so you
don't get too overwhelmed
with these ideas.
Because we're getting a
little bit abstract.
See you in the next video.