Determine whether the points on this graph represent a function.
Now just as a refresher a function is
really just an association between members of a set that we call
the domain and members of a set that we call a range.
So if I take any member of the domain, lets call that x, and I give it to the function,
the function should tell me
what member of my range is that associated with it.
So it should point to some other value. This is a function.
It would not be a function if it says "Well, it could point to y
or
it could point to z.
Or maybe it could point to e.
Or whatever else. This would not be a function.
Because over here, so this right over here is not a function. Because it's not clear if you
input x, what member of the range are you going to get?