Now that we've seen that as we take i to higher and higher powers it cycles between 1, i, negative 1, negative i, then
back to 1, i, negative 1 and negative i. I wanna see if we can tackle some -- I guess you could call them
trickier problems -- and you right see them in this surface and they are also a kind of fun to do them
and realise that you can use this the fact that I the powers of I cycle through these values you can use this
to really, on the back of an envelop, take arbitrarily high powers of i. So let's try, just for fun,
let's see what i to one hundredth power is and the realisation
here is that 100 is a mutiple of 4, so you could
say this is the same thing as i to the, i to the 4 times 25th power and this is the same thing,
just from our exponent properties i to the 4th power raised to the 25th power, right, if you have
something raised on an exponent and that is raised to an exponent that's the same
thing as multiplying the two exponents and we know that i to the 4th, that's pretty
straightforward; i to the 4th is just 1, i to the 4th is 1 so this is 1 so this is equal to
the 1 to the 25th power which is just equal to, just equal to 1. So once again we use
this kind of cycling ability of i when it takes its powers to figure out very high
exponent of i. Now let's say we try something a little bit stranger, lets try i to the,
let's try it i to the five hundred and first power. Now in this situation 501 is not a
multiple of 4 so you can't just do that simply but what you could do is you could write
this is a product of two numbers; one that is a multiple, one that is i to a multiple
of 4th power and then one that isn't, also you could rewrite this: 500 is, is a multiple of
4, so you could write this is i to the five hundredth power, i to the five hundredth
power, times i to the first power, right? you have same base, when you multiply
them you can add exponents, so this is i to the five hundred and first power. And we
know that this is the same thing as i to ... i to five hundred power is the same thing as i to
the fourth power four times what? Four times one hundred and twenty-five is 500, so
that's this part right over here: i to the 500 is the same thing as i to the 4th to the
125th power and then that times i to the first power, times i to the first. Well i to the
4th is 1, 1 to the 125th power is just going to be 1, this whole thing is 1 and so we
are just left with, we are just left with i to the first, so this is going to be equal to i. So
it seems really daunting problem, something that you have to sit and do all day
but you can use the cycling result; i to the 500 is just going to be 1 and so i to the
501 is just going to be i just times that. So i to any multiple of 4 -- let me write this
generally -- so if you have i to any multiple of 4, so this right over here is, well we'll just
restrict k to be non negative right now; k is greater or equal to zero
so if we have i to any mutiple of 4 right over here we are going to get, we are going to get
1 because this is the same thing as i to the fourth power to the kth power and
that is the same thing as 1 to the kth power which is clearly equal to 1 and if we have
anything else, if we have i to the fourth k plus 1 power or plus 2 power we can then just
do this technique right over here. So let's try with a few more problems, just to
make it clear that you can really really arbitrarily crazy things. So let's take i to the
seven thousand three hundred and twenty-first power. Now we just have to figure out
-- this is going to be some multiple of 4 plus something else, so to do that, well you
could just do that by sight 7320 is dividable by 4, you can verify that by hand and then you have one left
over also this is going to be i to the 7320 times i to the first power, this is a multiple
of 4 this right here is just a multiple of 4, I know that because any 100 is a multiple of
4, any 1000 is a multiple of 4 and any 100 is a multiple of 4 and the 20 is a multiple of
4 and so this right over here simplified to 1... sorry, that's not ??? to the ith power either the first power, 7321 is 7320 plus
1 and so this part right over here is going to simplify 1 and its going to be left
with i to the first power or just i. Let's do another one. i to the, i to the ninety, ninety,
ninety, let me try something interesting, i to the ninety-ninth, i to the ninety-ninth power.
So once again, what's the highest multiple of 4 that is less than 99? It is 96, it is 96,
so this is same thing as the i to the 96th power times i to the 3th power, right? If you
multiply these same base, add the exponent, you'll get i to the 99th power, i to the
96th power, so this is a multiple of 4, this is i to the 4th and then that to the 16th
power, so that's just 1 in the 16, so this is just 1 and then you'll just lift with i to the
third power and you could either remember that i to the 3th power is equal to... you
could remember its equal to negative i or if you forget that you could just say look
this is just samething as i squared times i, this is equal to i squared times i, i
squared by definition is equal to negative 1 so you have negative 1 times i, is equal
to i, is equal to negative i. Let me do one more, just for, just for the fun of it. Let's take i
to the 38th power. Well once again this is equal to the i to the 36th times i squared, I'm
doing i to the 36th power just largest multiple 4 that goes into 38 what's left over is 2
this simplifies to 1 and I'm just left with i squared which is equal to negative 1.