Determine the sine of 135 degrees the cosine of 135 degrees and teh tangent of 135 degrees so lets start off
just by drawing a 135 degree angle in standard position so to do that let me draw some axis and I'll
put a unit circle on that axis that's about as good as I can hand draw
the unit circle and let me mark this up I'll mark it up a little bit neater
so this is when x is equal to one and this is when y
is equal to one. this is when y is equal to
negitive no excuse me this is when x is equal to negative onw
and this is when y is equal to negitive one and the only reason why I had to draw
kind of a dotted line is that I find it easier to draw a dotted line we can fill it
in and it actually should be a filled in line
so there you go
now lets draw a 135 degree angle in standard position so lets sit the vertex of that angle
at the origin, let me do this in a new color so this is going to sit at the origin
the initial side is going to go along the positive x-axis
just like that draw it as a ray. and then the terminal side since it's a positive
135 degrees we're going to go in a counterclockwise
direction if we go straight up to the y axis that gives us
90 degrees we have to get to 135 so we have to go another 45
so we have to go another 45 it takes us about right about
half way or exactly half way
through the second quadrant so it takes us right over there.
so that is 135 degree angle
now we know from our
the unit circle definition of trig function that the intersection between
the terminal side and the unit circle is going to have some coordinates
(x,y) we know from the unit circle definition
that x is equal to the cosine
of 135 degrees in this case and y
is going to equal the sine of 135 degrees
and we know that y over x is going to be
equal to the tangent of 135 degrees
so if we can figure out this intersection point the x and y coordinates we've essintially figured out
this entire problem.
and there is a little bit of a hint, what i'm going to do is create a triangle here and this really
does show the connection that show's that the unit circle definition is really just an extention
of the traditional soh cah toa right trainagle definition so what i'm going to do
is drop, i'm gonna do is create a right triangle
let me do it in a different color a color different from
the unit circle so i'm going to drop a right triangle here
that's 90 degrees this magenta line has gone straight down
and if we can figure out the base
if we can figure out this distance, let me do it in a different color here, if we can figure out this blue distance
we know that it's in the negative direction so if this blue distance
is what ever it might be, the negative value of that
because we're going to the left of the origin is going to be our x coordinate and whatever
this height is in magenta that's going to be out y coordinate do you see it right over here so the x coordinate
is where ever this blue distance takes us to the left
the height in magenta is out y coordinate
so lets think about what we know about this triangle
right over here
so my first question to you is what is the
length of the hypotenuse of this triangle
right over here the one that is formed between these points the origin
the intersection between the unit circle and the terminal side of the angle and where this
and where this vertical line intersects the x-axis so these three points
right over here what is the hypotenuse formed by these three points
Well this hypotenuse right over here
this distance this distance right over here it is a radius
it is a length of the radius of the unit circle and by definition the unit cirle has a
radius of length one so the hypotenuse here has length
has length one. Now my second question
to you is can you figure out the angles of this triangle
and in particular can you figure out the measure
can you figure out the measure of this orange angle
right over there? Well let's think about it.
It is essintally or it deffinitely is
suplementary to the 135 degrees. 135 plus this orange
angle must be equal to 180 degrees
so 180 minus 135 gives us
45, 45 degrees.
and this is often refered to as the reference angle. It
is that positive angle
between the terminal side of an angle whether that
135 degree angle and the x-axis.
Now my next question to you
is can you figure out the last angle in this triangle? We know that is one is a right angle we know that this one is 45
degrees can you figure out what this top angle is right over here.
Well we know that the angles in a triangle
have to add up to 180 degrees
so if you call this angle theta, if you call that angle theta we know that theta
plus 45 degrees plus 90 degrees
must add up to 180 degrees
or theta plus 135 must add up to
180 so if you subtract 135 from both sides you get that
theta is equal to 45 degrees so this is also equal to 45 degrees.
let me zoom in
on this triangle because it
is getting a little bit messy so let me zoomin
so this is the exact same triangle i'm just going to blow it up and I'm going to try to use the exact same colors.
So this is just a zoomed in version of the same triangle this right over here
is a right angle we know that the hypotenuse has length
one it's opposite the right angle, we know that this
angle right over here is 45 degrees
and we know that this angle up here is 45 degrees
so my next question to you is can we figure out
the length of these sides?
and the first thing, well i'll let you think about that for a second.
The first thing you might realize from your traditional geometry
is that this a triangle that has two angles that are the same
and if the two angles are the same the two sides here are going to be the same aswell
so we know from our geometry that this side is equal to that side.
some times it's easier to visualize if you have a triangle like this and these two base angles
are congruent then you know that these two sides are congruent this is one of the fundamental things
that we learned in geometry, this is just reoriented in a different way.
So we know those those two sides are going to be the same thing.
and what we're eventually going to realize
that triangles like this 45 45 90 triangles we're going to use the pythagorian
theorem this time but, these are good triangles in general to know the ratio
you know that the two sides are going to be equal and that the ratio between them and the hypotenuse
but we'll figure it out this time. So we can use the Pythagorian
Theorem, we can call that x actually let me not call them x