I've written the same subtraction problem twice.
Here we see we're subtracting 172 from 629. And all I did here is I expanded out the numbers.
I wrote 629 as 600 plus 20 plus 9 and I rewrote a 172. The 1 is one hundred (so that's there),
this is 7 tens, it's in the tens place so it's 70. And then the 2 is two ones so it just represents 2.
And we will see why this is useful in a second.
So let's just start subtracting. We will start with the ones place.
So we have 9 minus 2, well that's clearly just 7.
And over here we can also say: "Well, 9 minus 2 (we have the subtraction out front), that is going to be 7."
Pretty straightforward. But then something interesting happens when we get to the tens place.
We're going to try to subtract 2 minus 7 or we're going to subtract 7 from 2.
And we haven't learned yet how to do things like negative numbers (which we'll learn in the future) so we have a problem.
How do you subtract a larger number from a smaller number?
Well, luckily we have something in our toolkit called Regrouping, sometimes called Borrowing.
And that's why this is valuable. When we're trying to subtract the 7 from the 2, we're really trying to subtract this 70 from this 20.
Well, we can't subtract the 70 from the 20 but we have other value in the number.
We have value in the hundreds place.
So why don't we take a hundred from the 600 so that becomes 500 and give that hundred to the tens place?
If we give that hundred to the tens place, what is a 100 plus 20?
Well, it's going to be 120.
So all I did: I didn't change the value of 629. I took a hundred from the hundreds place and I gave it to the tens place.
Notice: 500 plus 120 plus 9 is still 629. We haven't changed the value.
So how would we do that right over here?
Well if we take a hundred from the hundreds place, this 6 hundred becomes a 5... 5 hundred.
And we give that hundred to the tens place, it's going to be 10 hundreds.
So this will now become a 12.
But notice, this 12 in the tens place represents 12 tens or a 120.
So this is just another way of representing what we've done here.
There's no magic here. This is often called Borrowing.
Well, you say: "Hey, I took a 1 from the 6 and I gave it to the 2 but wait, why has this 2 become a 12? Why was I able to add 10?"
Well, you've added 10 tens or a hundred.
You took a hundred from here so 6 hundred became 5 hundred, and then 20 became a hundred and 20.
But now we're ready to subtract.
12 tens minus 7 tens is 5 tens. Or you could say a 120 minus 70 is 50.
And then finally you have the hundreds place.
5 minus 1 is equal to 4. But that's really 500 minus 100 is equal to 400.
And so you get 457 which is the same thing as 400 plus 50 plus 7.