So when you were swimming or showering,
have you ever wondered
why your cells don't fill up with water?
Or why the substances in your cells
don't leak into the pool?
We actually have a very important structure
that prevents this from happening.
This is what we call the cell membrane.
The cell membrane is what's on the outside of a cell.
If we have a very basic picture of a cell here
with a little nucleus on the inside,
this pink outside layer is what we call the cell membrane.
The cell membrane can protect the cell
from the outside environment
and it can determine
what can enter and leave the cell.
This is a property that we call 'semi-permeability'.
It is somewhat permeable.
Some things can enter while other things cannot.
This is such an important part of the cell
because it is one of the reasons why
we can actually survive in the world.
So, what actually makes up this structure?
Well, the main building blocks of the cell membrane
are what we call "phospholipids".
There are other substances
that make up the cell membrane,
but the most important building blocks are phospholipids.
Phospholipids have three major components.
The first is a phosphate head group.
The second is a glycerol backbone.
The third are two fatty acid tails.
The way we draw this is
to draw the phosphate head like a head
and the two fatty acid tails like strings from a balloon.
The way I remember this is that
the phospholipid looks like a balloon,
but with two strings instead of one.
Now, where's our glycerol backbone?
Well, our glycerol backbone is actually
what it sounds like.
It holds the fatty acid tails to the phosphate head.
It's the backbone of this molecule.
So it's usually not drawn in the picture,
but just remember that it's there,
and that it holds the two fatty acids tails
to the phosphate head.
So this structure actually has an interesting property.
The head group is actually 'hydrophilic', or polar.
'Hydrophilic' means that it's water-loving.
The phosphate head group will do whatever it can
to get to water. It loves water.
But these fatty acid tails,
because they're long carbon chains,
are 'hydrophobic'.
I remember hydrophobic because phobia means fearing.
Hydro means water, so hydrophobic means water-fearing.
These two fatty acids will do whatever
they can to get away from water.
A molecule that has both of these things together
it what we call an 'amphipathic' molecule.
It means that the molecule has hydrophilic and hydrophobic sections.
So, in water, what would this do?
Let's say we put a ton of these molecules in water.
Once in water, the hydrophobic heads
want to be as close to water as possible,
but the tails don't.
So what will happen is these phosphate groups
will cluster together,
while the tails will try to shield themselves from water.
Since this is a substance that's in water,
water is going to be down below too,
so this will actually form a really unique structure,
because the fatty tails will start grouping like this.
The phospholipids will be upside down
so that the phosphate head groups can be close to water
while this inside section can be away from water.
This is what we call a phospholipid bilayer.
This is the basic structure of a cell membrane.
Like we mentioned, this inside part is hydrophobic.
Now we have this structure that looks like this,
which we call a phospholipid bilayer,
or lipid bilayer for short.
But doesn't this side section also interact with water?
How can this structure be like this if this section
still touches water?
The fatty acids don't want to touch water.
What actually happens is that the structure of a circle forms.
Like this.
Now, this is a fairly crudely drawn picture,
but in a cell the lipid bilayer is pretty thin
compared to the entire cell,
so you'll notice that this water here
isn't a problem anymore.
In our cells, water can be on the inside and outside.
No matter where this cell membrane touches water,
only the phosphate head groups will touch.
Moving on to a new picture,
we mentioned before that the cell membrane is semi-permeable.
We're going to explore that a little bit more.
So I've pre-drawn a cell membrane.
As we mentioned, the cell membrane
is actually a sphere that surrounds our cell.
For the sake of this lesson,
we're going to draw it out in a straight line.
We're going to say that the top side is the outside,
or the extracellular space,
and the bottom can be the inside,
or the intracellular space.
So, you'll notice that the cell membrane
has these phospholipids packed closely together.
Usually only small molecules can pass through.
Another property of the cell membrane
that we've discussed is that this inside section [with the tails]
is really hydrophobic.
Generally only small non-polar molecules
can pass through the cell membrane.
This is what we call "passive diffusion".
So what is a good example of a small non-polar molecule?
Well, the most common type is gases.
Things like O2 or CO2 for example.
These are things that surround us every day,
and our cell, in a sense,
breathes these molecules in and out.
So gases can easily pass through the cell membrane
and they pass through very quickly.
They are small and non-polar.
So, what else does the cell interact with?
The most common thing is water.
Water is actually a pretty small molecule and it's polar.
Something else that's similar to water is ethanol.
This is the type of alcohol that we drink.
So how does this molecule interact with the cell membrane?
Well, we've said that the cell membrane likes small molecules.
So these can pass through the cell membrane.
But the cell membrane prefers non-polar molecules.
So these will pass through really slowly.
They can pass through
because they're so tiny that they sneak by.
But this happens pretty slowly
because the hydrophobic region still
doesn't like having water in there.
So, if we have small, polar molecules,
what about something that is large
but nonpolar, like benzene?
Benzene can actually pass through the cell membrane.
Even though it's large, it's non-polar,
so it's going to get along well with the hydrophobic region,
but it's going to pass through very slowly.
As a fun fact, benzene used to be used
in labs for researchers to wash their hands.
Scientists found out that
benzene can pass through our skin and harm us.
What about something that is large and polar?
Well, a molecule like this might be sugar, or glucose.
Glucose cannot pass through the cell membrane.
It's large and it's polar;
it's the complete opposite to what
the cell membrane wants to let through.
So glucose will have to be absorbed
by our cells through other means,
but it cannot pass through the cell membrane.
What about charged molecules?
These are also all over the place.
What's an example of a charged molecule?
Something like a chloride ion, a sodium ion,
or any sort of ion.
A common example of charged molecules are amino acids.
Since these are charged, they are also polar
and cannot pass through.
In summary, our cell membrane
protects our cell
and determines what enters and leaves,
a property that we call semi-permeability.
This cell membrane is made up of
a bunch of phospholipids put together.
Since our cell membrane has a large hydrophobic region,
it prefers non-polar molecules,
and since these phospholipids are packed so closely,
the cell membrane also prefers small molecules to pass through.
The cell membrane is semi-permeable,
allowing generally small and non-polar
molecules to pass through.