The Eastern and Western fronts,
even though they were fronts of the same war,
were very different in character.
A lot of it came out of the fact of who was fighting it
and especially how big the actual fronts were.
The Western front, which was generally this region,
was a much smaller front than the Eastern front.
The Eastern front was essentially this entire region.
And because of that, trench warfare did not become
a major factor on the Eastern front.
In fact, it was fairly useless on the Eastern front.
If you imagine trying to dig a bunch of trenches --
Trenches are a huge advantage for the defending army,
as long as you can block off the entire region with trenches.
So over here, you can't go around the trenches.
If you want to make some ground
an attacking army has to cross the trenches,
and because you now have machine guns
the defending soldiers could sit behind their trenches
and mow down the attacking army, very easily.
And that is what caused the Western front,
especially after the Schlieffen plan was not executed
as quickly as possible, it turned into a stalemate.
So, you just had a hugely defensive stalemate.
Because both parties had their trenches,
it was hugely advantageous for the defending side.
On the Eastern front, you had this huge front,
you couldn't have--
they didn't have enough people
to dig trenches across this entire front.
And you can imagine, if you tried to dig a trench,
but you weren't able to cover the entire front,
then the attacking army doesn't have to storm your trench,
they could just go around your trench.
And because trench warfare was not a significant factor,
not anywhere near as much a factor on the Eastern front,
it was a much more fluid front.
You had offensives and counter-offensives between
the Germans and Austrians on one side,
and the Russians on the other.
Now, the other factor,
- and this was mainly with Russia as a variable -
the other factor was what was going on in Russia.
Russia had several things going for it:
mainly it had a huge standing army
even before the war
and it was able to amass even more.
So it had a huge army.
But what was going against it --
- and this is why they eventually
had to get into a very unfavorable treaty
with the Central Powers
near the end of the war -
is that it had huge internal problems.
I am not just talking about the Military,
I am talking about the entire Empire.
It was arguably due to the
economic and the human cost of the war
but as we enter into 1917,
you first have the February Revolution;
Czar Nicolas II has to abdicate the throne
because of the riots that are going on
because of the unhappiness,
the unease,
of people going hungry
the morale of the troops going down,
And on top of that, Russian military,
even though it had a huge army
at the beginning of the war,
the Russian industry was not ready
to fully supply the army
as good as the German army was.
And on top of that,
it had communication problems
and in the beginning phases
of the Eastern Front,
it even had issues
coördinating its actual armies.
We will cover this in much more depth
in a future video.
But what we will see is:
Western Front, Schlieffen plan not executed
as fast as possible,
ends up in a stalemate --
This did allow the Germans
to bring some of their troops
back to the Eastern front
to fight the Russians.
This goes back and forth
as we will see,
but once you enter into 1917,
you have a revolution in Russia:
first the February Revolution
- Czar Nicolas has to abdicate -
and then later that year,
the Bolsheviks overthrow the interim governement.
You now have Communist Russia
and the Bolshevik military are in no mood
to continue to fight the Germans
and Austria-Hungary.
And so they get into a treaty with them
and take themselves out of the war.
We'll cover that in more detail
in a future video.