According to the pictograph below, how many survey respondents
have type O positive blood ? How many have O negative blood ?
So pictograph is really just a way of representing data with pictures that are
somehow related to the data
So in this case they give us little pictures of am assuming blood drops
right over here
And they tell us
each blood drop
each blood drop in this pictograph represents 8 people
so you can kinda view that as the scale of these graphs
Each of this is 8 people
So, For Example
You say how many people have A positive would be
1, 2, 3, 4, 5 , 6 , 7 blood drops
but each of those blood drops represent 8 people, so it would be 56
people have type A positive
But, lets answer the actual question that they are asking us
How many survey respondents have type O positive
O Positive
So this is O and then we care about O positive
So we have, 1 blood drop, 2, 3
Let me just do this in a new different color.
We have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8
So we have 8 drops
I'll put those in quotes cause of the pictures of drops
and then the scale is,the scale is 8 people. 8 people
Let me write it this way
Times 8 people per drop
8 people per drop
and so, 8 times and 8 and actually the drops you can view them as cancelling out
if you view them as units
so drops, drops
8 times 8 is equal to 64
64 people
So they could have literally written the number 64 right over here
64 People have type O positive blood
So now lets think about the O negative case
O negative blood
Well this is O and then within the blood group O
This is O negative
and we have 1 drop, 2 drops
So we have 2 drops
Two Drops
Times 8 people per drop
8 people per drop
so 2 times 8.
each of these represent 8
So 8 and then 16
Or, 2 times 8 is equal to 16, 16 people
so 16 of the survey respondents
16 have type O negative and 64 have type O positive