Find the sum 3 1/8 + 3/4 + ( -2 1/6)
We have two positive numbers, let me draw a
number line , we are going to start with 3 1/8,
this is 0, then we have 1, 2, 3 and then we have 4.
3 1/8 is going to be right over there
3 1/8, is going to be 3 1/8ths to the right of 0
So it is exactly that distance from 0.
The length of this arrow is 3 1/8th.
When ever we have fractions with different denominators
i like to deal them with improper fractions, which
makes addition , subtraction, multiplication easier
So 3 1/8 ths = 25/8
To that we are going to add 3/4ths,
we are going to move another 3/4ths.
to the right , this length is 3/4ths
Where doees this put us, we need to add it.
we have 25/8 + 3/4. The LCM of 4 & 8 is 8
So 3/4 = 6/8.
So it is 25/8 + 6/8 = 31/8
This number right over here is 31/8
32/8 =4 so 31/8 is a bit less than 4
The length of this arrow is 31/8
To write it as a mixed number, 31/8 = 3 7/8ths
Now to that we need to add - 2 1/6
So let us think about what - 2 1/6ths is like
So we are going to add -2 & - 1/6ths
we can draw -2 1/6ths like this
We can think in a couple of ways, when we add
it is same thing as subtracting 2 1/6ths
This value is going to be difference between 31/8 and - 2 1/6ths
From 31/8, we subtract 2 1/6ths
31/8 - 2 1/6ths
2 1/6 = 13/6
LCM of 8 & 6 is 24
31/8 = 93/24 , and 13/6 = 52/24
So 93/24 - 52/24 = 41/24
It is positive 41 /24
This is little bit less than 2