In the last video, we gave a basic outline of the different scenarios that might play out in 2013
or at least the different budgetary proposals on the table
from the administration, from the Republicans
and what will happen if they don't come to an agreement
which is the Fiscal Cliff
which is this fairly unusual situation where
the both parties to the negotiations set up this thing
that will automatically happen in the beginning of 2013
then it would be painful for both parties
and the thinking being, that it will maybe force them into some type of agreement sooner than later
The fiscal cliff is something neither the Republicans or the administration want
because it raises taxes, which the Republicans don't want
and it reduces spending, which the president doesn't want
and the core argument, and we touched it on the last video and we'll go in more depth in this one is,
just as we are beginning to recover our last recession
it might not be useful for our economy to suck out half a trillion dollars
so let's think about the different issues at play
so right over here- let's have some charts, most of these are from the congressional budget office
and there are a bunch of assumptions that go into this
and people will debate the assumptions that they make
but they at least directionally show the right things
So this right over here, this first chart
is... compares deficits or surpluses
and really ever since 2000s, we've been running deficits
as we got into the late, I guess, 10s, or 2008, 2010 time frame, 2009 time frame
as we went into a financial crisis
When the economy contracts, you get hit in two ways
when you think about deficit and spending
On one end, you bring in less revenue
the economy is shrinking
on the other end, you have to spend more
you have to give people more benefits
more unemployment benefits, things like that
so whenever you see the economy shrink,
you will see naturally, (all other things being equal,)
you will see deficit increase
and that's what we saw right over here
and on top of that, the government is trying to bail things out
is putting stimulus spending and all that
in order to minimize the effect of the deficit
and that's why you see here, in 2008, 2009
we started running significant, significant deficits.
Now, what's interesting, is what's going to happen going foward.
In going forward, there's two of these scenarios right here
There is the CVO's baseline projection
and then there's the alternative fiscal scenario
and just to be clear where we are
We are entering this phase, right over here
in 2013
and the baseline projection, is essentially if the government takes no more action
And if the government takes no more action, then the fiscal cliff will be triggered.
We will essentially have 500 billion less in 2013's deficit
and so what you see here is the deficits go down dramatically
go down dramatically
we have to borrow less on an anunal basis.
Now the alternative fiscal scenario
is if the- is if we essentially continue-
if we extend our existing spending,
and if we continue to extend Bush era tax cuts,
we go along this path.
And so if you care a lot about deficits,
the fiscal cliff scenario, which is this top line,
this is actually the fiscal-
let me write that in a color you can see-
that's actually the fiscal cliff scenario
and actually looks pretty good
Hey, look! We have much much lower deficits in that scenario
than if we were to continue the tax cuts
and than if we were to continue the spending
So there, that looks like an argument FOR the fiscal cliff.
Now, let's look at this, now this is where we're going to talk about the "aggregate debt"
When we say deficit, we're talking about the shortfall in a given year.
The debt is the aggregate amount that the government owes
so this is federal debt held by the public
historically and as predicted in CBO's baseline
and what a lot of what CBO, when they project,
they can only do so much in projecting
how good the economy might be, or how bad it might be,
to a large degree, they extrapolate from where we are right now
And right over here, you see debt as a percentage of GDP
so you can imagine during World War II, we had a lot of debt as a percentage of GDP
see over here after the end of World War II
we started crossing over 100% of GDP is our debt-
the aggregate amount that the government owes
and then it de-levered, then you see this rough trend,
roughly from the early 80s, until now, where we had increasing aggregate debt
There was, there were some moments in the late 90s, early 2000s where we took it down
very very strong economy, we started running surpluses,
we started to pay down some of our debt
but then we kind of hit back on this debt increasing trend-line
And once again, if we continue, in the alternative fiscal scenario
which is really continue to do what we do today
which is extend the tax cuts, and continue to have roughly the same level spending
you see that the debt only continues to increase
only continues to increase
In the baseline projection- this is actually the fiscal cliff scenario
This is where no new legislation is passes
Those triggers, in which the Bush era tax cuts expire
and the spending cuts that are triggered by the fiscal cliff scenario hit
we run lower deficits, and and we actually see the debt,
as a percentage of GDP, actually starts to go down,
which is, at least from a balance sheet perspective,
seems like a good thing.
So these fist two charts say,
Hey! Well, maybe this fiscal cliff thing isn't so bad.
The, well, actually will significantly lower the deficit on an annual basis,
and as a percentage of GDP, we will, as a country, de-lever.
Now let's think of the arguments why,
well, maybe we don't want to be that aggressive
when it come to reducing our deficit
or reducing our debt as a percentage of GDP
This first chart, right over here,
is the- let me write over here-
is the percent of our population that is employed.
and you see right- and so its a proxy for employment or unemployment
or in this case it's employment
and you see we hit a major recession at the end of 2008
We saw the percent of our population that is employed go down dramatically
we kind of hit bottom over here,
and we're having kind of a shaky, hopefully a shaky recovery
right now it's not even clear how good that will be
but hopefully we're having a shaky recovery of sorts
and so just as we're starting to recover,
it might not be helpful to take,
essentially 500 billion dollars out of the economy
in order to pay down debt
so the fiscal cliff scenario might make us go back
into a little bit of a lurch
and most economists are projecting about, on the order of, a percent slower growth
if the fiscal cliff scenario were to hit
Actually, most economists- not a percent.
They're actually expecting a two percent hit to the economy
if the fiscal cliff scenario would happen
and rather from 1.7 percent growth,
we might go to negative, a slight recession- slight receding of the economy
so that could be, that's obviously not a good scenario that we want to be in
The other chart that I have right over here,
these are yields on ten-year treasury notes
this seems like a very technical thing to talk about
but this is essentially the interest,
one way to think about it is the interest that the government is paying when it is borrowing money for ten years
And one of the main arguments for paying down debt
is that if the government keeps borrowing money
it's going to crowd out other borrowers
it's going to make demand for money high
and maybe the supply will become more and more scarce
and interest rates will go up
so a lot of borrowing can make interest rates go up
and the other idea is, well, it there's a lot of just borrowing and spending going on
and if we don't have a lot of productive capacity,
it could also lead to inflation
or maybe when the government has a huge debt
they have an incentive to try to have inflationary policies
so that in real terms, that debt seems to be less
But when you look at the debt markets,
these are market driven numbers-
the federal government does not control ten-year yields-
(the federal reserve controls short-term yields)
you see that we have historically low interest rates
so the bond market, there are some very smart people
who are living or make their living investing in the bond markets
one of the biggest markets if not the biggest
It's saying that its not worried about deficits
it's willing to lend to the US government at all time low interest rates
it's not expecting any inflation
if anything, the bond market is saying that the biggest risk in the economy is continued sluggish growth
the biggest risk in the economy is maybe even some form of deflation
So this super-low bond yield right over here would be an argument,
that yeah, if you believe what the bond market is saying
we, one definitely should not suck money out of the economy
and the risks of maintaining high levels of debt
might not be as high as some people are saying
that you're not going to see interest rates and inflation go through the roof tomorrow
Now, if you ascribe to the second point of view that
ok, yes, we should be responsible, we should start to lower-
at least minimum lower our deficit
and over time, as a percentage of GDP, lower our debt,
the other question is, "How do you do that?"
The Republicans would want to do it mainly through spending cuts
while the Democrats want to do that possibly through spending cuts
but also by maintaining some of the tax,
or letting some of that tax cuts on the wealthy expire
and maybe even adding some other tax.
And so these two charts inform some of those positions,
and I'm trying to give as balanced of an approach as I can.
So, for a Democrat, they might look at this chart right over here and they might say
Well, look! Average tax rates for the highest income tax payers-
if you look at it on a historical basis
It looks like it is relatively low,
and a lot of this comes from the idea
that even though the marginal tax rates are higher than what you see here
High income tax-payers, a lot of their income might be from capital gains,
from dividends, those are taxed at 15%
They also might have a more sophisticated accountants
who can get them more deductions
and that's why you have them paying-
and they're getting more sophisticated as time goes by
and that's why you see this trend going down
and so this could be an argument, at least relative to historic basis
that this category folks might be able to afford to pay more
There's also another argument in terms of, kind of a stimulus arguement
or how to minimize the impact on the economy
that, if you were to give-
so if you have a dollar, you want to somehow stimulate the economy with
well one, the government would spend the money,
and there're many arguments, there're many good arguments
why the government is not always the most efficient spender of money
and not always spending it in the best way
but they will definitely spend it
so you give it to the government, they'll definitely spend it and then some.
So the'll definitely spend the dollar
at least it will enter into the economy.
now, if you give it to the middle class,
they are also likely to spend it
or to spend a good chunk of it, maybe save a little bit
and the argument would be that if you give it to someone who's affluent
If you give to someone affluent, they're likely to save it.
Now, saving is not always a bad thing.
If you are low on investment, you need more savers.
If interest rates were going through the roof right over here,
that means that we need- we don't have enough supply of money.
In which case, it makes sense that we would try to incent savers.
So if you have a situation of-
In the late 70s, where you had inflation going through the roof
You want people to actually invest more
you want to higher supply of money
makes complete sense to put more money in hands of people who are likely to save and invest that money.
And here, at least if you believe the bond market,
it looks like we have a demand problem
its very cheap to get capital
if anything, there's a surplus of capital out there
but there's not enough demand in order for people to-
I guess the economy to run at its potential.
So a Democratic argument would be, look:
If we're going to have this dollar,
the person we're best off giving it to is the middle class
or, possibly to some degree, the government
because at least they will be spend it
It will help stimulate the economy.
Here, it would go into savings, but that doesn't seem like what the government needs right now.
Now, the counter argument, that you might get from someone at the right,
is that, first, the government is just hugely inefficient spender of capital
and there's a lot of evidence to-
you definitely need a government, but they don't always spend the money in the most efficient
and even, sometimes it leads to levels of corruption
and often times, when you do something in the name of stimulus
maybe it might make sense to do in the short term,
but once that program is in place,
it's very hard to remove that program.
People start to depend on it, even when you-
when in theory, you don't need the stimulus anymore
it's very hard to shrink the size of government.
And so, there's some argument for that,
if you look at outlays- government expenditure as a percentage of GDP,
it does look like- on a historical basis, it is high.
Now, to some degree, this is due to the fact that we have entered into kind of a major recessionary phase
we see that in all the major recessions
In all the major recessions, the government gets less revenue
so the government gets less revenue, and has to do more outlays
This happens in every- this happens- well, I would have to say, in most recessions
and this happened in dramatic form
where we started to have more outlays,
we had, actually at this point we had wars that we were funding
and we were doing these trillion-dollar stimulus packages
and we had these trillion-dollar bailouts at the same time that the economy was
the economy was receding right over here
But just, when you look at this, it does look like the government spending,
as a percentage of GDP, is at historical highs.
And as we say, and, you know, as the argument would have it,
it's very hard to get that to shrink even when it should be shrinking
and it's often being deployed in less than efficient ways
So I will leave you there
My intent is really not to sway you in one way or the other
but to really to just hope you have good information
when you think about the issues surrounding
the Fiscal Cliff.