In this first problem over here, we're asked to find out
the length of this segment, segment CE.
And we have these two parallel lines,
AB as parallel to DE.
And then we have these two – essentially – transversals
that form these two triangles.
So let's see what we can do here.
So the first thing that might jump out at you
is that this angle and this angle are vertical angles.
So they are going to be congruent.
The other thing that might jump out at you
Is that angle CDE is an alternate interior angle with CBA.
So we have this transveral right over here,
and these are alternate interior angles –
and they are going to be congruent.
Or you could say that if you continue this transversal,
you would have a corresponding angle
with CDE right up here.
And this one is just vertical.
Either way, this angle and this angle are going to be congruent.
So we've established that we have two triangles.
And they have two corresponding angles which are the same.
And that, by itself, is enough to establish similarity.
You can actually –
We actually could show that this angle and this angle
are also congruent by alternate interior angles.
But we don't have to.
So we already know that they are similar.
Actually, we could just say it just by alternate interior angles.
These are also going to be congruent.
But we already know enough to say that they're similar,
even before doing that.
So we already know that triangle.
I'll try to write it color coded, so that we have
the same corresponding vertices.
And it's really important to know what angles
and what sides correspond to what side,
so that you don't mess up your ratios,
or so that you do know what is corresponding to what.
So we know triangle ABC is similar to triangle –
So A – this vertex A – corresponds to vertex E over here –
Is similar to vertex E.
And then vertex B right over here
corresponds to vertex D, EDC.
Now what does that do for us?
Well that tells us that the ratio of corresponding sides
are going to have the same.
They're going to be the same.
They're going to be some constant value.
So we have corresponding side
So the ratio for example, the corresponding side for BC
Is going to be DC
We can see it
Just for the way that we've written down the similarity
If this is true then BC is the corresponding side to DC
So we know that BC, the length of BC over DC
Right over here
Is going to be equal to the length of,
Well, we wanna figure out what CE is,
That's what we care about
And I'm using BC and DC cause we know those values
So BC over DC is going to be equal to
A coresponding side to CE
The corrresponding side over here is CA
Is going to be equal to CA over CE
Corresponding sides
This is the last and the first, last and the first
CA over CE
And we know what BC is
BC right over here is 5
We know what DC is
It is 3
We know what CA or AC is right over here
CA is 4
And now we can just solve for CE
So we can,
There's multiple ways that you can think about this
You could cross multiply and you get,
Which is really just multiplying both sides by both denominators
So you get 5 times the length of CE
Is equal to 3 times 4
Which is just going to be equal to 12
And then we get CE
CE is equal to 12 over 5
Which is the same thing as 2 and 2 fifths
2 and 2 fifths or 2 4
This is gonna be 2 and 2 fifths
And we're done
We're able to use similarity to figure out this side
Just knowing that the ratio between corresponding sides
Are going to be the same
Now let's do this problem right over here
Let's do this one.
Let me draw a little line here.
So this is a different problem now.
So in this problem we need to figure out what DE is
And we all once again
We have these 2 parallel lines like this
And so we know corresponding angles are congruent
So we know that angle is going to be congruent to that angle
Cause you could view this as a transversal,
We also know that this angle right over here
Is going to be congruent to that angle right over there
Once again, corresponding angles for transversal
And also in both triangles,
So I'm looking at triangles CBD and triangles CAE,
They both share this angle up here
So we've actually shown,
Once again, we could have stopped at two angles
But we've actually shown
that all three angles of these two triangles,
all three of the corresponding angles
are congruent to each other
So we now know,
And once again this is an important thing to do,
Is to make sure that you get
Is that you write it in the right order
when you write your similarity,
We now know that triangle CBD is similar
Not congruent,
It is similar to triangle CAE
Which means that the ratio of corresponding sides
Are going to be constant
So we know for example, that the ratio between CD
Is going to be the same
That the ratio between CB to CA,
Lets write this down,
We know that the ratio of CB over CA
Is going to be equal to the ratio of CD over CE
And we know what CB is,
CB over here is 5
We know what CA is
And we have to be careful here
It's not 3
CA this entire side is gonna be 5 plus 3
So this is going to be 8
And we know what CD is
CD is going to be 4
And so once again, we can cross multiply
We have 5 CE, 5 times CE is equal to
8 times 4
8 times 4 is 32
And so CE is equal to 32 over 5
Or this is another way to think about that
6 and 2 fifths
Now we're not done because they didn't ask for what CE is
They're asking for just this part right over here
They're asking for DE
So we know that this entire length, CE right over here
This is 6 and two fifths,
And so DE right over here,
what we actually have to figure out
It's going to be this entire length 6 and 2 fifths minus 4
Minus CD right over here
So it's going to be 2 and 2 fifths
6 and 2 fifths minus 4 is 2 and 2 fifths
So we're done
DE is 2 and 2 fifths