Find the natural logarithm of 3 using a calculator.
Round your answer to the nearest hundredth.
And this is a reminder: natural log of 3 --
this is just another way of saying log base e of 3.
Or what power do I have to raise e to get to 3.
And 3 is a little bit larger than e.
e is 2.71 and then it goes on and on.
So 3 is a little bit larger than e. So I'm guessing it gonna be
1. something something.
Let's get our calculator out and just calculate it.
So natural log, that's this button over here "ln".
I'm assuming it's maybe from french "log naturelle"
or something like that.
So natural log of 3 is
1. (and they want us to round to the nearest hundedth).
So 1.09 and at the thousandths place is an 8,
which is greater or equal to 5, so we want to round up.
So we want to round 9 up, that essentialy takes us to 10.
So 1.10.
So this is approximately equal to 1.10,
when we round to the nearest hundredth.