The seventeen hundreds in Europe are often
referred to as the age of enlightenment,
it was a time we had come out of the renaissance,
we'd rediscovered science and reason,
and in the seventeen hundreds,
we saw that come about
with even more progress of society.
As we exit the seventeen hundreds
and enter into the eighteen hundreds,
we start having the industrial revolution,
and people saw the steady march
of human reason, of human progress.
And because of... because of this,
a lot of people were saying
'hey, humanity will continue to improve and..
and it will improve forever,
to a point that poverty will go away,
we will turn to this perfect utopian civilisation
without wars, without strife of any kind.'
And, there was something to be said about that
you had significant improvements,
in fact you had even more dramatic improvements
once the industrial revolution started.
But not everyone in the late seventeen hundreds
was as optimistic,
and one of the more famous not-so-optimistic people
was Thomas Malthus.
[writes Thomas Malthus] right over here.
and I will just quote him directly,
this is from his essay on the principle of population.
[Quote] 'The power of population
is so superior to the power of the earth to
produce subsistence for man,
that premature death must in some shape
or other visit the human race.'
Very uplifting.
'The vices of mankind are active
and able ministers of depopulation.
They are the precursors
in the great army of destruction,
and often finish the dreadful work themselves.
But should they fail in this war of extermination,
sickly seasons, epidemics, pestilence
and plague advance in terrific array,
and sweep off their thousands
and tens of thousands.
Should success still be incomplete,
gigantic inevitable famine stalks in the rear,
and with one mighty blow levels the population
with the food of the world.'
So not..not so uplifting
of a little quote right over here.
But this was his general sense.
He lived in a time when people were being
very optimistsic that the progress,
the march of progress, would go on forever
until we got to some utopian civilisation.
But from Thomas Malthus' point of view
he felt that if people could reproduce
and increase the population, they will.
That there's no way of stopping them.
So from his point of view, the way he saw it -
so let me on that axis,
let's say that, that is the population,
and this axis right over here,
let's say that.. that is time.
So by his thinking
and everything he'd seen in reality up to that point
would back this up
that if people had enough food and time,
they would reproduce,
and they would reproduce in numbers
that would grow the population.
So in his mind the population would just
keep on increasing.
It'll just keep on increasing,
until it can't support itself anymore,
until the actual productivity of the land
can't produce enough calories
to feed all of those people.
So in his mind there would be some
natural upper bound,
based on the actual amount of food
that the Earth could support.
So let's say that this is -
(let me do that in a different colour)
So in his mind there was some upper bound
there was some upper bound,
and once you get to that upper bound
then all of a sudden
the vices of mankind will show up and
if those don't start killing people
well then all of these other things will -
epidemics, er.. pestilence, plague and then famine
people are actually starving to death.
So in his mind, once you got to this level,
maybe you had a couple of good crops,
people are feeling good about themselves,
they overpopulate.
But then all of a sudden you have a bad crop,
or because you have a bad crop,
people start fighting over resources,
and wars happen,
or maybe the population is so dense that
a plague develops.
And then you have a massive wave of depopulation.
And so you would just oscillate around this limit.
And this limit some people would refer to as a
Malthusian limit, but it's really just the limit at which
the population can sustain itself,
and from Thomas Malthus' point of view,
he did recognise that
there were technological improvements,
especially in things like agriculture,
and that this line was moving up.
He had seen it in his own lifetime
that this line had moved up.
But from his point of view,
however far you move this line up,
the population will always compensate for it
and catch up to it
and eventually get to this Mathusian,
eventually get to this limit and then the same kind of
not so positive things that he talks about
would actually happen.
And some people now say
'Oh Thomas Malthus, he was so pessamistic,
he was obviously wrong, look at what's happened,
we have so much food on this planet right now,
we've gone through multiple agricultural revolutions'
And they are right, in the last two hundred years,
since Malthus or since the early eighteen hundreds
we really have been able to outstrip population.
So this line, this line up here, has been moving up
much faster than even population.
So right now we actually do have
more calories per person on the planet
than we've had at any time in history.
But it's not saying that Thomas Malthus was wrong,
it's just saying that maybe he was just a little bit, er,
he was a little bit pessimistic
in when that limit will be reached.
Now the other dimension where you might say that
he was maybe wrong,
was in this principle that
a population will increase if it CAN increase,
that if there IS food and there IS time,
people WILL reproduce.
And a good counterpoint to that is
what we've now observed
in modern developed nations.
And so this right over here shows
the population growth.
I got this from 'The World Bank',
that the population growth
over some modern developed nations.
You can see that the United States is pretty low
but it is still positive,
it's still...well, it's still over half a percent in,
but even that adds up when you compound it.
But if you look over here, Japan and Germany,
and Japan and Germany have
less immigration than the U.S,
especially Japan, they are actually negative.
So just this population left to its own devices
especially if you account for people
not going across borders,
just the population itself growing,
they actually have negative growth.
So there is some reason to believe that
this is evidence that Thomas Malthus was wrong
or not completely right, he didn't put into account
that maybe once a society becomes rich enough
and educated enough,
that they might not just populate the world
or have as many kids as they want.
They might try to do other things with their time
whatever that might be.
So I just wanted to expose you to this idea
time will tell if Thomas Malthus
if we can always keep this line,
if we can always keep this line of food productivity
growing faster than the population;
and time will tell whether our populations can become
I guess we could say, developed enough
so that they don't in excrib (I can never say that word)
[execrably], they don't always just keep growing,
maybe they DO become a Japan or Germany situation
in the world population,
especially if we have a high rate of literacy,
eventually does level off.
So that it never even has a chance of
hitting up against that Malthusian limit.
But though I would introduce you to the idea
and now you can go to parties
and you can talk about things like Malthusian limits.
And if you wanna know what country, you know,
is maybe closest to the Malthusian limit right now,
and we've talked about this before,
but a good case of example is something like
Bangladesh. They are right now the
most population-dense country in the world,
they have nine hundred people per square kilometre.
And just to give you a sense of perspective
that's thirty times more dense than the U.S is.
So if you took every person in the U.S
and turned them into thirty people in the U.S
that would give you a sense of
how dense Bangladesh is.
And it's probably due, to a certain degree
that it is very fertile land,
it's the river delta of the Ganges
essentially makes up the entire country,
but they do, they've had in the past had famines,
they gotten a little bit beyond that,
but still you do have major problems
with the flooding and the resources.
So hopefully they'll be able to er,
they'll be able to say ahead of the curve.