Find the absolute value of x
when x=5, x= -10 and x=-12
So the absolute value,
the way of writing it is almost
more complicated than what it acutally is.
The absolute value is really just the distance of x from 0.
distance from 0
So let me just draw a fast number line over here.
So let's just put zero right over here,
since we are taking the distance from 0.
So, let's just think about absolute value of x, when x=5.
That's equivalent to the absolute value for 5.
We just substitue 5 for x.
The absolute value of 5 is the distance of 5 from 0.
So you go 1,2,3,4,5,
5 is exactly 5 to the right of 0.
So the absolute value of 5 is just 5.
Now, i think you already get to see,
this is a pretty straight forward concept.
Now, let's just do something a little more interesting,
Absolute value of -10.
or the absolute value of x, when x= -10.
Let's just put in -10 in for x.
This is the distance -10 is from 0.
So let's just go: -1,-2,-3,-4,-5,-6,-7,-8,-9,-10.
I should extend the number line more.
So this right here is -10.
So how far is it away from 0?
Well, it is 10 to the left of 0,
so, you put a 10 here.
So in general absolute value will always be a positive quantity.
If we are thinking abot absolute value of just numbers,
it is just going to be really the positive version of that number.
Let's do one more.
Well they tell us to do one more.
The absolute value of x, when x=-12.
So we have the absolute value of -12.
We don't even have to look at the number line,
is just going to be the positive version of -12,
is just going to be equal to 12.
and this is saying that -12 is 12 away from 0.
We can draw it over here.
This is -11,-12 is right over here,
it is 1,2, 3, 4, 5, 6,7.8,9,10,11,12 away from 0.