In the following polynomial, identify the terms
along with the coefficient and exponent of each term.
So the terms are the things being added up in this polynomial.
So the terms here, let me write the terms here...
The first term is 3x squared,
The second term it's being added to -8x.
You might say wait, isn't it minus 8x?
And you could just view that it's being added to
-8x, so -8x is the second term, and the third term
here is the 7, it's called the polynomial
poly, it has many terms, or you could view each term
as a monomial, it's a polynomial with only one term in it.
So those are the terms, now lets think about the coefficient
of each of the terms.
The coefficient is what's multiplying the power of x,
or what's multiplying the x part of the term, so
over here, the x part is x squared,
that's being multiplied by three,
so three is the coefficient on the first term.
On the second term, we have -8 multiplying x,
and we want to be clear-- the coefficient isn't just 8,
it's -8, it's -8 that's multiplying x, so that's the coefficient right over here
And here you might say, hey wait!
Nothing is multiplying x here, I just have a 7
there is no x, 7 isn't being multiplied by x.
But you can think of this as 7 being multiplied
by x to the zero, cause we know that x to the zeroth power
is equal to one.
So we would even call this constant, this 7,
this would be the coefficient on 7x to the zero.
So you could view this, you could view this, as a
coefficient, so this is also a coefficient,
so let me make it clear-- these three things are coefficients.
Coefficients. Now the last part, they want us
to identify the exponent of each term.
So the exponent of this first term term is 2,
it's being raised to the second power,
the exponent of the second term,
remember -8x, x is the same thing as x to the first power,
so the exponent here is 1,
and on this last term, we already said
this is 7 is the same thing as 7x to the zero,
so the exponent here on the constant term,
on 7, is 0, so these are, these things right over here,
those are our exponents, exponents.
And we are done.