Let's do some more of these classic age word problems.
So we're told that William is 4 times as old as Ben.
12 years ago, William was 7 times as old as Ben.
How old is Ben now?
So, once again, it's a good idea
to try to do this on your own first and
then I'll work through it.
So, what's the unknown here?
The unknown here is: How old is Ben now?
So let's set a variable equal Ben.
We do x or y but since Ben starts with a B,
let's use B for Ben.
So let's let B = Ben's current age
Ben's age now.
So let's see how all these other information relates to
Ben's current age and then maybe we could set up
some equations and solve for this.
I'll do a little more structure in this,
where you could have done many of the problems
you've been working on in this way,
so let's about Ben, and then let's think about William
I'll put 'William' in blue.
So let's think about, William.
And then there's 2 points in time we're talking about.
We're talking about now, today and
we're gonna talk about 12 years ago.
Over here, let's say today, or let's call that 'Now'
This will be our 'Now' column and this
would be our '12 years ago'.
So let's see what we can fill in here.
So what is Ben's age now?
Well, we just defined that as the variable B.
That's the unknown, that's what we have to figure out.
So that's just going to be 'B'.
What's Ben's age 12 years ago?
Well, maybe we want to express it in terms of B.
If it's 'B' now, 12 years ago it was just 'B - 12'.
Fair enough.
Now, what is William's age today?
This first sentence gave us the information.
William is 4 times as old as Ben, and we can assume
that they are talking about today.
So if Ben is 'B', William is going to be '4B'.
And so how old was William 12 years ago?
If he's '4B' right now, 12 years ago it would be 12 less than that.
12 years ago it would be '4B - 12'
So that's kind of interesting.
But we haven't quite yet made use of the second statement.
12 years ago, William, so this is William 12 years ago.
12 years ago, William was 7 times as old as Ben.
So 12 years ago, this number is going to be 7 times this number.
or another way to think about it is to take
this number and multiply it by 7
and you're gonna get this number.
12 years ago, Ben's age was 1/7 of William's age, or
William's age is 7 times Ben's age
Let's see if we can set that up as an equation.
We can have, 7 times this, Ben's age 12 years ago,
is going to be equal to William's age
And it seems like we've done the hard part.
We set up the equation, we just have to use
our algebraic tools to solve for 'B'
Let's do that.
The first thing that we want to do. We can distribute the 7.
7 times B, 7 times negative 12.
So we have '7B - 84' is going to be equal to '4B - 12'
this whole expression is 7 times Ben's age 12 years ago
Now what we can do to solve all of these?
Well, we can subtract '4B' from both sides.
Actually I can do 2 steps at the same time, but let's just keep it simple.
Let's subtract '4B' on both sides.
That goes away, and on the right hand side I have a '-12'.
On the left hand side, I'm left with, '7B - 4B = 3B'
and then I still have my '-84'.
I want to get rid of this '-84', so let's minus 84 on the left hand side.
So let's add 84 on both sides.
On the left hand side, I'm just left with '3B',
and on the right hand side, I have
'-12 + 84 = 72'
Now if I want to solve for B, I just have to divide the whole
equation by 3.
And so I am left with 'B' is equal to, drum roll, '72/3'
It would be 24.
So 'B' is equal to 24
Going back to our question: What is Ben's age now?
It is 24.
Let's verify this is actually the case.
So they are telling us that William is 4 times as old as Ben.
So what is William's current age?
So '4 x 24 = 96'
So William is a senior, we should call him Mr. William.
He is 96 years old. Maybe he's Ben's grandfather or great grandfather.
Then they say 12 years ago, William, William was 84 years old.
They say that he is 7 times as old as Ben.
Well, 12 years ago, if he's 24 now, Ben was 12.
And indeed, '84 = 7 x 12'
And it all worked out.