What I want to do in this video is take an expenditure view of GDP
So we can think about how GDP can be counted, measured, and how active the different parts of an economy are.
So GDP- the market value of all final goods and services produced-not just changed hands-produced
within a country in a given period.
And the symbol we use for GDP and I don't know why-but the symbol is "Y"-Y is the GDP
And so let's think about it from an expenditure point of view.
Think about what are all the pieces?
If were thinking of expenditure for all the players that might...
have spent money on the final goods and services that were produced in our country
Well you could have your firms
The firm's mother spend money on these goods and services
You also have your households, they obviously could've spent
some money on goods and services produced in this country.
Then you also have, you also have in fact
in all countries you have the government, the government could've spent money
on the goods and services produced in this country, and
if we assume that we are trading with other countries, there are other countries
that might've spend money on the goods and services, other
outside...let's just write foreign
people outside the country money to spend money on goods and services
so foreign purchases, and another way to think about it
would've been this is exports
our country is exporting its people outside of the country and they're purchasing it, now this is almost complete
but if we look at all of the money that firms are spending, all the money that households are spending,
all the money that governments are spending. Some of it that they are spending might not
be on goods and services that are produced in this country, they might be spending some of the stuff on
things that are produced outside of this country so we would have to subtract it out if we really
wanted to have goods and services produced within the country, so what we're gonna want to do is subtract out foreign products
or another way of thinking about it, the typical way of thinking about it..we would subtract imports
So if you think about it all of the goods and services that meet these classifications, the final goods and services
produced in the country in a given time, that firms spent money on and add that to the good and services that households spent money on
and add that to the goods and services that the Government spent on, and all the goods and services-the exports-and
make sure we're not counting the goods and services that other countries produce so we subtract those out
this would give you a pretty good measure of all the goods and services produced within a country
and this is pretty close to the way that economists actually do measure it, so what they do is say
Y is equal to "Investment", and we saw in the previous video investment in the macroeconomics term isn't quite what it is in the everyday term
It really essentially means the spending by firms, so pretty much everything that the firm spends
In theory you're spending that money to make future goods and services or to make goods and services, so
that's all considered investment and a little bit of the household spending is considered investment, just new houses
but the bulk of household spending is considered to be consumption, and then everything that the government spends on
whether it's the military, and all the salaries for police people, and whatever they do...the grounds-keeping at the White House
whatever else if you are thinking about the U.S. That goes straight to "G". And over here you have foreign exports minus
foreign inputs so you have exports minus imports so you could view this is a net exports
if this number is positive then net exports are positive and we're exporting more than we're importing, if this number
is negative, net exports is negative that means we are importing more than we are exporting but in a traditional
expenditure-view of GDP this whole part right over here will be referred to as net exports
and so you sum up these things which are very closely related to the more intuitive versions we started off with
then you essentially have broken down the expenditure-view of GDP in the traditional sense
In the next two videos I'm going to start thinking of a bunch of different examples and we'll think of which bucket it would fall into
and how it would affect one of these buckets.