We are asked to simplify a log base 5 of 25 to the "x" power over "y"
So I will give you some logarithm properties and I do agree that this does require some simplification
over here
That this having this right over here inside of the logarithm is not a pleasant way to look at it
So the first thing that we realize is that this is one of our logarithm properties
So logarithm for a given base so lets say that the base is "x" of a/b
That is equal to log base "x" of a minus log base "x" of b
Now here we have 25 to the "x" over y
So we can simplify
Log base 5 twenty five to the "x" over "y" to this property means that its the same thing
as log base 5 to the twenty five to the "x" power minus log base 5 of "y"
Now this looks like we can do a little bit of simplifying
It seems like the relevant logarithm property here is if I have log base "x" of a to the "p" power
That's the same thing as b times log base "x" of a
This exponent over here can go outfront, which is what we did right over there
So this part right over here can be written as "x" times the logarithm of base 5
of 25 and then of course we have minus log base 5 of "y"
And this is useful beacuse log base 5 of 25 is actually very easy to think about
This part right here is asking us what power
do I have to raise 5 to to get to 25
So we have to raise 5 to the 2nd power to get 25.
So we are left with, this is equal to 2 times "x" minus log base 5 of "y"