So far we've been dealing with one way of Probability, that was the probability of (A) occur,
The number of events that satisfy A over all number of the equally likely events
All of the equally likely events.
And so in the case of a coin, The Probability of heads was a fair coin
With 2 equally likely events, satisfies being "Heads"
So there's a half chance of having a "Heads"
Similarly for tails, if you took a die
The probability of getting an even number.
Well there's 6 equally likely events, and there are three even numbers you can get
Which are, two, four and six
So there's three over six, or simply,
One half chance
And this is a really good model
of equally likely events. Now I'm going to change things up a little
I'll draw a line, this was just one way about thinking of probability
Now we're going to talk of probability where we can think of equally likely events
And in particular I'm going to set up an unfair coin
So this right over here, is supposed to be my unfair coin.
One side of that coin is heavier than the other, So this is the head's side
And obviously on the back, is Tails
As I said, this is an UNFAIR coin
Now I'm going to make an interesting statement about this unfair coin
It doesn't fit into the model I've created above,
And this interesting statement is, above we had a 50-50 chance of getting heads
I'm going to say, here, that the probability of getting Heads, for this coin right here,
is 60% (Sixty Per Cent)
Or another way to say,
0.6 or 6 upon 10.
Or another way to say this is 3/5 or three-fifths
Now we can't say there are two equally likely events
There are two possible events
The coin may fall on the heads, or tails
So it is obvious that either we'll get Heads or Tails
But there aren't really two equally likely events
Counting the number of events that satisfy, over all the possible events
In this situation, we can visualize the probability.
This is fundamentally different from the model we talked about above.
We have to kind of take, a frequentive approach
Think about it in terms of frequency,
And the way to conceptualize, 60% chance of getting heads
If we had a super large number of trials. This means if we are to flip this coin
Like a zillion times
We would expect, 60% of those would come up as heads
So I'm clear how I determine, that this is60%! Maybe I ran a computer stimulation, maybe I should know exactly all about physics
Of this, and I can completely marvel how it's going to fall everytime
Or maybe it's like, I have a tonne of trials, I flip the coin a million times And I said, well, 60%
Of those, therefore, came up heads.
And we can make a similar statement about Tails!
So, the probability of Heads is 60%
The Probability of Tails, well there're only two possibilities, whether there can be heads or tails!
So if I say the probability of heads or tails, is going to be equal to 1 !
Because there also can be a chance of getting hundred percent Heads or tails
And these are mutually exclusive events, you can't have both of them
So this is going to be, the probability of tails is, going to be 100% - Probability of Heads
which of course is 60% (as above)
Which is equal to 40%
or as a decimal, it is 0.4
Or as a fraction, four tenths, or Four upon Ten, or in its simplest form, it is Two Fifths, 2 over 5
So once again, we can't call them equally likely events. If we toss a coin a zillion times, and we get
60% of the coins as heads, it is obvious that the rest coins have to be tails
It's time for some problems now,
The probability of getting heads on our first flip and heads on our second flip.
So once again these are independent flips. The coin has no memory, regardless what I got on the first
flip, I have equal chance of getting heads on the second flip. I can get heads and tails on the first
as well, so the probability of heads on the first flip X Probability of getting heads on the second flip.
Now we already know that the probability of getting heads on the first flip is 60%
Or let's write it in the decimal form, it is 0.6
Also, P(H2) is 0.6. And we can just multiply. I'll do it right here, so this is 0.6 x 0.6
It is equal to 0.36.
We're taking 60% of 0.6. 0.36, or another way to say it that we have 36% of getting two heads in a row
Given this unfair coin, remember if it was a fair coin, one half times which is one over four which
1/4 or 25%.
Now let's see a slightly complicated example;
Let's say, the Probability of getting a tails on the first flip, getting a heads on the second flip,
And getting a tails on the third flip. So this is going to be equal to the probability of getting a tails on the first and third flip, and a heads on the second
It is equal to The Probability of Getting Tails on the First flip, multiplied by the probability of getting
heads on the second flip, heads being on the second time doesn't affect the probability of heads and similarly, a tails, again, on the third flip
And we know that the probability of getting a tails is 0.4
The Probability of getting a heads(on any flip) is 0.6 and the probability of getting tails on the third flip is 0.4
So once again we just have to multiply all these probabilities,
So 0.4 X 0.4 X 0.6 = 0.096
Or another way it to write is 9.6%, a little less than 10%. We have a 9.6% chance of getting this probability
Remember, in this case, the position of heads or tails, first, second or third does not affect
Their probability
Thanks!