In this video I want to familiarize you with the idea of a limit, which is a super important idea.
It's really the idea that all of calculus is based upon.
But despite being so super important, it's actually a really really really simple idea.
So let me draw a function here - actually, let me define a function
here. A kind of a simple function. So let's define f(x) - let's say that f(x) is going to be (x-1)/(x-1).
And you might say, "Hey Sal, look, I have the same thing in the numerator and the denominator.
If I have something divided by itself, that would just be equal to one! Can't I just simplify this to f(x)=1?"
And I would say, "Well, you're almost true, the difference between f(x)=1 and this thing right over
here is that this thing is undefined when x=1. So if you set - let me write it over here - if you have
f(1), what happens? In the numerator, you get (1-1), which is... let me just write it down...
in the numerator you get 0, and in the denominator you get (1-1), which is also 0. And so anything divided
by 0, including 0/0, this is undefined. So you can make the simplification - you can say that this is
the same thing as f(x)=1, but you would have to add the constraint that x cannot be equal to 1. Now this
and this are equivalent. Both of these are going to be equal to 1, for all other x'es other than 1. But
at x=1, it becomes undefined. This is undefined and this one's undefined. So how would I graph this function?
So let me graph it... That is my y=f(x) axis, and then this over here is my x-axis, and then let's say
this is the point x=1, this over here would be x=-1, this is y=1, right up there I can do -1 but that
doesn't do much relative to this function right over here, and and let me graph it. So it's essentially for
any x other than 1, f(x)=1. So it's gonna look like this... except at 1. At 1, f(x) is undefined, so
I'm gonna put a little bit of a gap right over here, this circle, to signify that this function
is not defined - we don't know what this function equals at 1, we never defined it.
This definition of the function doesn't tell us what to do at 1 - it's literally undefined when x=1.
So this is the function right over here, and so once again, if someone were to ask you what is f(1), you'd go...
and let's say, well this was a function definition, you would go x=1. Oh wait, there is a gap in my function
over here, it is undefined. So let me write it again... well, it's kind of redundant but I'll rewrite it.
f(1) is undefined. But what if I were to ask you, what is the function approaching
as x=1? And now, this is starting to touch on the idea of a limit. So as x gets closer and closer to 1...
what is the function approaching? Well this entire time, what is it getting closer and closer to?
On the left hand side, no matter how close you get to 1, as long as you're not at 1, f(x)=1.
Over here from the right hand side, you get the same thing. So you could say - and you'll get
more and more familiar with this idea as we do more examples - that the limit as
x (and lim, short for limit) - as x approaches 1 of f(x) is equal to...
As we get closer we can get unbelievably, infinitely close to 1 as long as we're not at 1...
And our function is going to be equal to 1, it's getting closer and closer to 1,
it's actually at 1 the entire time. So in this case, we can say the limit as x approaches 1 of f(x)
is 1. So once again, has very fancy notation, we're just saying, "Look, what is the function approaching
as x gets closer and closer to 1?"
Let me do another example where we're dealing with a curve, just so that you have the general idea.
So let's say that I have the function f(x) - let me, just for the sake of variety, let me call it g(x).
Let's say that we have g(x) is equal to - I can define it this way, we can define it as x²
when x does not equal 2, and let's say that when x=2, it is equal to 1. So once again, kind of an interesting
function that - as you'll see - is not fully continuous. It has a discontinuity. Let me graph it.
So this my y=f(x) axis, this is my x-axis right over here. Let's say this is x=1, this is x=2,
this is -1, this is -2... And then let me draw..So everywhere except x=2, it's equal to x². So let me draw it like this,
this is gonna be a parabola, it looks something like this... It's gonna look something...
Let me draw a better version of the parabola. So it looks something like this, not the most beautifully
drawn parabola in the history of drawing parabolas, but I think it will give you the idea of what a parabola
looks like, hopefully. It should be symmetric... Let me redraw it, because that's kinda ugly.
That's looking better, okay, alright, there you go. Alright.
Now, this should be the graph of just x², but it's not x² when x=2. So once again, when x=2,
we should have a little bit of a discontinuity here, so I'll draw a gap right over there,
because when x=2, the function is equal to 1.
I'm not doing them on the same scale... On the graph of f(x)=x² this would be 4, this would be 2,
this would be 1, this would be 3. So, x=2, our function is equal to 1.
So this is a bit of a bizarre function, but you can define it this way, you can define a function however
you like to define it! And so, notice, it's just like the graph of f(x)=x² except when you get to 2,
it has this gap, because you don't use the "f(x)=x² when x=2", you use "g(x)=1".
If I've been saying f(x), I apologize for that.
You use g(x)=1, so then just exactly at 2, it drops down to 1, and then it keeps going along the function x².
So there is a couple of things. If I were to just evaluate the function - g(2),
well you look at this definition. Okay, when x=2, I use this situation right over here,
and it tells me it's going to be equal to 1. Let me ask a more interesting question, or perhaps a more
interesting question. What is the limit as x approaches 2 of g(x)? Once again, fancy notation, but
it's asking something pretty pretty simple. It's saying "as x gets closer and closer to 2...
as you get closer and closer - and this isn't a rigorous definition, we'll do that in future videos -
as x gets closer and closer to 2, what is g(x) approaching? So if you get to 1.9, and then 1.999, and then 1.999999
and then 1.9999999, what is g(x) approaching? If you were to go from the positive direction,
if you were to say 2.1, what's g(2.1)? What's g(2.01)? What's g(2.001)?
What is that approaching as we get closer and closer to it?
And you can see it visually just by drawing the graph. As g gets closer and closer to 2...
And if we were to follow it along the graph, we see that we're approaching 4,
even though that's not where the function is - the function drops down to 1 - the limit of g(x) as
x approaches 2 is equal to 4. You can even do this numerically using a calculator.
And let me do that, because I think that will be interesting. So let me get a calculator out...
Let me get my trusty TI-85 out... So here is my calculator... And you can numerically say,
okay, what's it gonna approach as you approach x=2? So let's try 1.9. For x=1.9, you would use this
top clause, right over here. So you'd have 1.9², and so you would get 3.61.
Well, what if you get even closer to 2? So 1.99, and once again let me square that,
well I'm at 3.96. What if I do 1.999 and I square that?
I'm gonna get 3.996. Notice, I'm getting closer and closer and closer to our point.
If I got really close - 1.999999999999²? What am I gonna get to? It's not actually going to be
exactly 4 - this calculator just rounded things up - because we're gonna get to a number really really
really really close to 4. And we can do something from the positive direction, too, and it actually
has to be the same number when we approach from the below, what we're trying to approach,
and above what we're trying to approach. So if we try 2.1², we get 4.4...
Let me go a couple of steps ahead...
2.0001². So this is much closer to 2 now. Now we're getting much closer to 4.
So the closer we get to 2, the closer it seems like we're getting to 4.
So once again that's a numeric way of seeing that the limit as x approaches 2 from either direction
of g(x) - even though right at 2, the function is equal to 1, because it's discontinuous -
the limit as we're approaching 2, we're getting closer and closer and closer to 4.