There are 11 major muscle groups in the body
and I'm just going to go through them really quickly
I'm not going to talk too much about the names
of the muscles, but I want you to get a sense for where they are located
on the body. So the arm, the leg, and the core.
and I'll write that over here. So the 11 groups
there are three - actually four- in the arm.
three in the leg
and four in the core.
And just being familiar with where these muscles are is actually
really really helpful and powerful because when you
go to the gym or you're working out somewhere else,
it's important to stretch these muscle groups out
it's important to also focus on each one
and try to figure out which one is weak or strong
and develop whichever one is imbalanced
sometimes the left and the right side are not equal in their strength.
So it's important to be aware of where they're located
and we're going to go through that really quickly right now.
So let's do the arm first.
You have first the forearm. And you can see that one the best from the front.
And above that you have the biceps, and that's about right there.
There's your biceps. And behind your biceps, actually on the other side
is the triceps, and that's right there.
And above both the biceps and the triceps is the shoulder.
And actually I'm going to draw that right there.
You can actually see it from the front and the back.
I'm just gonna draw it right there, just for simplicity.
So those are the four arm muscles, and now let's just jump down to the leg.
And put in the quads, this is your quadriceps.
And this is actually called the quadriceps because it's actually four different muscles working together
And below the quads- or actually on the other side of your quads, rather- is your hamstring.
Right here is your hamstring.
And I want to give a special shout out to the hamstring
because it does a lot of work and a lot of people forget to stretch it out.
And you can often get in a lot of pain from not having a good stretched out hamstring.
Below it is the calfs.
And the calf is actually sitting on the opposite side
of the bones in the lower leg, the tibia and fibula
which is why it's so boney on the front part of your lower leg,
but on the back it's very meaty and muscley.
So you have three leg muscles there.
Now let's put in the core muscles.
So you have, let's do the front first.
So right here is where we'll talk about getting a six-pack.
Your abs. That's an important muscle group.
Helps you do sit-ups.
And above it is your chest. So right here is your chest.
And there are two in the front. And similarly there are
two in the back. So the back ones-let me do in yellow-
are your trapezius, and trapezius actually kind of
comes down like a diamond almost- kind of like that.
And it helps with the neck and upper back.
And then almost like you have wings in a way
you have two other muscles, or actually another muscle
with two sides on it, called the Latissimus dorsi.
Actually kind of a large spread out muscle- and I'm not drawing all of it.
But it basically kind of spreads all the way through your back
and this is the major muscle of your back.
So when people say "I threw out my back" often times, if it's the
lower back they're talking their Latissimus dorsi.
And that means that we have now our four core muscles shown up here.
So counting them out, we've got our 11 muscle groups.
So just to again go over it very quickly, we've got one shoulder, biceps, forearm, and triceps.
In our leg we have our quads, our hamstring and our calf.
And then in the core of our body we have our abs, our chest,
our upper back-which would be the trapezius- and the lower back-which is the latissimus dorsi.
That's your eleven groups.