What I want to do in this video is give ourselves
a basic introduction to the phenomenon of light.
And light is, atleast to me, it is mysterious
because on one level it really defines our reality
it may be the most defining caracteristic of our reality
everything we see, how we percieve reality is based
on light bouncing off of objects, or bending around objects or difffracting around objects.
and then being sensed by our eyes and then
sending signals into our brain that create models of the world we see around us
so it really is almost a defining
characteristic of our reality, but at the same time,
when you really go down to experiment and observe with light,
its starts to have a bunch of mysterious
properties and to a large degree it is not fully understood yet.
And probably the most amazing thing about light
...well, actually there is tons of thing amazing about light....
but one of the mysterious things is
when you really get down to it, and this is actually not just true of light,
this is actually true of almost anything once you
get onto a small enough quantum mechanical level,
but light behaves as both a wave AND a particle.
And this is, probably not that intuitive to you, because its
not that intuitive to me!
In my life I'm used to certain things
behaving as a waves, like sound waves,
or the waves of an ocean.
And I'm used to certain things behaving like particles.
Like... Basket balls, or... I don't know...
Or... My coffee cup. I'm not used to things
behaving as both!
And it really depends on what experiment
you run and how you observe the light.
So, when you observe it as a particle,
And this comes out of Einstein's work with the photo-electric effect.
And I won't go into the details here, maybe in a future video
when we start thinking about quantum mechanics.
You can view light as a train of particles moving at the speed of light.
Which I'll talk about in a second...
We call these particles PHOTONS.
If you view light in other ways
and you see it even when you see light beam
refracted by a prism here, it looks like it is a wave.
And it has the properties of a wave.
It has a frequency and it has a wavelength.
And like other waves, the velocity, of that wave, is the frequency times its wave length [v = f * lambda]
Now, even within, even if you ignore this particle aspect of light
If you just look at the wave aspect of the light it's still fascinating because
most waves require a medium to travel through.
So for example: If I think about how
sound travels through air.
So let me draw a bunch of air particles.
Air particles right here
I'll draw a sound wave traveling through the air particles.
What happens in a sound wave is:
You compress some of the air particles
and those compress the ones next to them.
And so you have points in the air that have higher, I guess you could say, higher pressure
and points that have lower pressure,
and you can plot that.
So we have high pressure over here. High pressure, low pressure, high pressure, low pressure...
And as these things bump into each other and this wave essentially travels
to the right, and if you were to plot that
you would see this wave form traveling to the right.
But this is all predicated, or this is all based on this energy
traveling through a medium and I'm used to visualizing waves in that way but light NEEDS NO MEDIUM!
Light needs no medium
Light will actually travel fastest through nothing, through a vacuum.
And it will travel at an unimaginably fast speed: 3*10^8 m/s.
Just to give you a sense of this:
This is 300 million meters per second. Or another way
of thinking about it is: It would take light less than a
seventh of a second to travel around the earth, or
it would travel around the earth more then seven times in a second.
So unimaglably fast. And not only is this just a super fast rate,
or a super fast speed but once again
it tells us that light is something fundamental to our universe,
because it's not just an unimaginable fast speed, it is THE FASTEST speed,
not just known to physics, but POSSIBLE in physics.
So once again something very unintuitive to us in our everyday realm.
We always imagine that: "OK, if something is going at some speed,
maybe if there is a ant riding on top of that something
moving in the same direction it would be going even faster.
But nothing can go faster that the SPEED OF LIGHT.
It's absolutely impossible based on our current understanding of physics.
So its not just a fast speed it is THE FASTEST SPEED. It is the fastest speed possible
And this right here is an approximation,
it's actually 2.99 something, something times 10 to the 8th meters per second...
But 3 times 10 to the 8th is a pretty good approximation.
Now within the visible light spectrum and I'll talk about
whats beyond the visible light spectruum in a second.
You are probablly familiar with
colors and maybe you imagine it as a colors of rainbow,
and rainbow really happen because the light from the sun,
the white light, is being refracted by these little water particles.
and you can see that in a clearer way when you see
light being refracted by a prism right over here.
and the different wavelengths of light, so white light
contains all of the visible wavelengths.
But the different wavelengths get refracted differently by a prism.
So in this case the higher frequenty wavelengths,
the violet and the blue, get refracted more, its get bent,
it's direction gets bent more than the low frequency wavelengths,
than the reds and the oranges right over here
And if you want to look at the wavelength of light,
visible light, its between 400 nanometeres and 700 nanometers.
And the higher the frequency, the higher the energy of that light.
And that actually goes into, when you start talking
about the quantuum mechanics of it.
That the higher frequency means that each of these photons have higher energy.
They have a better ability to give kinetic energy to knock off electrons,
or whatever else they need to do.
So higher frequency, let me write that down:
[HIGHER FREQUNCY means HIGHER ENERGY]
Now, I keep referring to this idea of the visible light.
And you might say: "What is beyond visible light?"
And what you'll find is that light is just a part
of a much broader phenomenom that is just a part
that we happen to observe.
And if we want to broaden the discussion a little bit.
Visible light is just, really, part of the electromagnetic spectrum
So light is really just electromagentic radiation.
[Electromagnetic radiation]
And everything that I told you about light just now,
it has a wave property and it has particle properties,
This is not just specific to visible light.
This is true of all of electromagnetic radiation.
So at very low frequencies, or very long wavelengths,
we're talking about things like radio waves,
the things that allow radio to reach your car,
the things that allow your cell phone to
comunicate with cell towers.
Microwaves, the thing that start vibrating water molecules
in your food so that they heat up.
Infrared, wich is what our body realeses and thats
way you can detect people through walls with infrared cameras.
Visible light... Ultraviolet light, the UV light coming
from the sun that'll give you sunburn.
X-rays! The radiation that allows us to see through
the soft material and just visualize the bones.
Gamma rays! The super high energy that comes from quasars
and other certain types of physical phenomenons.
These are all the examples of the exact same thing!
We just happen to perceive certain frequencies of this as visible light!
And you might say: "Hey, Sal, how come
we only perceive certain frequancies of this?
How come we only see these frequencies?"
And I'll put these...
Literally we can see those frequencies with our unaided eye.
And the reason, or at least my best guess of the reason of that is:
That's the frequency where the sun dumps out a lot of electromagnetic radiation.
So its illumating the earth, and if
as a species you wanted to observe things
based on reflected energy, a reflected electromagnetic energy,
it is most usefull to be able to perceive the things
where there is the most electromagnetic radiation.
So it is possible that in other realities or other plantes
There are species that perceive more in the ultraviolet range,
or infrared range.
Or even on earth there are some
that perform better at either end of the range.
But we see really well in the part of the spectrum
where the sun just happens to dump a lot of radiation on us.
Now I'll leave you there, I think that's a pretty good overview of light.
And if any of this stuff seems kind of unintuitive or
daunting or really on some level confusing
this wave-particle duality, this idea of
of transfer of energy through nothing
and it seems unintuitive: Don't worry!
It seems unintuitive even for the best of physicists.
So you're already at the leading edge of physics thinking!