Alright, so this video introduces our projectile launcher.
It's a project that you can build, and we take you through step-by-step how to do that
in the next two videos.
But first, I wanna just show you some of the things it can do.
So, we're adjusting it to 60 degrees, taking it back to position four, and launching the
ping pong ball straight away into the trash can.
This one kinda fires off to the side, but we'll get it on the next go-around.
And, so, the launcher allows you to make the calculations for projectile motion come alive.
You can get a sense for how to make the projectile launch more accurate, and you
can get a sense for how different materials launch differently in the launcher.
You can see these hacky sacks don't do so well compared to the ping pong balls.
And the paper, also, was pretty inaccurate.
So it opens up the opportunity for a lot of conversation around those types of things.
You can look here once we've got the projectile angles and the nature of the projectile
figured out, we're able to knock the cans down, one right after another, with a high degree
of accuracy.
So we're gonna take out that Coke can right there.
Sal has done a great job of putting together a number of projectile motion videos
online, and you can take a look at how to do the calculations.
I'll have the links down below this video.
We went ahead and took this launcher out to the pool to see what we could do there.
To see if we could get the ping pong balls in the life preserver.
But, if you like launcher, watch the next two videos and we'll show you how to make it.