We've got 6798 minus 3359.
So let's see how far we can get with the subtraction.
So immediately when we're going to the one's place, we're going to subtract a 9 from an 8.
So we've immediately reached a little bit of a stumbling block.
And to see what our options are here in terms of regrouping I'm going to rewrite both of these numbers.
So I'm going to rewrite 6798 literally. So this is equal to 6 thousand, that's this right over here,
that's six thousand, plus seven hundred, plus ninety, plus eight, minus all of this.
So minus... So I can do it... I can subtract each of the places so I can say this is going to be
minus three thousand, minus three hundred, minus fifty, minus nine.
So there and here we're just explicitly showing what those place values represent:
A 6 in the thousand's place is 6000, a 3 in the hundred's place is 300.
Let's go back to our problem: We wanted to subtract a 9 from an 8.
Well, that's a little bit of a stumbling block, but what if we could take some of the value from some of these and give it to the 8?
In particular, we can go one place value up to the 90. And what if we would take 10 from the 90?
So let's do that. If we would take 10 from the 90 then 90 becomes 80.
But we don't want to change the value of the entire number so we're going to give that 10 to this 8.
So we're going to give that 10 to the 8. We're essentially regrouping right over here.
And then that 8 can become an 18. Notice, I did not change the value of the number.
I just essentially changed how it represented it.
Instead of saying it 6000 plus 700 plus 90 plus 8, I'm just saying that 6000 plus 700 plus 80 plus 18.
Those are both going to give you 6798.
But now it becomes a little bit easier for us to actually subtract.
Now if we subtract, I have 18 minus 9 which is 9. I have 80, not 90 now.
I have 80 minus 50 which is 30.
And these are all positive so this is plus 9, this is a positive 30.
80 minus 50 is 30.
I have 700 minus 300 which is 400, and I have 6000 minus 3000 which is 3000.
So this is literally going to be 3000 + 400 + 30 + 9 or 3439.
Now how would you do it if you didn't wanted to write it down like that?
And this is where you'll see a kind of shorthand notation, this is often called Borrowing.
So you see I've got an 8 in a one's place, I want to take a 10 from this 90 so it's going to become an 80.
But we will just write it as 8 because it's in the ten's place - this 8 represents the 80.
And I'm going to give that 10 to the one's place so 10 plus 8 is 18.
And now you can subtract. 18 minus 9 is 9, 8 minus 5 is 3, 7 minus 3 is 4, 6 minus 3 is 3.
Three thousand four hundred and thirty nine.