Part B. For x is not equal to zero, express f prime of x as a piecewise-defined function.
Find the value of x for which f prime of x is equal to negative 3.
So the first thing you might be wondering is why did we even have to take out x is equal to zero from the...
Or why, Why is the dervative not going to be defined there.
And that's just because you're going to see the derivative is going to be something different when we approach
x is equal to zero from the left verses when we approach x is equal to zero from the right.
And that's why they just took it out of there for us.
But let's just figure out what that derivative is for all of the other values for x.
So f prime of x is equal to...
So for x is less than zero, we're going to take the derivative of this first case...
So the derivative of one is just zero, the derivative of negative 2 sine of x...
Well the derivative of sine of x is just cosine of x. So it's going to be negative 2 cosine of x.
Negative 2 cosine of x, for, for x is less than zero. And then for x is greater than zero...
I'll do this in another color, I'll do it in orange...
We have this case right over here and we'll just do the chain rule.
Derivative of negative 4 x with respect to x is negative 4.
And the derivative of e to the negative 4 x with respect to e... wait wait,...
The derivative of e to the negative 4 x with respect to negative 4 x is just e to the negative 4 x.... e to the negative 4 x.
Sometimes you can say this is the derivative of the inside times the derivative of the outside with respect to the inside.
So either way, it's negative 4 e to the negative 4 x for x is greater than zero.
So we did the first part: we expressed f prime of x as a piecewise-defined function. It's not... we didn't define the derivative...
Actually I forgot a parenthesis here. We didn't derive... we didn't define the derivative when x is equal to zero...
Cause it's actually not going to be defined there. Now let's do the second part...
Find the value of x for which f prime of x is equal to negative 3.
And so, if this wasn't piecewise-defined, you'd just, you'd just very simply just say, oh look, f prime of x is equal to negative 3...
You would take whatever f prime of x is equal to and you would do some algebra to solve for it.
But here you're like, which case do I use? I don't know if the x that gets us to negative 3 is going to be less than 0 or I don't know if it's going to be greater than 0.
So I don't know which case to use. And one thing that they realize is to... is to look at these functions a little bit...
...and realize that cosine of x is a bounded function.
Cosine of x can only go between positive 1 and negative 1. So negative 2 cosine of x can only go between positive 2 and negative 2.
So this can only go between positive 2 and negative 2, so it can never get to negative 3.
So if anything is ever going to get to negative 3, it's going to be this part of the derivative or this part of the derivative definition.
So it's going to have to be this thing right over here.
And hopefully there's some values of x greater than zero where this thing right over here is equal to negative 3.
So let's try it out. Negative four e to the negative 4 x needs to be equal to negative 3.
We can divide both sides by negative 4, we get e to the negative 4 x is equal to negative 3/4ths divided by negative 4 is 3/4ths.
We can take the natural log of both sides and we will get negative 4 x is equal to the natural log of 3/4ths... natural log of 3/4ths.
And just to be clear what I did here, I mean you literally could put the natural log here, natural log there, and...
you could put the natural log there as well to see that step. The natural... this is saying what power,
What power do I have to raise e to, to get e to the negative 4 x. Well obviously I just need to raise
e to the just... the negative 4 x power over there. So this, this power is negative 4 x.
And then we just took the natural log of the right hand side as well. And then to solve for x you can divide both sides by negative 4.
So you get x is equal to... or we... or we could say... we could multiple both sides by negative 1/4th... either way....
Negative one fourth natural log of 3/4ths. And what we need to do is verify that this x...
So we used this case right over here. We used that case. But we have to make sure that this x, that this, that we can use this case...
That this x is greater than zero, and we might be tempted right when we look at this, say wait wait...,
This looks like a negative number, But we have to remind ourselves that the natural log of 3/4ths,
Since 3/4ths is less than e, the natural log of 3/4ths is going to be a negative number.
It's going to be e to some negative exponent. So since this is negative, and ... and this part right over here is negative,
So that is also negative, you have a negative times a negative so this right over here is goign to be positive.
So this is a positive value right over here, so you would use, you would use, you would use
this case right over here so that's our answer: x is equal to negative 1/4th natural log of 3/4ths.
Or the derivative we could write f prime of -1/4 times the natural log of 3/4ths is equal to... is equal to negative 3. And we're done.