In your mathematical careers, you might encounter people who say it is wrong to say that 'i' is equal to the principal square root of negative 1.
And if you ask them why is this wrong, they'll show up with this kind of line of logic that actually seems pretty reasonable.
They will tell you that, "Okay. Well, let's just start with -1.
We know from definition that -1 is equal to i times i. Everything seems pretty straightforward right now." And then they'll say,
"Well look, if you take this, if you assume this part right here, then we can
replace each of these i's with the square root of negative 1" And they'd be right.
So this would be the same thing as the square root of negative 1 times the square root of negative 1.
And then they would tell you that, "Hey, look, just from straight-up properties of the principal square root function,
they'll tell you the square root of a times b is the same thing as the principal square root of a, times the principal square root of b.
And so, if you have the principal square root of a times the principal square root of b, that's the same thing as square root a times b
so based on this property of the radical of the principal root, they'll say this over here is the same thing as
the squrae root of negative 1 times negative 1 if I have the principal root of the product of 2 things that's the same
thing as the the product of each of their principal roots
I am doing this in other order here.
here I had the principal root of the products, over here I have this on the right and then from that
we all know that negative 1 times negative 1 is 1 so this should be equal to the principal square root of 1
and then the principal squre root of 1, remember this radical means
principal squre root, positive
squre root that is just going to be positive 1 and
they'll say this is wrong. clearly negative 1 and positive 1 are not the same thing
and therefore you can't make the subtitution that we did in this step and you should then point out is
that, this was not the incorrect step that it is true that negative 1 is not equal to 1 but the faulty line of reasoning here was
in using this propperty
when both a and b are negative, if both a and b are negative this will
never be true, so a and b both can not be negative infact normaly when this property is given,
sometimes is given a little bit in footnotes you might not even notice it because its not relevant when you
learning it in the first time but usually they give a little bit of construct there, they usually say for
a and b greater than or equal to zero so thats where they listes property this is true for a and b be
greater or equal to zero and in particular it's false if both a and b are negative, Now I've said
that, I've just spend lat three minutes saying that people who tell you this is wrong are wrong but with
that I said I do say you have to be a little bit careful about it, when we take traditional principal
square roots so you take thi principal square root of 4, we know this is positive 2 that 4 actually
has two square roots, negative 2 ia also a square root of 4, if you have negative 2 times negaive 2
is also equal to 4, this radical symbol here means principal square root or when we just dealing with
real numbers non imaginary non complex numbers you can
really ??? as positive
square root, this is two square roots, positive and negative 2 if you have this radical symbol right here, principal square roots it
means the positive square root of 2. So when you start thinking about taking square roots of negative
numbers or even in the future you'll do imaginary numbers and complex numbers and all the rest you have
to expend the definition of what this radical means, so when you are taking the square root
of really of any negative number you'll really saying this is no longer the traditional principal
square root function you've now talking this is the principal complex square root function, this is now
to find for complex inputs or the domain it can also generate imaginary or complex output or you
should call that the range and if you assume that, then really straight from this you get that the
square root of negative x is going to be equal to i times the square root of x and this is only and i'm
going to make this clear because I just told you that this will be false if both a and b are negative,
so this is only true, so we can apply this we can apply this we can apply when x is greater than or equal to
zero, so if x is greater than or equal to zero the negative x is clearly a negative number or I guess
it can be zero, it's a negative number and then we can apply this right over here if x was less than
zero then we'll be doing all of this nonesense up here and we will start to get nonesense equal
answeres and if you look at it this way you'll say hey look i can be the square of negative 1 if we were
taking the if it's the principal branch of the complex square root function, then you could
rewrite this right over here as square root of negative 1 times the square root of x and so really,
the real fault in this logic when people say hey negative 1 can't be equal to 1, the real faughlt is
using this property, when both a and b when both of these are negative numbers that will come up with
something that is unambiguously false, if you expend the definition of complex or expend the definition of
principle root include negative numbers in the domain and including and to include imaginary
numbers then you can do this you can say the the square root of negative x is the qsuare root of
negative 1 times or instead (say) the principle square root of negative x, I should be particulare in my
words, is the same thing as the principal square root of negative 1 times the principal square root of x
when x is greater than or equal to zero and I don't want confuse you, if x is greater than or equal to
zero this is clearly, this negative x, that is clearly negative or I guess you say a non positive number.