We have to simplify the principal square root of -52 and we're going to assume because we have a negative
52 here inside of the radical then this is the principal branch of the complex square root function
that we can actually input negative numbers in the domain of this function
that we can actually get the imaginary or complex result.
So we can rewrite negative 52 as negative 1 times 52.
So this can be rewritten as the principal square root of negative 1 times 52.
And then if we assume that this is the principal branch of the complex square root function,
we can rewrite this -- this is going to be equal to the square root of negative 1 times the principal --
or I should've say the principal square root of negative 1 times the principal square root of 52.
Now, I want to be very, very clear here.
You can do what we just did if we have the principal square root of the product of two things.
We can rewrite that as the principal square root of each and then we take the product, but you can only do this --
or I should've say you can only do this if either both of these numbers are positive or only one of them is negative.
You cannot do this if both of these were negative.
For example: you cannot do this.
You cannot say the principal square root of 52 is equal to negative 1 times negative 52.
You could do this so far; I haven't said anything wrong. 52 is definitely negative 1 times negative 52,
but then since these are negative, you cannot then say that this is equal to
the square root of negative 1 times the square root of negative 52.
In fact, I invite you to continue on this train of reasoning here,
and we're going to get a nonsensical answer.
This is not okay. You can not do this right over here, and the reason why you can not do this is that
this property does not work when both of these numbers are negative.
Now that said we can do it if only one of them are negative or both of them are positive on this thing.
Now, the principal square root of negative 1, if we're talking about the principal branch of the complex square root function, is i.
So this right over here does simplify to i. And let's see if we can simplify the square root of 52, any.
And to do that, we can, well, think about its prime factorization;
see if we have any perfect square sitting in there. So 52 is 2 times 26, and 26 is 2 times 13.
So we have 2 times 2 there, or 4 there, which is a perfect square.
So we can rewrite this as equal to (this is equal to) -- well, we have our i now.
Square root of -- the principal square root of negative 1 is i; the other square root of negative 1 is negative i.
The principal square root of negative 1 is i, and then we're going to multiply that times the square root of 4 times 13.
4 times 13. And this is equal to i times the square root of 4 -- principal square root of 4
times the principal square root of 13. The principal square root of 4 is 2, so this all simplifies --
and we can switch the order over here -- this is equal to 2 times the square root of 13 --
2 times the principal square root of 13, I should say, times i.
And I just switched around the order; makes it a little bit more easier to read if I put i after the numbers over here,
but I'm just multiplying i times 2 times the square root of 13;
this is the same thing as multiplying 2 times the principal square root of 13 times i.
And I think this is about as simplified as we can get here.