I am here with Dr. Lawrence Baker
from Stanford Medical School,
who specializes in healthcare policy,
and I have just a very basic question:
and that is we see these BlueCross and BlueShield
all of the time and sometimes are used together.
Sometimes are used differently.
This seems confusing to me.
What are these things
and how are they related to each other?
Dr. Baker: They're related in some really interesting ways.
They go way back in time ...
So BlueCross and BlueShield began as separate things.
Let's see if I can get this right.
BlueShield was started by doctors
who wanted to set up a Healthcare plan
and to help their patients get coverage for healthcare
(Sal Khan: preventive shields - right right).
So that was started longtime ago:
these both go back BlueShield and BlueCross
to the 1930s really they're getting started.
BlueCross was started by the hospitals
separately from BlueShield originally.
They get together later as a way
to help patients to get coverage for hospital care.
Sal: I guess the cross is because once you're in the hospital
you might get a little religious.
Dr. Baker: Exactly! I mean not sure
if that's why they had in mind originally but...
Sal: But what about the BLUE?
Dr. Baker: I don't know where the BLUE comes from.
Sal: Is that just the color that makes people feel good?
It's like a healthcare color?
Dr. Baker: think it must be healthcare color.
Sal: Red would be inappropriate.
Dr. Baker: Let's go with blue. Blue is.. you're not bleeding.
Sal: Exactly! Blue is...you look at the sky. OK!
What happens I do see these words used together.
So these were separate plans?
Doctors created the BlueShield,
Hospitals created the BlueCross.
Dr. Baker: and then they grew over time and changed.
So they got started in the 30s,
they were..around through the 40s, 50s, 60s, 70s..
and so a couple of things happened along the way
that starts to make things confusing a little bit.
One is that they're operating in every state,
to some extent independently.
So states regulate health insurance in this country or..
have a lot to do with regulating health insurance in this country.
And so every state had its own laws and as a result..
the BlueCross and the BlueShield plans in different states
grew up in different ways.
So what you come down to today is really different plans..
in every state because of this history of development.
As states developed their laws differently,
the plans would evolve in the different states separately.
Sal: I see, just to give myself a kind of framework of
what was happening is in the pre 1920s, early 1930s:
there were not really weren't healthcare plans,
the physicians say, hey we want people to have a way
for people to see us without having to, you know,
someway for them to be paying a little bit every month
or every year and that is,
if something would happen, they can see the doctors.
The hospitals kind of have the same model but
they did it differently in every state,
because the state is the regulatory.
Dr. Baker: The state, especially in the 1930s,
there weren't a lot of state regulations
about the health insurance.
There wasn't health insurance. But as states evolved,
as their healthcare system evolved, as their plans evolved,
it grew separately
in slightly different directions in every state.
So that led to the formation- really of you see..
BlueCross of Tennessee or BlueShield of Florida,
BlueCross/BlueShield of Michigan.
They are all different
because they are all in their own state environment.
Sal: So this is normally these kinds of brands,
we all have heard of them in that way.
But normally a brand means something.
It means more quality or less quality.
But in...or some type of spin on....you know
Apple means fun consumer experience
or something like that.
But in this case - if I'm hearing you correctly
If there's BlueCross of California and BlueCross of Texas:
they have nothing to do with each other
or very little to do with each other?
Dr. Baker: So they all had their start kind of together in the 30s,
and then they've all grown in their own ways.
But they've stayed related and
some of them to greater extents than others.
So one of the things that happened, along the way,
was that they formed an association.
There's now something in the US called
the BlueCross/BlueShield Association.
Which is - I guess -
an association of a lot of the plans in different states
that allows them to talk to each other,
to try to work together.
Sal: This is an umbrella
for all of the BlueCross and all of the BlueShield.
So that's why we hear them used so frequently together,
people say: BlueCross/BlueShield.
Dr. Baker: Yeah, so there are 2 reasons
that you hear that together.
One is the Association that tries
to work with plans from both groups.
The other is that in some states, over time,
the 2 got together
and actually became 1 health insurance plan.
So there are states where the health insurance plan
is BlueCross and BlueShield of a state.
And there are other states where they stayed separate.
So, we're here in California
where BlueShield and BlueCross
have historically stayed as separate plans.
But there are some states where they're the same thing
and then you hear BlueCross and BlueShield.
Sal: So if someone tells you BlueCross of State X,
that just means to you Health Insurance Plan.
There is nothing else that you can really take from that.
Dr. Baker: So once upon a time,
you may have been able to take more from it.
But these days...
it's possible for them to vary in quite a few different ways.
Some of the BlueCross and BlueShield plans -
especially the BlueCross plans
have become 'for-profit' plans.
So historically these were always non-profit, but in the last..
Sal: So, BlueCross especially:
some of them have gone for-profit?
Dr. Baker: Yes, but I think in both cases.
But BlueCross is the one that I pay more attention to.
Sal: Right.
Dr. Baker: So they may be for-profit or not-for-profit plans.
They may act in similar ways,
and they do because the Association
- at least the ones in the Association -
tend to act with some similarity from place to place.
Sal: and just to - because I've explained this all the time -
about even Khan Academy is a not-for-profit.
A not-for-profit is an entity, it can in theory charge revenue.
Khan Academy doesn't. But it could charge revenue
but there is no owner of the organization
who can, kind of, become rich off of it.
It is owned by the public.
While for-profit has shareholders
and it can be bought and sold
and issue dividends and all the rest.
Dr. Baker: Yes, so historically in America,
most healthcare plans were not-for-profit entities.
They couldn't take money that they earned and
give it out to people who might be the owners
- it had to be reinvested.
In fact even in the early days of BlueCross and BlueShield
in some states they were treated as quasi public entities,
and they've kind of grown away from that a bit more.
But there's this history,
especially with BlueCross and BlueShield,
a very not-for-profit public spirited entities.
When you get to for-profit plans,
which we really didn't have in the US in a big way
until maybe the last decade or two.
Where we've seen some conversions,
these are situations where the plan can act explicitly
as a profit generator for its shareholders, for its owners.
Sal: Right and some are now publicly traded
and they're on the stock exchange.
And so when we talk about some of them
becoming for-profit here,
it's that, literally, the license to use the name
either BlueCross or BlueShield,
or maybe some of the assets of the former not-for-profit
are somehow transferred.. or,
I guess, the for-profit buys them.
Dr. Baker: So we had a series of these things.
We call them conversions:
when the company converted
from being a not-for-profit to a for-profit.
There were a lot of states in which
those conversions, or situations in which they happen,
where the public - the government -
somebody compelled the for-profit entity
in the conversion to create a public good.
So there are some foundations that now exist but..
Sal: Oh, I see.
Dr. Baker: In the conversion,
they allowed a transfer of not-for-profit to for-profit
but you had to create something valuable for the public.
So some of the things that we see now in states:
some of the big foundations that exist in healthcare
are conversion foundations
around the for-profit conversions of..
Sal: I see. But, when we see things like,
I always get confused between BlueCross and BlueShield,
but I believe that Anthem has a Blue...
Dr. Baker: BlueCross in California.
So Anthem is a company that is - well
it is a large company that has BlueCross,
I think mostly BlueCross or all BlueCross,
affiliates or sub-entities in different states.
I think that they have 14 or 15.
Sal: Right, so these are for-profit BlueCrosses,
if they have Anthem with them?
Dr. Baker: I believe that's correct.
Sal: Right, right.
And, is there any, I guess how they operate,
from a consumer point of view, any difference
between a for-profit BlueCross or BlueShield?
Anything that we can tell?
Dr. Baker: So that's a really interesting question.
There are people who've gone to look and
they've tried to, sometimes,
find some evidence for differences.
There are a few studies out there where
people can find some differences but
there is not a lot of evidence
that they behave really differently.
At the end of the day,
they have to compete in the same market place
for the business of the same companies, the same people.
And if they behave really obviously different:
if one was obviously way better than the other,
the market would sort out who is going to win this.
And the market has allowed both types to exist.
So, there are certainly differences
in the written charters and
maybe differences in the preferences in the stated ideals
of the people who run these organizations
and that might make a difference in some cases.
But it is hard when you aggregate it all together and
you really go try to do national data or something
to find a big difference.
Sal: So the big picture here is,
as much as I've looked at healthcare plans even when
we're trying to figure out for employees at Khan Academy,
which healthcare plan to choose and which not.
And I've thought: Oh,
what's the difference between BlueCross and BlueShied?
There's actually very little that I can tell
just by looking at those brands.
I really have to dig deeper
into the actually healthcare policy.
That's going to be different from state to state.
Some will be for-profit, some will be not-for-profit,
and even that's not enough to tell you.
General rule of thumb:
you really have to look at the healthcare plans.
Dr. Baker: You have to look at the healthcare plans
and it's BlueCross and BlueShield, but
there's other plans out there.
There's Kaiser around here.
There's Aetna and Cigna and other plans.
And they can vary from state to state and
even within, you can see variations.
So BlueCross in California or BlueShield in California
might offer some different types of choices.
So if you said that I've got a really nice plan from BlueCross
and I look at another state and you look at a BlueCross plan
it might be that you're just looking at a less generous one,
where there is another you could look at.
So you even need to look within a company at the specifics.
Sal: Definitely when we go from state to state,
it would be weird to have brand loyalty.
Dr. Baker: Yeah, BlueCross and BlueShield have
this history of being public spirited entities
and some of that persists to this day.
Maybe that is something to think about but
in a general sense,
there are so many things that they can vary on
that you'd want to be very careful
with any choice you're making
and know that it can really vary across state lines.
Sal: Interesting.