I always rush those videos at the end because right when
I YouTube 10 minute limit,
but I just want to make sure that you understand what I did.
I used the first few examples-
and essentially what they told us--
to figure out an equation that tells me well,
if I know the term t, how do I get the t'th term, right?
Actually,it works here too.We could write 8 plus 9 t minus 1.
Because here, this is the first term, so this t minus 1 term
goes to 0, and that's why we only have 8.
And it works on all of these,and it makes sense.
Every term is going to be 9 more than the previous one.
We start at 8, and the reason why it's t minus 1 instead of t
is because we only start adding 9 after the first term.
For example, if this was actually 9, 18, 27,
if we just went like that,
we could've just said it's 9 times t, right?
That could have been the formula.
Or we could've said 9 plus 9 times t minus 1.
These would have been the same thing. But it started at 8,
so that's why we had to make it a little bit more cloogy.
Hopefully that explains it a little bit better.
Let's do the next problem. Problem six I will do in yellow.
They draw a bunch of lines,so they draw three lines.
One line, two lines, then we have a third line.
OK, so this is s degrees, r degrees, t degrees, z degrees,
y and x degrees.
Three lines intersect in a point as shown in the figure above
Which of the following pairs of angle measures
is not sufficient for determining all six angle measures?
Is not, so they're going to make us go through all of them.
Hopefully one of the early choices. So choice a, t and z.
So I'm going to do choice a in this brown color.
So choice a, t and z.
Well first of all, if I know t,
I immediately know z because they're opposite angles, right?
So I could figure out that. I could figure out that.
Well if I know either of those,I could then figure out
let's see, in order to do anything from here,
I need to know one of the other angles.
And this is actually the way you should think about it.
t and z only gives us the relationship between these two
purple lines, right?
It essentially tells us at what angle these two purple
lines intersect.
But it gives us no information about the angle that
this yellow line intersects, right?
Think about it, if I welded these purple lines together,
I could still move this yellow line around without
changing t or z.
So there's no way just knowing t or z I can figure out
what angle this yellow line is at.
And if you did the other choices, you could try it out.
For example, if I didn't know t and instead they told me r,
then I would be in business.
If I knew r, for example, then I could use the fact that s,
r, and z all form one line. And I could figure out s.
If I knew z,
then I could figure out t because they're opposite
If I know r, I could figure out s because they're opposite.
And then if I knew s, I could figure out y, right?
So z and t alone will not help you, so our choice is a.
And normally on the SAT when they give you something where
you have to kind of try out every choice they give you,
it's normally going to be one of the first choices because
they try to make the questions as fast as possible.
They don't want you to waste too much time.
If you ever see yourself wasting too much time on a question,
you're not necessarily doing it wrong,
but you may not be doing it the quickest possible way.
Problem number seven.
The sum of two numbers that differ by one is t.
So let's call those two numbers x and y.
We know that the sum of x plus y is equal to t.
But we also know that the numbers differ by 1.
And then they say in terms of t,
what is the value of the greater of the two numbers.
So let's just assume that x is greater than y.
Let's just write x is greater than y.
So that means that x minus y is going to be equal to what?
Well they told us that the sum of two numbers
that differ by 1.
So x is actually exactly 1 more than y.
So that when I subtract y from x I get 1.
So if I want to know the value of the greater of the two
numbers I defined x, actually,
as the greater of the two numbers
I just have to solve the system of equations for x.
So let's add the two equations. x plus x is 2x.
What's y plus negative y? Well, they cancel out, right? 0.
Then what's t plus 1? Well it's t plus 1.
And now to solve for x, you get x is equal to
divide both sides by 2 or multiply by 1/2-- t plus 1 over 2.
And we are done. And that is choice c. Next problem.
Problem number eight. This color is getting obnoxious.
OK, number of siblings per student in a preschool class.
So let me draw this chart.
So this is number of siblings,number of students.
The table above shows how many students in a class of
12 preschoolers had 0, 1,2, or 3 siblings.
OK, right, I haven't actually included the information.
0, 1, 2, 3.
So 3 kids had 0 siblings, 6 kids had 1 sibling,
2 kids had 2 siblings, and then 1 kid had 3 siblings.
Later, a new student joined the class, and the average
number of siblings per student became equal to the median
number of siblings per student.
How many siblings did the new student have? Fascinating.
OK, so let's say the new student has x siblings.
x siblings is how many the new student has.
So we don't know where the new student falls in, but let's
figure out where the average and the median are before the
student even joins. So the median number of siblings.
The average number of siblings per student became
equal to the median number of siblings per student.
So what is the average number of siblings per student?
We just add the number of siblings for all of the students,
so we should get 12 terms. So we can multiply 3 times 0
that's essentially 0 plus 0 plus 0-- plus 6 times 1,
plus 2 times 2, plus 3 times 1, divided by 12.
This is the current average of siblings per student.
This is 0, so this equals 6 plus 4 plus 3 over 12,
which is what? 10,10,this 13.
This equals 13/12,which is 1 1/12.
So before this new student joins, there's 1 1/12.
This is the average.
That's before the new student joins.
What's the median?
Let's list out all of the-- let me do it in another color
because I'm running out of space-- so I have a 0, 0, 0,
there are three students with 0.
Then you have 6 students with 1. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
Then you have how many students with 2?
2, 2. And then one student with 3.
So there are 12 terms in all,and what's the middle one?
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. So the middle term is 6.
So the median before that student joined is 1, right?
And the average before that student joined
is a little bit over one, it's 1 1/12.
So the only way that you can bring the average down--
right, because that's essentially what we have to do,
this new student-- to bring this average down,
he either has to have 1 sibling or 0 siblings.