I would guess that you are reasonably familiar
with linear scales.
These are the scales that you would typically see in most of your math classes,
and so just to make sure we know what we are talking about
and maybe thinking about in a slightly different way
let me draw a linear number line.
Let me start with the zero
and what we are going to do is we are gonna say:
look if I move this distance right over here
and if I move that distance to the right, that's equivalent to adding 10
so if you start at zero and you add 10, that will obviously get you a 10
If If you move that distance to the right again, you're gonna add 10 again
that will get you to 20
and obviously we could keep doing it and get to 30, 40, 50 so on and so forth
and also just looking at what we did here
if we go the other direction
if we start here and move that same distance to the left
we're clearly subtracting 10
10 minus 10 is equal to zero
so if we move that distance to the left again,
we would get to negative 10 and if we did it again we would get to negative 20
so the general idea is, however many times we move that distance
we are essentially adding or how many times we move that distance to the right
we are essentially adding that multiple of ten
if we move to it twice, we're adding 2 times 10
and that not only works for whole numbers, it would work for fractions as well
where would 5 be?
Well, to get to 5, we only have to multiply 10
or I guess one way to think about it is 10 or rather
one way to think about it is 5 is half of 10
and so if we want to only go half of ten
we only have to go half this distance
so if we go half this distance,
if we go half this distance
that will get us to one half times ten
In this case that would be five
If we go the left
that would get us to negative five
and there's nothing,
let me draw that a little bit more centered, negative five
and there's nothing really new here
we're just kinda thinking about it in a slightly novel way that's going to be useful
when we start thinking about logarithm
but this is just the number line that you've always known
if we want to put one here, we'd move one tenth of the distance
cause one is one tenth of ten
So this would be 1,2,3,4
I could just put
I could
I could label frankly any, any number right over here
Now this was the situation when we add 10 or subtract 10
but it's completely legitimate to have an alternate way of thinking of what you do when you move this distance
and let's think about that
so let's say i have another line over here
and you might guess this is going to be the logarithmic number line
we give ourselves some space
and let's start this logarithmic number line at 1
and I'll let you think about, after this video, why I didn't start it at zero
and if you start at 1
and instead of moving that
so I'm still going to define that same distance
that same distance
it's gonna be a little smaller
i'm still gonna to define that same distance
but instead of saying that that same distance is adding 10
when I move to the right
I'm gonna say when I move to the right
that distance when I move to the right on this new number line that I've created
that is the same thing as multiplying by 10
so if I move that distance
I start at 1
I multiply by 10
that gets me to
that gets me to 10!
and then if I multiply by 10 again
if i multiply by 10 again
If I move by that distance again,
I'm multiplying by 10 again
and so that would get me to 100
and I think you can already see the difference that's happening
and what about moving to the left that distance?
Well we already kind have said what happens
cause if start here
we start at a 100
and move to the left by that distance
What happens?
Well, I divided by 10
100 divide by 10 gets me 10
10 divided by 10 gives me 1
and so if I move that distance to the left again
I'll divide by 10 again
that will get me to
one tenth
and if I move that distance to the left again
that will get me to one over a hundred
and so the general idea is
is however many times I move that distance to the right
I'm multiplying my starting point by 10 that many times
and so for example
when I move that distance twice
so this whole distance right over here
I went that distance twice
so this is times 10 times 10
which is the same thing as times 10 to the second power
and so really, i'm raising 10
I'm multiplying it, times 10 to whatever power however many times i'm jumping to the right
Same thing
If I go to the left that distance twice
Let me do that in a new colour
this will be the same thing as dividing by 10 twice
dividing by 10, dividing by 10
which is the same thing as multiplying by,
well one way to think of it
1/10²
or dividing by 10²
is another way of thinking about it
and so that might make a little
you know
that might be, hopefully, a little bit intuitive
and you can already see why this is valuable
we can already, on this number line,
plot a much broader spectrum of things
than we can on this number line
we can go all the way up to a 100
and then we even get some nice granularity
if we want to go down to one tenth and one hundredth
here we don't get the granularity at small scales
and we also don't get to go to really large numbers
and if we go a little distance more
we get to 1000 and then we get to 10000 so on and so forth
so we can really cover a much broader spectrum on this line right over here
but what's also neat about this
is that when you move a fixed distance
so when you move a fixed distance on this linear number line
you are adding or subtracting that amount
so if you move that fixed distance you are adding to, to the right
if yo go to the left you're subtracting to
when you do the same thing on a logarithmic number line
and this is true of any logarithmic number line
you will be scaling by a fixed factor
and one way to think about what that fixed factor is
is this idea of exponents
so if you wanted to say
Where would 2 sit on this number line?
Then you would just think to yourself
well if i asked myself, where does 100 sit on that number line?
and actually, that might be a better place to start
if i said, If I hadn't already plot it
Where does 100 sit on that number line?
I'd say, how many times do I have to multiply 10 by itself to get 100?
and that's how many times I need to move this distance
and so essentially I would be asking
10 to the what power is equal to 100
and then I would get that 'question mark' is equal to 2
and then I would move that many spaces to plot my 100
another way of stating this exact same thing is
log base 10 of 100 is equal to 'question mark'
and this 'question mark' is clearly equal to 2
and that says I need to plot 100 to 2 of this distance to the right
and to figure out where would I plot the 2 I would do the same exact same thing
I would say
10 to what power is equal to 2?
or log base 10 of 2 is equal to what?
and we can get the trusty calculator out
and we can just say log
and on most calculators it's just a log without the base specified
they're assuming base 10
so log of 2 is equal to roughly 0.3
0.301
so this is equal to 0.301
so what this tells us is
we need to move this fraction of this distance to get to 2
If we move this whole distance
it's like multiplying 10 times 10 to the first power
but since we only get 10 to the 0.301 power, we only want to do 0.301 of this distance
so it's going to be roughly a third of this
so let me
it's going to be roughly
actually a little less than a third
0.3 not 0.33
so 2 is going to sit
2 is going to
let me do it a little more to the right
so 2 is going to sit right over here
now what's really cool about it is
this distance in general, on this logarithmic number line
means multiplying by 2
and so if you go that same distance again
you're gonna get to 4
if you multiply that same distance again, you're going to multiply by 4
and if you go that same distance again, you are going to get to 8
and so if you said well
Where would I plot 5 on this number line?
Well there's a couple of ways to do it.
You could really figure out what the base 10 logarithm of 5 is
and figure out where it goes on the number line
or you could say look!
If I start at 10
and if I move this distance to the left
I'm going to be dividing by 2
so if I move this distance to the left I will be dividing by 2
I know it's getting a little bit messy here
i'll maybe do another video where we learn how to draw a clean version of this
so if I start at 10 and then go that same distance I'm dividing by 2
and so this right here would be
that right over there would be 5
Now the next question you say
Where do I plot 3?
Well we can do the exact same thing that we did with 2
we ask ourselves
what power do we have to raise 10 to, to get to 3
and to get that
we once again get our calculator out
log base 10 of 3 is equal to 0.477
so it's almost halfway
so it's almost going to be half of this distance
so half of that distance is gonna look something like right over there
so 3 is going to go right over here
and you could do the logarithm
let's see we're missing 6, 7 and 8
oh we have 8
we're missing 9
so then to get 9, we just have to mutiply by 3 again
so this is 3
and if we go that same distance
we multiply by 3 again
9 is gonna be squeezed in right over here
9 is gonna be squeezed in right over there
and if we wanna get to 6
we just have to multiply by 2
and we already know the distance to multiply by 2
it's this thing right over here
so you multiply that by 2
you do that same distance and you're gonna get to 6
and if you wanted to figure out where 7 is
once again you could take the log
let me do it right over here
so you take the log of 7
it is going to be roughly 0.85
so 7 is just going to be squeezed in
roughly right over there
so a couple of neat things you already appreciated
one, we can fit more on this logarithmic scale
and, as i did with the video with Vi Hart
where she talked about how we perceive many things with logarithmic scales
so that is actually a good way to even understand some of human perception
but the other really cool thing is when we move a fixed distance on this logarithmic scale
we are multiplying by a fixed constant
now the one kind of strange thing about this and you might have already noticed here
is that we don't see the numbers lined up the way we normally see them
there is a big jump from 1 to 2
then a smaller jump from 3 to 4
then a smaller jump from that from 3 to 4
then even smaller from 4 to 5
then even smaller from 5 to 6
and then 7, 8, 9
7 is gonna be right in there
it gets squeezed squeezed squeezed in
tighter and tighter and tighter
and then you get 10
and then you get another big jump
because once again if you wanna get to 20, you just have to multiply by 2
you just have to multiply by 2 again
so this distance again gets us to 20
if you go this distance over here that will get you to 30
cause you're multiplying by 3
so this right over here is our times 3 distance
so if you do that again, if you do that distance
then that gets you to 30
you're multiplying by 3
and then you could plot the whole same thing over here again
but hopefully this gives you a little bit more intuition of why logarithmic number lines
look the way they do
or why logarithmic scale looks the way it does
and also it gives you a little bit of appreciation for why they might be useful.