We're asked to divide and simplify.
And we have one radical expression over another radical expression. The key
to simplify this is to realize I have the principal square root of x
over the principal root of y, this is the same thing
as the principal root of x over y.
And this really comes out of the exponent properties. If I have two things,
that I take to the some power, and taking the principal root is the same thing as taking it to the
one-half power. If I'm raising them to some power, and then
dividing, that's the same thing as dividing first, and then raising them
to that power. So let's apply that over here.
This expression over here is going to be the same thing as the principal root,
the principal - it's hards to write a radical sign that big - the principal root of
sixty x-squared y over forty-eight x.
And then we can first look at the coefficient terms, or the coefficients of, each of
these expressions, and try to simplify that. Both the numerator and
and the denominator is divisible by twelve, sixty divided by
twelve is five, forty-eight divided by twelve is four.
Both the numerator and denominator is divisible by x.
X-squared, divided by x is just x.
X divided by x is 1. Anything we divide the numerator by, we have to divide the
denominator by, and that's all we have left. So, if we want
to simplify this, this becomes, this is equal to, -the- -the-
Make the radical sign.
And then we have five-fourth's,
five-fourth's
And actually we can write it in a slightly different way, but I'll write it this way, five-fourth's, and we have
nothing left in the denominator other than that four, and in the numerator we have an x, and we have
a y. We have an x and we have a y.
And, now, we could it just like that,
but we might want to take more things out of the radical sign. And so one possibility
that you can do, is that you can say that this is really the same thing as
this is equal one-fourth times five, times five xy,
all of that under the radical sign,
and this is the same thing as the square root of, or the principal square root of,
one-fourth times the principal root of
five xy, and the square root of one-fourth. If you think about it, that's just
one-half times one-half. Or another way you could think about it is, this is the same thing,
this right here is the same thing as -
So you could just say that this is one-half, one-half times one-half is one-fourth.
Or if you don't realize it's one-half, you say, hey, this is the same thing as the square root of one over
the square root of four, and the square root of one is one,
and the square root - the principal root of four is two, so you
get one-half once again. And so if you simplify this right here to one-half,
then the whole thing can simplify to one-half times
the principal root.
I'll just write it all in a orange, times the principal root of
five xy, and there's nothing else that you can really take out of the radical time here.
Nothing else here is a perfect square.