Let's see if we can write the fraction "11 over 25" (or we can call it "eleven twenty-fifths") to see if we can write that as a decimal
and we're gonna round it to the nearest thousands place.
And so another way of viewing this, eleven over twenty-five,
this is the same thing as eleven divided by twenty-five,
so we can literally say, we can literally divide 25 into 11 and whatever we get
that is going to be the decimal representation of 11/25.
And, since we're going to go into the places less than the ones place
we're gonna go into the tenths place and the hundredths place and the thousandths place,
let's add some zeroes to this eleven right over here after the decimal
and now let's start to divide.
25 doesn't go into 1
25 doesn't go into 11.
25 does go into 110.
So, when 25 goes into 110 four times (4 x 25 is 100), so it goes into it 4 times
let's keep the decimal up here, so we'll write 0.4
4 times 25 is 100, and now we can subtract: 110 minus 100 is 10.
And now we can bring down another zero.
25 goes into 100 exactly four times. 4 x 25 is 100, and then you subtract and you get zero.
so we actually didn't even have to round this one. This fraction is exactly, this is exactly 0.44.