So let's compare these 2 alkenes.and even though they look similar to each other
they are actually different compounds.The reason they are different molecules is
because of their double bond.We know double bonds do not have any free rotation about them
So these are 2 different stereo isomers of each other.
So no free rotation around the double bond means the molecule in the left can not rotate to look like molecule in the right.
so let's name these 2 molecule.So if I start this with carbon number 1 this is carbon 2,3,4.
4 carbon alkene so that will be butene.
and the double bond starts at carbon 2 so that will be 2-butene like that.
over here in the right 1,2,3 and 4.
So a 4 carbon alkene starting with double bond at 2
so this also be 2-butene.
But we need a way to distinguish between these 2 molecules because
we know they are different they are stereo isomers of each other.
and there are 2 systems that you could use to distinguish between these 2.
So the first system that we will use is cis-tran system.
So when you are using this cis trans system you look for 2 identical groups
This methyl group here and methyl group over here.
and I can see if I extend this double bond I can see my 2 identical groups
are on the same side and we call that cis.
so cis-2-butene is the molecule on the left.The 2 identical groups are on the same side
of the double bond.On the right we have a methyl group over here and a methyl group over here
and if we look at the position of the double bond we can see that our 2 identical
double groups are across from each other they are on opposite side.
so we use the word trans to describe that situation .SO this is trans-2-butene on the right.
trans means across.So if we take trans Atlantic flight you are taking a flight across the Atlantic
which of these 2 stereo isomers is more stable.
Well if you think about steric hindrance about how bulky methyl group is you want to keep
bulky group as far away from each other as they possibly can.
this methyl group over here when its across from methyl group its much further
away then if its on the same side as in the situation on the left here.
So the molecule in the right is actually more stable so this is actually more stable.
trans-2-butene is more stable than cis-2-butene and the reason is decreased steric hindrance.
Alright let's do another example of the cis trans system.
So here a double bond like this and I want to figure out whether this molecule is cis or trans.
I would need to look forward 2 identical groups.And I have this isopropyl group over here and
methyl group here so those are not 2 identical groups.I could use hydrogens though
So i know there is hydrogen here and I know there is hydrogen over here.So those are the same things
So I can think about those 2 groups in relation to each other and once I go ahead and draw
on my double bond line in here I can see those 2 hydrogens are on opposite sides
So this would be the trans stereo isomer for this molecule.
So you can sometimes use the cis-trans system sometimes you can't use the cis trans system.
Another system that can be used at any time is EZ system.
So let's go ahead and talk about the EZ system.So let's look at a molecule here and
when we look at the stereo chemistry of the double bond for this molecule and the
EZ system everything is based on highest priority based on atomic number.
So we are going to look at the atoms connected to our double bond
and we are going to assign priority based on atomic numbers.If I look at the carbon on the left
I am gonna look at the atom directly bonded to that carbon.
so Br bonded to that carbon and I have carbon bonded to that carbon.
So Br's atomic number vs carbons.Obviously Br has a higher atomic number so it gets a number 1.
and the carbon having a lower atomic number gives this substituent a lower priority.
so this would be a number 2.
So we have a higher priority gets number 1 and lower priority gets number 2.
Over here in the right whats bonded to the carbon on the right
there is a hydrogen over here and there is a oxygen and we know that Oxygen has a higher
atomic number than hydrogen and so this oxygen down here get number 1 and
hydrogen get number 2.We use our same trick that we did before we kind of extend
this double bond here so its easier to see which sides are highest priority groups are on
so in this case our 2 highest priority groups are number 1 over here which is Br
and number 1 over here which is the OCH3.
So our 2 highest priority groups are on opposite sides from each other .Opposite sides
of the double bond.So we call this the E stereo isomer.so this is E which comes from the
German word entgegen which means opposite.
So the 2 highest priority groups are on the opposite sides of double bond is E.
So let's go ahead and switch that up again and so this time let's put the methyl group
over here and Br down here.and we will keep this side exactly same OCH3 like that.
Alright so assign priority well we know that Br is a higher priority than carbon
so this is highest priority substituent so this will get number 1.
and then the methyl group is gonna get number 2.over here we already know OCH is gonna get number 1
and hydrogen is gonna get number 2 so this time when we look at our 2 highest priority groups
and we look at the double bond we can see that our 2 highest priority groups are on the
same side of the double bond.and this is called the Z which comes from the German
word Zusammen which means together.
So when your 2 highest groups are together or on the same side it is Z.
The ways to remember this is to think to yourself Ze Zame Zid.
If your 2 highest priority groups are on ze zame zid you know you are dealing with Z stereo isomer.
Let's do another example of EZ system.This example is going to be little bit harder.
here is our double bond and here is our Br here is our cl and let's put
aldehyde in here and then let's make this alcohol.so CH2OH.
So assign E or Z to this molecule.
SO once again we start with the carbon on left and we look at the Br compare it to
cl.So we know that Br has a higher atomic number than Cl.So Br gets higher priority
and cl gets lower priority.
Over here on the right we have a carbon and a carbon so that's a tie.
So obviously we need to keep going.We need to find the first point of difference for all.
and so the easiest thing to do in this case is to go ahead and draw the molecule
expand a little bit.so attach this carbon on one end of our double bond.this is our carbon.
so this is the carbon double bonded to an oxygen and the easiest thing to do is to
pretend like that carbon is bonded to 2 different oxygens.
even though it is actually only bonded to 1.We have seen this old trick before.
and then this is hydrogen here.and then down here we have a carbon bonded to 2 hydrogens
and then bonded to O and then this oxygen also bonded to hydrogen.
let's go ahead and assign priority now.
So this the carbon bond right side of our double bond.
This carbon on the top here we have a tie between these 2 carbons.
so we go to the next one.next atom that are bonded to this atom.
So that would be oxygen oxygen hydrogen.
so Oxygen oxygen hydrogen for the top one bottom one will be oxygen hydrogen hydrogen.
OHH for the bottom one there.
Comparing oxygen to oxygen top keep going
first point of difference oxygen vs hydrogen oxygen has a higher atomic number so
of course it would get the highest priority.
so I go back over here to the molecule in the left and ai say my aldehyde end up to getting
higher priority than alcohol like that.
So now I go ahead and put my double bond there like that.
and I think to myself where are my 2 highest priority substituents.
My 2 highest priority groups this one and this one they are on ze zame zid.
So this must be Z stereo isomer for this molecule.
So the EZ system works for any double bond.Cis trans system is somewhat limited.
So you will see some people don't really like the Cis trans system.
I prefer using the EZ system all the time but historical for reasons the Cis and trans still come
up a lot inorganic chemistry textbooks.