What i want to do in this video is to discuss
a special class of triangles called '30-60-90
triangles'. And I think you know why they're
called this.
The measures of its angles are,
30 degrees, 60 degrees and 90 degrees.
And what we're going to prove in this video
and this tends to be a very useful result
at least for a lot of what you see in a
geometry class, and then later on in
Trigonometry class.
Is the ratio between the sides of a
30-60-90 triangle.
That if the hypotenuse has length x.
(so that's, remember the hypotenuse is
opposite the 90 degree side.)
If the hypotenuse has length x, what we're going
to prove is that the shorter side which
is opposite the 30 degree side has length
x/2, and that the 60 degree side...
the 60 degree side, or the side that's opposite
the 60 degree angle I should say is going
to be the (the square root of 3 x the shorter side.)
so the square root of 3 times (x/2)
that's going to be its length.
So that's what we're going to prove in this video.
and in other videos, we're going to apply this.
We're going to show that this is actually a useful
result.
Now lets start with a triangle that we're
very familiar with... so let me draw ourselves
an equilateral triangle... so drawing the
triangles is always the hard part.
So this is my best shot at an equilateral triangle.
And lets call this A, B, C
I'm just going to assume I've constructed an
equilateral triangle,
so Triangle ABC is equilateral.
and if it's equilateral, that means all
of it's sides are equal, and lets say that it has
an equilateral with sides of length x.
so this is going to be x
this is going to be x, and this is
going to be x.
we also know, based on what we seen from
equilateral triangles before, that the measures
of all of these angles are going to be 60 degrees.
So this is going to be 60 degrees
this is going to be 60 degrees, and then
this is going to be 60 degrees.
Now what I'm going to do is I'm going to drop
an altitude from this top point right over here.
So I'm going to drop an altitude right down
and by definition when I'm constructing an
altitude it is going to intersect the
base right here... at a right angle.
So that's going to be right angle, and then
this is going to be a right angle.
and it's a pretty straightforward proof to show
that this is not only an altitude,
that is perpendicular to this base.
But it's a pretty straightforward proof to show that it
bisects the base and you can pause it
if you like and prove it yourself.
But it really comes out of the fact that it's easy
to prove that these two triangles are congruent.
So let me... prove it for you.
So lets call this point D right over here.
So triangles ABD and BDC
they clearly both share this side, so
this side is common to both of them right over
here.
and then this angle right over here is
congruent to this angle over there.
This angle right over here is congruent to
this angle over here.
and so, if these two and congruent to each other.
The third angle has to be congruent to each other.
So this angle right over here needs to be
congruent to that angle right over there.
So these two are congruent.
And so you can use actually a variety of our
congruence postulates, we could say
SAS (side, angle side) congruents
we could use ASA (angle, side angle)
any of those to show that triangle ABD
is congruent to triangle CBD.
and what that does for us.
and we could use as I said (Angle,Side,Angle)
or (Side,Angle,Side)
whatever we like to use for this.
what that does for us is that it tells us that
the corresponding sides of these triangles
are going to be equal.
in particular... in particular,
the length AD is going to be equal to CD
these are corresponding sides.
so these are going to be equal to each other.
and if we know that they're equal to each other.
that add up to x, remember this was an
equilateral triangle of length x.
we know that this side right over here is going
to be x/2... we know this is going to be x/2
not only do we know that, but also knew when
we dropped this altitude we showed that
this angle has to be congruent to that angle,
and their measures have to add up to 60.
So if two things are the same, they add up to 60.
this is going to be 30 degrees,
and this is going to be 30 degrees.
so we already shown one of the interesting parts
of 30-60-90 triangles.
That if the hypotenuse. Notice, and I guess I
didn't point this out that by dropping this
altitude I've essentially split this equilateral triangle.
into two 30-60-90 triangles.
30-60-90 triangles.
and so we're already shown that if the side
opposite the 90 degree side is x.
That the side opposite the 30 side is going to be
x/2. That's what we showed right over here.
Now we just have to come up with a third side,
the side that is opposite the 60 degree side.
the side opposite the 60 degree side...
right over there.
and lets call that length... well I'll just use
the letters we already have.
This is BD.
now we can just the Pythagorean Theorem
right here.
BD^2 + this length right over here ^2
+ (x/2)^2 is going to be equal to the
hypotenuse squared.
so we get BD... BD^2 + (x/2)^2
this is just straight of the Pythagorean Theorem.
+ (x/2)^2 is going to this hypotenuse ^2
it's going to equal x^2
and just to be clear... I'm looking at this
triangle right here...
I'm looking at this triangle over here in the right.
and I'm just applying the Pythagorean Theorem.
this side ^2 + this side ^2 is going to equal
the hypotenuse ^2.
The lets solve now for BD
you get BD^2 + (x^2)/4... (x^2/4)
is equal to x^2... is equal to x^2.
You would view this as (4x^2)/4 that's the same
obviously it's x^2.
And then if we subtract 1... if you subtract
(1/4)x^2 from both sides or (x^2)/4
from both sides. you get
BD^2 =
4x^2/4 - x^2/4 is going to be.
3x^2/4
so its going to be 3x^2/4
take the principle root of both sides.
you get BD is equal to... is equal to
square root(3 times x)... times x
the principle of 3 is the square root of 3
the principle root of x^2 is just x
over the principle root of 4 which is 2
and BD is a side opposite the 60 degree side
so we're done, if this hypotenuse is x,
the side opposite the 30 side is going to be
x/2
and the side opposite the 60 degree side
is going to be the
square root of (3x/2)
depending on how you want to view it.