So here's a picture of mom and a little fetus
and at this point when the fetus is still attached by
the umbilical cord everything that goes into the fetus
is really originating from mom. She controls all
the nutrients and all the oxygen that goes into that baby.
And with oxygen in mind, there are a couple of interesting ways that the baby, in this case this little
fetus on the right, has come up with to be able to get as much oxygen as possible from mom.
because remember the fetus is trying to grow and it wants to make sure that all of it's tissues that are
growing and developing have enough oxygen. So there are a couple of tricks.
And the first trick, let me actually just draw it out for you, is simply looking at a single vial of blood.
If we look at a single vial of blood from mom, and compare it to a vial of blood from baby.
So let me try to draw the vials about the same height and width.
These are the two vials. If I was to take now, let's say a little bit of mom's blood and spin it down, let's say in this little tube.
And then do the exact same thing with the baby's blood, take some of baby's blood and spin it down.
That spun blood, once it's spun down, would actually separate out into little parts, right?
You'd have three different layers.
And this first layer would be something like this. This is called the plasma.
The next layer right below it, remember there's a little layer of white blood cells and platelets.
And below that, right here, is a layer of red blood cells.
Remember red blood cells are the ones that contain the hemoglobin.
They're the ones that are going to move oxygen around.
And in mom, the percent that this red layer takes up is about 35%.
Meaning this whole thing would be 100%, and of that just over 1/3, or 35% exactly, is that bottom red layer.
That's the red blood cell layer.
So we would call this the hematocrit.
So this is mom's hematocrit. And this is a very typical number for a pregnant woman.
It varies depending on whether you're a man or a woman, and what age you are.
But for a pregnant woman, 35% is a pretty reasonable number.
Now going over here to the baby side.
Let's draw in what baby's blood probably looks like.
The baby has a lot less of the blood taken up by plasma
so that layer is going to be smaller. And then the next layer, the white blood cell layer,
that's a very small layer anyway so that's not going to change much.
And the final layer, the third layer, is the red blood cell layer.
This layer takes up about 55%.
So I hope I didn't misdraw that, but that's about 55%.
So here the hematocrit is much higher, and what does that mean?
If the hematocrit is higher in the baby, about 55% percent, then that means that the baby actually has
more red blood cells going around, in a given amount of volume of blood, and those red blood cells
can then take up more oxygen because that's really the part of blood we care about when it comes
to moving oxygen around.
So that's one trick, in terms of tricks, for getting more oxygen.
Simply having more of the red blood cells in a given volume of blood. Kind of the amount of red blood cells is going to go up in the fetus
and that's kind of one trick. When I say trick that's what I mean.
So what's another trick, or strategy, that the baby or the fetus can come up with
to get more oxygen from mom?
Well if we think of the amount, you can also think of the type.
And what I mean by that is: thinking specifically about the type of hemoglobin.
So we know that the adult hemoglobin has four units to it.
So let me draw out the adult hemoglobin over here on the left.
Let me first write out adult hemoglobin.
So "Hb" for hemoglobin and "A" for adult.
I'll write adult here so we keep track of which is which.
And there isn't one type of adult hemoglobin. There is a main one, which is the one I am going to draw.
But there're few different types of little (...)
The main one, as I said, is this one,
has a couple of alpha units, this is just a protein peptide,
that is in some conformation we call it alpha,
and a couple of beta units,
and these are slightly different looking than the alpha ones
and there's a 2 to 2 ratio, so which hemoglobin has four units
and here you can see that you have two of each type.
Now, on the fetus side you actually have something a little different
so we also have over here hemoglobin, Hb,
this time F, for fetus,
and just as before the fetus has a few different type of hemoglobin,
but the main one is HbF, and it's actually this one also shares that alpha units
and has two of them just as before,
but instead of beta unit, this one has what we call it gamma unit,
this is the Greek letter for gamma,
now oxygen is gonna bind and both of hemoglobin,
both the adult and the fetus, can bind four oxygens,
let me just draw in four oxygens here, you got the idea.
now inside of red blood cells there's a little molecule and
actually I just gonna sketch it out for you,
this molecule has three carbons, let me just number the carbon one two three,
and coming off of the two carbon, this one right here,
is an oxygen, and coming off of that oxygen is a phosphate.
Remember that phosphate has typically five bonds,
so I just gonna show you what this little molecule looks like,
in fact, the exact same thing is happening of the three carbons.
so this molecule that exist inside of the red blood cells, it looks like this,
has a couple of phosphates, and coming off this number one is something like this,
so this is the little molecule, and it's called --
and you can --maybe when you can take a stab and try to guess what it's called--
it's called 2,3 --I'm reffering to this 2 and this 3--
Di --because it got two phospho--
so, Di-phospho- glycerate.
so that's Di-phospho, and then glycerate just refers to this part right here,
this is kind of the part that is being refered to when we say gycerate,
so Diphosphoglycerate.
and 2,3-diphosphoglycerate, we just fix that,
is actually sometimes shortened down to 2,3-DPG
'cause people don't like to say the whole thing,
so they'll say 2,3-DPG, and that's what this molecule is.
so this molecule 2,3-DPG, is inside red blood cells,
and it actually helps the red blood cell get rid of oxygen,
the way it does that is, actually is a tiny little molecule I'll draw it.
now that you know what the whole sturcture looks like, I'll draw --it's a yellow dot,
this is the same thing, I just make the equal sign, the equal of same thing,
This little molecule will go and bind in the middle here,
and it likes to bind to the beta subunits,
actually the beta subunits are shaped so that this thing can bind very easily.
and it nit, it sits kind of nicely between all four subunits, the betas and the alphas,
and what it does is that actually makes the conformation or
'the shape of the molecular' change, so these little oxygens want to move off.
So basically what it does is that it makes it easier for the oxygen to be released from the hemoglobin.
Now when this molecule comes around this side, on the fetus side it tries to bond,
guess what happens, well this gamma subunits basically say, go away! go away!
They don't want to bind to this 2,3-DPG.
They don't have the right shape for it.
And so they basically want this little molecule to get lost.
And so this molecule doesn't bind as easily to hemoglobin F.
and this result those molecules of hemoglobin don't get rid of oxygen
nearly as easily as hemoglobin A does.
Now why would we even have a molecule like 2,3-DPG around?
What it would be doing there?
well, interestingly, the level of 2,3-DPG actually go up
in situations where you actually have more niver oxygen,
so let's say chronically you're without oxygen.
So the situation like that be, when you're chronically without oxygen.
Well, let's say you live --I don't know what the-- the top of the Himalayan Mountains.
And you know, the altitude is so high, if you got a high alitude,
that the air itself doesn't have a lot of oxygen in it.
and that situation your tissues are kind of always, or chronically, without oxygen.
Now another situation could be, let's say you have lung disease.
Let's say you have lung problem or lung disease, and it's a chronic lung disease,
where you're always having difficulty, you know, getting oxygen to the blood.
Well again, the tissues are really lacking of the oxygen,
so there the red blood cells would make a lot of the 2,3-DPG.
Or a final situation, maybe you're anemic,
maybe you don't have a lot of red blood cells circulating around the body,
and for anemic, the tissues are not getting as much oxygen
as they wish they would.
And again, in this situation you might have more 2,3-DPG.
So 2,3-DPG, its basic job is to try-- to make sure that oxygen is left off of the hemoglobin,
so that if you have tissue that really needs that oxygen,
it's more easy to-- to actually deliver the oxygen to that tissue.
So, going back to the trick for the fetus,
you can see the fetus has different type of hemoglobin from the adult.
So, let me draw a little curve and you'll see what this different incept doing.
so let me sketch out a curve.
let's just draw out a little graph here.
this'll be the partial pressure of oxygen on this axis,
and this'll be O2 or oxygen saturation,
looking at how many of those spots on hemoglobin are taken up.
so this'll be going up that way.
let's start out with mom's hemoglobin, or adult hemoglobin,
you know, has kind of S-shape, because of the cooperativity
that we've talked about at the past.
so this'll be hemoglobin adult type, or hemoglobin A.
now, if I have, let's say, really high level of 2,3-DPG,
let me just draw out what that would look like,
so let's say we have a situation where that high level of 2,3-DPG,
and it could be because of one these reasons,
maybe live on a high mountain, or you've chronic lung disease,
or you're always anemic, if you had one of these situations,
and your 2,3-DPG level were really high, or higher than usual,
then what will happen to your curve, it was actually--
it would look like this, the curve for oxygen binding or oxygen saturation
basically kind of shifts over to the right.
So we call this a right shift, because the whole thing looks like it has just kind of moved over a little bit.
And now, at any point --let's say I just choose a random point over here,
and I choose the same point here.
So this is the same partial pressure of oxygen, right?
which is somewhere down here.
Now for the same partial pressure of oxygen, my curve actually went down,
meaning I have less oxygen bound to hemoglobin in the presence of molecule.
and that makes sense with what we just said, because the molecule helps kick off the oxygen.
Now what if you had an opposite situation,
what if I actually drew out a curve like this,
and this could be --let's say, a situation where you have a low levels of 2,3-DPG.
Well, with low level of 2,3-DPG, you can see that this would make sense
because now of all sudden, that molecules are not around, it's not doing anything
to help get the oxygen off, so of course oxygen is gonna stay down to hemoglobin,
and at the same partial pressure of oxygen, more of the hemoglobin would be bound by oxygen.
Now, think back to the idea of fetal hemoglobin,
remember, fetal hemoglobin we said has this gamma unit,
and the gamma doesn't like 2,3-DPG, it doesn't like to bind to it,
and so it says, get lost! go away!
and so in a sense the way I drawn it for a low level of 2,3-DPG,
I could --just this --well, erase that,
and say, well, this is the situation in the fetus.
The fetal hemoglobin is basically this curve, right?
This is kind of the hemoglobin F curve.
If you just look at the curve, it looks like it's left-shifted.
But the-- but the real concept behind it,
it's that it's because those hemoglobin molecules don't like to bind to 2,3-DPG,
and so of course it's gonna go in the opposite direction of the blue curve.
So looking at these two curves now, the white one and the red one,
the white one represents mom, the red one represents baby,
and the white one, if you wanna look at the point where about half of the
hemoglobin molecules are bound to oxygen, that might be right about there,
meaning this is about half way up to here,
this is actually 50% of the way there.
So 50% of the hemoglobin molecules are bound to oxygen,
when the pressure of oxygen --the partial pressure of oxygen--
is about 27. And for the fetus, the same kind of point of reaching half way saturation
is reached when the partial pressure is about 20.
So it's interesting for a lower partial pressure of oxygen,
the baby or the fetus is able to accomplish the same thing we adult can accomplish
at only higher amount of oxygen in the environment or in the blood.
And this values are called p50, so if you see p50
--if you see that term, you can remember now that the hemoglobin F p50
is lower than the hemoglobin A p50.
and that is --again, the actual number is 20 versus 27, or there about.
so these are the two tricks than one, is the-- you know, the amount of hemoglobin
or red blood cells in the fetus,
and the other is the type and hemoglobin F binds oxygen much more tightly and has a lower p50
~o0o~