The function f(x) is graphed, what is its domain? So the way it's graphed right over here we can assume
that this is the entire function definition for f(x) So for example
if we say well what does f(x) equal when x is equal to -9? Well we go up here
we dont see its graphed here it's not defined for x = -9
or x = -8 1/2 or x = -8 it's not defined for any
of these values it only starts getting defined at x = -6
at x = -6 f(x) is equal to 5
and it keeps getting defined f(x) is defined for x
all the way from x = -6 all the way to
x = 7 when x = 7 half of x is equal to 5
you can take any x value between -6 including -6
and positive 7 including positive 7 and you just have to see
you just have move up above that number wherever you are to find out
what the value of the function is at that point.
So the domain of this function definition
Well f(x) is defined for any x that is greater than
or equal to -6 or we can say -6 is less than or equal to
x which is less than or equal to 7. If x satisfies
this condition right over here the function is defined.
So that's its domain, let's check our answer and do a few more of these.
The function f(x) is graphed what is its domain?
Well exact similar argument this function is not defined
for x is -9 -8 all the way down or all the way up
I should say to -1. At -1 it starts getting defined.
f of -1 is -5 so it's
defined for -1 is less than or equal to x
is defined all the way up to x = 7 including x = 7. So this
right over here -1 is less than or equal to x is less than or equal to 7 the
function is defined for any x that satisfies this
double inequality right over here. Let's do a few more
the function f(x) is graphed, what is its range?
So now we're not thinking about the x's for which this function is defined
we're thinking about the set of y values, what is
where do all the y values fall into?
Well let's see the lowest possible y value or the lowest possible
value of f(x) that we get here looks like its 0 the
function never goes below 0 so f(x)
is 0 is less than or equal to f(x) it does equal 0 right over here
f of -4 is 0 and then the highest y value
or the highest value that f(x) obtains in this function definition
is 8, f of 7 is 8 it never gets above 8 but
it does equal 8 right over here when x is equal to 7
So, 0 is less than f(x) which is less than or equal
to 8 so that's its range.
Let's do a few more this is kinda fun. The function f(x) is graphed
what is its domain? So once again this function is defined for -2
-2 is less than or equal to x which
is less than or equal to 5. If you give me an x anywhere in between
-2 and 5 I can look at this graph to see where the function is defined
f of -2 is -4 f of -1 is
-3 so on and so forth and I can even pick the values inbetween
these integers. So -2 is less than or equal to x which is
less than or equal to 5.