This is a painting by Claude Monet which is a series of more than half a dozen canvases.
Taking the subject of Gare St. Lazare which is a train station in Paris.
It dates to the winter of 1876-1877, just a few years after the first impressionist exhibition.
Monet was living in Argenteuil which was the suburb of Paris
And of course, he would have taken the train there and back as the typical suburban dweller into the city
This whole phenomenon of commuter railways into the city, wanting to live in the countryside, but working at the city.
Paris just recently renovated during the second empire by Baron Haussmann.
The train stations were new, the boulevards were new.
So this was an epitome of the modern, the new, the industrial. But it is so radical.
We think of Monet of painting the waterlilies, the pastoral suburban landscape.
But here, what could be more gritty than these coal-burning steam engines.
Yeah, when Monet had been in Argenteuil, he had painted landscapes with chimneys in the background
or modern railways, bridges, or elements of modern life.
But here he's completely embracing the gritty ickiness of modernism.
If you look at the composition of the painting, it is actually not so different from the traditional landscape painting.
If you look back at the canvases of St. Claude whose got trees framing.
This visual movement puts him back into space. Also these diagonal lines that recede and carry our eyes back.
But the painting is intensely flat. Because of the emphasis of surface.
Especially if you look into this canvas, you have this locomotive moving into the station
under this enormous iron gridwork.
And what could be more substantial than the iron locomotive
and yet because of the way the scene is painted, it began to obliterate, dissolve the solidity of the locomotive
of this massive iron
and Monet, it is exactly his intent to focus on the play of light, and the play of color.
And what could be more wonderful space to do that than this entrapped space with the steam,
droplets of water playing against the sunlight
that are coming from the windows above.
Monet is thinking about the surface, how the surface is flickering
and the colors that are changing on the surface
and he's not thinking so much in the way academic painter would have thought about
creating foreshorten objects in space
creating prespective lines, modeling it, and giving it solidity.
So really if you look into these details, there are actually no lines, or contours to the object.
There is no sense of traditional modelling at all
and the surface is incredibly painter-ly, it is almost abstract.
Sometimes the word "scumbled" is used.
What's interesting is you can compare Monet completely removing the lines virtually from his canvas
to some other painters worked in this area at the same time.
i'm thinking about a painting by Caillebotte who is a contemporary of Monet's.
This is actually a bridge just over the train tracks we saw in Monet's painting
and here everything is so linear, crisp, clean, and clarified
and in fact the linear perspective is very intense.
Right, it sorts of over dramatizing the perspective, but there is a real illusion of space here
which Monet kind of denies us.
Everything is so, that ironwork, it's so there.
Where in Monet everything is disappearing, the steam, everything just became pure light, pure color.
We have a sense here of street, of urban street, people passing each other, the pace of modern life.
And of course, Manet did that as well in his painting of the railway, passing people on the streets
And this is the same location, looking down onto those train tracks. Exactly.
We could look for a moment at the real station today. The photograph.
So really, it is not a pretty place. Not at all.
Yet Monet chose to make this luminous, just an extraordinary expression of the beauty
of modern urban life.
Here is the map of the train station just below. We are looking at the roof of the train station.
Just past that, the railway tracks we were looking at, and past that the bridge that we saw in Caillebotte.
And of course the boulevards that had been recently built by Baron Haussmann.
Which really rip through the city, creating this modern bourgeois society.
That is exactly what Monet was painting, and Manet too.
So, if we go back to this canvas then, what we are seeing is a beautiful expression of impressionism.