[music playing]
We're looking at a really wonderful Caravaggio.
This is a painting of "The Calling of St. Matthew"
in San Luigi dei Francesi in Rome.
In the Contarelli chapel.
That's right. In the larger church.
And it's in a chapel with two
other paintings by Caravaggio,
all about Matthew.
So Matthew is one of Christ's disciples.
And so which one is he here?
It's a little hard to find him here actually.
It's a complicated group of figures here.
It's very complicated.
I love the subject.
Christ is walking in.
Now which one is Christ?
There are two figures on the right.
Yeah. I think St. Peter is in
front of Christ on the right.
He's the sort of heavy, powerful,
rough-looking guy.
Yeah. With the short-
cropped hair.
And behind him, half obscured,
facing us is Christ with his arm outstretched.
He looks much more noble,
younger, more delicate actually.
And there is a kind of delicacy
to his gestures that remove him, I think,
from the regular world of the other figures
seem to occupy as he seems to point over,
and Matthew is the one who is
pointing to himself in disbelief.
He's the older figure
with the large beard.
With a black hat.
Yes, and a dark tunic.
And I think, if I remember correctly,
the story is that Matthew is a tax collector,
and he's sitting with his fellow
tax collectors as Christ walks in,
and he says Matthew, and basically says,
"you, come with me."
And it's this moment of conversion.
This is this incredible moment
of spiritual awakening.
Right, which is a very typical
subject in Baroque art.
So there's this notion of
transformation.
At this moment that Christ says,
"hey you, you're coming with me."
Matthew points to himself, "me?"
You can't possibly mean me.
Right. I'm a tax collector.
Well, there is all kinds of negative implications.
It's not just that he's working for the I.R.S.
A little bit more shady than the I.R.S.
It's much more shady.
Look at the environment they're in.
It's so important for Caravaggio.
He's not showing Christ in Heaven.
He's not showing Christ in an
elevated, classicized environment.
He's in this what looks like the back room of a tavern.
And when we look at it,
it looks like he is surrounded by younger men
who are counting money.
Yeah, they are leaning over
sort of greedily, the figure especially on the left.
And their arms. They've got swords.
They're dressed in very fancy clothes.
You can sort of imagine one of them
whipping out their swords
and getting into a bar room brawl almost.
That's right. But there is this
real sense of this money
is not gotten legally.
Imagine if you walked into a bar now
and you walked into the back room
and there were very overly dressed,
ostentatiously dressed young men with guns
counting money.
Would that be an environment you
would want to be in?
I think that's what makes this moment
of conversion all the more wonderful.
But how potent this must have been
when this painting was made in 1599 or 1600
when Christ is being shown in really
this much more contemporary environment
and all of this is made real.
Very real. The figures are so removed
from the idealized beauty of the High Renaissance.
It must have been challenging, a little scary,
but really exciting.
Caravaggio brings the spiritual down to
an everyday level that we can all totally relate to
instead of that distance that was
there in the High Renaissance.
But it is really interesting if you think that
these are paintings in Rome,
with all the pomp and ceremony of Rome,
and Caravaggio is giving such a fresh --
it is really wonderful and fabulous.
The thing that I always think about
with this painting when I try to relate it
to living in the 21st century, I imagine
sometimes my own version of it reading
maybe it's the holidays, and I'm supposed
to be shopping for friends and family,
and instead I'm buying something for myself,
and I'm getting my credit card out,
trying to imagine Christ walking in a door
of Banana Republic and saying,
"You. I've chosen you."
Look at the way that Caravaggio
is handling light here.
It's not just Christ walking in.
He is the embodiment of a
kind of spiritual force
in that as he points to Matthew,
and your eye can go from his glance
across his hand to Matthew's finger,
following that diagonal line,
of the sunlight which seems to be
pouring in maybe with a doorway
that they've opened.
Who knows what.
And it is almost as if that point of Christ
sends these piercing rays to Matthew
that gets to him but also in a way
that interrupts this moment
of reality in the tavern
so that he is sort of suspended between this moment
of calling and transformation and conversion,
but also still immersed in his reality.
Of course it is also a very Baroque characteristic
of this caught extreme moment of time,
and also what is very Baroque about it
that I appreciate is this way the divine
has entered everyday life.
We see that with St. Theresa and so
many other Baroque paintings.
In a sense the Baroque is taking these
intensely spiritual forms
that have come out of the Renaissance,
maintaining the high naturalism and really building
on the high naturalism of the Renaissance
but putting it in an environment, where
as you said earlier,
it is completely accessible, and very,
very real and immediate.
There is something to me sometimes not even
just real and immediate,
but almost pedestrian and dirty.
If you look at the bare feet of Peter, of Christ,
there is something gritty about Caravaggio.
Look at the window.
It looks as though it has been covered so as
not to let light in.
It's soot.
The walls look dirty and grimy.
This is not an ideal environment.
I have one thing I thought
is always very curious.
If you look at Christ's hand, because there
is a lot of attention compositionally on that hand,
right under the cross of the window,
and that slight bend of the wrist,
it is the hand that Michaelangelo had painted,
but of Adam,
but here, in an interesting
kind of reversal,
there has been the tradition of course of
seeing Christ as the second Adam.
That's right.
Adam causes the fall of mankind and
Christ redeems mankind.
And so in a sense bookends on this story.
And this moment of redemption,
personal redemption for Matthew.
Just as Adam was created, in a sense
Matthew is recreated.
Díváme se na úžasný Caravaggiův obraz
Díváme se na úžasný Caravaggiův obraz.Je to obraz