Let's write 113.9% (percent) as a decimal.
So percent – this symbol right over here –
literally means 'per hundred.'
So this is the same thing as 113.9 per 100 –
which is the same thing as 113.9 ÷ 100.
So essentially, if we wanted
to write this as a decimal,
we just take a 113.9,
and we divide it by 100.
So let's do that.
113.9 ÷ 100.
If you divide a number by 10,
you move the decimal once to the left.
If you divide a number by 100,
you're moving the decimal twice to the left.
If you were dividing by 1000,
you'd move to the left once more.
10,000 –
Each time you divide by 10,
you'd go one step to the left –
which, hopefully, makes sense.
If you were to multiply by 10, we would be
moving the decimal over to the right.
And there are other videos that go into
far more depth on the intuition behind that.
But anyway, we're dividing 113.9 by 100.
So move the decimal two spaces to the left.
So the decimal will end up right over here.
So this will be equal to 1.139.
And we are done.