Created by the hottest, most violent, and
most energetic objects and events in the Universe, gamma rays travel
across vast stretches of space, only to be absorbed by Earth's atmosphere.
Scientists had no way to detect and study gamma rays
from the cosmos until high altitude balloons and rockets carried
gamma ray sensors above the atmosphere. Deadly to humans,
gamma rays are created on Earth by natural radioactive decay,
by nuclear explosions, and even by the lightning in thunderstorms.
Coronal mass ejections from our Sun emit gamma rays,
followed by masses of charged particles. Monitoring these
gamma rays provides scientists with an early warning of incoming charged particles
that may cause disruptions in power and communication networks.
The most energetic of all EM waves - gamma rays carry
enough energy to kill living cells. Doctors are able to selectively
use gamma radiation to destroy cancer growths.
Gamma ray wavelengths are the shortest of all electromagnetic waves,
about the size of an atom's nucleus. In fact, it is so short
that the rays sail through atoms as easily as comets sail through our solar system.
This makes detecting gamma rays difficult for scientists.
Gamma ray detectors typically contain densely packed crystal blocks.
As gamma rays pass through, they collide
with electrons in the crystal. The sensor doesn't directly detect gamma rays.
Rather, it detects the charged particles created by those collisions.
Scientists have used gamma rays to determine the elements
that make up Martian surface soils. When struck by cosmic rays,
chemical elements in soils and rocks emit uniquely
identifiable signatures of energy in the form of gamma rays.
The gamma ray spectrometer on NASA's Mars Odyssey Orbiter
detects and maps these signatures, such as this map of hydrogen concentrations.
Gamma rays stream from stars, supernovas,
black holes, and pulsars to wash our sky with gamma ray light.
NASA's Fermi gamma ray telescope imaged the
location of these sources, mapping out the Milky Way galaxy by creating
a full 360 degree view of the Galaxy from our perspective
here on Earth. While the visible light sky is predictable and
follows regular patterns, the gamma ray sky does not. Bursts of
high-energy gamma radiation arrive from deep space every day.
These explosions of gamma rays last fractions of a second to minutes,
popping like cosmic flashbulbs, momentarily dominating the
gamma ray sky, and then fading. This video of
the Vela Pulsar beams gamma rays every 89 seconds as it rotates.
Gamma ray bursts are the most energetic and luminous
electromagnetic events since the Big Bang and can release more
energy in 10 seconds than our Sun will emit in its entire 10 billion-year
expected lifetime. NASA's SWIFT satellite
recorded this gamma ray burst of an exploding star 13 billion
light years away. It is among the most distant objects
ever detected, when the universe was just 630 million years old.
A recent observation of a gamma ray burst produced the greatest
total energy to date, equivalent to 9,000 typical supernovae!
By continuing to study gamma rays, we will unlock
important new understanding in astronomy, its use in medical treatments,
and allow us to further enhance our protection for
our satellites, and other electronics here on Earth.
Other NASA instruments monitor the changes in other aspects
of the Earth's climate system, such as clouds, aerosol particles,
or surface reflectivity, and scientists are examining their many
interactons with the energy budget. A portion of solar radiation
from the Sun that is just beyond the visible spectrum is referred to
as near-infrared. Scientists can study how this radiation
reflects off the Earth's surface to understand changes in land cover
such as growth of cities or changes in vegetation. Our eyes
perceive a leaf as green because wavelengths in the green region
of the visible light spectrum are reflected while other visible wavelengths
are absorbed. Yet, the chlorophyll and the cell structure of the
leaf are also reflecting near-infrared light, light we cannot see.
This reflected near-infrared radiation can be
sensed by satellites, allowing scientists to study vegetation from space.
Using these data, scientists can identify some
types of trees, can examine the health of forests, and can even
monitor the health of vegetation such as forests infested with pine beetles
or crops affected by drought. Studying the emission and
reflection of infrared waves helps us to understand the Earth's system
and its energy budget. Near-infrared data can also help scientists
study land cover such as changes in snow, ice,
forests, urbanization, and agriculture.
Scientists are beginning to unlock the mysteries of cooler objects across
the Universe such as planets, cool stars, nebulae,
and much more using infrared waves.
,00:00:00.00
,00:03:40.98