In this problem we're asked to figure out the length of BC
We have a bunch of triangles here in some lengths of sides
and a couple of right angles,
and so maybe we can establish similarity between some
of the triangles
There's actually 3 different triangles that I can see here,
this triangle, this triangle and this larger triangle
If we can establish some similarity here,
maybe we can use ratios between sides
somehow to figure out what BC is
So when you look at, you have a right angle right over here,
so, you, in triangle BDC, you have one right angle,
in triangle ABC you another right angle
If can we share, if we can show that they have another angle
or another corresponding set of angles
that are congruent to each other,
then we can show that they're similar
And actually both of those triangles, both BDC and ABC,
both share this angle right over here
So if they share that angle, then they definitely share two angles
So they both share that angle right over there
Let me do that in a different color just for
just to make it different than those right angles
They both share that angle there,
and so we know that two triangles
that have at least two of their angles
are, are that at least have two congruent angles,
they are going to be similar triangles
so we know, we know that triangle, I'll write this,
triangle ABC, ABC, we went from the unlabeled angle
to the right, yellow right angle to the orange angle
So let me write it this way
Went from the unlabelled angle right over here
to the orange angle or to the yellow angle
I'm having trouble with colors
to the orange angle, ABC
And we want to do this very carefully here,
because the same points or the same vertices may not say,
play the same role in both triangles
We want to make sure we're getting the similarity right
White vertex to the 90 degree angle vertex to the orange vertex
That is going to be similar to, to triangle
So which is the one that is neither right angle?
So we're looking at the smaller triangle right over here
Which is the one that is, neither a right angle
or the orange angle what's going to be vertex B
Vertex B had the right angle
when you think about the larger triangle but we haven't thought
about just that little angle right over there
So we have started vertex B then we're going to go to the right angle,
the right angle is vertex D, vertex D,
and then we go to vertex C which is in orange
Show, so we have shown that they are similar
And now that we're si that we know
that they're similar, we can attempt to take ratios between the sides
And so let's think about it, we know what the length
of AC is AC is going to be, AC is going to be equal to 8, 6 plus 2
So we know that AC, AC, what's the corresponding side
on this triangle right over here
So you can learn to look at the letters, A and C
is going to corres is going to correspond to BC,
the first and the third, first and the third
AC is going to correspond to BC
And what is and so this is interesting
cause we're already involving BC
And so, what is going to correspond to
And then if we look at BC on the larger triangle,
so if we look at BC on the larger triangle,
BC is going to correspond to what on the smaller triangle?
It's going to correspond to DC
And it's good because we know what AC is and we know what DC is
And so we can solve for BC
So I want to take one more step to fi
to show you what we just did here
Cause BC is playing two different roles
On this first statement right over here,
we're thinking of BC, BC corresponds
BC on our smaller triangle corresponds to AC on our larger triangle
And then in our, in the second statement BC
on our larger triangle corresponds to DC on our smaller triangle,
so in both of these cases, so these are our larger triangles
And then these are, this is from the smaller triangle right over here,
corresponding sides
And this is a cool problem because BC plays two different roles
in two, in both triangles
But now we have enough information to solve for BC
We know that AC is equal to 9
We know that A oh sorry, AC is equal to 8,
AC is equal to 8, 6 plus 2 is 8
And we know that DC is equal to 2, that's given
And now we can cross multiply,
8 times 2 is 16 is equal to BC times BC is equal to BC squared
And so BC is going to be equal to the principle root of 16 which is 4
BC is equal to 4, BC is equal to 4 and we're done
And the hardest part about this problem is just realizing that BC
plays two different roles and just keeping your head straight is,
and just keeping your head straight on those two different roles
And just to make it clear,
let me actually draw these two triangles separately
So if I drew ABC separately it would look like this,
it would look like this
So this is my triangle ABC and then this is a right angle,
this is our orange angle
We know that the length of this side right over here is 8
And we know that the length of this side,
what we figured out thru this problem is 4
Then if we want to draw BDC we would draw it like this
So BDC BDC looks like this
So this is BDC, that's a little bit easier
to visualize cause we've already
this is our right angle,
this is our orange angle and this is four
and this right over here is two
And I did it this way to show you that you kinda have to flip
this triangle over and rotate it
just to have kind of a similar orientation
and then it might make it look a little bit clearer
So if you've found this part confusing,
I encourage you to try to flip and rotate BDC
in such a way that it seems to look a lot like ABC
And then this ratio should hopefully make a lot more sense