Express twenty five degrees Celsius as a temperature in degrees Fahrenheit using the formula Fahrenheit
or F is equal to nine fifths times the Celsius degrees plus thirty two, so they're telling us that we have twenty five degrees
Celsius. So, we can put that in for "C" here and we'll get the temperature in Fahrenheit degrees. So, lets do that! So, we get "F" is equal to nine over five
times, now for "C" we are going to put in twenty five, times twenty five plus thirty two...and now we
can simplify this before we multiply twenty five times nine. Now remember, that's the same thing as nine
fifths times twenty five over one. We can essentually devide the numerater and the denominator of our
eventual product by five. If we devide twenty five by five we get five. If we devide five by five we
get one. So, this boils down to nine times five plus thirty two. So our Fahrenheit degrees are going to
be nine times five is forty five plus thirty two degrees or it's equal to forty five plus thirty two
is seventy seven. So this is seventy seven degrees Fahrenhiet.