Let's say I have some type of a block here
This block has a mass of 'm'
So the mass of this block is equal to 'm'
And it's sitting on this (you can view this as) an incline plane
or a ramp or some type of wedge
And we want to think about what might happen to this block
We'll start thinking about the different forces that might keep it in place
or not keep it in place
and all of the rest
So the one thing we do know is
if this whole setup is near the surface of the Earth
We'll assume that it is for the sake of this video
There will be the force of gravity
trying to bring or attract this mass
towards the center of the Earth
and vice versa the center of the Earth
towards this mass
So we're going to have some force gravity
Let me start at the center of this mass right over here
You're going to have the force of gravity
The force due to gravity is going to be equal to
the gravitational field near the surface of the Earth
we'll call that 'g'
'g' times the mass
Let me just write it as the mass times the gravitational field
near the surface of the Earth
and it's going to be downwards
we know that, or at least
towards the center of the Earth
Now what else is going to be happening here?
Well, it's a little bit confusing because
you can't say the normal force is acting directly against
this force over here
Because remember the normal force acts
perpendicular to a surface
So over here the surface is not perpendicular
to the force of gravity
So we have to think about it a little bit differently
than we would if this were sitting on level ground
The one thing that we can do
and frankly that we should do
is maybe we can break up this force
the force due to gravity
We can break it up into components
that are either perpendicular to the surface
or that are parallel to the surface
and then, we can use those to figure out
what's likely to happen
what are the potentially netting forces
or balancing forces over here
Let's see if we can do that
Let's see if we can break this force vector
the force due to gravity
into a component that is perpendicular to the surface
of this ramp
And also, another component that is parallel
to the surface of this ramp
I'll do that in a different color
That is parallel to the surface of this ramp
This is a little bit of unconventional notation
but we'll call this one over here
the force due to gravity that is
perpendicular to the ramp
with that little upside T
I'm saying it's perpendicular
Because it shows a line that is perpendicular
to this bottom line (this horizontal line)
And this blue thing over here
I'm going to call this the force
or the part of force
due to gravity
that is parallel
I'm just doing those two upward vertical bars
to show something that is parallel
to the surface
So this is the component of force that is
perpendicular
component of force that is parallel
So let's see if we can use a little bit of
geometry and trigonometry
given that this wedge is at a
theta degree incline relative to the horizontal
If you were to measure this angle right over here
you would get theta
So, in future videos we'll make it more concrete
like 30 degrees or 45 degrees or whatever
But let's just keep it general
if this is theta
let's figure out what these components of the
gravitational force are going to be
Well we can break out geometry over here
This, I'm assuming is a right angle
and so, if this is a right angle
we know that the sums of the angles in a triangle
will add up to 180
so, if this angle, this angle, and this 90 degrees
(Right angles are 90 degrees)
add up to 180
that means that this one and this one
need to add up to 90 degrees
or this is theta
this angle right over here is going to be
90 minus theta
Now, the other thing that you may or may not remember
from geometry class is
if I have two parallel lines here
I'm going to assume this line is parallel to this line
and then I have a transversal
So a let's say I have a line
that goes like this
We know from basic geometry that
this angle is going to be equal to this angle
It's comes from alternate interior angles
And, we prove it in the geometry module
or in the geometry videos
Hopefully, this makes a little bit of
intuitive sense
and we could even think about
how these angles would change as
the transversal changes and all of the rest
But, the parallel lines makes
this angle similar to that angle
or actually, makes it identical
it's congruent
this angle is going to be the same measure
as that angle
So can we apply that anywhere over here?
Well we have (and it's not obvious)
This line is perpendicular to the surface
of the Earth
right over here that I'm knid of shading in blue
and so is this force vector
it is also perpendicular to the surface of the Earth
So this line over here
and this line over here in magenta
are going to be parallel
(I can even draw that)
That line and that line are both parallel
When you look at it that way
you'll see that this big line over here
can be viewed as a transversal
Or you can have this angle and this angle
are going to be congruent
They're going to be alternate interior angles
So this angle and this angle
by the exact same idea here
it just looks a little more confusing here
because I have all sorts of things
But this line and this line are parallel
You can view this right over here as a
transversal
So this and this are congruent angles
So this is 90 minus theta degress
This too will be 90 minus theta degress
90 minus theta degrees
Now, given that can we figure out this angle
Well one thing, we're assuming that this
yellow force vector right here
We're assuming that it is perpendicular to the surface
of this plane
or perpendicular to the surface of this ramp
So that's perpendicular
This right here is 90 minus theta
So what is this angle right here
going to be equal to?
This angle (let me do it in green)
What is this angle up here going to be equal to?
So this angle plus 90 minus theta plus 90
must be equal to 180
or this angle plus 90 minus theta
(Let me write this down I don't
want to do too much by head)
So let's just call it x
So x plus 90 minus theta
plus this 90 degrees right over here
needs to be equal to 180 degrees
We can, let's see
We can subtract 180 degrees
from both sides
So if you subtract 90 twice
you're subtracting 180 degrees
you get x minus theta is equal to 0
or x is equal to theta
so whatever the inclination of the plane is
or of this ramp
that is also going to be this angle right over here
and the value to that is that
now we can use our basic trigonometry to
figure out this component and this component
of the force of gravity
and to see that a little bit clearer
let me shift this force vector down over here
the parallel component
let me shift it over here
and you can see the perpendicular component
plus the parallel component
is equal to the total force due to gravity
and you should also see that this is a right triangle
that I have set up over here
this is parallel to the plane
this is perpendicular to the plane
and so we can use basic trigonometry
to figure out the magnitudes
of the perpendicular force due to gravity and
the parallel force due to gravity
So the magnitude
(let's think about it a little bit)
the magnitude of the perpendicular force
due to gravity
I should say
the component of gravity that is
perpendicular to the ramp
the magnitude of that vector
A lot of fancy notation
but it's really just the length of
this vector right over here
so the magnitude of this
over the hypotenuse
of this right triangle
Well what is the hypotenuse of this right triangle
Well it's going to be the magnitude of the total
gravitational force
(I guess you can that)
So you can say that is 'mg'
We could write it like this
but that is really the
(Well I can write it like that)
And so this is going to be equal to what?
We have the
(if we're looking at this angle right here)
we have the adjacent over the hypotenuse
Remember
(Let's do this in a new color)
Soh Cah Toa
Cosine is adjacent over hypotenuse
So this is equal to cosine of the angle
so cosine of theta is equal to
the adjacent over the hypotenuse
so if you multiply both side by the magnitude
of the hypotenuse
you get the component of our vector
that is perpendicular to the surface
of the plane
is equal to the magnitude of the force due to gravity
the magnitude of the force due to gravity
times the cosine of theta
We'll apply this in the next video
just so you can make the numbers a little more concrete
sometimes just the notation makes it confusing
you'll see it's actually pretty straight forward
and then this second thing
we could use the same logic
we have, if we think about the parallel vector
right over here
the magniude of the force of the component
of the force due to gravity that is parallel to the plane
over the magnitude of the force due to gravity
which is the magnitude of 'mg'
that is going to be equal to what?
Well we have, this is the opposite side of the angle
and then, so then the blue is the opposite side
or at least its length
is the opposite side of the angle
and then right over here
this magnitude of 'mg'
that is the hypotenuse
and so you have the opposite over the hypotenuse
Opposite over hypotenuse
sine of an angle is opposite over hypotenuse
so this is going to be equal to the sine of theta
this is equal to the sine of theta
or you multiply both sides times
the magnitude of the force due to gravity
and you get the component of the force
due to gravity that is parallel
that is parallel to the ramp
is going to be the force due to gravity total
times sine of theta
(times sine of theta)
and hopefully you should see where this
came from
because if you ever have to derive this again
when you're 30 years after you took
a calculus or physics class
you should be able to do it
but if you know this right here
if you know this right here
and this right here
we can all of a sudden
start breaking down the forces
into things that are useful to us
because we could say
hey look this isn't moving down into this plane
so maybe there's some normal force
that's completely netting it out
in this example
and maybe if there's nothing to keep it up
if there's no friction
maybe this thing will start accelerating due to the
parallel force
and we'll a lot more about that
and if you ever forget these
think about them intuitively
you don't even need to go throught
this whole parallel line and transversal
and all that
if this angle went down to zero
then we'll be talking about
essentially a flat surface
there is no inclination there
and if this angle goes down to zero
then all of the force should be
acting perpendicular
to the surface of the plane
so if this went to zerop
the perpendicular force should be the same
as the total gravitational force
and that's why it's cosine of theta
because cosine of zero right now
is 1
and so these would equal each other
and if this equalled zero then
the parallel component of gravity should go to zero
because gravity will only be acting downward
and once again
if sine of theta is zero
so the force of gravity that's parallel
will go to zero
so if you ever forget
just do that little intuitive thought process
and you'll remember which one is sine
and which one is cosine