In the last video we talked about pensions
and how there're defined benefit plans
and how they could get underfunded
of how there could be temptation for people to underfund them
In this video I want to make things a little bit more concrete
by looking on actual numbers especially at the state level
So right over here is a map of obviously the United States
and what it shows is how funded the pension liabilities are in the different states
so for example
actually Texas for example
83% of their pension liabilities are funded
They set aside 83% of they right amount of money for their pension obligations
Not 100% it is underfunded
but it's not crazy
California, pretty high
78% but one of these states is jumping out to you
probably because it's been shaded in red
and that is the state of Illinois
and Illinois is in trouble because
it's only funded 45% of its pension obligations
and Illinois really jumps out because
it's in red
but there're a lot of states pretty close to Illinois
Louisiana 56$, Oklahoma 56%, Kentucky 54%, West Virginia 58%
and this is an issue because
it's set a side in the past very little money
for the pension obligations that are starting to hit now
especially if you have a retiring baby boomer population
and in order to meet those obligations
those promised obligations
they're going to have to dig into money
that was being spent in other places
that going in the past when they were under funding the pension
they were able to fund other things nicely
but not fund the pension
and kind of kick the can down the road
but now that the can can't be kicked any further
it's going to have to go the other way around
you're going to have to take money from other things to fund your pensions
and to make it clear
let's focus on the state of Illinois
So this right over here there're a couple of things going on
In this kind of yellow ochre colour
and I'll circle it in yellow-ochre
they're talking about the total liabilities
and just to make this graph clear
it's not just about the total liabilities
the entire height of each of these bars is the total
is the total liabilities
and you see how it's just completely
it's completely blossomed here
and there're a lot of things that go into the total liabilities
the same things that we talked about in the last video
they're things like return on investment
Return on investment
if you're in a low interest rate environment like we are right now
For example in my savings account
I think is getting like 0.4% interest
It's getting pretty much no interest
If you're in a low interest rate environment
if your're not getting good returns
a lot of pensions tend to go into very safe assets
but those are going to get very low returns
you're going to have to set aside
more money
And so
you see these obligations essentially just growing dramatically
on top of that you have things like cost of living adjustments
These are attempts at kind of factoring in inflation
how much things are costing in that region
but there are also negotiated
and especially in the case of Illinois
they've grown faster than the rate of inflation
And so you have these liabilities
and you see they're getting less and less well funded
So if we go right over here
and this is what this green line is
the funding ratio so how well funded are these liabilities
red says the red part of the bar that is not paid for
and the green is the ratio of what is funded
essentially this higher part
is the ratio of this part right over here to the entire bar
And you see right over here
Illinois is in a bad situation
Their total liabilities are 138 billion
this is in millions
so it's a 138 thousand milllions
so it's 138 billion
This is for 1 state
and 85 or 86 billion of that is unfunded
that they have to figure our somewhere to get the money
because the right amount of money was not being set aside
And to do that they're going to have to dig into other things
so this right over here
this is the pension contribution
let me circle this
so in this yellow colour right over here is the pension contribution
and now the state
in order to get to a funded position
they're going to have to make up for the underfunding of the past
and also the other factors that are making this obligation even larger
they're going to have to dig into other things
and so you see right over here in yellow
these are the pensions
these are the contributions they're going to have to make for the pensions
and you see that growing
it's going in excess by 2018 of 6 billion a year
but what's really fascinating about this graph
is that it's passing total education funding in the state
so the cost of funding retirements
for people who have already done service for the state
but aren't in service to the state right now
is going to pass up
and this is happening very soon
is going to pass up actual spending on a state-wide basis on education
and at the state level
education is a major major major expenditure
so it's going to be passing up a major expenditure
a very important expenditure on the future of the state
based on past obligations
and to understand where this is going
and just to understand Illinois' situation
there are 750 thousand
Illinois...I don't know how to say this
Illinoians? Illinoisians?
who are members of the State's five pension systems
so this is the teacher's retirement system
this is the state universities' retirement system
this is the state employees' retirement system
this is the state judges' retirement system
you see that there're a lot fewer judges than that
there's been many more teachers
many who have been in the state universities
and this right over here is the General Assembly
very few people who are in the Illinois State Assembly
and you can see kind of comparable salaries
this is the retirement benefit
not just the salaries
this is on average how much these folks
are getting once they retire on an annual basis
so you see that they're pretty reasonable
especially for the judges
although that they are a small fraction
but in all fairness this was promised to these people
they planned
they probably took lower compensation while they were working
with the expectation that they were going to get these benefits
once they retired
they probably stayed on their jobs longer
This is a way of retaining employees
because they knew they were going to get these benefits
So you can say these are really great benefits
but at the same time these people probably sacrificed other things
in order to get these benefits now
But it's a very hard question
when you look at this
You say these people
they've done service
they've put these expectations
but at the same time
this is really cutting in
and this is just one thing I'm showing
It's really cutting in to very important areas of investment
for the entire state
So the whole reason of really just surfacing this
whole pension issue is just to put this in
and hopefully people understand what these issues are
because that's the only way that fairly hard decisions
are going to have to be made
Decisions on cutting necessary investments
or restructuring or who knows what it may be
I don't envy the people who have to make these decisions