Over which interval does y(x) have an average rate of change of -4?
So... average rate of change, if you think about it... you're literally just averaging (for example), this bowl section right over here.
The slope is really really steep, it gets less steep... very negatively sloped.
It gets less negative, less negative...
Slope is 0 here. Then it gets positive... more positive, and more positive... and more positive.
But when you get to this point right over here... You see you got to where you started from.
And the average... One, you could say the average... the net change has been 0.
And any interval over which the net change has been 0, also tells you that the average rate of change is going to be 0.
So you could view that the average rate of change is really the slope of the line that connects the 2 endpoints of your interval.
So another way of asking, "Over what interval does y(x) have an average rate of change of -4?" is: "Can you come up with an interval where the slope between the endpoints of the interval is -4?"
So let's see what choices they give us.
This first interval is x is between -1 and 1 (-1< x <1). So this is X < -1. When X = -1... y(x) is all the way over here.
Y(-1) = 7
Then when X = 1, our graph is down over here.
Y(1) = -1