In the last video we learned that if we have two different triangles
And if all of the corresponding sides of the two triangles have the same length,
then by side side side we know that
the two triangles are congruent. And I also touched a little bit on
the idea of an axiom or a postulate.
But I wanna be clear: sometimes you'll hear this referred to as
a side side side theorem - theorem - and sometimes you'll hear it as
a side side side postulate or axiom - postulate or axiom.
And I think it's worth differentiating what these mean.
A postulate or an axiom is something that you just assume, you assume from the get-go,
while a theorem is something you prove using more basic,
or using some postulates or axioms.
So, and really in all of mathematics you make some core assumptions.
You make some core assumptions. You call these -
You call these the axioms or the postulates.
Axioms - axioms or the postulates
And then using those, you try to prove theorems.
So maybe using that one I can prove some theorem over here
And they'd be using that theorem
and then this axiom, I can prove another theorem over here
and them using both of those theorems
I can prove another theorem over here - I think you get the picture.
This axiom might lead us to this theorem
And these two might lead us to this theorem right over here
And we essentially try to build our knowledge
Or we build a mathematics around these core assumptions.
In an introductory geometry class, we kind of
We don't rigorously prove side side side
We don't rigorously the prove side side side theorem
And that's why a lot of geometry calls you kind of just take it as a given
As a postulate or an axiom
And the whole reason why I'm doing this is
One I just want you to know the differences between the words
theorem and postulate or axiom
And also so that you don't get confused. It is just a given
but in a lot of books and I've looked at several books
they do refer to it as a side side side theorem
even though they never prove it rigorously.
They do just assume it.
So it really is more of a postulate or an axiom.
Now with that out of they way, we just take -
we're just going to assume going forward that we just know
that this is true, we're gonna take it as a given
I wanna show you that we can already do something pretty useful with it.
So let's say that we have a circle.
Let's say we have a circle. There's many useful things
that we can already do with it.
And this circle has a center right here at A
and let's say that that we have a chord
a chord in this circle that that is not a diameter.
So let me draw a chord here.
So let me draw a chord in the circle, so that's a kind of a segment
of a secant line, and let's say that I have
Let's say that I have a line that bisects - that bisects this chord from - from the center.
And I guess I can call it a radius 'cause I'm gonna go from
the center to - to the edge of the circle right over there.
So I went to the center to circle itself.
And when I say bisects it, these are all
I'm just setting up the problem right now.
When I say bisecting it, it means it splits that line segment in half.
So what it tells us is, is that the length of this segment right over here
is going to be equivalent to the length of this segment right over there.
And what I wanna do is, so this is, I set it up I have a circle.
This radius bisects this chord right over here.
And what I wanna do is prove - the goal here is to prove, is to prove
that it bisects this chord at a right angle.
Or another way to say it, let me add some points here
Let's just call this B, let's call this C, and let's call this D.
I wanna prove that segment AB, segment AB is perpendicular
It intersects it at a right angle, it is perpendicular to segment CD, to segment CD.
And as you can imagine I'm gonna prove it pretty much
using the side side side whatever you wanna call it
side side side theorem, postulate or axiom.
So let's do it, let's think about it this way.
So you can imagine if I'm gonna use this I need to have some triangles,
there's no triangles here right now, but I can construct triangles,
and I can construct triangles based on things I know.
For example, I can construct - this has some radius
So let's call this, that's a radius right over here, the length of that is just going to be the radius of the circle,
but I can also do it right over here, the length of AC
is also going to be the radius of the circle.
So we know that these two lines have the same length
which is the radius of the circle, which is the radius of the circle
or we can say that AD is congruent to AC
or the have the exact same lengths.
We know from the set up in the problem
we know from the set up in the problem
that this segment is equal in length to this segment over here.
We could even, let me add a point here so I can refer to it
so if I call that point E we know from the set up in the problem
that CE is congruent to ED or they have the same length
CE has the same length as ED.
And we also know that both of these triangles - the one here on
the left and the one here on the right, the one here on the right
the both share the side EA so EA is clearly equal to EA.
So this is clearly equal to itself, it's the same side.
The same side has been used for both triangles.
The triangles are adjacent to each other.
And so we see a situation where we have a tri - where we have two different triangles
that have corresponding sides being equal.
This side is equivalent to this side right over here.
This side is is equal in length to that side over there.
And then we have obviously AE is equivalent to itself
It's a side on both of them.
It's a corresponding side on both of these triangles.
And so by side side side, so by side side side
we know, we know that triangle, triangle ABC
triangle ABC is congruent to triangle AE -
Oh sorry, it's not ABC it's AEC, sorry.
We know, it should let me write it over here
by side side side we know, we know that triangle AEC, AEC
is congruent to triangle AED.
But how does that help us? How does that help us knowing
that you know we use our little theorem
but how does that actually help us here?
Well what's cool is once we know that two triangles are congruent
So because, so because they congruent that tells us
So from that we can deduce that all the angles are the same.
And in particular we can deduce that this angle right over here
that the measure of angle CEA, CEA is equivalent
to measure of angle DEA, DEA, the measure of angle DEA.
And the reason why that's also, why that's useful
is that we also see just by looking at this
that they are supplementary to each other.
They're adjacent angles, their outer sides form a straight angle.
So CEA is supplementary and equivalent to DEA.
So they're also supplementary. So we also have the measure
of angle CEA, the measure of angle CEA
plus the measure of angle DEA is equal to 180 degrees.
But they're equivalent to each other so I can replace
the measure of DEA with the measure of CEA, measure of angle CEA.
Or I could rewrite this as two times
the measure of angle CEA is equal to 180 degrees.
Or I could divide both sides by two and I'd say the measure
of angle CEA is equal to 90 degrees
which is going to be the same as the measure of angle DEA, because they're equivalent.
So we know that this angle right over here is 90 degrees
so I can glue it with that little box
and this angle right over here is 90 degrees
and because AB intersects where, intersects CD we have a
90 degree angle here and there
and we could also prove this over there as well
they are perpendicular to each other.