[music]
We're at the Musée d'Orsay, and we're looking at
a cast from 1917, the year that Rodin died,
of his "The Gates of Hell," which is
this huge project that the artist worked on
for the last decades of his life,
that he never finished. And in fact,
we're not even sure how it fits together,
because it was found in pieces in his studio.
And so we're looking at a plaster cast, to be specific.
It's impossible to think about doors without thinking about
Ghiberti's doors on the Baptistry of the Cathedral of Florence,
which were called the "Gates of Paradise,"
because they were so beautiful.
So this is a modern answer to that, isn't it?
Right, because those of course depict Biblical scenes
from the Old and New Testament,
but here we're really unmoored from that tradition,
from that iconography, in many ways.
Well, it's a literary tradition, and it's referring back
to Dante, but ever so loosely.
So we have Dante at the top there -
- Right, he's in the tympana.
You know, that's also a stand-alone sculpture,
which is called "the Thinker," and is here
Dante, in a sense, gazing into Hell.
I think we should actually say, right at the front,
that this was a commission,
and this was intended to actually be for a building
that was to be on the site of the Musée d'Orsay,
which was to be a museum of decorative arts,
which was never built.
But this was a commission that Rodin got,
and when he had finished the design of the doors,
he was ready to cast it, but then
the project itself fell through,
so he kept working on it.
And in a sense, the sculpture continued to evolve.
You do see so many figures that you recognize
as stand-alone sculptures by Rodin,
but the thing that strikes me most is
just how much the figures emerge
from the "background" of the doors.
And I said "background" sort of in quotes,
- And the "doors" should be in quotes!
- And the "doors" should be in quotes, right!
Because they could never function any more.
But it's like, the doors don't even look like solid forms.
They're like vapor from which these forms emerge
and spill out into our space.
It's almost as if we imagined the surface of those doors
to be the surface of the ocean,
and sort of waves coming forward,
and these figures sort of rising and then falling.
And there's this sort of constant sense
of motion and undulation.
In a sense, form taking shape and then
form receding into a sort of indistinctness.
Almost like a sense of eternal becoming.
So, this sort of foment of the creative.
But this dark notion, because
the stand-alone figures that we're seeing
are figures that are tragic.
We have Paolo and Francesca,
we have Ugolino,
- the figures who Dante finds in Hell,
who are being tortured and punished
for their sins on Earth.
All the way at the top, instead of angels
we have three Shades.
These are figures that are actually a repeat.
So, it's one figure that's seen three times,
almost sort of cinemagraphic, in a sense,
but creating a kind of unified form with sort of -
- it's a little bit difficult to see from below -
but with shoulders that actually create
a flat plateau, and three arms
that sort of pull downward,
and pull our eye down into the Gates themselves.
You know, I'm so reminded of Michelangelo
when I look at all of these figures,
and the expressive power of the body,
especially the male body,
and also the way that some of the forms are fragmented
reminds me of looking at ancient Greek and Roman sculpture.
So, this is a really modern reinvention of sculpture.
Yes. Clearly informed by Michelangelo,
clearly informed by the classical.
But this notion of the fragmented self,
this notion of re-use, this notion of reworking -
very much a nineteenth century,
very much a modern notion.
And in a way, I think, the forms,
although derived from the narrative
of Dante's "Inferno," really come to take on
a kind of more universal significance about
the human condition, about suffering,
about sin, about emotion, and the power of the body.
[music]