I'm now going to do a few classic problems
that show up a lot at math competetions
and sometimes on standardized tests,
and they seem like very daunting
and intimidating problems, but hopefully
over the course of this video,
you'll realize that
if you kind of see what they're asking for,
it's really not that bad.
So let's try this first one right over here.
They tell us
a
a +
a + b
a + b +
a + b + c
a + b + c =
a + b + c = 7
and then they ask us, what is
5a
5a +
5a + 5
5a + 5b
5a + 5b +
5a + 5b + 5
5a + 5b + 5c equal to?
And the first reaction is like,
"Well, you just gave me one equation right over here,
one equation with three unknowns,
how do I solve for a, b, or c?
Don't I have to be able to solve for
a, b, or c in order to figure out
what 5a + 5b + 5c is?"
So I'll let you think about that for a second.
So, the big idea here
is to realize that 5a + 5b + 5c
that's just the same thing as
5(
5(a
5(a +
5(a + b
5(a + b +
5(a + b + c)
If you distribute the 5 here,
5 times a,
5 times b,
5 times c,
you get 5a + 5b + 5c,
another way you can think of it is
we are factoring a 5 out.
If you factor a 5 out,
you are left with 5(a + b + c)
Now, how do we evaluate this?
Well, that first equation gave us all
the information that we needed.
They told us that a + b + c
They told us that a + b + c = 7
a + b + c
a + b + c = 7
so 5(a + b + c) is the same exact thing,
and I think you see
where this is going now,
is 5(
is 5(7)
is 5(7), and now this becomes
pretty straightforward,
and that's going to be equal to 35.
Let's do one more of these,
and this is going to be
a little bit more involved,
but hopefully you see the same idea.
So we're told,
a
a +
a + b
a + b +
a + b + c
a + b + c is equal to -1
And we have two more variables here,
we're told that x
we're told that x + y
we're told that x + y is equal to 7
and then they ask us this big hairy thing,
what is this equal to?
And I'll give you a few seconds
to give it a little bit of thought.
Well, you can imagine,
you're given three variables
with one equation up here,
another two variables with another equation,
we have five unknowns with two equations,
there's no way we're going
to be able to individually figure out what
a
a or
a or b
a or b or
a or b or c
a or b or c or
a or b or c or x
a or b or c or x or
a or b or c or x or y
a or b or c or x or y is,
but maybe we can use
what we saw in the last example
to solve this.
And so what we might want to do
is rearrange it so that we have the
xs and ys kind of grouped together,
and the as, bs, and cs
kinda grouped together.
So let's try that out.
Let's focus first on the
as,
as, bs,
as, bs, and
as, bs, and cs
So we have -9a, -9b --
I'll go in alphabetical order --
-9b and -9c, and I think you see
what's emerging.
And then let's work on the xs and the ys.
And then we have -7x, and
then we have a -7y
So, all I have done is rearranged
this expression here,
but this makes it, in a way,
a little bit clearer of what's
going on here.
These first three terms,
I can factor our a -9,
and I get -9
and I get -9(a
and I get -9(a +
and I get -9(a + b
and I get -9(a + b +
and I get -9(a + b + c)
and these second two terms,
I can factor out a 7.
-7
-7(
-7(x
-7(x +
-7(x + y)
and just to verify,
if you wanted to go the other way,
multiply this -7 times (x + y)
and you'll get this
Multiply -9 times (a + b + c),
(distribute it)
you'll get this right over here.
And so this makes it a little bit clearer.
What is (a + b + c) equal to?
Well they tell us right over here,
a + b + c is equal to -1
this whole expression is -1,
at least in the parentheses,
and what is (x + y) equal to?
(Let me do this in a new color)
What is (x + y) equal to?
Well, they tell us right over here,
x + y is equal to 7
So this whole thing simplifies to
-
-9
-9(
-9(-
-9(-1)
-9(-1) -
-9(-1) - 7
-9(-1) - 7(
-9(-1) - 7(7)
and so this is equal to--
we're in the home stretch--
-9(-1), well that's positive 9,
and then -7(7) is negative 49
so it's 9 - 49,
which is equal to
which is equal too
which is equal tooo
which is equal toooo
which is equal toooo!
negative 40.
And we are done.