Let's say we've got a company here that has
exactly four shares, just to simplify things.
Obviously very few companies have only four shares,
but this will simplify the explanation.
And let's say that each of those shares right now
is trading in the market, or I guess we could say,
in the last transaction that's occurred in trading these shares,
they're trading at two dollars per share.
So the market is saying that
each of those shares is worth two dollars,
there's four of those shares in total,
and we're going to assume that this company has no liabilities,
so the shareholders just outright own the assets,
so if there's four of these shares times two dollars,
the market is saying that
this company's assets are worth exactly eight dollars.
Eight dollars, right over here.
The asset value, the market value of the assets is
the same as the market cap in this case
because we have no liabilities.
Now what I want to think about is,
what happens if the company wants to raise some more money?
Let's say that they want to issue some more shares and sell them
to raise some money to buy a factory or whatever.
So what they literally do is,
the board approves for them to literally create
two more shares, so now they have a total of six shares outstanding,
and then the company goes, they get an investment banker
and they do a secondary offering in the public markets
and they sell these incremental shares.
And they're able to sell them, let's just say for simplicity,
at two dollars per share.
Normally when you increase the supply a little bit
you won't get quite what the previous market value was,
but you get roughly two dollars a share, for simplicity.
And by selling two shares that they just created
for two dollars a share,
the company is able to raise another four dollars.
So the whole reason why I'm going through this exercise
is to ask a question.
Did dilution take place?
And there are different ways to think about it.
When you think about dilution, it's like you could imagine.
If you have a sweet syrup and you add water to it,
it becomes less sweet.
Each cube of that water, each drop of that water
has less sugar in it. You've diluted it.
And so there seems to be an analogy here.
We now have more shares for the same company.
And it is true.
If you were the owner of this share over here,
before the share offering up here,
you owned 25% of the company.
After the share offering, you owned one sixteenth.
So — not one sixteenth, one sixth.
So after, you own one sixth, or approximately 16%.
So it looks like the percentage that you own of the company has been diluted
and that's true to some degree.
But sometimes the dilution takes on another meaning
that somehow, because more shares are being used
for the ownership of the same company,
maybe these shares are worth less.
And that's the one thing that I want to challenge.
There is dilution in the percentage that you own,
but there is not dilution in what the shares are worth.
Because before, if you had four shares representing
something that is worth eight dollars,
now you have six shares representing
something that is twelve dollars.
Because the company didn't just issue these shares
and get nothing in return for it.
It got four dollars of cash.
You can't debate the value of four dollars.
Four dollars are worth four dollars.
So now the assets of the company are worth twelve dollars.
So you have twelve dollars of assets, no liabilities,
six shares, twelve dollars divided by six shares
is still two dollars per share.
So the value per share has not been diluted,
just the percentage of the company that you happen to own.