Tina Olsen: We are in the European Galleries of the Portland Art Museum
I am Christina Olsen
Maribeth Graybill: And I'm Maribeth Graybill
Tina: And we're standing in front of this incredible object by a follower of Bernardo Daddi
and what we see is a Madonna--the mother of Christ--surrounded by this group of saints and angels
--and this is not just a painting--it's really an object
Maribeth: What really draws me to this piece of the many--many Madonna and Christ as infant paintings in this room
--is what you've just pointed out that it is not a flat surface--it's not an easel painting
--but the whole thing is in fact a miniature church
Tina: Yes!
Maribeth: And so that there is the panel--the back-panel which has a steeple above it
--and then are doors--there's an entry way and these doors can be close
--and when they're closed--as we walk around the side--we can see it's just plain gilt
--perhaps gilt leather or gilt wood on the outside
--but then when you enter this space--when you open the doors
--suddenly you're in the presence of the Madonna
Tina: Absolutely--I love that too and I love this way
in which you realize that the object was both of course a representation
but also something that you the viewer and the devotee have a relationship with
--and the doors open and you are in the presence of the Madonna and this scene is revealed to you
--and let's talk about this scene because it's really really not just an image of the Madonna
but also the story of her life--we see the angel Gabriel on the top left door
--and the angel Gabriel comes down from heaven and tells Mary
that she will be the mother of Christ--that she will bear a son
Maribeth: The enunciation scene--and what's so wonderful
in these two is the sensitivity of this artist's gestures
--so Gabriel raises his right hand to make an announcement
Tina: Absolutely!
Maribeth: Mary--you know--and she as you've pointed out earlier
--places her hand over her heart and inclines her head in this beautifully modest -- "me?..me?"
--we can almost hear the conversation between them because it's so dramatically enacted for us
Tina: Absolutely! And then below the angel Gabriel
--we see in fact the nativity scene when Christ is born in the manger
Maribeth: With a cow and a donkey
Tina: And angels above with halos
Maribeth: And Joseph below interacting I think with a sheperd
--and then over here on the right-hand side is the crucifixion
--Christ on the cross--emaciated--his skin even takes on a sort of deathly pallor
--blood is coming from his wounds--and at his feet--standing on the ground-- his moth Mary is swooning
--and accompanied by John and other follows of Jesus
Tina: And John holds her up in this incredible--and she's just mourning her son has died
--and I love the way in which then the object has both an immediate time and also a narrative time
--in other words we come upon it and there the virgin is
--but what we see to the left and right is both what has happened before and what will happen to come
--so this is just this unbelievable sense of presence and kind of multiple senses of time in the object
Maribeth: And it just occurs to me as you say that
--that if we think about it--the panels have narrative things
--you know--things have happened--things that are recorded in the Bible
--but the central panel of Mary enthroned--that's not in the biblical text
--but also because that's presented hieratically--that's eternal--it's outside of time
Tina: And that's the relationship with us
--I mean it's really the central panel that is always alive and always speaking to us
--as both an image but also an alive efficacious diety