Where we left off in the last video, we had somewhat ...
simplified our polynomial P of X.
from the way that it was originialy described in the problem.
But it still doesn't seem like were any closer to finding
the roots. At least we were able to reduce the degree from a fourty-seventh degree polynomial to a
product of a first degree and a twenty third degree polynomial,
but it still doesn't seem like we're any closer to finding the roots, especially the root that matter.
And here we're going to have a little bit of an Ah-ha moment here.
That this part in blue, which is really just a sum of all of the degrees of X from
X to the zero all the way to X to the twenty three.
This is, if you view the common ratio was X, as a finit geometric series.
And, I have done it in other videos, there is a way to find the sum of a finit geometric series.
And we'll use a similar technique right here, to simplify this a little bit, to help us find the roots.
So let's just call this whole thing S.
S is equal to X to the 23 plus X to the 22 plus all the way down to X plus 1.