We humans like to get our heads around all of the complexity around us by classifying things,
and you can imagine there's no more obvious thing to classify
than all the living things around us, than all of the life that surrounds us
so what I want to start talking about is, how do we classify all of the life around us and this is more
often generally referred to as taxonomy, but the most basic question you have when you look at all of
the life around you, you start to see similarities between some of these living things. You see obviously
this this this thing right over here is more similar to the things that look like it than it does to
the grass behind it, or to that tree, and so we start saying oh maybe maybe I should group this thing
right over here into a group with other things like it and that's the very most building block of how we
classify all of the living things around us, is putting them into buckets called species. So for example,
this is one particular animal, but we see other animals that seem to look like it so we say they're all
a part of a species of lions, and this animal its one animal and there's other animals that have stripes
but some might be fatter, or taller, or skinnier, or whatever else darker or lighter, but we say they're
similar enough that we call them all, we call them all tigers. We call all the animals even though they
might be a little bit bigger, skinnier, or fatter, lighter, or darker we call all of them that have this
kind of, they look similar to this thing right over here we'd call this, call this a donkey. We would
call this a donkey. We would call the things that we think are like this animal right here a horse. Now
that might seem like a straight, pretty straight forward way to think about it. Oh everything that looks
kind of like this character right here is a lion. Everything that looks kind of like this character right
here is a tiger, but that by itself is not a good enough definition for species. Things that look like
each other or things that act like each other, because what we will see is that there are some things
that could be very different, at least in how they look or act that are actually closely related, and
then we will talk about what it means to be closely related, and then we can see things that look very
similar, that they have similar structures, they have similar behavior like for example bats and birds
but they're actually all very very distantly related, so we need a more exact definition for species than
just things that look like each other or just things that act like each other and so the most typical
definition for a species are animals, animals that can interbreed, that can interbreed interbreed and
when we say interbreed literally they can produce offspring with each other and and the offspring are
fertile, and offspring are fertile. Which means that the offspring can then have have further have babies,
that they're not, they're not sterile. They're capable of breeding with other animals, and producing and
producing more offspring and to show an example of this this right here is a male lion, you find a male
lion and and a female lioness and most of the time they will be able to have offspring and the offspring
can go and mate with other lions or lionesses depending on their sex, and then they can have viable offspring
so it seems to work out pretty well for lions. Same thing is true of tigers. Now it does turn out that
if you get a male lion. If you have a male lion, and a female tigress they can breed. They can breed
and they can produce offspring, and their offspring which was made famous by napoleon dynamite. He was
kind of fascinated, these are kind of fascinating animals. Their offspring is called a liger. You get
a male lion breeding with the female tiger you produce a liger which is a hybrid a cross between a lion
and a tiger, and they're fascinating animals actually larger than either lions or tigers. They're the
largest cats that we know off, but these ligers cannot be referred to as a separate species, or you can't
say that lions and tigers are the same species because even though they are able to interbreed their
offspring for the most part is not able is not fertile. is not able to produce offspring. There have been
one of stories of ligers being mated with either a lion or tiger but those are one off stories. In general
ligers can't interbreed, and in general this combination isn't going to produce offspring that can keep
interbreeding and are fertile. So that's why we say that lions and tigers are different species, and that
ligers we wouldn't even call it a species at all we would actually call it a hybrid between two species
now the same thing is true and actually you might be asking yourself well this was a male lion and a
female tigress what about if we went the other way around. What if we had a female lioness and a male
tiger? In that case you would produce something else called a Tiglon or a tigloon actually don't know
how to pronounce that and that is a a different hybrid that has slightly different properties than a liger.
S o I encourage you to look up what a tiglon is. Similarly you give me a male donkey, you give me a male
donkey and donkeys are clearly a species by themselves
because if you give me a male donkey and a female donkey they can reproduce, produce another donkey and
then that donkey can mate with other donkeys to produce more donkeys. So not only a donkey interbreed
with another donkey but that product that child donkey can then interbreed with can keep interbreeding
with other donkeys. Similarly horses they can interbreed and produce fertile offspring, but if you give
me a male donkey and a female horse they can mate and they can produce a mule. they can produce a mule
but once again like the ligers mules are not at least as far as I know, mules cannot, they're not fertile.
Mules cannot produce further offspring. They cannot interbreed with each other, and because even though
donkeys and horses can breed and produce mules their offspring aren't fertile we don't consider donkeys
and horses part of the same species, and we would consider mules like a liger or a tiglon, we would consider
them a hybrid. So these are all hybrids, what we would call a cross. In general the world hybrid is
used when you have two things, two different types that are somehow coming together, somehow having a
combination, and once again like the case with the tiglon you might say well what if I had a female donkey
what if I had a female donkey and a male horse, and then you would actually produce something called
a hinny, like called a hinny which similarly isn't as common as a mule and people like to use mules they're
actually very good work animals because they, they have some good properties of both donkeys and horses
hinnys are less common, but once again it is possible and they have different properties than mules,
and I do want to emphasize this idea because when we started of we just kind of tried to think oh well
how can we classify things and we said well hey maybe things that look and act similar should be called
species but i want to show you where maybe things that look and act different, we shouldn't call them
species. I want to show you a very typical case one that is really all around us all the time where this
definition animals that can interbreed and the offspring are fertile really does beseem to become much
much more important than just some notion of animals that look alike or animals that act the same and
the best example of that is with dogs. As I said this is a very typical species here because dogs and
I just took a sample of different types of breeds of dogs they can look very very different. Its obvious
look at the difference between these, for example this little chihuahua here and this dog right over
here obviously they're size wise their look even the way they act are almost are much much more different much
than maybe how this donkey would act relative to this horse or how this lion would act relative to this
tigress and that they obviously look, they look very different. They're completely different sizes but
these two things actually can interbreed although with these two in particular seems like the mechanics
would get kind of difficult, but assuming they get over the mechanical hurdles they could interbreed and
produce fertile offspring same for these two characters. Same for these two characters over here, and
because of that even though all the different breeds of dogs and most of this is really due to human
doings trying to breed for particular, specific traits. Even though they look so different and act so
different because they can interbreed and they can produce fertile offspring we consider all of these the same species.