PROBLEM: "The scale on a map is
7 centimeters for every 10 kilometers –
or 7 centimeters for 10 kilometers.
If the distance between two cities is 60 kilometers –
(So that's the actual distance.)
– how far apart, in centimeters,
are the two cities on the map?"
Well they give us this scale.
For every 10 kilometers in the real world,
the map is going to show 7 centimeters.
Or another way to think about it is if you see
7 centimeters on the map,
that represents 10 kilometers in the real world.
Now, they're saying that the distance
between the two cities is 60 kilometers.
So, it's essentially 6 × 10 kilometers.
So times 6.
So if you have to 6 × 10 kilometers on the map,
you're going to have 6 × 7 centimeters.
So times 6.
And 6 × 7 centimeters gets you to 42 centimeters.
So how far apart in centimeters
are the two cities on the map?
Well, 42 centimeters.