simplify three A to the fifth over nine A squared times A to the fourth over A to the third
so before we even worry about the A's we can actually simplify the three and the nine
they're both divisible by three
so let's divide the numerator and the denominator here by three
so if we divide the numerator by three, the three becomes a one
if we divide the denominator by three, the nine becomes a three
so this reduces to, or simplifies to, one A to the fifth times A to the fourth
or maybe i should say A to the fifth over three A squared
times A to the fourth over A to the third
now this, if we just multiply the two expressions this would be equal to
one A to the fifth times A to the fourth in the numerator
and we don't have to worry about the one, it doesn't change the values
so it's A to the fifth times A to the fourth in the numerator
and then we have three times A squared times A to the third in the denominator
now there's multiple ways that we can simplify this from here
one, sometimes its called the quotient rule, and its just the idea that if you have
A to the 'x' over A to the 'y', that this is going to be equal to A to the 'x' minus 'y'
and just to understand why that works lets think about A to the fifth over A squared
so A to the fifth is literally A times A times A times A times A
that right there is A to the fifth
and we have that over A squared, and i'm just thinking about the A squared right over here
so we have that over A squared, which is literally just A times A
that is A squared
now we can clearly, both the numerator and the denominator, are both divisible by A times A
we can divide them both by A times A
if we divide the numerator by A twice, so by A times A, so lets get rid of an A times A
and if we divide the denominator by A times A, we just get a one
so what are we just left with
we are left with just A times A times A over 1, which is just A times A times A
but what is this?
this is A to the third power, or A to the five minus two power
we had five, we were able to cancel out two, that gave us three
so we can do the same thing over here, we can apply the quotient rule
and i'll do this in two ways, so lets apply the quotient rule with the A to the fifth and the A squared
and also, let me do it this way
so lets apply with these two guys and then lets apply it with these two guys
and of course we have the one third out front
so this can be reduced to one third times, if we apply the quotient rule with A to the fifth over A squared
we just did it over here
that becomes A to the third power
and if we apply it over here with the A to the fourth over A to the third
that'll give us A to the four minus three power
or A to the first power
and of course we can simplify this as A to the third times A
well actually let me just do it over here
before I even rewrite it we know that A to the third times A to the first
is going to be A to the three plus one power
we have the same base so we can add the exponents
we're multiplying A times itself three times and then one more time
so that'll be A to the fourth power
so this right over here becomes A to the fourth power, A to the three plus one power
and then we have to multiply that by one third
so our answer could be one third A to the fourth
or we could equally write it A to the fourth over three
now the other way to do this problem would've been to apply the product
or to add the exponents in the numerator and then add the exponents in the denominator
so lets do it that way first
so if we add the exponents in the numerator first
we don't apply the quotient rule first, we apply it second
we get in the numerator A to the fifth times A to the fourth
would be A to the ninth power, five plus four
and then in the denominator we have A squared times A to the third
add the exponents because we were taking the product with the same base
so it'll be A to the fifth power
and we still have the three down here, we have a one third, or we could just write a three over here
now we could apply the quotient property of exponents
we could say look we have A to the ninth over A to the fifth
A to the ninth over A to the fifth is equal to A to the nine minus five power
or it's equal to A to the fourth power
and of course we still have the divided by three
either way we got the same answer