Factor 'x' squared minus forty-nine 'y' squared
so what's interesting here is that,
while x squared is clearly a perfect square
-it's the square of x
forty-nine y squared is also a perfect square
it's the square of seven y
so it looks like we might have a special form
-just thing is what happens if we take:
a plus b times a minus b
I'm just doing it in the general case so we can see a pattern here
this would be: a times a
- which would be a squared-, plus: a times negative b,
-which would be negative ab-, plus b times a,
-or a times b again, which would be ab-
and then you have b times negative b, which would be minus b squared
Now, these middle two terms cancel out: minus ab, plus ab
and you're left with a squared minus b squared
and that's the exact pattern we have here, we have an a squared minus a b squared
so, in this case, a is equal to x, and b is equal to seven y.
So we have x squared minus seven y, the whole thing, squared
So we can expand this as a difference of squares
or actually this thing right over here is a difference of squares
so we can expand this, like this, so this will be equal to:
x plus seven y, times x minus seven y
and, once again, we're just pattern matching,
based on this realization right over here:
if I take a plus b, times a minus b, I get a difference of squares
this is a difference of squares,
so when I factor it, it must come out to something that looks like
a plus b times a minus b, or x plus seven y, times x minus seven y