We're asked to subtract, and we have the complex number two minus three i,
and from that, we are subtracting six minus eighteen i.
So, the first thing I'd like to do here is to just kind of get rid of these parentheses.
So we just have a bunch of real parts and imaginary parts that we can then add up together.
So we have two minus three i and then we're subtracting this entire quantity,
and to get rid of the parentheses, we can just distribute the negative sign,
or, another way to think about it, we can say that this is negative one times all of this.
So we can just distribute the negative sign and negative one times six is negative six--let me do these in magenta--
so this is negative six,
and then negative one times negative eighteen i, well that's just going to be positive,
positive eighteen i: negative times a negative is a positive.
And now we want to add the real parts and we want to add the imaginary parts,
so here is a real part here: two, and then we have a minus six,
so we have two minus six,
and we want to add the imaginary parts.
We have a negative--let me do that in a different color--
we have a negative three i right over here, so negative three i (or "minus three i")
right over there, and then we have a plus eighteen i
or positive eighteen i, so then we have a positive eighteen i.
If you add the real parts: two minus six is negative four.
And you imag-- add the--add the imaginary parts: if I have negative three of something,
and to that I add eighteen of something,
well, that's just going to leave me with fifteen of that something.
Or another way you can think about it:
if I have eighteen of something and I subtract three of that something,
I'll have fifteen of that something.
In this case, that "something" is the imag-- is i, the imaginary unit,
so this is, so this is going to be plus fifteen--plus fifteen i--and we are done.