Let's multiply 9 times...8,000...8,085.
That should be a pretty fun little calculation to do.
So like always let's just rewrite this,
so I'm going to write the 8,085.
I'm going to write the 9 right below it and write our little multiplication symbol.
And now we're ready to compute.
So first, we can tackle 9 times 5.
Well we know that 9 times 5 is 45.
We can write the 5 in the ones place
and carry the 4 to the tens place.
So if 9 times 5 is 45.
Now we're ready to move on to 9 times 8.
And we're going to calculate 9 times 8
and then add the 4 that we just carried.
So 9 times 8 is 72, plus the 4 is 76.
So we'll write the 6 right here in the tens place
and carry the seven.
Now, we are ready to calculate
(and I'm looking for a suitable color)
9 times 0...9 times 0 hundreds plus
(and this is the 7 in the hundreds place,
so that's actually 700)
or if we're just kind of going with the computation,
9 times 0 plus 7.
Well 9 times 0 is 0, plus 7 is 7...is 7.
And then finally, finally, we have
(and once again I'm looking for a suitable color)
9 times 8, 9 times 8,
this is the last thing we have to compute.
We already know that 9 times 8 is 72
and we just write the 72 right down here.
And we're done!
8,085 times 9 is 72,765.
Let's do one more example just to make sure that this is really clear in your brain.
At least the process for doing this, and I also want you to think about why this works.
So let's try...let's try 7 times 5,000...5,396.
And I encourage you to pause it
and try it on your own as well.
Well 5,000...(I'm going to re-write it)
5,396 times 7 - first we'll think about...
first we'll think about what 7 times 6 is;
we know that's 42.
Put the 2 in the ones place, 4 we will carry.
Then we need to concern ourselves with 7 times 9.
But then we have to calculate that
and then add the 4.
7 times 9 is 63 plus 4 is 67.
So, we get...we put the 7 down here and carry the 6.
Then, we have to worry about 7 times 3
plus this 6 that we have just finished carrying.
7 times 3 is 21 plus 6 is 27.
So, we'll write the 7 here in the hundreds place
and carry the 2.
And finally, we have 7 times 5,
which is 35 but we have to add the 2.
35 plus 2 is 37.
So 5,396 times 7 is 37,772.