I'm now going to introduce an ancient method
for generating a list of primes up to some limit N
called the Sieve of Eratosthenes.
Now Eratosthenes was born in 276 BC
so this method is over 2200 years old.
but it's very simple and elegant
and you could teach it to any child.
Now let's say for example
we want to calculate all the primes up to a 100
but this would work in the same way
if we wanted to calculate up to ten thousand or a billion.
It proceeds as follows:
assume all numbers are unmarked.
Grey is unmarked.
We start at the beginning
and if we find a number that is unmarked
we know it's prime.
So we hit two
and we say 2 is prime because it's unmarked.
And then the second phase is
now we can eliminate all multiples of 2
because we know they're composite
so -bam- we jump along
and we eliminate all multiples of 2
red means composite
And now we repeat.
We step along from 2 to 3
3 is unmarked, so we mark 3 as prime.
And now we can eliminate all multiples of 3.
And a really simple optimization
is - notice 6 is already crossed off -
we actually cross off the multiples starting at
the square of that number.
So 3 times 3 is 9,
we start at 9 and mark all multiples of 3
as composite.
And again, we go back, we jump along to 4
well, 4 is marked, we know it's composite
we jump along to 5,
we found an unmarked number, 5 is prime.
Now, 5 times 5 is 25,
we go to 25, we mark off 25, 30, 35, 40, 45
and so on..
Those are composites.
We proceed forward until we hit 7,
we know 7 is prime, because it's unmarked,
7*7 is 49
we mark 49 and all multiples of 7
above it as composite
and now we move along until we hit 11
11 is prime.
And notice now - 11*11 is greater
than a 100, so we can actually stop
at this point.
We could have stopped at 10 even,
because now all remaining unmarked numbers,
if you'll notice, are prime
and, we could in one swoop
mark them all as prime.
And that's the whole algorithm.
It's so simple.
And just to generalize how we do this
so we could write up a programme
to perform this sieve
is if we want to find all primes up to some number N,
we first create a main loop
so we have 'for all numbers a'
from 2 to the square root of n
so notice here, we stopped when we hit 10
-- I showed it as 11 -- we actually stop
because we have found all primes.
So from 2 to the square root of n
we proceed as follows:
if 'a' is unmarked
then we know 'a' is prime
and when we find a prime number
we mark all multiples of 'a' off as composite
and that's it.
So you find a number prime,
mark off the multiples,
go back to the beginning,
increment 'a' by 1
so we're at 2, then we go to 3
then we go to 4, 5 and so on
and when we're done, we have all primes.
Notice here, that this is also a loop,
so we have a main loop 'for'
and when we find a prime
this marking off of multiples is also a loop
so it's important to notice here
that we have a nested loop --
we have a loop inside a loop.
Here is an example of this algorithm in action
i wrote in javascript below.
If I put in a 100,
here are all the primes under a 100
and if I put in 200
here are all the primes under 200
and if I put in 850,
here are all the primes under 850.
And below I have this programme
with a recording explaining how I set it up.