the maximum value of the expression one over
sine squared of theta plus three sine theta
co-sign theta
plus five cosine squared of theta is
let's rewrite this, so this is one over
one over, so i have a sine squared of theta
i have a sine squared of theta and then
at least my brain whenever i see a sine squared of theta
i always look for cosine squared of theta because
i know when i take the sum of them it equals one
i don't have just one cosine squared of theta
here at five cosine squared of thetas let me just
take one of them
so i have a plus cosine the squared theta
because i took one of them i only have four
of these left
so plus four cosine squared of theta
and then i have this stuff plus
three sine
of theta of co-sine of theta
so what this
first first step allowed me to do is just turn
two characters right over here sine squared
theta plus cosine squared theta
that is equal to one
so we've simplified it to one over
one over
one plus
now lets think about how we can write co-signed squared
of theta
i'll write our identities here
co-signed squared of theta we've proved these
in the
trigonometry playlist. This is equal to
one-plus cosine
one-plus co-signed of two theta
all of that
over
two and my goal here is that i really
just wanna get everything, well i just wanna simplify and maybe
we will do calculus
value of the numerator
solicit cosine squared theta is equal to this
so four times this is just going to be
so four times this before divide by two instances
would be two times this numerator
so it's going to be too
plus too
co-signed
of to data that's this term right here
and then this term
this term right over here we could use the
tree guided me that
signed of to data
is equal to two sign of state a
co-sign if data
or you divide both sides right to you get
a one-half sign of
tuesday dot
is equal to sign of feder
co-sign of theta so this is this right over
here this part right over here is going to
be one-half signed up to date a bore multiplying
it by three
just going to be plus three halves
sign of two data
sighing of
too
glitzy thus
part over here clearly simplifies
this is the recent history right this is one
over
three
plus
to co-signed of to data
plus thirty halves
sign
of to data
now we really just looking for in the minimum
we're looking for the
minimum value of the denominator which would
give us the same as the maximum value of the
new murder or just be one over at this minimum
values alexia how how lol we can get assuming
were above zero t how low we can get
for this denominator write your words will
look for its minimum value so one day we can
do just to simplify things
the middle value of this
is going to be the same demand
the bid of this thing over right there
to kind of confuses the problem
the minimum value
the replies to cosign
to stayed up plus three have sign
of two data
is going to be the same thing is the minimum
value of three plus
on the screen to the substitution the tuesday
it is equal to exodus simplify things a little
bit you don't have to do that
so three plus two co-signed of acts
plus three halves
sayed
of acts
so this is a pretty simple expression to see
how we can figure out some minimum value and
my temptation is to take the derivative find
out where the derivative is equal to zero
and then that will either be a maximum or
a minimum point
so let's take the derivatives the derivative
of this expression right over here with respect
to acs
would really love three with the for texas
zeroed route of two cosine of axis negative
negative to sign of x
derivative of three have side of actions will
be plus
three halves cosine of x
and that is going to be equal to zero we want
to find where the slope is your committee
worry about somewhere minimum point
and let's see we can
admit
we had to sign of extra boats side so we get
the rehabs
co-signed of acs is equal to two
signed of x and then we can divide both the
sides both sides of this equation
by
will survive like to first alaska too many
steps of three
forts co-signed of x
is equal to sign
of acs
and to divide both sides by cosine of x
so we get three
over for is equal to sign of x over a co-signer
of x
which is the same thing as the pentagon that
cs
so uh... annexed by you that gives us three
or attended of annexed by his three-fourths
is going to give us either a maximum or a
minimum point celeste think about this
let's think about this a little bit will be
drawn by unit circle
so think about that too
technip to expel use that will give us a tangent
of three-fourths
so that we draw my unit circle
that's the unit circle
redraw unit
download this is always the hardest part so
redraw this
r ight
their inspired units or call
so how can i get the triangle
or or
we're listing but that would how can i get
a triangle who where and angle is attended
of three four two river candid is opposite
over adjacent
right tangent is opposite over adjacent so
if missus wire triangle right over here
if this is acs
opposite over adjacent is equal to three fourths
so opposite could be three an adjacent could
be
and we hopefully immediately recognize this
this is the
this is a three four five triangle too right
triangle
three square plus four square it is twenty
five
which is five squares as of three four
triangle
there's too
headed values so x could be like this and
this obviously isn't
isn't eight unit high partners who over here
but we can divide everything by five it would
be so we could have the situation
we could have been situation over here
where this is actually this is the uh... circle
the hypothesis one
this is three over five
and this is for over five
this word tended of ax here
canada backs would give us the reports but
it was going to give us a maximum value were
minimal value
well over here both close sign
both co-signed of acts and sign of x are going
to be positive so both of these are going
to be positive values so screw them
probably maximize
maximize the six pressure over here
by the other
x that gives us the same tangent
remember the standard is really just the slope
the radius of the unit circle would be
the angle would be the single this is the
same this has the same kenton value
so dispatched
this x
over
this actually and this case the tended to
still
the tended to still going to be three-fourths
but over here
the science co-signed our negatives over here
overhear the
xc ward at or the co-sign is going to be negative
four fifths
and the sign value
or or the wide values used to be negative
three-fifths
and this will give us
this will give us
minimum boy because here everything is every
ball the sign in the coastline are negative
so let's use
let's use this x right over here
and notice we don't even have to figure out
what the axis 'cause we know
but if it ended overhears four-fifths
the speed of both the sba science going to
be
the size of the three fifths of the course
i was going to be forecast
or which will give some actual point or the
tenant could be
for three-fourths and then the side will be
negative benefits and of course i will be
negative forfeit so let's use these overuse
of the middle of
is going to be equal to three plus
went two times coastline of x_ were using
this one over here so to transpose side of
exco sign of experience
negative four fists
negative
for fests
and then plus three halves
plus three has times in the sign of x sinai
lectures negative three fifths
negative
three fits and what is this
going to be equal to this is going to be equal
to
three
plus
this is negative eight fifths
dreamweaver should write three minus eight
fifth
three minus the this
minus nine tenths
minus nine tenths and so this is going to
be equal to
we could put everything over ten
thirty over ten
minus sixteen over ten
right that's eight fists
minus nine or ten and this gives us what
this gives us five or ten
five over ten or or one-half
so the minimum value the minimum value for
denominator everything we've been dealing
with so far has been our denominator
the middle of the idea of all of this business
over here
the minimum value is one-half
so the maximum value
that this whole expression takes is when the
minimum values one out so we get one over
one-half
equal to to we're done