Hello, this is Sal from the Khan Academy. And this is going to be a simple video on how I made videos.
So first, just the equipment set up, I have a Wacom tablet right over here,
and this is the tools for tablet; I think this is like $200 or $300
if you can get a basic Bamboo tablet for like $80. It does the same thing as you pay more money;
you just get more writing surface area right over here. It functions as a mouse
with more importantly, you get a pen with it. Looks comfortably with the tablet and
you can use that to actually write.
I just have a completely standard -- actually it's below standard PC right over here.
It was like the state of the art PC in 2008. And this art program that I have right over here is the SmoothDraw 3.
This is freeware; you can use any art program you want to.
I just like to use SmoothDraw 'cause it's lightweight; I don't have the most powerful computer in the world
so it keeps the computer from freezing up and all that some of fancy art programs
and all the fancy stuff they do in the background. SmoothDraw 3 is kind of bare bones,
but at least you want it to be -- I really bare bones or maybe just want a bunch of more powerful computer,
but the minimum if you want is the ability to be pressure sensitive.
So, we -- let us draw three here. See while I'm writing I can write really lightly or I can write really dark,
and so you can -- it looks a little bit more interesting, I should've taken the felted pen right over here;
I just use the little paintbrush thing. You could use whatever you want.
I put it in brush size 6 in some sort of pastel colors right over here,
and you can see you can write really lightly or you can write really dark,
you can shade things in, and the reason why I like why it's important for something to be pressure-sensitive
is when you write with it, so "this is test writing" right over here, it looks --
it doesn't look like just computer writing; it looks at least pretty close to like actual,
like it looks like a digital, felted pen of some kind.
So all I've done so far is I have his little pen tablet; I'm able to draw on this,
and this isn't too different than what most kind of designer or artists would do in order to do some kind of graphic design,
but I haven't showed you how to actually make a video.
The actual video production is having screen capture software;
I use Camtasia Recorder which comes with Camtasia Studio,
and I think it costs like $200 or $300 for that.
I believe there's other screen capture software including some free ones.
They all have different positives and negatives; you can test them out,
with Camtasia, so I'll just Camtasia Recorder here,
and so you see is going to capture everything it sees at this portion of this screen,
and I set it up as a 1280 by 720 dimensions,
and so when I make the video I just going to capture this part here
and that's why when you see a Khan Academy video, you don't see all this other stuff right over here.
And so if I press record, it's going to start capturing everything that happens on the screen here,
and it's going to capture my voice as captured by this microphone.
Now the first like thousand kind of Khan Academy videos I did,
I used literally like a $20 Logitech USB microphone, and actually the sound is pretty decent.
And we now operated -- I think this is a Sampson microphone right over here; it's about $200.
What I found is that there's not a general -- you know, I tried some $30 microphones that work out just great,
and some $200 microphones or even $300 microphones that didn't work out just so well and had a buzzing noise or what ever,
this one seems to work well for me; both the Wacom tablet and the Sampson microphone,
they're just both USB devices you just plug them in,
and so it will see is when I start recording this video,
so I'll press record right over here on the Camtasia, and I'm just going to start making a video,
and you'll see it captures everything it records on the video,
so let me just show you test mode -- let me clear this first --
so let's say -- so let me justify a little bit, I press record, it'll give me a little bit of a countdown --
I'll like to test my pen off the screen right here (the side of the recording region),
and so now it's actually recording everything that I'm saying is part of this video,
so this is a video, 3 plus 5 is equal to 8. And I can change colors, I can underline 3 in orange,
I can underline the 5 in -- well, that's orange again -- let's say in purple, whatever I want,
I'm just changing. I tend to like these kind of pastel colors and the feel of the pastel chalk on top of the chalkboard,
And you'll see when I'm done recording this video, the video got produced.
And I can actually play the video -- my pen off the screen right here (the side of the recording region) -- so that's not me talking!
That's the video talking! And so now it's actually recording everything that I'm saying is part of this video,
so this is a video, 3 plus 5 is equal to 8. And I can change colors, I can underline 3 in orange --
and once if you're happy with it, if you can just literally click save, it'll offer you to the edited Camtasia Studio and all that,
but I just save it as an AVI file, and when it's saved as an AVI file, you can actually upload directly to YouTube if you want,
or you can make a process in it and edit if you want to. I tend to not process or edit the videos unless if I made some error and I can fix that very easily,
and yeah, so you just save it and you upload it. That's the technical part of making a video,
and hopefully, that's not too difficult if you already have a PC it's literally talking about a couple $100 of equipment and software --
and actually you can probably get the software for free, share your software whatever else, now about the subjective parts about making a video.
For me, personally, it might vary from everyone who does videos, I'm a big believer -- and we got some feedback from our user based effect,
they like the conversational nature of the video, the videos are literally exactly in the way I'm talking right now,
and so for me, the way I prepare the videos is I read up a lot of --
if I'm doing something -- if I'm doing algebra worked examples that doesn't require a lot of preparation;
I can kind of work through the problem in real time.
But if I'm doing -- say, history video, I'll read a bunch of stuff,
I'll look for a bunch of public domain documents and maps and pictures on the web,
and what's about the art program is you can copy and paste things on to this.
And let me show you -- let's say I'm doing a -- so let me bring out a web browser,
and as you can see, this computer is not state of the art.
But let's say I wanted a map of Europe -- I'm actually am doing videos on World War I right now,
and so I'll do a search for Europe 1914, and I'll also search on the word "public domain" just to make sure I'm getting a map that I can use.
So I'll do a search for that, and I'll do a search for images, and most of these are Wikimedia Commons,
this is Europe at the beginning of World War I, I can go to that page and I can verify --
I can look at the licensing and I can verify right over here that this is a public domain map,
so I can literally take this map -- I can copy the image, I can paste it right over here on to my art program --
so let me change the pen. On to my art program, and now if I want to talk about World War I
I can start recording, I can get my screen thing up, screen capture, and I can talk about -- I can mark up this map.
I can say, "Look, Germany had to fight two fronts in World War I and the western front right over here and the eastern front right over here which was huge,
because each front was huge, you couldn't do trench warfare so there's a much more fluid front."
As you can see, you can start taking things off the web that you have the rights to or that applicable licensing terms associated with them, and also mark them up.
So once you get the technical stuff down, my advice is, "Try to do as much preparation and as much reading as possible to
steal the thoughts in your own brain; if it helps to, take notes, write your notes out multiple, multiple times,
and then try to make the video. When you make the video,
I often erred on the side of doing these long videos; I don't think that's a good idea, the shorter the videos, the better.
I think the optimal is about 3 or 4 minutes; It will minimize the chance of making a mistake and will allow you to be more natural
because you won't be stressed about all the things you actually have to talk about.
And focus on the underline intuition on things. I think that's what people really crave;
they don't want just get some superficial formulas or superficial facts; they want to get deep thing.
They want to understand it as your brain understands it; that's why I not a big fan of the other scripted videos.
Often times you can tell when someone's reading versus what they're thinking,
and so I think people will appreciate if they see, 'Why, you're thinking through this;
you're actually reasoning through why you couldn't have trench warfare on the eastern front or
why completing the square actually gets you a quadratic formula.' I think you're told,
'Everyone has different styles of tones, but as natural as possible, let yourself be free as possible.'
I actually force myself to smile often before the videos, it'll actually change your mood and you guys are, 'Ha, ha, ha!'
Laugh at the videos if you can, whatever whenever you can,
and the one thing I also found is this is very easy to freeze up, to press record,
and what I often do is I delude myself. I can miss myself, 'Okay, Sal, don't worry about the next video,
just do the practice round.' And when you do a practice round, it'll actually make you a lot less stressed when you just do the video,
and then when you're done with it, at like 7 or 8 minutes later, I'm like,
'Hey, that wasn't so bad.' And you're probably going to be more critical of yourself than you need to be,
and we all are, upload it or show it to some friends,
and I think they're going to find all those things that you thought when you said, 'Um' that one time,
I mean, you should try not say um if you can.
But what you stuttered at one time, you made that you went back and fix that one mistake.
You'll find that people don't mind as much as you thought, and sometimes I actually thought it was a positive thing for the video."
So with that, let you go, I look forward to seeing the type of videos that I'll produce.