Let's start again with a point let's call that
point, "Point A." And what I'm curious about
is all of the points on my screen that are exactly
2cm away from "Point A." So 2cm on my screen
is about that far. So clearly if I start at "A" and I go 2cm
in that direction, this point is 2cm from "A." If I call that
"Point B" then I could say line segment AB is 2cm
the length is 2cm. Remember, this would refer to
the actual line segment. I could say this looks nice but if
I talk about it's length, I would get rid of that
line on top, and I would just say, "'AB' is equal to
2. If I wanted to put units, I would say 2cm.
But I'm not curious just about B, I want to think
about ALL the points. The set of ALL of the points
that are exactly 2cm away from "A." So I could go
2cm in the other direction, maybe get to point
"C" right over here. So "AC" is also going to be equal
to 2cm. But I could go 2cm in any direction. And so
if I find that of all of the points that are exactly 2cm
away from "A," I will get a very familiar looking
shape, like this: (I'm drawing this free-hand,) so I would
get a shape that looks like this. Actually, let me draw
it in I don't want to make you think that it's only the
points where there's white, it's ALL of these points
right over here. Let me clear out all of these and I will
just draw a solid line. It could look something like
that (my best attempt.) And this set of all the points
that are exactly 2cm away from "A," is a circle, which
I'm sure you are already familiar with. But that is
the formal definition, the set of all points that are
a fixed distance from "A." If I said, "The set of all points
that are 3cm from "A," it might look something like this:"
That would give us another circle. (I think you get the
general idea.) Now, what I want to introduce to you
in this video is ourselves to some of the concepts
and words that we use when dealing with circles.
So let me get rid of 3cm circle. So first of all, let's
think about this distance, or one of these line segments
that join "A" which we would call the center of the
circle. So we will call "A" the center of the circle,
which makes sense just from the way we use the word
'center' in everyday life, what I want to do is think
about what line segment "AB" is. "AB" connects the
center and it connects a point on the circle itself.
Remember, the circle itself is all the points that
are equal distance from the center. So "AB," any point,
line segment, I should say, that connects the center to
a point on the circle we would call a radius. And so
the length of the radius is 2cm. And you're probably
already familiar with the word 'radius,' but I'm just
being a little bit more formal. And what's interesting
about geometry, at least when you start learning at the
high-school level is that it's probably the first
class where you're introduced to a slightly more formal
mathematics where we're a little more careful about
giving our definitions and then building on those
definitions to come up with interesting results and
proving to ourselves that we definitely know what we
think we know. And so that's why we're being a little
more careful with our language over here. So "AB" is
a radius, line segment "AB," and so is line segment,
(let me put another point on here) let's say this is
"X" so line segment "AX" is also a radius. Now you
can also have other forms of lines and line segments
that interact in interesting ways with the circle.
So you could have a line that just intersects that
circle exactly one point. So let's call that point
right over there and let's call that "D." And let's say
you have a line and the only point on the circle that
the only point in the set of all the points that are
equal distance from "A," the only point on that
circle that is also on that line is point "D." And we
could call that line, "line L." So sometimes you will
see lines specified by some of the points on them.
So for example, if I have another point right over here
called "E," we could call this line, "line DE," or we
could just put a little script letter here with an "L" and
say this "line L." But this line that only has one point
in common with our circle, we call this 'a tangent line.'
So "Line L" is tangent. Tangent to the circle. So let me
write it this way, "'line L' is tangent to the circle
centered at "A"" So this tells us that this is the circle
we're talking about, because who knows? maybe we had
another circle over here that is centered at "M."
So we have to specify. It's not tangent to that one,
it's tangent to this one. So this circle with a dot in
the middle tells we're talking about circle, and this
is a circle centered at point "A." I want to be very
clear. Point "A" is not on the circle, point "A" is
the center of the circle. The points on the circle are
the points equal distant from point "A." Now, "L" is
tangent because it only intersects the circle in one
point. You could just as easily imagine a line that
intersects the circle at two points. So we could call,
maybe this is "F" and this is "G." You could call that
line "FG." And the line that intersects at two points
we call this a secant of circle "A." It is a secant line
to this circle right here. Because it intersects it
in two points. Now, if "FG" was just a segment, if it
didn't keep on going forever like lines do, if we only
spoke about this line segment, between "FG," and not
thinking about going on forever, then all the sudden,
we have a line segment, which we would specify there,
and we would call this a chord of the circle. A chord of
"circle "A." It starts on a point of the circle, a point
that is, in this case, 2cm away and then it finishes
at a point on the circle. So it connects two points on
the circle. Now, you can have cords like this, and you
can also have a chord, as you can imagine, a chord that
actually goes through the center of the circle. So let's
call this, "point 'H.'" And you have a straight line connecting
"F" to "H" through "A." (That's about as straight as I could
draw it.) So if you have a chord like that, that contains
actual center of the circle, of course it goes from one
point to another point of the circle, and it goes through
the center of the circle, we call that a diameter of a
circle. And you've probably seen this in tons of problems
before when we were not talking about geometry as formally,
but a diameter is made of two radiuses. We know that a radius
connects a point to the center, so you have one radius
right over here that connects "F" and "A" that's one radius
and you have another radius connecting "A" and "H,"
a point connecting to the center of the circle. So the
diameter is made of these two radiuses (or radii as I
should call it I think that's the plural for radius) and so
the length of a diameter is going to be twice the length
of a radius. So we could say, "the length of the diameter,
so the length of "FH" (and once again I don't put the
line on top of it when I'm talking about the length) is
going to be equal to "FA," the length of segment "FA" plus
the length of segment "AH."" Now there's one last thing
I want to talk about, when we're dealing with circles,
and that's the idea of an arc. So we also have the parts
of the circle itself. (So let me draw another circle over
here) Let's center this circle at "B." And I'm going to find
some points, all the points that are a given distance
from "B." So, it has some radius, I'm not going to specify
it right over here. And let me pick some random points
on this circle. Let's call this, "J," "K," "S," "T," and "U."
Let me center "B" a little bit more in the center here...
Now, one interesting thing is, "what do you call
the length of the circle that goes between two points?"
Well, you could imagine in every language, we would
call something like that an "arc," which is also what it's
called in geometry. We would call this "JK," the two end
points of the arc, the two points on the circle that are
the inputs of the arc, and you would use a little notation like
that, a little curve on top instead of a strait line.
Now, you can also have another arc that connects "J"
and "K," this is called the 'minor arc,' it is the shortest
way upon the circle to connect "J" and "K." But you could
also go the other way around. You could also have this
thing, that goes all the around the circle. And that is
called the 'major arc.' And usually when we specify the
major arc, just to show that you're going kind of the long
way around, it's not the shortest way to go between
"J" and "K," you will often specify another point that you're
going through. So for example, this major arc we could
specify. We started "J," we went through, we could have
said "U," "T," or "S," but I will put "T" right over there.
We went through "T" and then we went all the way to "K."
And so this specifies the major arc. And this thing could
have been the same thing as if I wrote "JUK" these are
specifying the same thing, or "JSK." So there are
multiple ways to specify this major arc. The one thing I want
to make clear is that the minor arc is the shortest distance,
so this is the minor arc, and the longer distance around is
the major arc. I will leave you there. Maybe the next few
videos we will starts playing with some of this notation.