Rewrite the following expressions as the product of positive exponents, and then evaluate the expression
when x is equal to 2
So let's do this first part
They want us to rewrite it as the product of positive
exponents, so they don't like the fact that we have this
negative third power and the 5 to the negative second power
so you want to rewrite those as negative exponents.
And to do that, we just have to remember that something
to a negative power is just (let me write it over here)
if I have x to the negative 2 power, this is the exact
same thing as 1 over x to the positive 2 power. If I have
a to the negative b power, this is the exact same thing as
one over a to the b power
You can get rid of that negative by just putting a 1 over
this whole thing. By taking the inverse of the whole expression
you can get rid of that negative.
So let's do that over here. x to the negative 3 power,
that is equal to this (let me do this in a different
color). x to the negative 3rd power, that's the exact
same thing as one over x to the third power, by definition
Now we're going to multiply that by 5 to the negative 2
power. Well, 5 to the negative 2 power, same exact thing
that's the same thing as 1 over 5 to the 2nd power,
1 over 5 to the positive 2 power.
And then finally, we have just a straight up x squared
the exponent is already positive there, and we can just
leave that as times x squared.
So we did the first part; we rewrote the following
expression as a product of positive exponents.
Now let's evaluate the expression when x is equal
to two. So everywhere we see an x, we should put a 2. So this
becomes one over two to the (let me do this in the
same color). This becomes one over two to the third
power times 1 over 5 squared times two squared.
Every place we saw an x, we're now putting a 2.
Two to the third power (just as a reminder)
that's 2 times 2 times 2. That is equal to 8
So this is equal to one over eight times one over
five squared.
Five squared is equal to 5 times 5 which is equal to 25.
This is equal to 25. And we're going to multiply that
times two squared, so that's
2 squared is equal to 2 times 2, which is equal
to 4. So times 4.
And you can even view this as times 4 over 1
And so you multiply all the numerators
That's what we do when we multiply fractions
You multiply all the numerators
One times One times four is equal to 4
And you multiply the denominators
8 times 25 is going to be 200
And you can simplify this - the numerator and
the denominator are both divisible by 4
Divide the numerator by 4 and you get 1
Divide the denominator by 4 and you get 50
So this is equal to one over 50.
And just so you see there, there's actually a way to
simplify it before we got to this stage over here.
Actually from this stage we could have multiplied it out
If you (let me just rewrite this thing)
So this product, if we multiply it out, this 2 squared
you can view it as 2 squared over 1.
So if we were to multiply this out, the numerator
would have been equal to 1 times 1 times 2 squared
2 squared is just 2 times 2, so there would have been
2 times 2 in the numerator, we can ignore the 1,
that doesn't change the value.
And the denominator would have been
2 times 2 times 2 (that's what 2 to the third power is)
2 times 2 times 2 times 5 times 5
That's what 5 squared is, and of course multiplying it
by one doesn't change its value.
And then it would have been more obvious that you can
divide the numerator and the denominator by 2 once
you can do it again
and then you'd just be left with one over two
times 5 times 5.
And this of course down here is 50.
This 10 times 5 which is 50 and you would have
gotten the same result.