Plot the following numbers on the number line.
So the first number we have here is five.
And so five is five to the right of zero. Five is right over there.
Then we get one third. So one third is between zero and one.
And we can actually split this into thirds:
So that would be one third, two thirds, and then three thirds which is one.
So one third is going to sit right over there.
It's one third of the way from zero to one.
That's one third, right over there.
We have negative one point two. So negative one is right over here.
This is is more negative than negative one.
It's negative one point two. It's negative one and then another point two.
So it is going to be right over here.
So this is negative one point two.
Zero is pretty straight forward. Zero is right over there.
It's even labeled for us at the zero.
Five was labeled for us too at five.
We have negative two and one fourth. So let's go to negative two.
Negative two is here. It's more negative than negative two.
It's negative two and then another negative one fourth.
So it's negative two and then we go one fourth of the way to negative three.
So negative two and one fourth is is going to be right over here.
And then finally we have four point one. So four is right over here.
Point one is another tenth greater than four. Another tenth on the way to five.
So four and one tenth is going to be right over here.
Four point one. And we are done.