I've got a handful of matrices here - I have the matrix A, that's an M by N matrix.
You can see it has N columns and M rows.
And actually let me throw in one entry there, it might be useful.
This is the...
This is the Jth column, so the Mth row is gonna look like this
A m j. That's that entry right there.
And then I have matrix B defined similarly
but instead of being an
m by n matrix, B is an n by m matrix.
So this entry right here
let me just, I might
I realize this might be useful
this is going to be my nth row,
this is going to be my jth column
And then I also wrote out their transposes
so if you look at the transpose of B
B was an N by M matrix
now the transpose is going to be M by N matrix.
And each of its rows become its columns
and the same thing I did for A,
its transpose is right there
A was M by N, the transposes N by M
and each of these rows become each of these columns.
Now, fair enough.
Let's define two new matrices right now.
Let's define the matrix C.
Let me do it over here where
Let me do it over here
I think...I think the real estate well be valuable
in this video
Let's define my matrix C as being equal to
the product of A and B
So what's...what are going to be the dimensions of C?
Well an M by N matrix times an N by M matrix,
these two have to be equal
even for the matrix...matrix product to be defined.
And it's going to result
with an M by N matrix.
So it's going to be an M by M matrix.
Now's let define another matrix,
let's call it D. D...
And it's equal to B tranpose
B transpose times A transpose.
And the dimensions are going to be the same
because this is an M by N times an N by M.
So these are the same.
which is a requirement for this product to be defined
and so the dimensions of B
are going to be M by M. M by M.
So let's explore a little bit what the different entries
of C are going to look like.
So let me write my matrix C
right here.
So it's just going to have
a bunch of entries
C one one, C two two, C one two...
all the way to C one M.
You can imagine it's cause its an M by N matrix
you're going to have C M M over here
you know how the...you know how this drill goes.
But what I'm curious about is
how do we figure out what C...the general C, i, j is?
How do we figure out what a particular entry is?
We know that C
is the products of A and B.
So to get to a particular entry in C...
and we've seen this before
so let's...
a particular entry in C
so C, i, j
it's going to be
you can view it as
the dot product of the ith row in A
the ith row in A
with the jth column in B
just like that
And what's that going to be equal to?
It's going to be equal to
A, i,1...
A, i, 1 times B, 1, j
B, 1, j
plus A, i, 2
A, i, 2
times B, 2, j...B, 2, j
and you're just going to keep going
until you get to the last term here
A, i, n
times the last term here B, n, j.
B, n, j.
Fair enough.
Now, what about our matrix D...
What are its entries going to look like?
So D, similarly, it's going to look like
you know, you are going to have
d 1 1, d 1 2
sorry...d, 1, 2, all the way to
d 1 m, you're going to have d m n
I could keep putting entries here,
but I'm curious about just the
some general entry here
let's say I want to find
D sub j i
That's what I want to find.
So I want to find a general way
for any particular entry of D.
The jth row and the ith column
which is a little bit different than
the convention we normally use
for these letters...but it's fine.
The first one is D's row
the second one is D's...is this entry's column.
So how do we figure that out?
So D sub j i
It's going to be equal to
D is the product of these two guys.
So to get the jth row
and ith column entry here
we essentially take the dot product
of the jth row here
So we're going to take the dot product of the jth row here.
Which is is that right there.
With the ith column of A,
with the ith column A.
which is that right there.
So I'm going to take the dot product of that.
And you might already see something interesting here.
This thing right here is equivalent to
that thing right there.
And this thing right here
is equivalent to that thing right there,
because we took the transposes.
But let's actually
just write it out.
So what is this dot product
going to be equal to?
Well it's going to be
B, i, j
well let me write it this way
it's going to be B i j times
A
i
one.
Or we could write it as
A i one times B one j.
And it's going to be plus B 2 j times
A i 2, which is
the same thing as A i 2 times B 2 j.
A i 2 times B 2 j.
And you are going to keep going
until you get B n j times A i n.
Or, you could write that as
A i n times B n j.
B n j.
Now, notice something.
These two things are equivalent.
They are completely equivalent statements.
The...
D sub j i is equivalent to C sub i j.
Let me write that.
So D....or I could write C sub i j,
is equivalent to
D sub j i.
Or another way you could say it is
anything that's at row...
all that entries that's at row i
column j,
in C, is now in row j column i in D.
And this is true for all the entries.
True for all entries.
I stayed as general as possible.
So what does this mean?
This is the definition of a transpose.
So we now get that C
C transpose is equal to D.
Or you could say that C is equal to
D transpose.
Now this is pretty interesting,
cause how did we define these two?
We said that our matrix C
is equal to our matrice...
our matrice...the matrix product A and B.
And we said that D
is equal to, our matrix product
B transposed times A transposed.
I did that...those definitions right there.
Here are the definitions.
Now we just found out that
D is equal to the transpose of C.
So we could write that C transpose
which is the same thing as A times B
transposed, is equal to D.
So it is equal to D, which is just
B transpose, A transpose.
And this is a pretty neat takeaway.
This is a pretty neat takeaway here.
If I take the product of two matrices, and then
transpose it, it's equivalent to
switching the order, or transposing them
and then taking the product of the reversed order.
B transpose, A transpose.
Which is a pretty pretty neat takeaway.
And you can actually extend this to an arbitrary
number of matrices that you are taking the
product of. If you're taking...
I'm not proving it here, but it's actually
a very simple extension from this right now.
If you take the matrices, let's say,
A...let me do a different...different letters.
X Y Z. If you take their product and then
transpose it, it's equal to Z transpose, Y transpose,
X transpose.
I haven't proven this general case
and you could keep doing it with 4 or 5
or N matrices multiplied by each other.
But it generally works.
And you could...essentially prove it
using what we proved in this video right here.
That you take the product of two matrices,
take their transposes equal to
the product of their transposes in reverse order.