So, we're going back to our little burger stand
where we had our demand curve
in terms of burgers per hour, and now I want
to think about something, from the persepective of
our burger stand, and think about at any given point
on this demand curve, how much revenue would
we get per hour? And when I talk about revenue,
let's just think about in terms of
"How many total sales will I get in a given hour?"
Let me just write it over here - total revenue.
Well, the total revenue is going to be how
much I get per burger times
the number of burgers I get. The amount that
I get per burger is price, so it's going to be equal to
price ; and then the total number of burgers in that
hour is going to be the quantity.
Pretty straightforward.
If I sell 10 things at $5, I am going to get $50 of revenue -
$50 of sales in that hour.
Now, let's think about what the total revenue will
look like at different points along
this curve right over here.
Actually, let me just make a little table right over here.
So if I make one column price, one column quantity,
and then let's make one column total revenue.
Alright, so let's look at a couple of scenarios here.
We could actually look at some of these points that
we already have defined. At Point A here, price is $9
- so I'll do it in Point A's colour - price is $9,
quantity is 2. $9 x 2 burgers.
$9 per burger x 2 burgers per hour - your total
revenue is going to be $18. And you can see it
visually right over here: this height, this height right over here is $9,
and this width right over here is 2, and your total revenue
is going to be the area of this rectangle, because the height
is the price and the width is the quantity.
So, that total revenue is the area, right over there.
Now, let's go to point - let me do a couple of them,
just to make it really clear for us - let's try Point B.
So, at Point B, when our price is $8, and
our quantity is 4 - 4 burgers per hour - our total
revenue is going to be $8 x 4 which is $32 per hour.
Once again, you can see that visually. The height
here is $8, and the width here - so the height
of this rectangle is $8 - and the width is 4. The total
revenue is going to be the area: it's going to be the
height times the width, just like that.
Now, let's go to a Point that I haven't actually graphed
here, actually - let me just, actually - I'll go through
all the Points, just for fun. So, now at Point C, we have $5.50.
$5.50 is the price. The quantity is 9. $5.50 x 9.
9 x 5 = $45, and then you have another $4.50, so that
is $49.50. So, once again, it's going to be the area
of this rectangle, the area of that rectangle right over there.
So, you might already be noticing something interesting.
As we lower the price, at least in this part
of our demand curve - as we lower the price -
we are actually increasing, not just the quantity,
we're increasing the total revenue. Let's see if this
keeps happening. So, if we go to Point D - I'll do it
in that same colour - we have $4.50, and we are
selling 11 units. 11 x $4.50, let's see this is going
to be $44 plus $5.50. Once again, that is $49.50.
So, this rectangle is going to have the same
area as that pink one that we just did for scenario C.
Now, I'll actually just do one more down here,
just to see what happens, because this is interesting.
Now we've lowered the price, and it looks like
things didn't change much. And now let's go
and just do one more Point, actually, for
the sake of time - Point E. And I encourage you
to do other ones - try F on your own! Point E - my price
is $2 per burger, my quantity is 16 burgers per hour.
I sell a total of 32 burgers [Should be: My total revenue is $32 per hour].
Actually, let's just do the last one - F - just to feel
a sense of completion, So, $1 per burger, I sell 18 burgers
per hour. My total revenue, when you multiply them
is $18 per hour. And once again, that's the area of
this rectangle. This short and fat rectangle, right over here.
And E, was the total area - the total revenue at E was
the area of that, right over there.
And you could graph these, just to get a sense
of how total revenue actually changes with respect
to price or quantity. Let's plot total revenue wih respect
to quantity. So, let's try it out.
So this is going to be total revenue, and this axis
right over here is going to be quantity.
And we're once again going to be from - let's see,
this is zero, this is 5, this is 10, this is 15, and this is 20, right over here.
And then total revenue - let's see, it gets as high - it gets
pretty close to $50. So let's go - this is $10, $20, $30, $40, and $50.
So that's $50, $40, $30, $20, and $10.
So when our quantity is 2, and our price is $9
- but we don't have price right on this axis here -
our quantity is 2, and our total revenue is $18.
So, it's going to be something like there.
Then, when our quantity is 4, our total revenue is $32, right about there.
Then, when our quantity is 9, our total revenue is almost $50.
So, right over there. And then, when it's 11, it's also
at that same point, right over there, And then,
when our quantity is 16, our total revenue is $32.
And then finally, when our quantity is 18, our total revenue is $18.
And what you see, is that it's plotting out a curve
that looks like this, and if you remember some of
your Algebra 2, this is a concave downwards parabola, right over here!
And you can see, there is actually some point
at which you can maximise your total revenue, and
if you really tried all the points here, you'd see that
maximum point is if you tried this point right over here.
Right at price $5, and quantity 10.
At price $5 and quantity 10, in that hour you would
sell [gain] $50. So this is the maximum point
right over there, $50.
Now the whole reason why I'm talking about this
- I could have talked about this independently of any discussion of elasticity, just to see how total
revenue relates to price and quantity at different points on the demand curve -
but there is an interesting relationship. In that
very first video, and we actually used this exact demand curve for it,
when we explored elasticity, we saw that up here, at
this part of the curve - let me do this in a different colour -
at this point of the curve in orange, for any change - when you do a change in your price,
since the prices are pretty high - that is a much lower
percent change in price than the impact that
you get on quantity. Because, over here, although
they look like they're close, the, or I should say, the absolute
- for every 1 down we move in price, we're moving 2 up in quantity -
but that 1 down in price is a very small percentage of price,
because our prices are high here, and it's a very large
percentage of quantity right over here.
So, you get huge changes in percent quantity for very small changes in price
at this part of the curve. So, this part of the curve is elastic.
Or, you could say that its price elasticity for demand is >1.
You get larger changes in percent quantity for a given change in percent price.
Now, these parts of the curve down here, we saw the opposites happening.
You move 1 unit down in price, you move 2 units
to the right in quantity, but over here, price is much
lower, so this is a much larger change, percentage change in price,
and this is a much smaller percentage change in quantity.
So, you get large percentage changes in price for small
percentage changes in quantity. That means that here,
you are relatively inelastic.
And then, right over here, right at this point -
right in this region right over here, we saw that
we had unit - we were unit elasticity right over there.
So, there's an interesting relationship going on.
While we were elastic - this part right over here -
when we lowered price in this region - while we were elastic -
when we lowered price, we got increases in revenue.
So, let me write this down.
And this is generally true - there's a couple of boundary cases
on the math that make it a little bit - you can't
make it absolutely true, but while we are elastic,
at the elastic points of our demand curve, a decrease in price -
price goes down, total revenue was going up.
You do a price cut on this part of the demand curve,
you get more revenue. Then, when you are at unit elasticity,
what was happening?
Unit elasticity you are right at this point right over here,
and roughly, when you do a price cut, and I'm going
to say that this is roughly true - your total revenue stays constant.
But just right at the point, right when you're going through
that point, that unit elasticity point. And, finally,
when you are inelastic, when large percent changes
in price result in not so large percent changes in quantity demanded,
then a price change going down,
resulted in a lower total revenue - resulted in total
revenue going down. And this should hopefully
make a little bit of intuitive sense, because over here,
at this point, if given percent change in price,
you were getting a larger percent change in quantity.
So, the percent in price went down, your percent in quantity grew even more,
so you made up any decrease in height with an increase
in width, so your area increased. Down here,
your decrease in percent price wasn't made up
for a decrease in percent quantity, so when you made
your rectangles a little bit shorter, you weren't able
to compensate by growing the width as much - so, you
actually had a lower area, a lower total revenue.