Rewrite the expression below
applying the commutative
and associative properties of addition,
and then show that both expressions yield
the same result.
So, one, we could just
evaluate the expression the way
that it is written, then
we could mess around with it using the
commutative and associative properties of addition.
So lets first add 17.5 plus 3
so that's going to give us
20.5, so this is
going to be 20.5.
And to then to that we're going to add negative 7.5.
Now adding -7.5 is the exact same thing
as subtracting 7.5.
so this is going to be equal to -
the .5s cancel out -
and then 20 minus 7 is 13.
So that's our first way of getting the answer
and we kind of adhere to the parentheses.
Now let's use the commuatative property.
The commutative property tells us that the order doesn't matter;
we can commute these numbers around,
they can move (commute).
It's like you're going to work.
They can move around. So lets just move the numbers around.
Let's make it, let's make it, actually
we could do all sorts of crazy things.
We could make it, one we could
just change the order here.
We could make this -7.5 plus 17.5 plus 3.
We could keep the parentheses, just like that,
so we would have essentially just changed the order of this expression,
but let's use the commutative and the associaive property.
So now we've commuted everything around,
and now we can reassociate everything.
So instead of putting the parentheses like that,
we could put the parentheses like that.
So that's what the associate property tells us.
Let me write this down.
So associative property of addition
tells us that (a+b)+c where you do a+b first
is the same as a+(b+c) where you do b+c first.
The commutative property
tells us that a + b = b + a
that you can move these guys around.
So let's evaluate this one.
We actually got here using both the commutative and the associative property,
so we get -7.5 + 17.5.
This is the exact same thing as
17.5 -7.5.
It might be easier for you to realize,
"Okay, I'm adding two numbers of different signs, so
what I could do is take the difference between the two,
and since the larger number is positive,
I have a larger number.
Or you could just do this as 17.5 - 7.5."
So 17.5 - 7.5,
the .5s cancel out. 17 - 7 is 10.
So this part right here
becomes 10. And we still have the plus three there
and that once again that is going to be
equal to 13. And we could keep commuting this around and
keep reassociating it
and no matter how we do it, we are going to get 13.