Simplify 3 times the principal root of 500x to the 3rd power. So what we're gonna do here is to try and
break up the stuff we have under the radical sign into some things that are perfect squares, then we
can separately take the square roots of those things and leave the left-overs inside of the radical
sign. The other thing we have to remember is the principal square root, this radical sign here really
means the positive square root of a number. So let's think about this a little bit. So let's see if we
can break down the 500 x to the third into some perfect squares and some things that maybe aren't perfect
squares, because 500 is not a perfect square, x to the third is not a perfect square, right from the
get-go. So, when in doubt, we can just start to prime factorize this and maybe we'll discover some perfect
squares. So 500 is divisible by 5 and its 5 times 100, and you probably already recognize that 100 is
a perfect square. It is 10 times 10. But if you didn't know that, you could just keep factoring. You
could say a 100 is 2 times 50 , 50 is 2 times 25 and 25 is 5 times 5. So, you'd see the perfect squares
here , coz you would see, you would see two 2s, you have a 2 times two and you have a 5 times a 5. So
you could really just say that a 100 is 10 times 10 or you could say its 2 squared times 5 squared.
Either of those things would allow you to break this down. And then x to the third is, just clearly,
the same thing as x to the third, right over here, is clearly the same thing as x squared times x, which
allows us to break it down into perfect squares and something that is not a perfect square. So let's
just rewrite these numbers under the principal root sign. So, this is going to be equal to 3 times ,
I'll save some space here, 3 times the 500, I could rewrite it as a 100 times 5 and a 100 I could write
as 10 squared. So this right here, I could write as 10 squared, I don't have to do all of this business
down here, but this will help you recognize that this is a perfect square. Its 4 times 25 , and those
are perfect squares. So a 100 is 10 squared, I'm gonna write this as 10 squared squared, 10 times squared