My name is Rishi Desai, and I work for Khan Academy. One of the cool things that I get to do is to
put together videos and questions related to health and medicine topics
and put those on the Khan Academy web site, so that all sorts of
users from around the world can access that information.
Right now, Khan Academy is actually doing something really quite different from this.
We're collaborating with the AAMC -- the Association of American Medical Colleges
and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation to basically flip this around.
We acutally want users to to make the videos, to make questions,
and actually send them to us. The reason we are doing this is that
2015 MCAT exam is coming around,and it's gonna
have some the same materials before; you know, biology, chemistry, and physics
but it's gonna have some new materials; things like psychology and sociology, and we
think that you, that's right, you might be a good person to help teach some
someone that content. So we want you to pick one topic that you really
are comfortable with, and make 3 videos and write 10
questions related to that topic, then take all of it and send it to
us by mid-June. And we want folks that are passionate, people that are
clear and concise, can be engaging and fun. Someone that
really really understands this material can teach it well. We are gonna go through all these
missions and we are gonna find some winners. We are gonna offer the winners a free
one-week trip to a training camp where you get to whole your skills at making
videos, writing good questions, and then we're gonna offer a chance
to become a Khan Academy teaching fellow, so if it sounds like
something that you might want to try, I say, "Go ahead and get started; you're gonna have a blast."