Let us say this triangle over here is an equilateral triangle
which means all of the sides are of equal length
Let us say the length of this side is "s",
what i want to do is to come up with a way to
find out the area of this equilateral triangle
as a function of "s". To do this i am going to
split this equilateral triangle into 2
I am going to drop a line from this top vertex, which
divides the triangle into 2. This angle is equal to that angle
we proved all these in an earlier video
In a regular equilateral triangle all of the angles are equal
60 degrees, this is 60, this is 60 and this one up here
is 60 split into 2, each angle 30 degrees each
and the other thing we know is the altitude will bisect
this length into equal parts. Now if the entire length
was "s", all three sides will have the same length,
then each of these is "s/2" If this length is known we can
find out this side. The reason why we need to know this is
the area of a triangle is 1/2 * base * height.
If this is 's/2", the side over here is √3s/2
In a 30:60:90 triangle if the side opposite to 30 degrees is 1
the side opposite to 60 degrees is going to be √3
and the side opposite 90 degrees is 2 times it.
In this case the side opposite to 30 degrees is "s/2"
side opposite 60 degrees will be √3s/2
Now we need to figure out what the area of the triangle is.
The area of a triangle is 1/2 * base * height of the triangle.
The base of the triangle is "s". The height of the triangle is √3s/2
so area = 1/2 * s * √3s/2 = √(3ss)/(22)
So we if we an equilateral triangle with each side = 1,
the area is √3/4. If we have a equilateral triangle with each
side = 2 the are will be √(3 22)/(22) = √3