A function f of x is plotted below -
highlighted interval where f prime of x
requisite the first derivative of x
or the first derivative of f was aspect to x
is greater than zero
and f double prime of x with the second derivative of f with aspect to x
is less than zero.
So lets think about what they're saying.
So we're looking for a place with a first derivative
is greater than zero
that means that the slope of the tangent line is positive
that means that the function is increasing over that interval.
So if we just think about it here
over this whole region right over here
the fuction is clearly decreasing.
Then the slope becomes zero right over here,
then the function starts increasing again
all the way until this point right over here hits zero
and then it goes and the fuction starts decreasing.
So we're gonna - just as first constraint right over here
tells us it's going to be something in this interval right over there
and then they say when the second derivative is less than zero.
So this means that the slope itself -
whether it's positive or negative -
that it's actually decreasing.
We're gonna be concave downwards right over here.
The slope itself, it could be positive,
but it'll be coming less and less and less positive.
And so we're looking for a place where the slope is positive,
but it's becoming less and less and less positive.
If you're looking right over here -
the slope is positive, but the slope is increasing -
it's getting steeper and steeper and steeper as we go -
and then all of the sudden it's getting
less steep, less steep, less steep, less steep -
all the way to when the slope gets back to zero.
So if we wanna select an interval
it would be this interval right over here.
Out slope is positive, our function is clearly increasing,
but it is increasing at a lower and lower rate.
(so I will select that right over there).
Lets do one more example:
A function f of x is plotted below.
Highlight an interval where f(x)>0
so the same thing where our function is increasing
but it's increasing at a slower and slower rate.
So our function is increasing in this whole region right over here
and we see it's really steep here
then it's getting less steep and less steep
and it's getting closer and closer to zero
- the slope of the tangent line or the rate of increase of the function.
So I would pick anything right around this region right here.