I want to do a quick primer on refraction.
And our focus here is going to be on seismic waves.
But the principal of how things refract
when they go from a fast to a slow medium or a slow to a fast medium,
It`s actually the same as you would see
when you're studying ligth waves or any type of wave.
So let's think about it a little bit.
Let&#x27;s say I have a slow medium rigth over here
and let&#x27;s say I have a fast medium over here.
So that we can travel thorugh both solid and liquid, let&#x27;s think about maybe P-waves,
and a slow medium could be maybe some type of liquid
and our fast medium could be some type of solid.
So let me draw the boundary right over here.
And let's say, so if I have something that cut off a P-wave,
a P-wave, let's say it going through the water
and going right perpendicularly to the boundary,
it will then just continue to travel
in the faster medium in the same direction.
Going right if it goes right at the boundary.
If it goes right at the boundary, it`ll just travel faster in the faster medium.
And that's because that faster medium is going to be more dense
and the molecules are going to bump into each other faster.
In the same amount of time more molucules kind of
a chain reaction is going to travel further because they are more closely packed
and they rebound faster than it would in the slow medium.
So obviusly no refraction is going on.
It has not been deflected.
And just as a bit of a reminder.
In general, refraction is when a wave gets defelcted.
Reflection is when it bounces back,
refraction is when it gets deflected a little bit.
Let me just make that clear.
So if I have some type of boundary here
and I have a wave that bounces off, that's reflection.
But if the wave goes through the boundary
and just gets bent a little, bit it's direction changes, that is refraction.
And that's what we are talking about.
So cleary so far this P-wave has not been refracted.
But if this P-wave comes in at an angle,
so let's make this P-Wave come in at an angle, what's going to happen is,
the way you should think about it is, the easiest way to think about which direction
it will be refracted or at least the way I think about it,
is literally, I imagine some type of vehicle.
Some type of vehicle with wheels on it. This is the top view of my vehicle.
So if I have some type of vehicle and the wheels will be able to move slowly in this medium.
Kind of viewed as kind of a mud. So it doesn&#x27;t get good traction
and then the fast medium it is a road so it get&#x27;s good traction, it can move faster.
So what's going to happen when the vehicle gets to the boundary.
Well, this bottom rigth wheel is going to go on the fast medium
before any of the other wheels do.
So it&#x27;s going to get the traction first.
these wheels on the left side of the vehicle these wheels right here,
these are still going to be stuck in the mud so what&#x27;s going to happen is:
this wheel right over here is moving faster
so it's essentialy going to be able to turn the vehicle.
These guys are still stuck in the mud.
And so you fast foward a little bit, the direction of the vehicle will change.
And so the vehicle will now move in a derection something like this.
The same thing would happen in a wave.
If the P-Wave is approaching the boundary like this
and something analogous is happening at the molecular level.
You can kind of view it as a even billard balls, they are kind of hitting each other -
I won't go into that because it can get a little confusing
depending on the different cases and the different boundaries.
But this is the easiest way to think about which direction it will refract.
And hopefully makes a little bit of a intuitive sense.
And so when you go from a slow to fast medium or a P-wave,
it's angle would accentuate in that direction.
If you went from the fast medium to the slow medium -
once again, you can just go to same thought expireeement,
so let's say you have our wave coming like that.
Draw the car! Visualise the car right here.
And you say: look, this tire is going to get stuck in the mud,
because it was on the road now this top tire right over here,
is getting stuck in the mud first,
so it is going to be moving slower,
so these tires are going to be able to move faster.
So the vehicle is going to turn.
So you'll be refracted in a direction like that
when your going from the fast to the slow medium.
So that is just a primer on refraction generally.
Now, let's think about what would happen
when sound waves are travelling through the Earth.
And this all help infrom us of essentially how do we figure out
what the actual structure of the Earth is.
So, if the Earth was just made up of some uniform material
and you had an earthquake rigth here on Earth,
maybe a little below the surface, you know,
it's happening in the crust but a little bit below the surface of the Earth.
If Earth was of uniform density, it was all the same material,
how would those, let's just think about the P-waves
because P-waves can travel in anything,
let's think about how those P-waves would travel.
Well, they would just go in straight lines,
there is nothing that would refract the P-waves.
It would just go in straight lines radially outward
from where the where the earthquake occured.
Now, at a first approximation we know that
as we go deeper and deeper in the Earth
there is more and more rock above,
that the weight of that rock is kind of compressing the rock below.
So you get higher and higher pressures,
and higher and higher densities.
So this is a uniform Earth.
But let's imagine a earth that is made up of unifrom material that is all solid.
A completely solid Earth,
but one where the density is constantly increasing as you go down.
So let's just think about it in beofre we go into the countinous case
cause we are talking about the density
as you go deeper it is getting countinously more dense.
Let's think about the discrete case,
where we have we the least dense layer.
So let me draw it right over here.
So let's say this is the surface of the Earth,
and this is least dense.
Then let's say you have another layer over here that is more dense.
So this is more dense.
Let's say you have another layer that is even more dense,
So you have another layer over here that is even more dense.
Then let's do one more layer.
This layer here, this is the densest layer,
So in general your P-wave, your seismic wave
is going to travel faster in denser material.
So it is going to travel the fastest here than here.
Then here it is going to the slowest in the least dense material.
So if you are coming in an angle,
let's think about what's going to happen.
So let's say you have your P-wave coming in at an angle like this.
So it is going straight thorugh the least dense material.
So what's going to happen to the...
let me do a slightly shallower angle, let's say it is like that.
What is going to happen when it goes into the more dense material?
So once again, let&#x27;s imagine in our little car.
So this tire is going to be able to go a little faster
before the tires on the other side.
So the car is going to be deflected to the left.
To the down left so now it is going to travel like this,
so it is now going to travel like this.
Now, what&#x27;s going to happen at this boundary?
Once again, imagine the car!
This tire right here is going to be able to travel faster before the other tires
so it will be deflected even more in that direction.
Then we go into the densest material.
Once again, the tires on kind of the bottom side when we look at it this way,
will be able to move faster before the other tires.
So we are going to get deflected even more.
So you see as you go from least dense material to more dense material
you are kind of curving outward.
So if this was continous, if we had a countinous structure
where as you go down it just gets more and more dense.
So this is less dense
and then just continuously it gets more dense.
So this is the most dense down here.
How would the refraction look?
Well, there would just be a continuous curve, it would look like this.
Your P-wave would constantly be refracted out like that.
It would curve outwards.
So this was the simplest example where Earth is uniform.
And you know, that&#x27;s pretty easy to dismiss,
obviously things will get denser because the more pressure down.
Let&#x27;s assume another thing.
We have a uniform Earth in terms of composition
but let&#x27;s say it gets denser.
So denser at the center.
Then how would the P-waves travel.
Or how would any seismic waves travel.
Well then, if you have your earthquake right over here,
the ones that are going straight down still would go straight down,
because we know that we won&#x27;t get refracted
if we&#x27;re kind of going perpendicularly to the change in medium or the change in boundaries.
But things that are coming in a slight angle as they get deeper,
they are going get deflected more an more and more
and they are going to be refracted outwards
just like we saw in this example here.
They are going in this ange, they are going to be outward like that,
if they go here, they are going to be refracted outward like that.
They are going to be refracted outward like that.
If you are here, you are going to be refracted outward like that.
If you are here, you are going to be refracted outward like this.
What we are going to to in the next few videos
is use what we&#x27;ve just learnt about refraction
in the case of seismic waves,
hopefully we&#x27;ve learnt it in this video,
and how we would refract as we are going through ever increasing denser material.
We are going to use that information
to essentially try to figure out the composition of the Earth.
Based on what we have actually observed.