In the first video
on social security, I keep talking about
how the tax
that you pay for social security is called
the FICA tax.
What I want to do in this video is
one, let you know what FICA actually stands for
and then think a little bit
how it is actually calculated.
So first, what does it stand for?
Literally it stands for
(while writing)
Federal... Insurance... Contributions... Act...
That's the acronym.
So it'd be FICA
and some people will call it FICA tax.
FICA tax.
This isn't just to support social security
or to be technically correct to support
the old age survivors and disability insurance.
It's also...
part of FICA tax is for that and part is for Medicare
So to make things clear...
So it's the part of our social security
or what we associate with social security
which is really the OASDI
did I get that right? OASDI...
So, part of it is for social security
and then that part is 12.4%... of the gross salary
but half of that is paid for by the employer
and half is paid by the employee.
We'll do a calculation in a second
so 6.2% and 6.2%.
The part is paid by the employer -
that's part of the payroll tax
stuff that the employer pays above and beyond
the gross income that they're giving to the employee
We'll do that calculation in a second.
The other thing that FICA tax is used for is Medicare...
Medicare...
This is for
total amount of 2.9% of the employee's gross salary
or 1.45% from the employer
as part of the payroll tax,
and 1.45% from the employee...
If you add these two things up
you get 15.3% total FICA tax.
15.3%... once again half is paid by
the employer and half is paid by the employee.
Now let's just do calculations
so that it makes a little more tangible sense
of what I am even talking about with this FICA tax.
So, let's imagine that you make 100,000$ a year
and it's a nice number because
it makes the maths easy.
Then your employer... employee...
Let me write it like this...
Employer... employee...
So, for social security...
your employer will contribute 6.2% of this.
So above and beyond paying
the 100,000$ gross salary, they will also pay 6.2%
or 6,200$...
The employee will also pay 6,200$
and that will be deducted from
their paycheck so what they get net of 6,200$
and then for Medicare...
we'll do that in pink...
Then for Medicare the employer will contribute 1,450$
once again
above and beyond the gross salary of 100,000$
and the employee will pay
1,450 out of their gross salary.
So the total amount
that is paid by the employer...
Total amount paid by the employer...
...is 7,650$ in payroll tax for this one employee
and the total amount
by the employee is the exact same amount: 7,650.
So just to be clear,
if you want hire an employee
and pay them a 100,000$ in gross salary
you actually have to set aside a 100,000$ and 7,650.
So the employer...
the total that the employer is paying...
the employer...
the total that they're paying... total paying...
Or let me just think of it this way...
The total that the employer has to set aside...
If you include the salary is going to be...
107,650$ so they can cover the gross salary
plus this payroll tax over here.
The net that the employee is getting...
and once actually this isn't even the net,
I shouldn't call it the net...
the employee is getting after paying FICA taxes
is going to be a 100,000 minus 7,650
but I won't even write that number down
oh, I mean, what is that?
That's... 92,350$
because that's before paying
just the traditional federal income tax
and the traditional state income tax
so that's gonna cut it down a good bit
so the employee is gonna take home
probably on the order of 60,000-70,000$
so above and beyond this thing right here.
So even if the employer is paying this much,
the employee is getting a lot less
in terms of what they get to take home.
Now one thing that I think it is worth mentioning
is on like traditional federal income tax...
in traditional federal income tax your first several
tens of thousands dollars you make
are not taxed and as you go up the brackets
each incremental dollar
as you enter one bracket or another
you start to pay a higher percentage on those.
The FICA tax is actually very different
some people would even
call it a regressive income tax.
That's because you only pay
the FICA tax on the first 160,000
and at least this is the number in 2011
you only pay on the first 160,800$.
So someone
who makes 200,000$ will pay the same FICA tax
as someone who makes a 160,800$.
So you only pay it on the percentage below that
and the reason why is it
that the person making 200,000$
will get the exact same benefits
as well as the person who makes 160,800$
and this number...
essentially they tried index it roughly to inflation
so it will go up over time... but to some degree
someone who makes, let's say, below this threshold
is gonna pay this percentage
between them and their employer
is gonna pay this percentage of their income.
While someone who makes much more than this
will have to pay a smaller percentage of their income
but they'll end up getting the same benefits.
And so, that's one reason
why it is considered regressive
is that as you make more money you're paying
a smaller percentage of your income on FICA tax
and the other reason why it's considered
regressive is actually on the benefits side.
Because obviously someone who...
if you have two people
receiving social security benefits...
so you have this person,
so when this is when they turn 65...
let me put it this way...
So let's say that you have two people...
they worked their whole lives
and let's say they both retire at 65...
although that the retirement age is increasing...
It's slowly being indexed up
and then they retire.
It's known that the wealthier people...
And there's also
a demographic space on race and things like that...
but it's known that wealthier people actually live longer
so they actually get benefits
for a longer period of time.
So they're actually able
to get their benefits for longer.
So it depends when you fall into it
likely, that even though there's this cap
someone higher up the income chain
also probably did pay more into it
but they're also getting
a bigger check for paying more into it
the check that you eventually get is based
to some degree on what level of FICA tax
you were paying and they're very well likely
to be able to collect this payments for longer
than someone who maybe doesn't have
quite the same... I guess, quality of life
and doesn't actually live as long.