simplify the expression 18x to the fourth
minus 3x squared
plus 6x minus 4, all of that over 6x
so theres a couple ways to think about it
there all really equivalent
you really just view this up here as being the exact same thing
as 18x to the fourth over 6x
plus negative 3x squared over 6x
or you could say minus 3x squared
over 6x plus 6x over 6x
minus 4 over 6x
now theres a couple ways to think about it
one is
I just kind of decomposed this numerator
up here, if I just had a buch of stuff
a+b+c over d
thats clearly equal to A over D plus B over D
plus C over D
or maybe not so clearly but hopfully tht helps clarify but
another way to think about it is kind of like
your distributing the division
if I divide a whole expression by something thats
equivalant to dividing each of the terms by that something
Another way to think about it is that were multiplying this entire expresion
so this is the same thing as one over 6x
times these entire thing
times 18x to the fourth-3x squared
plus 6x minus 4 and so here this would be just the straight distributive property.