Let's now use what we know about the Chain rule and the Product rule
To take the derivative of an even weirder expressions.
We are going to take the derivative of e^cos(x) times cos(e^x)
Let's take the derivative of this.
So we can view this as the product of two functions,
so the product rule tells us that this is going to be the derivative with the respect to x
of e^cos(x) times cos(e^x) plus the first function
just e^cos(x) times the derivative of the second function cos(e^x)
And so we just need to figure out what these two derivatives are.
So we can use the Chain Rule here.
Just to make it clear, we got this from the Product Rule.
But then to evaluate each of these derivatives, we need to use the Chain Rule.
So let's think about this a little bit.
So let's think about what the derivative of this function is.