What I want to do in this video is give you
at least a basic overview of 'probability' –
a word that you've probably heard a lot.
And you are probably a little bit familiar with it.
But, hopefully, this will give you
a little deeper understanding.
So let's say that I have a fair coin over here
And so, when I talk about a fair coin, I mean
that it has an equal chance of
landing on one side or another.
So you can maybe view it as the sides are equal –
their weight is the same on either side.
If I flip it in the air, it's not more likely
to land on one side or the other.
It's equally likely.
So you have one side of this coin –
(So this would be the heads, I guess.
I'm trying to draw George Washington.
I'll assume it's a quarter of some kind.)
And then on the other side, of course, is the tails.
So that is heads.
The other side right over there is tails.
So, if I were to ask you,
"What is the probability –
I'm going to flip a coin.
And I want to know, "What is
the probability of getting heads?"
And I could write that like this:
WRITING: The probability of getting heads.
And you probably, just based on that question,
have a sense of what probability is asking.
It's asking for some type of way of getting your
hands around an event that's fundamentally random.
We don't know whether it's heads or tails.
But we can start to describe
the chances of it being heads or tails.
And we'll talk about different
ways of describing that.
So, one way to think about it – (And this is the way
that probability tends to be introduced in textbooks.)
– is you say, "Well, look. How many different
equally likely possibilities are there?"
"So how many equally likely possibilities?"
So, number of equally – (Let me write 'equally.')
– of equally likely possibilities.
And of the number of equally likely possibilities,
I care about the number that
contain my event right here.
So, the number of possibilities that meet
my constraint – that meet my conditions.
So, in the case of the probability
of figuring out heads,
what is the number of
equally likely possibilities?
Well, there are only two possibilities.
We're assuming that the coin can't land
on its edge and remain standing straight up.
We're assuming it lands flat.
So, there are two possibilities here –
two equally likely possibilities.
You could either get heads,
or you could get tails.
And what number of possibilities
meet my conditions?
Well, there's only one: the condition of 'heads.'
So, it'll be 1 over 2.
So, one way to think about is that
the probability of getting heads
is equal to 1 over 2 –
is equal to one-half (1/2).
If I wanted to write that as a percentage,
we know that 1/2 is the same thing as 50%.
Now, another way to think about –
or conceptualize – probability,
that will give you this exact same answer, is to say,
"Well, if I were to run the
experiment of flipping a coin,"
So, this flip, you view this as an "experiment".
I know this isn't the kind of
experiment that you're used to.
Normally, you think of an experiment as doing
something in chemistry or physics, or all the rest.
But an experiment is every time
you run this random event.
So one way to think about probability is, "if I were to do this experiment, many, many, many times,
if I were to do it a thousand times,
or a million times,
or a billion times, or a trillion times –
(And the more, the better.)
– what percentage of those would give me the outcome I care about?
What percentage of those would give me heads?
And so, another way to think about this
50% probability of getting heads is
if I were to run the experiment tons of times,
if I were to run this experiment forever –
an infinite number of times,
what percentage of those would be heads?
You would get this 50%.
And you can run that simulation.
You can flip a coin.
(And it's actually a fun thing to do.
I encourage you to do it.
if you take 100 or 200 quarters or pennies,
and you stick them in a big box,
and shake the box, so you are kind of
simultaneously flipping all the coins,
and then count how many of
those are going to be heads,
you're going to see that the larger
the number of coins that you are doing,
the more likely you are going to get
something really close to 50%.
But there's always some chance that
even if you flipped a coin a million times –
there's some super-duper small
chance that you get all tails.
But the more you do, the more likely that things are
going to trend toward 50% of them being heads.
Now, lets just apply these same ideas.
And while we're starting with probability –
at least the basics –
this is probably an easier
thing to conceptualize.
But a lot of times, this is
actually a helpful one too:
this idea that if you run the
experiment many, many times,
what percentage of those trials are going
to give you what you were asking for?
– in this case, heads.
Now let's do another very typical example
when you first learn probability.
And this is the idea of rolling a die.
So here's my die, right over here.
And, of course, you have
the different sides of the die.
So that's the 1. And that's the 2.
And that's the 3, etc. And what I want to do –
And we know of course that there are – (assuming a fair die) six equally likely possibilities.
When you roll this, you could get
a 1, a 2, a 3, a 4, a 5, or a 6.
And they are all equally likely.
So if I were to ask you,
"What is the probability,
given that I'm rolling a fair die" –
(So the experiment is rolling this fair die.)
"What is the probability of getting a 1?"
Well, what are the number of
equally likely possibilities?
Well, I have six equally likely possibilities.
And how many of those meet my conditions?
Well, only 1 of them meet my conditions –
that right there.
So, there is a 1/6 probability of rolling a 1.
What is the probability of rolling a 1 or a 6?
Well, once again, there are six equally
likely possibilities that I can get.
And now there are now two possibilities
that meet my condition:
I could roll a 1, OR I could roll a 6.
So, now there are two possibilities
that meet my constraints (my conditions).
So there is a 1/3 probability
of rolling a 1 or a 6.
Now, what is the probability –
And this might seem a little silly
to even ask this question.
But I'll ask it just to make it clear.
What is the probability of rolling
a 2 and a 3 –
And I'm just talking about
on one roll of the die.
Well, in any roll of the die,
I can only get a 2 or a 3.
I'm not talking about taking
two rolls of this die.
So in this situation, there are 6 possibilities,
but none of these possibilities are a 2 AND a 3.
On one trial, you can't get a 2
and a 3 in the same experiment.
Getting a 2 and a 3 are mutually exclusive events.
They cannot happen at the same time.
So the probability of this is actually 0.
There's no way to roll this normal die,
and all of a sudden you get a 2 AND a 3.
And I don't want to confuse you with that,
because it's abstract and impossible.
So let's cross this out right over here.
Now, what is the probability
of getting an even number?
So, once again, I have 6 equally likely
possibilities when I roll that die.
And which of these possibilities
meet my condition – the condition of being even?
Well, 2 is even. 4 is even. And 6 is even.
So three of the possibilities meet my
conditions – meet my constraints.
So this is 1/2.
If I roll a die, I have a 1/2 chance
of getting an even number.