Determine in the data in the table is direct, inverse
or joint variation. Then identify the equation that
represents the relationship. So lets just think about
direct , inverse of joint variation means.
Direct variation - if y varies directly with x
if y = constant multiple of x. if you divide both sides by x
y / x = k, so the ratio betwen y & x is some constant
and you can go the other way around x = consta x ynt
or x/y = k these are not the same k
I am saying these are constant relationship
inverse relationship is some degree the opposite.
If x increases y should increase in direct variation.
if you increase x by some factor x going up by 3x
then y should also increase by the same factor 3
inverse variation you have y being some constant over
1/x; y = k x 1/x
if you multiply both sides by x then you have x.y = k
If you increase x they y will go down
and if you take x and increase by a factor of 3
you are decreasing this by a whole factor of 1/3
so then you are going to reduce y by 1/3
now finally they talk about joint variation
joint variation deals with more than one variable
if area of a rectangle = length x breadth, this is
a example of joint variation. area depends on two variables
joint variation deals with more than two variables
as x goes from 1 to 2, y is going from 12 to 6
if x is going up by 2, y is oming down by 1/2
as x goes from 1 to 3, y is multipled by 1/3
this is not direct variation as x increases
y is decreasing this is going to be inverse variation
when x increases by a certain factor,
y is decreasing by the same factor.
if x is increasing by 3, y is decreasing by 1/3 of the
original value. So we have inverse variation in place.
They ask identify the equation that represents this relationship
we know that inverse variation the product of x and y
needs to be some constant. let me make another
column x times y, 1x12 = 12; 2x6=12; 3x4=12; 4x3=12
clearly in every situation x.y = 12
so the equation that represents the relation ship is
x.y = 12