It looks like this exercise is asking use to do many
things and i encourage you to pause this video and try to do it on your own
first and then see maybe how I tackle the same exact thing
so the first thing they're saying is Draw
a 60 degree angle in standard position together
with a unit circle.Use the triangle
below, so this triangle right over here, to find the x- and y- coordinates
of the point of intersection of the terminal side and
the circle.So let me draw a unit circle here
so that is my y-axis
and then this could be my x-axis
and then I'm gonna draw a unit circle, which is a circle of radius one
so I'm gonna do my best to draw
its obviously hard to freehand
draw a circle, but I have a little easier time when I draw it as
a dotted line, I can later make it undotted
okay!...so that's pretty close, my best attempt
at freehand drawing a unit circle
so there you go...filling the dots
now that i need it to be a solid line
so that's my best attempt...fair enough.so I've drawn
the unit circle..."Unit circle"
it has radius One, so this point right over here
is going to be the point (1,0)
the x-coordinate is 1 and the y-coordinate is 0
This point right over here, on the Y-coordinate.So thats the point (o,1)
and then this over here is the point (-1,0)
and this point right over here is a zero x-coordinate and a negative one y-coordinate (0,-1)
there you go.So those are those 3 points or those 4 points
right over there.So that is my unit circle
now they say draw a 60 degree angle in standard
position together with a unit circle. so standard position,
you start to draw a ray, its centered at the origin
its along the positive x-axis, that's your initial side of your angle
and then you...since we're going positive 60 degree, we'll go in a
counter clockwise direction, so we're going positive
60 degrees, counter clockwise direction and so your terminal side
would be a ray that looks something like that, so that's
our 60 degree angle in standard position
Use the triangle below, so that's this triangle to find the x- and y-coordinates
of the point of intersection of the terminal side and the circle.
so it sounds very complex but all they're saying is
what are the x- and y-coordinates of that point right over there
so what is the x-coordinate and what is the y-coordinate
and I'll give you a little bit of a hint here
we can drop...we can construct a right triangle by taking a line
from that point and going straight down, since it went straight down
we know that this is a 90 degree angle
we also know that if this is a 60 degree angle right over here
so this is a 60 degree angle ..and this is a 90 degree angle
we know that all the angles of a triangle have to add up to 180 degrees
so we know that this up here is going to be a 30 degree angle
so using that information..and this triangle right over here
and what we know about similar triangle, can we now figure out what x- and
y- are going to be.. well lets think about it
lets think about it a little bit
so what is...what is the x-coordinate of this
that's just the distance we have to go along the x-axis over here
this is the x and then we would go y up that much. so this distance right over here
essentially the bottom of this 30, 60 90 triangle
this is going to be..this length is going to be equal to
our x-coordinate.and then this height over here
the height of this triangle, the length of this side
that's going to be equal to our y-coordinate...
so if we just figure out the lengths of these sides, then we know what the x- and y-coordinates
are going to be, and we also know that these are similar triangles
you have a 60 degree angle here ...you have a 60 degree angle here
you have a 30 degree angle up here...you have a 30 degree angle up here.
you have a 90 degree angle over here...you have a 90 degree angle over here
so all the angles are the same, these are similar
triangles, which tell you the ratio of corresponding sides are going to be the same
well lets think about the ratios of the corresponding sides.
well what sides do we know on this triangle right over here, here they gave us all the sides
what sides do we know here?. well we knew that this was a unit circle
so what is the distance between our origin and this intersection point
so what is the length ..essentially of the hypotenuse of this right triangle
well the hypotenuse is a radius
of the unit circle,a unit circle is a circle which has radius 1
so the hypotenuse here has the radius 1
and so hopefully we can now use this information and knowing that the ratio
of the corresponding sides are going to be to same, to come up with
what x- and y- are.
so, one thing we can say is that the ratio of the short side of this triangle
to the long side should be the same as the ratio of the short side of this triangle
to the long side, or the ratio of the side opposite the 30 degree angle
to the hypotenuse should be the same as the ratio of the side opposite to the 30 degree angle to the
hypotenuse.so we could say the ratio of 1 to 2
the ratio of 1 to 2 would be the same as the ratio of
x to 1 ..to the hypotenuse
or this could immediately get solved because x divided by 1 is just equal to x
or we get x is equal to one half (x = 1/2)
lets use that same logic again.
The ratio of this side opposite the 60 degree side to the hypotenuse
so square root of 3 to the hypotenuse
should be the same as the ratio of the side opposite the 60 degree angle
which in this case is y to this hypotenuse ...to 1
well once again this is essentially Y divided by 1 (y/1) is just Y
so we get y is equal to square root of 3 over 2 (y=√3/2)
so we now know the x- and y-coordinates, this we can rewrite
as (1/2,√3/2)
now the last part they ask use to
confirm that the x-coordinate is equal to the cosine of 60 degree (cos60°)
let me do that in different color..confirm that the x-coordinate is equal to cos60°
well ..lets take out our SOH CAH TOA
again, just to remember what sine,cosine and tangent definitions are
SOH.... CAH
SOH CAH ...let me use a different color
SOH CAH TOA
So whats the Cosine of 60° going to be equal to?
So the cosine of this angle.
so the cosine of 60°(cos60°) is going to be equal to the adjacent over the hypotenuse(Adj/Hyp)
its going to be equal to x over the hypotenuse.
its going to be equal to x over the hypotenuse which is just 1, this is a unit circle
so x is going to be equal to the cosine of 60°(x=cos60°)
our x-coordinate is the same thing a cosine of 60°(cos60°)
and we already figured out that x is equal to one half (x=1/2)
so that all checks out. We can do the same thing for the sine.
We must make sure that the y-coordinate is equal to the sine of 60°(sin60°)
so sine of 60° ..based on our definition of these trig functions
is equal to the opposite over hypotenuse(Opp/Hyp)
so its equal to the opposite ..is our y-coordinate
the length here is the same as our y-coordinate
so its equal to y over our hypotenuse..well that's definitely equal to y
which we already got with square to 3 over 2 which is equal to square root of 3 over 2
so that checks out
and that y over x is equal to tangent of sixty degrees
well tangent is opposite over adjacent (opp/adj)
so let me right it over here ..running out of real estate
tangent of 60 degrees
TOA tells us its opposite over adjacent
the opposite side is y ..the adjacent side is x
so that also works out