If we have 2 groups and in each group I have 4,
(so that's one group of 4)
(and then here is my second group of 4)
we already know that we could write this as 2 times 4
which is the same thing as 4 plus 4.
Notice, I have 2 fours here. I have 4 plus another 4,
which is going to be equal to...
Well if I have 4 plus 4 or if I have 2 groups of 4, either way I'm going to have a total of 8 things.
And you see that right over here.
We have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8 things.
What I want you to do is pause the video now and try to group these same 8 things
but to group it in other way, so that we can represent 8 as the product of whole number.
Here I've represented 8 as the product of 2 and 4.
2 times 4 is 8.
See if you can represent 8 as a product of other whole numbers or
whole numbers in different ways. Grouping it in different ways.
So I assume you've paused the video so let's try it out ourselves.
So one thing we could do, we could view this instead of 2 groups of 4 we can view 8 as 4 groups of 2.
So that's one group of 2, two groups of 2, three groups of 2, four groups of 2.
So we could write that 4 times 2 is equal to 8.
And we could view this is the same thing as literally 4 twos.
We have 1, 2, 3, 4 twos.
Each of these have 2 in them so we're going to say:
1, 2, 3, 4 twos.
2 plus 2 plus 2 plus 2 is equal to 8.
These are both equivalent. 4 times 2, literally 4 groups of 2.
That's the same thing as taking 4 twos and adding them together.
Notice, we have 2 twos right over here, we added them together: 1, 2.
Here we have 4 twos and we're adding them together: 1, 2, 3, 4.
We take our 4 twos and we add them together.
How else we could we represent 8?
Well, we literally could view it as 8 groups of 1.
So let's do that. So 8 groups of 1 would look like this:
That's 1 group of one, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
So we could write this down as 8 times 1.
8 times 1 is (once again) equal to 8.
And if we wanted to write this down as a repeated addition, well this is literally 8 ones.
So 1 plus 1 plus 1 plus 1 plus 1 plus 1 (let's see... that's 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6) plus 1 plus 1 is equal to 8.
Now you might be a little stomp.
Well what's another way of getting to 8?
Well, you could literally view it as 1 group of 8.
So let me view it that way.
So this is just one entire group of 8, the whole thing!
The whole thing is a group of 8.
So we could write this down as 1 (let me scroll over to the right a little bit) times 8.
And 1 times 8 is equal to 8.
And how would we view that?
Well, we only have one 8 now.
We don't have to add that one 8 to anything else so we could literally write this down.
If we wanted to do it the way we've done the last few, we could literally write it down.
We just have one 8!
Well, one 8 is clearly going to just be equal to 8.
So now let me ask you another question.
So far we've been focused on each of these groups, but what if we actually view this as 4 groups of 8?
So what if we actually view this (let me clear this) as 4 groups of 8?
Then how many things are we actually going to have?
So let me make this very clear.
So we have one group of 8, two groups of 8, three groups of 8 and four groups of 8.
So we would view this as 4 times 8.
Or, which is going to be the same thing, as 8 plus 8 plus 8 plus 8.
Four 8s. What is this going to be equal to?
And I encourage you to pause the video and figure it out right now.
Well, there's a couple of ways that you could've thought about this.
You could've literally just counted these or you could say:
Well, let's see. You could skip count by eight: 8, 16, 24, 32.
Or you could've said: 8 plus 8 is 16, plus 8 is 24, plus 8 is 32.
Or you could've literally just counted all the triangles here.