i;m convinced, i will follow them. i will come too
only four of us involved. looking at trousers
and peale staicase, we've got a portrait of two of his
sons raphael and tishin peale. we wonder if these names are phinoria
he named his children after famous european painters
and scientists. that is amazing. he is amazing real
and this is the amazing portrait we are going to think about
full size portraits as being images of kings and
we are a stalk receiver here. and here peale
represented his twosons making up a staircase
and this painting was meant as a show piece for his first
american museum. this was a museum of art and there is amuseum of science as well.
that was a most famous exhibit of the bones of a
master don it is interesting to think about
what the museum of science and art meant
in a republic. here was an attempt to create an institution of education.
here we have true democracy. this is the first time
sice the new democracy existed it was this grand
experiment. peale understood that the public needed education to make wise decisions
and so peale founded the combiano, the first american art school
and had it ceded to the peennsylvania academy of
fine arts that he founded ten years after that
after he founded, as we said this first museum
we've talked about his achievements, but we haven't
really talked about his pre foresight, that is in evidence here.
that's true.ok this painting is all about
fusion and what is remarkable is none about clarity
with shich his sons are rendered with a staircase