In the last video
I gave the example of this bank that I keep using
And in this example
as opposed to giving the gold out to make loans
and be used for projects that gold gets redeposited
and then re-lent out
What we did in this examples is that the bank
every time it made a loan,
it just made a loan and that created an asset
and then it had a corresponding liability
where the liability was either a checking account
that the entrepreneur could use or bank notes
which are essentially cash
that the entrepreneur could use to pay their laborers
or to buy their land or whatever they needed to do.
So an obvious question was,
how much could a bank do it?
When does this stop?
Can a bank just keep increasing the left
and right hand sides of the balance sheet?
And to answer this question,
we'll introduce the idea of a reserve ratio.
So just, I guess, a bit of a review, just to make sure
we're clearly reading this balance sheet.
Let me label things a little bit more
because sometimes I assume too much.
Remember, these are the assets.
The assets are all of these.
Let me make a bold line here.
All of these is the assets of this bank,
including its building,
so its vault down there.
And then the liabilities.
I'll do that in this red.
I like this red color,
But these are the liabilities
over here, in this red color, that I am coloring right now
And the equity - whoever owns the bank,
whether it's stockholders or maybe
it's owned by an individual.
Maybe it's owned by me - is what's left over.
I'll do it in a nice neutral color.
This is the equity.
So the question is, how much can the bank... [continued later]
- let me do this, all of these are liabilities -
So the question is,
how much can the bank continue to issue out more loans
and increase its assets and its liabilities?
Remember, every time it'd issue a loan,
like for right here,
it issued a 100 gold piece equivalent loan to D -
and instead of giving D 100 gold pieces from, say, right here,
it just created a checking account for D,
which later D paid to A
and that's why it's labeled A right here.
Let me relabel another thing
because the gold is a different color
just so you see the gold.
This is the gold part of the assets.
Let me make that very clear,
that all of these right here is gold.
Maybe I'll color it a little bit
That's all gold and there's 500 gold pieces
So let's introduce the concept of a reserve ratio
Let's think a little bit about what even a reserve is.
A reserve is something that you keep aside
because you might need it one day.
And in this situation, all of these liabilities -
-	whether they're these bank notes outstanding in this example
or whether they're these checking accounts,
these demand accounts - these are all liabilities that
someone can come back to the bank on any given day
and say, hey, I want my gold now, for whatever reason.
Maybe I'm leaving town.
Maybe I don't trust the bank anymore.
For whatever reason,
maybe they just want to make some jewelry.
For whatever reason, that person wants their gold back.
These are demand accounts.
These checking accounts are demand accounts
and these notes are things that
can be exchanged for gold at any point in time
And we talked a little bit about this earlier
when we started the whole banking discussion,
but you have to leave aside a little bit of gold
just in case someone wants their gold back.
So this amount of the gold that
you have to leave aside as a reserve,
relative to the total amount of demands you have on that gold,
that's the reserve ratio.
And in this situation, this world that we've created,
The reserve store value is gold.
Later on we're going to get ourselves off of this gold system
and then that reserve store of value
is actually going to turn into cash,
but for right now and
I think it's easier actually to conceptualize gold.
Let's stick with gold.
The reserve ratio for this bank is the amount of gold assets
you won't see this formal definition anywhere
because most people are off the gold standard right now
but it's the amount of gold assets divided by total
I don't want to say total liabilities
because the bank could take out loans
that aren't demand loans.
Everything on the liabilities right now is on demand loans,
which means whoever has that liability can come back
and exchange it for gold at any moment in time,
but the bank could've taken just a regular loan
And a regular loan might not be on demand.
A regular loan might be a loan that
the bank doesn't have to pay back for 10 years,
in which case there's no reason why the bank
would have to set aside some gold to pay that back.
So let's make our definition not total liabilities,
but total demand liabilities.
So what would be total demand liabilities?
That would be total bank notes in this case
and bank notes are also something we'll later leave
a world where every bank is issuing bank notes,
but I just wanted to give you that kind of historical
context,
how bank notes even started off.
Total bank notes and demand accounts,
demand or checking accounts.
So let's see what it is for this bank that we have here.
So our total gold assets are 500
and what's our total demand accounts?
100 plus 100 plus 100
-	100, 200, 300, 400 - 600 -
and I think this is another 100 here - 700.
The total demand liabilities, I just figured out, was 700
and the gold assets in this bank are 500.
So right now the reserve ratio of this bank
is pretty high - 5/7. So I don't know what 5/7 is.
If I'm doing my mental math right, it's about 62% -
7 goes into 50 - no, no, 7 goes into 50, 7 times
- it's like 71%. Right. 7 times 7 is 49-- 71%.
So that's its reserve ratio.
And what keeps banks from just keep issuing more assets
and debts to expand its balance sheet
is a reserve ratio requirement.
So right now in the United States –
although we're not on the gold standard,
but you could imagine it in this world
our bank regulators might say that your reserve ratio
on demand accounts, so the amount of gold
you have to set aside for checking accounts
- so reserve requirement, we'll call it.
Let me change colors just to ease the monotony.
The reserve requirement
They might say the reserve requirement is equal to -
let's say they want to be safe.
Let's say they want to make it 20%.
In the U.S. right now, it's 10%,
although the reserve commodity isn't gold anymore.
Let's say your reserve requirement is 20%.
That means as long as - at any given moment in time,
more than 20% of these people
don't demand their money back,
the bank's going to have liquidity.
The bank is going to be able to fulfill its promise.
Because all of these people think at any given moment
They can go to the bank and get their gold.
In order for this system to work,
there has to be confidence
and in order for there to be confidence,
the bank has to be good for it
every time someone asks for their money.
So the bank has to stay liquidate
So essentially this reserve ratio is
what the regulators think that a bank needs to maintain,
in order to maintain, be liquid
Our bank as it is right now, it has a reserve ratio of 71%.
So as long as no more than 71% of these people
some of these loans, they might be out for a year or two.
So as long as -
- in that year or two that these loans are out -
as long as no more than 71% of these people don't come asking for their gold
we should be OK.
If all of a sudden for whatever weird reason, I don't know,
80% of these people who have demand deposits or
bank notes come and want to switch their money for gold,
this bank is going to run out of gold
and that's a bank run.
And there's a couple of reasons why that's really bad.
One is, all of a sudden these demand deposit accounts
all of a sudden don't seem to be that great
because you're not really getting your gold on
demand
because more people are asking for gold than there is gold.
And the other problem is, all of a sudden,
everyone will lose confidence in the system
and everyone's going to think,
oh boy, these banks that have these nice vault-looking buidlings
maybe they're not as safe as I thought.
So everyone is going to start pulling their money out.
And that's called a bank run.
So in this example, if I assume,
that this loan is really worth 300 gold pieces
and it's really going to be paid back
and this loan right here is really worth 100 gold pieces
and it really will be paid back,
this bank is solvent.
It has more assets than it does liabilities.
So if it has enough time,
it will be able to pay back all of its liabilities.
But if all of these people, all of a sudden, come in and
want not just 500 gold pieces, if they want 600 gold pieces,
right, they're owed actually 700 - so if they want 600 gold pieces
all of a sudden
everyone's going to lose confidence in the system
These people probably - if they're not able to get that,
they're probably going to want all their money back
so then all of these liabilities are going to come due.
And then maybe the bank is going to have to try to sell its assets
these loans to someone else
or maybe try to collect from someone,
but as you can imagine, it's a whole... big mess and
the whole system which is dependent on confidence
will just start to crumble.
But anyway, the initial question is, what is the limit to how much
you can expand the asset and the liability side of the balance sheet
just by creating these loans and these deposit accounts?
And that limit is driven by the reserve ratio,
whatever the regulators set.
Anyway, I'll see you in the next video.