I'm here with Dr. Lawrence Baker from Stanford Medical School, and we are going to talk about what?
How about Medicare?
I thikn we knew what was going to happen since we have a picture here already. So what is this a picture
of?
i think this is a picture of LBJ signing the medicare act in 1965. This is the time that we passed medicare.
Lindon Banes Johnson, LBJ. This looks like Truman over here. I think he was there maybe because he was
probably old enough by that time to be a recipient. Yeah, 65 and over.
I think we all have a general idea of what Medicare is. It is kind of a healthcare program or an insurance
program, for people who are retired. But then it starts to get fuzzy after that. There are all these
details that confuse most of us.
Yeah so we talk about Medicare in a bunch of different ways. Medicare is a program, it's a US governmnet
program. It is run by the federal government.
Yup
And sometimes it's thrown in with Medicaid. What is the difference, just at a high level?
So Medicaid is a different program, run by the federal government in coordination wit te state governments.
Medicaid is a federal and state program.
Medicare is a federal program. Medicare is for folks who are 65 or older, and people with disabilities.
Medicaid is the program that is aimed at lower income population.
So this is older people and disabilities and this is lower income and poverty issue.
yes
let me write it down: lower income, primarily retirees. Yeah, the vast majority of people in there are
people who are in there because they are over 65.
And we are just going to focus on Medicare. Medicare is federal government and Medicaid is federal and
state governments.
They obviously sound similar. Yeah they sound very similar.
They are easily confused, especially at the name level. They are really different programs. They operate
completely separately. In a few cases, there are people who get access to both of them. But they pay
differently, they run differently.
So at the federal level, they are still run by the same organization, the centers for Medicaid and Medicare.
Yeah the department of health and human services has a subpart called the centers of medicaid and medicare
services (CMS), the executive branch. So the executive branch of government and there is the secretary
of health and human services, and then within that we have CMS which is Centers for Medicare and Medicai
d services. It really should have 2 Ms in it, but it's shorter to just have one.
They administer at the federal level, both medicare and medicaid. Just to reiterate, medicare is really
mainly a federal thing, while medicaid is both. And they are run separately. So you have medicare is
and you have medicaid here.
I see.
Let's dive deep into medicare. So what is it?
So Medicare is an insurance program. It provides insurance for people who are eligible for it. So if
you're age 65 or over, or if you have a disability, a couple of small groups if you have lugarics or
if you have n stage renal diseases, a kidney failure, then you can get access Medicare too. But those
are small populations. But if you are in those groups, you are eligible for Medicare. Medicare will provide
you with insurance that will cover hospital bills, doctor bills, and some presciption drugs, it'll cover
a lot of the medical care. So here's the thing, I hear all these things, but this is the part that gets
confusing for everyone that you have part a, part b, part c and those are all parts
what are they referring to? Are they exactly insurance or they different?
So Medicare has these 4 parts. Part A, B, C and D and it can get a little confusing but we could break
it up into pieces, but the biggest one in terms of the number of people in it, is what sometimes we call t
traditional medicare, and that's what Part A and B is historically and you can take as a package. Sometimes
people call it standard medicare or original medicare. But you know when they passed the program, when
they first did it, part a was meant to cover hospital expenditure and part b was aimed at doctor cost,
cost for seeing physicians. Of course those 2 go so close together that now they are sort of a pair
so you'd only rarely find someone who only wants part A. Sometimes you hear that the doctor cost are
out patient. Hospital costs are in-patient, because in some sense you're living there while they are
treating you, while out-patient you go visit them for an hour and leave.
Yeah so that's a way of breaking up services medicine provides. Medicare actually gets a little bit,
it's mix-and-match, and so really medicare part A expenditure is when a hospital bills medicare for hospitale,
, for use of the room, use of the hospital
anytime a doctor bills medicare, even when they saw the patient in a hospital they are going to be a
part b expenditure.
I see. So it isn't a strictly an in-patient and out-patient difference. It really is along the lines
of hospital and doctor. It is useful to think about that, the out-patient and in-patient.
So we'll cover everything that happens?
Are we including drugs?
So drugs is one key issue, the first thing is i'd say that traditional medicare is pretty comprehensive,
It covers most of the things people would normally encounter.
So part A and part B do not cover drugs. So when Lindon Johnson was signing this, if Truman had to get
prescription drugs, and if he was a medicare recipient in 1965, he would have had to pay that out of
pocket
Yes. So one caveat I'll note is that if you get prescription drugs while you're in the hospital, you're
staying in the hospital and they are giving you drugs. That's going to be covered. It's when you're outpatient,
and you're going home and someone sends you to the pharmacy to pick up the drugs..
I see, so Medicare in its original would not cover that. The out-patient cost. So that became a problem
for some folks and that has generated changes in the medicare
There is a part now that covers that. So that is the Part D, an extension of the medicare program that
covers that
I don't know how far we want to get into that
I'll write it here, D for Drugs.
The whole story of Drugs in medicare has a lot to it, people would buy additional policies if they had
A and B and they'd buy a private supplement that might cover the drug itself
but now with the part D program and maybe people will buy that instead
and then there is other stuff going on there
And there's also a C right here.
So A and B, traditional, A hospitals and B doctors and what percent my health insurance copay. How does
it work with traditional health insurance?
So if yo ujust have Part A and Part B, on Part B side doctors are covered 80% of the medicare allowable
charges so medicare has a fee schedule that governs what the doctors can be paid for services and medicare
will cover 80% of the cost and the patient pays remaining 20
For part A, it gets a little more complicated but there is a copayment that you have to make if you go
to the hospital. Medicare will have a co-payment of a fixed amount - several hundred dollars coming u
p
it's just not as simple as 80-20. You're going to pay a co-payment there too.
So they are not bad coverage, but there are some costs you can run up and if you're pretty sick you might
have a bill that left over
And there is extreme flexibility here. So you can see any doctor you want, and go to any hospital you
want
yeah medicare part a and part b is, in a way of thinking, one of the last bastions as it existed
in 1965-70-75, when there were really minimal restrictions on what doctors you can see, doctors get a
lot of discretion in the kind of services they are going to provide
and there's not a lot of oversight that you might see in today's HMOs
But there are still, and maybe I'm wrong here, there still are doctors that wont take medicare patients?
So doctors can elect to be medicare doctors or not and some doctors decide
that they have enough patients from other places then medicare is a plan,
and you have to follow the rules and some people think that medicare doesn't
pay as well, as other options they have. Most of the doctors, the vast majority of doctors in the country
will work with medicare.