In the video on electronegativity, we learned how to determine whether a covalent bond is polar or nonpolar.
In this video we're going to see how we can figure out whether molecules are polar or non polar,
and also how to apply that polarity to what we call "inter-molecular forces.
Intermolecular forces are the forces that are between molecules.
And so thats different than an intra-molecular force, which is the force within a molecule.
So the force within a molecule would be something like a covalent bond.
An intermolecular force would be the force that is between molecules.
So lets look at the first intermolecular force.
Its called a dipole-dipole interaction
and lets analyze why it has that name.
If i look at one of these molecules of acetone here,
and I focus in on the carbon thats double bonded to the oxygen,
I know that oxygen is more electronegative than carbon,
and so we have 4 electrons in this double bond between the carbon and the oxygen.
I'll try to highlight them right here.
Since oxygen is more electronegative, oxygen is going to pull those electrons closer to it
therefore giving oxygen a partial negative charge.
Those electrons in yellow are moving away from this carbon,
so this carbon is losing a little bit of electron density
and this carbon is becoming partially positive, like that.
For this molecule, we're going to get a separation of charge.
A positive and a negative charge.
We have a polarized double bond situation here, we also have a polarized molecule.
And so there's two different poles, a negative and a positive pole.
We say that this is a "polar molecule". So acetone is a relatively polar molecule.
The same thing happens to this acetone molecule down here, so we get a partial negative
And we get a partial positive. So this is a polar molecule as well,
and it has two poles. We call this a dipole.
Each molecule has a dipole moment. And because each molecule is polar and has a separation of positive
and negative charge, in organic chemistry we know that opposite charges attract.
So this negatively charged oxygen is going to be attracted to this positively charged carbon.
There's going to be an electrostatic attraction between those two molecules.
And thats what's going to hold these two molecules together, and you would therefore need energy
if you were to try to pull them apart. The boiling point of acetone turns out to be
approximately 56 degrees celsius. Room temperature is between 20 and 25, at room temperature
we have not reached the boiling point of acetone.
And therefore acetone is still a liquid.
At room temperature and pressure, acetone is a liquid. And it has to do with the intermolecular force
of dipole-dipole interaction holding those two molecules together.
And the intermolecular force, in turn, depends on the electronegativity.
Lets look at another intermolecular force, and this one's called hydrogen bonding.
Here we have two water molecules and once again, if I think about these electrons here
which are between the oxygen and the hydrogen, I know oxygen is more electronegative
than hydrogen, so oxygen is going to pull those electrons closer to it, giving the oxygen
a partial negative charge, like that.
The hydrogen is losing a little bit of electron density, therefore becoming partially positive.
The same situation exists in the water molecule down here.
So we have a partial negative and we have a partial positive.
Like the last example, we can see there's going to be some sort of electrostatic attraction between those opposite charges.
Between the negatively partially charged oxygen and the partially positive hydrogen, like that.
This is a polar molecule, of course water is a polar molecule.
You would think that this would be an example of dipole-dipole interaction, and it is,
except that in this case its an even stronger version of dipole-dipole interaction that we call "hydrogen bonding".
At one time it was thought that it was possible for hydrogen to form an extra bond
and thats where the term originally comes from.
But of course its not an actual intra-molecular force, its an inter-molecular force, but it is the strongest intermolecular
force. The way to recognize when hydrogen bonding is present as opposed to just dipole-dipole is to see what
the hydrogen is bonded to. In this case, we have a very electronegative atom, oxygen, bonded to hydrogen.
That hydrogen is interacting with another electronegative atom like that.
We have a partial negative, and a partial positive, and we have another partial negative over here.
This is the situation that you need to have when you have
hydrogen bonding. Here's your hydrogen showing intermolecular force here,
and what some students forget, is that this hydrogen actually has to be bonded to
another electronegative atom in order for there to be a big enough difference in electronegativity for
there to be a little bit extra attraction. And so the three electronegative elements that you should remember
for hydrogen bonding are: Fluorine, Oxygen, and Nitrogen.
The mnemonic that students use is "FON". So if you remember "FON" as the
electronegative atoms that could participate in hydrogen bonding, you should be able to remember
this intermolecular force. The boiling point of water is of course about 100 degrees celsius.
Higher than what we saw for acetone.
This is due to the fact that hydrogen bonding is a stronger version of dipole-dipole interaction, and therefore
takes more energy or more heat to pull these water molecules apart in order to turn them into a gas.
So, of course, water is a liquid at room temperature.
Alright, lets look at another intermolecular force. This one is called "london dispersion forces".
These are the weakest intermolecular forces, and they have to do with the electrons that are always moving around
in orbitals. Even though the methane molecule here, if we look at it, and we have a carbon surrounded by
hydrogens for methane. And its hard to tell from how i've drawn the structure here, but if you go back and
see the video for the tetrahedral bond angle proof, you can see that in three dimensions, these hydrogens are
coming off the carbon and they're equivalent in all directions.
There's a very small difference in electronegativity between the carbon and the hydrogen.
That small difference is cancelled out in three dimensions, and so the methane molecule becomes
non-polar as a result of that. So this one is non polar and this one is non polar.
There's no dipole-dipole interaction, there's no hydrogen bonding.
The only intermolecular force thats holding two methane molecules together would be london dispersion forces.
Once again you can think about the electrons that are in these bonds moving in those orbitals.
Lets say for the molecule on the left, for a brief transient moment in time,
you get a little bit of negative charge on this side of the molecule, so it might turn out to be
those electrons have a net negative charge on this side, and then for this molecule
the electrons could be moving the opposite direction giving this a partial positive.
There could be a very small bit of attraction between these two methane molecules.
Its very weak, which is why london dispersion forces are the weakest intermolecular force, but
it is there. And thats the only thing thats holding together these methane molecules.
Since its weak, we would expect the boiling point for methane to be extremely low, and of course
it is. So the boiling point for methane is somewhere around negative 164 degrees celsius.
Since room temperature is somewhere around 20-25, obviously methane has already boiled, if you will,
and turned into a gas. Methane is obviously a gas at room temperature and pressure.
Methane is a gas .
If you increase the number of carbons, you're going to increase the number of attractive forces
that are possible, and if you do that, you can actually increase the boiling point of other hydrocarbons
dramatically. Even though london dispersion forces are the weakest, if you have larger molecules and you
sum up all those extra forces, it can actually turn out to be rather significant when you're working with
larger molecules. This is just a quick summary of some of the intermolecular forces to show you
the application of electronegativity, and how important it is.