I'm going to construct a sequence where
I start with some number ,,
let's say I start with the number a ,,
and then each successive term of the
sequence,
I'm gonna to multiply the pre ,,
to get each successive term of the
sequence,
I'm gonna multiply the previous term
by some fixed non zero number.
And I'm gonna call that r.
So the next term is going to be a ,,
is going to be a times r.
And then the term after that I'm gonna
apply ,,
I'm going to multiply
this thing times r.
So it's going to be a ,,
if you took ,, if you multiply a r
times r,
that's going to be a r ,,
a r squared. And then if you were
to multiply this turned ,,
term times r, you would get
a times r to the third power.
And you could keep
going on and on and on and on.
And this type of sequence ,,
or
this type of progression ,,
is called a geometric ,,
geometric sequence or progression ,,
geometric sequence. You
start with some first value.
Let me circle that in a different color,
since I already used the green.
So you start with some first value.
And then each success ,,
to get each successive term,
you multiply by this fixed number.
And in this case,
this fixed number is r.
And so we call our common ratio ,,
our common ratio. Why is it called
a common ratio?
Well take any two successive terms.
Take this term and this term,
and divide this term by
this term right over here.
a r to the third divided by a r squared.
So if you find the ratio
between these two things a ,,
Let me rewrite this. Same colors.
So if you took a r to the third power,
and were to divide it by
the term before it ,,
so if you were divide
it by a r squared,
what are you gonna be left with?
Well, a divided by a is 1.
r to the third divided by r squared
is just going to be r.
And this is true if you divide any term
by the term before it.
Or if you find the
ratio between any term and the
term before it, it's going to be r.
And so that's why it's called
a common ratio.
And so let's ,, go look some ,,
look at some examples of
geometric sequences.
So if I start with the number ,,
if I start with the number 5 ,,
so my a is five ,, and then each time,
I'm gonna multiply ,,
I'm going to multiply by ,,
I don't know ,, Let's say I multiply by
1/7.
So then the next term is going to be
5 over 7 ,,
5 over 7. What's the next term going to
be?
Well, I'm going to multiply
this thing times one_seventh.
So that's going to be
5 7ths times one 7th is 5 49ths.
So it's going to be 5 over ,,
5 over 7 squared ,,
or 49. If I'm oh ,, were to multiply
this times 1 7th,
what am I going to get?
And I'll just change the notation.
I'll just get 5 times,
I don't actually know in my head what
7 to the third power is.
I guess I could calculate it.
Two hundred and eighty plus 63 ,,
Let's see. So that would
be see 7 times 40 is 280.
7 times 9 is 63. So you're going to
get to 343,
I believe. Let's see.
Did I do that right? 7 times 280 plus
63 is 343.
And you can just keep going.
So this right over here is an example
of a geometric ,,
of a geometric sequence.
Started with some first value,
and each successive value I
multiplied by 1 7th.
1 7th is the common ratio here.
Let me give you another one.
Let's say I have this.
Let's say I have 3.
And then let's say I have 6.
And let's say I have 12.
Then I have 24. Then I have 48.
Is this a geometric series?
And if it is, what is
the common ratio here?
Well, you could figure out
the common ratio by just taking any two
successive terms and dividing.
Well first you could ,,
you could try it with two terms.
So 12 divided by 6 is 2.
So we have to multiply by 2.
To go from 12 to 24, you multiplied by
2.
To go from 24 to 48, you have
to multiply by 2.
To