this video we are going to see how to determine the relative acidity of the molecule but looking at how the conjugat ebases
stabilize by the idea of electronegativity
so over here in left we have h-a which is our generic brownnsted larry acid (BLA)we know that BLA donate protons so if ha donates a protons its gonna loose ha+
and so these two electrons move onto the a and so the a now is a lone pair of electron -one formal charge form a -
and so a- is the conjugate base to ha.we think about the stability of the conjugate base
more stable a- is the more likely ha is to donate a proton.so if we want to determine the acidity of a molecule look at the stability of a conjugate base.
the more stable the conjugate base more likely is molecule to donate a proton and therefore stronger the acid.
we know that strength of the acid can be demonstrated by looking at the pka value .so lets take a look at the molecule and pka values and analize the relative stability of the conjugate bases.
here we have methane so since all these hydrogens are equivalent so i am gonna say this is the acidic proton on methane has a pka value of approx.48 methane is not very acidic at all.look at ammonia that's the acidic proton has the pka approx.33
for water has pka value of approx.16.and for hf(hydrofluoric acid) pka value of approximately 3.
and so you can see the trend in pka value .as i move to the right there is decrease in pka value which means that hf is the most acidic.
so if we can go into right we increase in terms of acidity of these molecules.we can explain these trend by looking at how to draw the conjugate bases for these molecules.
so if methane donate a proton and these electrons move which stay behind on carbon
so we go ahead and draw on carbon so we have 3 hydrogens and one pair of electrons giving a negative one formal charge.for ammonia
ammonia donates a proton to nitrogen and nitrogen still bonded to two hydrogens and one lone pair of electrons picked up another lone pair of electrons
giving negative 1 formal charge.for water these electrons move in there on the oxygen and oxygen would have three lone pair of electrons giving the negative one formal charge that's the hydroxide anion and for hf these electrons move of onto the fluorine which would give the flourine the negative one formal charge make the fluride anion .
so now we have the four conjugate bases drawn so we know that the most acidic fluoride molecule going to have the most stable conjugate base and we try to look at the differences between these four conjugate bases
has the element that bears a negative one formal charge.
base carbon has the -one formal charge.for the seconde ex.amide anion nitrogen has -1 formal charge.for hydroxide has -1 formal charge.and for this
last example fluorine has -1 formal charge.so carbon nitrogen oxygen and fluorine are on the same period on the periodic table and as you move across
you get the increase in the negativity as i move to the right i get increase in the elctronegativity .
and so the negative charge is the most stable on a electronegative atom.
we can think about that in terms of definition for electronegativity that we talkd about in earlier video as the ability of an atom to pull electrons towards itself in a molecule here to
hf(hydrofluoric acid) think about these two electrons are electronegative than hydrogen so its going to pull those electrons in that bond closer to itself so electronegative atoms like electrons so thats just a very
simple way of thinking why most stable electronegative atom they like electrons more than a less electronegative atom so we can see that trend reflected in
the stability right conjugate bases and since the fluoride anion is stable conjugate base that make hf had the lowest pka value and is the strongest acid out the ones we mentioned here.
alright lets take a look at two more examples we have ethane and ethanol.
and we look at these two examples in the last videos and we talked about there difference in there pka values for ethane thats the acidic approach on th apka is approximately 50 and for ethanol
the most acidic proton ethanol and the pka value is approximately 16.and in the last video we talked about the fact that ethanol is 10 to the 34 times more acidic than ethane
so there is extremely large difference in those pka value since there is extremely large difference in the acidity of those molecules and we can explain that by looking at the conjugal bases
so ethane donate a proton and these electrons move of on to that carbon we can go ahead and draw in the conjugate base so there would be five hydrogens attached
and this carbon right here would have a lone pair of electrons and -one formal charge and so for ethanol these electrons move of onto the oxygen after it donates a proton and it can go ahead and draw the conjugate base for ethanol which is the ethoxide anion.
and so there is going to be oxygen here with now three lone pair of electrons around it giving it a negative one formal charge.so what i studied these conjugate bases i can see these negative charge on the right which is on oxygen which is an electronegative element versus on the left
right the negative charge on left which is not as electronegtive as oxygen and so since electronegative atoms or elements bear the negative charge better stable ethoxide anion this conjugate base is more stable than the conjugate base on left and since
ethoxide is more stable that makes the ethnol molecule to more likely donate a proton and therefore where ethanol is much more sick which we can see reflected in values for the pka.
so look at the molecule draw the conjugate base and think about the stability of conjugate base in terms of what the electronegativity of that atom that bears the negative charge.