So, if you're watching this video, I'm pretty sure that at some point in your life, or in the lives of
someone you know, they've had the flu. almost everybody is pretty familiar with how
awful it feels to get sick with the flu. Now, when people talk about the flu, they kind of talk about it in two different ways.
We're gonna get into both of those ways right now. Now, sometimes, they'll talk about the illness,
or the symptoms they had when they had the flu.
Now, other times, they'll talk about the virus, you know, the actual virus that causes the flu.
So, I'm going to actually break it down the same way.
We're gonna talk first about the illness, and then we're going to get into the virus.
and we're gonna draw a nice little line down the middle so that we don't, uh, get lost in this conversation.
So, I can't help it, but any time that I hear that someone has the flu, I immediately get into this mode where I have
a bunch of questions for them, and I really just wanna kinda convince myself that when they say they have the flu,
they really have the flu, and they don't have something else. So the questions that pop up in my head:
The first one is usually, is it abrupt, or is did it kind of start abruptly.
I'm just going to kind of write that. "Was it abrupt?"
And you know, I might say, "do you remember, uh, feeling well one evening and then waking up sick?" Or something like that.
"Do you remember exactly, kinda, when it started?" And most people with the flu can tell you within a day or two
exactly when their illness started. Now, another clue that something is the flu is that it usually lasts for about 3-7 days.
So, if someone is saying, "well, I got sick with the flu and then four months later, you know, I started getting better."
That's a very weird story, usually it would be a lot quicker than that.