Last video, we saw how to draw dot structure of molecule with single covalent bonds.
this video will talk about multiple covalent bonds.
so we start in the same way with the last video
i want to draw the dot structure for C2H4
i would find carbon over here
and once again carbon is in Group 4,
so it has 4 valence electrons.
so i'm going to go ahead and put in one carbon with four valence electrons
and i know i have another carbon in my dot structure.
it also has four vlence electrons like that
so immediately i can see there is going to see a single covalent bond between my two carbons like that
for hydrogens, and i know that
hydrogens is in Group 1 on our periodic table,
hydrogen hass one valence electron.
now it makes sense and go ahead and put two hydrogens on each carbon
so if i put one hydrogen over here
and then another hydrogen on this carbon
i have two more hydrogens
so i can go ahead and put two hydrogens in the carbon on the right
when i connect my dots, i can see that i have a bond between carbon and the hydrogen here.
and this is not the correct dot structure.
because if you count of the number of electrons around the carbons,
let's go ahead and do it.
let's do the carbon on the left
i'm going to get two, four, six and seven electrons
so it only has seven electrons around each carbon
carbon does not satisfythe octet rule
so the only way for the carbon to get the octet of the electrons around it,
it would be this magenta electron moved in here
and this electron mobves in here
to form a double-covalent code