Let's add 536 to 398,
and we're going to do it two different ways so you really understand what this carrying is all about.
So first, we'll do it in the more traditional way.
We start in the "one"s place, we say "what's 6 plus 8?"
Well, we know that 6 plus 8 is equal to 14.
And so when we write it down here in the sum....
We could say... well look, the 4 is in the "ones" place. So it's equal to 4, plus one 10.
So let's write that one "10" in the "tens" place.
And now we focus on the "tens" place.
We have one 10, plus three 10s, plus nine 10s... So, what's that going to get us?
1 plus 3 plus 9 is equal to 13.
Now we have to remind ourselves that this is thirteen 10s.
Or another way of thinking about it, this is three 10s and one hundred.
You might say, "Wait Wait! How does this make sense?"
Remember! This is in the 10s place, so we're adding a one 10, plus three 10s, plus nine 10s.
So we're actually adding 10 plus 30 plus 90, and we're getting 130.
And so we're putting the 30 (the 3 in the 10s place represents the "30").
So this is the 3 that represents the 30, and then we're placing this 1 in the 100s place.
Ten 10s is equal to 100.
And now we're adding up the 100s place.
1 plus 5 plus 3 is equal to...
Let's see... 1 plus 5 is equal to 6, plus 3 is equal to 9.
We have to remind ourselves: this is nine hundred. This is in the hundreds place.
So this is actually one hundred (let me make the colors the same), so this is actually one hundred, plus five hundred, plus three hundred...
is equal to nine hundred. And that's exactly what we got here.
One hundred, plus five hundred, plus three hundred, is equal to nine hundred. And we're done.
This is equal to 934.