Twenty teachers were asked about their favorite course.
Seven teachers said language.
Three teachers said history.
Nine teachers said geometry.
One teacher said chemistry.
Zero teachers said physics.
Create a bar chart showing everyone's favorite courses.
So we've got the bar chart right over here.
Let’s see what we need to plot.
So it said zero teachers said physics –
which is surprising to me,
since physics is arguably my favorite course.
But let’s plot what the data has.
So physics -
Right now looks like
it's halfway between zero and one .
So I just have to bring the “physics” down to zero.
Chemistry... they said –
Let's see.
One teacher said chemistry.
So we've got to bring “chemistry“ up to one.
Now nine teachers said geometry.
So “geometry”...
Let's bring that up to nine.
One teacher said chemistry.
Oh, I already read that.
History. History.
Three teachers said history.
So, let’s bring “history” up to three.
And then language - seven teachers said language.
So let's move this up to seven.
And I think we --
if I didn’t make any careless mistakes, we should be done.
Yep, very good.