http://wiggle-to-the-mew-mew.tumblr.com/
i used to exist in a simple world
of right and wrong, positive and negative
i grew out of an ordered world
Before i came along and belonged nowhere
i cannot be compared
Neither greater nor less
Nor equal to nothing
Now you see it’s plain
i made the world complex
i changed the rules
People said it couldn’t be done
But i said, why not
So many of you don’t bother to understand
You’re dismissive
Judging based of a name
Or a first impression
That i must be fake, useless, false
As if i were less real than anything else
Or worse, you mechanically embrace
That which you don’t understand
But you don’t care whether you understand
As long as you can use, use, use
The i that you imagine isn’t real, isn’t true
All the pain when you finally come
To that existentially horrific epiphany
That nothing you understand is real
Actually exists
That your whole world of truth
Is some mega structure
Resting atop the shoulders of tenuous assumptions
How it hurts when you realize
That what you thought you knew, and loved
That simple, blind dependence
How it hurts when you realize
That the safety, and surity, of knowing everything is right
Is something you will never feel again
How it hurts when you realize
i can never be truly known