Let's talk a little bit about
what it means to own shares,
or stock, in a company.
I think we all have
a general sense.
But what I want to do in this
video is make it a little bit
more tangible, to really
understand exactly what you're
buying when you buy
a share of stock.
So the general sense, and this
is exactly what it really is,
is when you buy stock or you buy
shares you are essentially
becoming a partial, or part
owner, of the company.
And just to contrast this with
bonds, because they are often
used in the same phrasing, oh
I'm going to go buy some
stocks or bonds, or I deal
with stocks and bonds.
Bonds, you become part lender
to the company.
So for example, if you by a--
well I'll just say a face
value bond of, let's say it's
a thousand dollars, and
there's a thousand people
who do that.
Each of you all are lending
a thousand to the company.
And since there's a thousand
of you, you're lending a
million dollars to
the company.
And I'm not going to go into
detail on that, because the
focus of this is going
to be stock.
But it's good to keep in
mind that they are
very different things.
Here you're owning the company,
here you're lending
the company.
So just to make this a little
bit more tangible of exactly
what we're owning, let me draw
a simple balance sheet for
some company x.
So this is Company-- let me do
a new color-- let's say we're
dealing with Company
x right here.
And let's say if we looked at
Company x's assets, and when
we talk about assets, it really
is the same thing that
we mean in the real world or in
our everyday life when we
talk about assets.
They are things that
have value.
Things that are going
to give us some
type of future benefit.
A house is an asset because it
gives us the future benefit of
being able to live in it and
protecting us from cold
weather and rain.
Cars are assets because
they provide us some
transportation.
Cash is an asset because it can
be exchanged for things we
need in the future.
So all of these-- a loan to
someone else is an asset
because in the future they
will pay us back.
A loan to me is a liability,
which we'll
talk about in a second.
But anyway, let's just, in the
very abstract sense, say this
is Company x's assets.
And let's say that they're
worth $100 million.
And I'm not going to go into
exactly how this number is
determined, or who's determining
it, or who's
saying this is a hundred
million.
But let's just say we agree that
this is how much their
land, and their patents, and
their copyrights, and their
cash, and their buildings,
and everything else
they have is worth.
All of the things that will
generate future value.
Now let's say that Company x has
also borrowed some money.
And maybe they borrowed it by
issuing bonds, which I will
not go into detail on.
So let's say they borrowed
some money.
And so they owe some people,
collectively, $80 million.
This could have been a straight
debt from a bank, or
this could have been
via a bond issue.
They might have issued-- maybe
they issued a million bonds
where each of those essentially
represent a debt of $80.
I won't go into that too much,
but I think you get the idea
what I mean, part lender.
But this is debt. $80 million
of debt right here.
And let's say that's all
of their liabilities.
There are other liabilities
other than debt.
But for simplicity, let's say
that's their only liability,
and that debt tends
to be the biggest.
Now, what's left
for the owners?
And a good way to think about
that is, what would happen if
this company were sold and
the debt paid off?
So if the company were sold and
these assets really are
able to be sold for
$100 million.
You would get $100 million.
You'd have to pay the debt
holders, you'd have to pay off
the debt first. So you'd have
100 minus 80, you'd have $20
million left for the owners.
I'll do that in this
other green color.
So you'd have $20
million left.
And this is called the equity,
or the owners' equity.
And this is completely the same
idea as when people talk
about having equity
in a house.
if I have a $300,000 house and
I still have $200,000 left on
the mortgage, then I have
$100,000 in equity.
So it's completely analogous.
And so you can see very simply
that assets-- I'll write this
down, you're getting a little
bit of a introduction to
accounting right here-- but
assets are going to always be
equal to liabilities
plus equity.
Because essentially, or you can
view it this way, if you
subtract liabilities from
both sides, assets minus
liabilities is equal
to equity.
This might be a little
bit more intuitive.
What we have leftover is
always what we own
minus what we owe.
That is what the owners have.
Now, when we say that I'm part
owner of our company, that
means that I have a piece
of this pie right here.
This is what I am a part
owner of, the equity.
So for example, if there are
two million shares-- so
Company x, let's say they have
two million shares, and let's
say that the equity is really
worth $20 million.
How much is each share
worth, if we believe
all of these numbers?
Well, we have $20 million of
equity, divided by two million
shares which gets us $10
of equity per share.
So if we believe all of these
numbers, and we know that
Company x has two million
shares, then we would say that
each share is worth $10.
And if we like these numbers,
and if someone is willing to
sell us a share for less than
that, we would buy it.
If someone was willing to pay
more than that, maybe
we would sell it.
And just to make all of this
a little bit more tangible,
let's look at an actual example
of a company, to show
you that I'm not making
all of this stuff up.
I got this off of your
traditional financial sources.
This is actually from
the filings of
this unnamed company.
And you'll get extra bonus
points if you figure out what
this company is.
And this is their actual
stock trading activity.
And I just want to draw the same
diagram that I drew up
here on this company, so you
can kind of see that this
actually happens in
the real world.
So first let's draw
their assets.
Let's say this is Company x.
And let's say these are its
assets right there.
Let's go to its balance
sheet, this is
actually what they reported.
This is June 30, so-- well we
want to take the more recent
date, this is-- they're just
trying to compare to what they
had before-- and let's
look at these.
This is some time ago, but
it doesn't matter.
We're learning.
We're not trying to decide
whether we want to invest in
this right now.
This is a very old financial
statement.
But let's just look at
what they're saying.
So they have our total assets
here. $30 million-- I'll just
do in round numbers-- $30
million right there.
You might be curious about hey,
what's all this current
asset business?
Those are things that are either
cash or that can be
turned into cash within
the next year.
So, for example, accounts
receivable.
That's money that other maybe
vendors owe them that they're
going to pay very soon.
Inventories, these are things
that they have, maybe in the
warehouse, that they
can sell and turn
into cash very quickly.
Other current assets.
Maybe that's stock or some other
type of investment that
they could sell and
turn into cash.
So they have 18 million
of current assets.
That's things that they can turn
into cash very easily and
very quickly, definitely
within the next year.
And then you have some property,
plant and equipment.
This is kind of that land and
buildings and machinery that I
talked about.
And then, who knows what
these other assets are.
Maybe those are trademarks
or patents or, who
knows what they are.
But all in all, they have
$30 million of assets.
Now let's go to the
liabilities.
So they have some current
liabilities, $16 million.
Current liabilities, just
so you know, those are
liabilities-- these are things
that they have to pay in cash
within the next year.
It could be debt, it could be
payables they have to pay some
other vendors.
Who knows what it is.
But you can kind of view it
as debt on some level.
Maybe debt that you have to
pay in the next year.
And then you have long term
debt of $5.5 million.
If you add these two up you get
pretty close to about $22
million, so just for simplicity
I'll put it over
here as $22 million.
So this company has $22 million
in liabilities.
These are their assets,
just to get all
the labelling right.
So what's left for equity?
Well just on this simple diagram
we have $8 million
left for equity.
And actually, they did the
calculation here for us.
The exact number is $8.39 or
$8.4 million in equity.
But this is a nice round number
for us to show it.
So this is real world stuff
that we're dealing with.
And if you wanted to know,
kind of, if you
believe these numbers.
If you believe that this
company's assets really are
worth $30 million, what
should you pay for it?
Well, then you're going
to divide by the
total number of shares.
And you'll see this in some
financial statements, and I
won't go into the details of the
difference between basic
and diluted, but the numbers
are very, very close.
So we don't have to worry
about it too much.
But let's just say that this
company has 2.7-- looks like
2.78 million shares.
So if the book value is 8.396--
I mean I wrote eight
here-- how much should each of
these shares-- how much should
each of these-- and when I say
book value, I mean these are
their books-- according to their
books, the equity is
worth 8.4 million.
So if we if we really believe
that the equity is worth 8.4
million, how much should
each share be worth?
Well, we'll just divide 8.4
million-- this is actually
8.4, I wrote eight there for
simplicity-- divided by the
number shares, 2.78 million.
So that's a million and
that's a million.
And I'll get a calculator out
for this one right here.
So, let's see, you're doing 8.4
million divided by 2.78
million shares.
So if we believe these numbers,
if we believe the
books, the book value
of the shares is
about $3.02 per share.
So this is $3.02 per share--
book value per share.
That's what we should be willing
to pay for this, or we
think a fair price per share of
this company is, if we take
these assets are really
worth $30 million.
Now, what are people actually
paying for these shares?
Well, we look at this
information right here.
And we see that the last trade
here was for $2.58.
So people are paying a discount
to the number we just
calculated.
So the only reason why people
are paying less than that, or
someone's willing to sell for
less than $3.00 is that
someone out there, especially
the person selling, thinks
that this company really-- the
assets of this company really
aren't worth $30 million.
He or she thinks that the assets
of this company are
worth less than $30 million.
And maybe they think that the
company's prospects aren't as
good, their product
isn't good-- the
sales are going down.
Who knows, maybe the person
buying it, maybe they think it
is worth $3.00 a share and
that's why they're willing to
pay $2.58 for it, because they
think it's going to go up.
And just so that we get some of
the other details that we
see here, this bid right here,
this is what someone has
explicitly said that they are
willing to pay for a share.
The ask is what someone has
explicitly said they're
willing to sell a share for.
This 52 week range is the
range of prices that the
shares have sold.
So, in the past year, these
shares sold for as low as a
$1.20, and that was actually a
great deal because then they
went up-- even now where they're
selling at $2.58.
The average volume right here,
this is the number of shares
sold per day-- exchanged
per day.
The market cap, right here,
you've probably heard that
word before.
That's essentially the market's
sense of what this
number really is.
We're saying that the books of
this company are saying this
company's worth $8 million.
But the market cap is saying
what the equity of the company
is worth in the market's mind.
And to get that number, they're
taking the $2.58 times
the number of shares-- times
the 2.78 million shares.
If we do that, we're going to
get 2.58 times 2.78 is equal
to, exactly-- well it's a little
different than what
they had, maybe it's little
round off error, but roughly
$7 million in market cap.
So like I said before, the
market is not paying $3.00,
it's paying $2.58.
And so the market is saying that
the equity, this piece
right here, is closer to seven
million, even though the books
are saying that this
number right here
is above eight million.
Well anyway, hopefully that was
a little bit useful and
gives you a little bit of a
sense of what it actually
means to buy shares
in a company.