Impressionism is so often painting of modern life,
of activities that we engage in now.
Things that we do every day,
we go to cafes, we go to performances
we sit in bars, we have a drink,
we stroll down the boulevards.
This is the stuff of modern life and the stuff of impressionist painting.
And in fact the paiting that we are lookin at is a painting that is about
what we are doing right now, that is looking at paintings.
I almost feel as though I am looking in a mirror when I look up at this painting.
And in fact we are in the Museum of fine arts in Boston
looking at Edgar Degas' "Visit to a museum".
We think that the painting shows Mary Cassat, Degas' friend
because Degas actually did a series of prints of Mary Cassatt
in two different galleries and the Louvre,
and he also did another oil painting of this subject.
He also did pastels so it was clearly one that he really liked,
but he did that with his subjects once he found the subject,
like the races or the ballet, or the nude.
He would visit it time and time again and rework it
and he clearly did that with this subject.
In fact art historians think that perhaps the woman,
who is seated is Mary Cassatt's sister - Lydia.
And Degas and Mary Cassatt were friends for 40 years
and Degas actually was the one who suggested that
Mary Cassatt exibit with the impressionists' group which she did.
She was the only American to do so.
They were really like-minded, it's interesting
because Degas is often critisized as being a misogynist, somebody who has a very difficult time with women
But it's more complex issue, it has to do also with class.
Mary Cassatt had come from a very wealthy American family
and so in some ways although she didn't have the pedigree
that Degas' family name had they were unpair.
The story is that Mary Cassatt saw a Degas' in a shop window
and pressed her nose against the window
so that she could see it and take it in and really admired it
and that similarly Degas saw a painting by Mary Cassatt in 1874
and really admired it and saw her as a kindred spirit.
In fact Degas is quoted saying to Mary Cassatt:
"Most women paint as though they are trimming hats. Not you"
So they had this really close relationship.
And Cassatt is reported to have stepped in when models were not able to do exactly what Degas wanted them to do.
So Degas took Mary Cassatt as his model for this subject at the museum
because by doing so he was immediately taking a woman
who was interested in looking at art and
who had a really good eye and a really intelligent eye.
Look at the pose that he's placed her in.
Her head is cocked back, she is really assessing
and there is a sense of the discerning here.
It's interesting, this balance of looking at printed material
and looking at visual material that's on the walls of the gallery.
That's something that we see around us if we just look around the gallery that we are in today.
So this is a painting that's in some ways about the way we read the visual and it's a painting about seeing.
The subject is somebody looking at art as we, the viewers
in the museum are looking at art, and so there's this perfect replication.
But more than looking, Mary Cassatt is standing.
tilting, gesturing, moving and so is her companion -
holding the book, looking up, tilting her head
and I think that's precisely what Degas was interested in the same way
that he is interested in gesture if we look at other subjects
that he found compelling like milliners or ballet dancers,
the way that they stand, the way that they move.
And I think there was something really interesting and modern to Degas
about the way people move and look at art, and gesture, and stand in an art museum.
Right, it's an expression of the modern world and it's interesting and I think instructive
to think about what Degas has not focused on.
He has not shown us what the specific works of art are that she is looking at.
We can't even see the body or the dress all that clearly.
The entire painting is beautifully brushy and gives this sense of the momentary.
That's right. If anything is specific it's the gesture, the poseture.
I think that Degas is very much thinking about the kinds of ...
puting away the rythorical gesture of history painting,
of images of acient Greece and Rome
that we think of when we think about salon paintings
by Couture, or Gerome,or Bouguereau.
For Degas' viewers this must have looked ugly.
These aren't the graceful gestures of painting condoned by ...
These are really modern and in some ways ugly gestures,
the way you may capture someone sitting on the subway.
All the paint is really quite muddy as well, the colours are muddy
and the composition is also at odds with what academic painting would expect.
They are looking to the upper right,
but the painting's construction, the orthogonals,
look for instance at the bench,
the way the plain of the floor meets the plain of the wall,
all of that rushes to the upper left and so they are an opposition to each other,
this is real sense of movement and energy in the painting
that's created by this compositional opposition
that is constructed but is so much at odds with
they way that academic painting would be organized.
In an academic painting we would likely see what they were looking at,
and we would see their expressions
and there would be some narrative to be constructed out of that,
but that's not what interested Degas.