Let's do some more percentage problems.
Let's say that I start this year in my stock
portfolio with $95.00.
And I say that my portfolio grows by, let's say, fifteen percent.
How much do I have now?
OK.
I think you might be able to figure this out on your own,
but of course we'll do some example problems, just in case
it's a little confusing.
So I'm starting with $95.00, and I'll get rid of
the dollar sign.
We know we're working with dollars.
ninety-five dollars, right?
And I'm going to earn, or I'm going to grow just because
I was an excellent stock investor, that ninety-five dollars
is going to grow by fifteen percent.
So to that ninety-five dollars, I'm going to add another fifteen percent of ninety-five.
So we know we write 15% as a decimal, as 0.15, so 95 plus
0.15 of 95, so this is times 95-- that dot
is just a times sign.
It's not a decimal, it's a times, it's a little higher
than a decimal-- So 95 plus 0.15 times 95 is what
we have now, right?
Because we started with ninety-five dollars, and then we made
another fifteen percent times what we started with.
Hopefully that make sense.
Another way to say it, the ninety-five dollars has grown by fifteen percent.
So let's just work this out.
This is the same thing as 95 plus-- what's 0.15 times 95?
Let's see.
So let me do this, hopefully I'll have enough space here.
95 times 0.15-- I don't want to run out of space.
Actually, let me do it up here, I think I'm about to run out
of space-- 95 times 0.15.
five times five is twenty-five, nine times five is forty-five plus two is forty-seven, one times ninety-five is
ninety-five, bring down the five, twelve, carry the one, fifteen.
And how many decimals do we have?
one, two.
15.25.
Actually, is that right?
I think I made a mistake here.
See five times five is twenty-five.
five times nine is forty-five, plus two is forty-seven.
And we bring the zero here, it's ninety-five, one times five, one times nine, then
we add five plus zero is five, seven plus five is twelve-- oh.
See?
I made a mistake.
It's 14.25, not 15.25.
So I'll ask you an interesting question?
How did I know that 15.25 was a mistake?
Well, I did a reality check.
I said, well, I know in my head that fifteen percent of one hundred is fifteen, so if
fifteen percent of one hundred is fifteen, how can fifteen percent of ninety-five be more than fifteen?
I think that might have made sense.
The bottom line is ninety-five is less than one hundred.
So fifteen percent of ninety-five had to be less than fifteen, so I knew my
answer of 15.25 was wrong.
And so it turns out that I actually made an addition
error, and the answer is 14.25.
So the answer is going to be ninety-five plus fifteen percent of ninety-five, which is the
same thing as 95 plus 14.25, well, that equals what?
109.25.
Notice how easy I made this for you to read,
especially this two here.
109.25.
So if I start off with $95.00 and my portfolio grows-- or the
amount of money I have-- grows by fifteen percent, I'll end
up with $109.25.
Let's do another problem.
Let's say I start off with some amount of money, and after a
year, let's says my portfolio grows twenty-five percent, and after growing
twenty-five percent, I now have $one hundred.
How much did I originally have?
Notice I'm not saying that the $one hundred is growing by twenty-five percent.
I'm saying that I start with some amount of money, it grows
by twenty-five percent, and I end up with $one hundred after it grew by twenty-five percent.
To solve this one, we might have to break out
a little bit of algebra.
So let x equal what I start with.
So just like the last problem, I start with x and it grows by
twenty-five percent, so x plus twenty-five percent of x is equal to one hundred, and we know this
25% of x we can just rewrite as x plus 0.25 of x is equal to
one hundred, and now actually we have a level-- actually this might be
level three system, level three linear equation-- but the bottom
line, we can just add the coefficients on the x.
x is the same thing as onex, right?
So 1x plus 0.25x, well that's just the same thing as 1 plus
0.25, plus x-- we're just doing the distributive property
in reverse-- equals one hundred.
And what's 1 plus 0.25?
That's easy, it's 1.25.
So we say 1.25x is equal to 100.
Not too hard.
And after you do a lot of these problems, you're going to
intuitively say, oh, if some number grows by twenty-five percent, and it
becomes 100, that means that 1.25 times that number
is equal to one hundred.
And if this doesn't make sense, sit and think about it a little
bit, maybe rewatch the video, and hopefully it'll, over time,
start to make a lot of sense to you.
This type of math is very very useful.
I actually work at a hedge fund, and I'm doing
this type of math in my head day and night.
So 1.25 times x is equal to 100, so x would equal
100 divided by 1.25.
I just realized you probably don't know
what a hedge fund is.
I invest in stocks for a living.
Anyway, back to the math.
So x is equal to 100 divided by 1.25.
So let me make some space here, just because I
used up too much space.
Let me get rid of my little let x statement.
Actually I think we know what x is and we know
how we got to there.
If you forgot how we got there, you can I guess
rewatch the video.
Let's see.
Let me make the pen thin again, and go back to
the orange color, OK.
X equals 100 divided by 1.25, so we say 1.25 goes into
100.00-- I'm going to add a couple of 0's, I don't know how
many I'm going to need, probably added too many-- if I
move this decimal over two to the right, I need to move this
one over two to the right.
And I say how many times does one hundred go into one hundred-- how many
times does one hundred and twenty-five go into one hundred?
None.
How many times does it go into one thousand?
It goes into it eight times.
I happen to know that in my head, but you could do trial
and error and think about it.
eight times-- if you want to think about it, eight times one hundred is
eight hundred, and then eight times twenty-five is two hundred, so it becomes one thousand.
You could work out if you like, but I think I'm running out of
time, so I'm going to do this fast.
eight times one hundred and twenty-five is one thousand.
Remember this thing isn't here.
one thousand, so one thousand minus one thousand is zero, so you can bring down the zero.
one hundred and twenty-five goes into zero zero times, and we just keep getting zero's.
This is just a decimal division problem.
So it turns out that if your portfolio grew by twenty-five percent and
you ended up with $100.00 you started with $80.00.
And that makes sense, because twenty-five percent is roughly one / four, right?
So if I started with $80.00 and I grow by 1/4, that means I
grew by $twenty, because twenty-five percent of eighty is twenty.
So if I start with eighty and I grow by twenty,
that gets me to one hundred.
Makes sense.
So remember, all you have to say is, well, some number times
1.25-- because I'm growing it by 25%-- is equal to 100.
Don't worry, if you're still confused, I'm going to add at
least one more presentation on a couple of more
examples like this.