Given a rectangle with length
"a-squared plus 6-a minus 27"
and with "a-squared minus 9",
write the ratio of the rectangle to its length
as a simplified rational expression.
So we want the ratio of the width to the length
to the length of the rectangle
and they give us the expressions for each of these
The expression for the width of the rectangle is
"a-squared minus 9", so the width is
"a-squared minus 9"; we want the ratio
of that to the length; the ratio of the width of the
rectangle to it's length. The length is given
right over there; it is "a-squared plus 6-a minus 27"
they want us to simplify this.
So the best way to simplify this, whether we're
dealing with expressions in the numerator or denominator
or just numbers is that we want to factor them
and see if they have any common factors
and if they do, we might be able to cancel them out
So if we factor this top expression over here
which was the expression of the width
this is of the form "a-squared minus b-squared" where
"b-squared" is 9, so this is going to be the same thing as
"a plus the sqrt of 9 times a minus the sqrt of 9"
so this is "a plus 3 times a minus 3"
and I just recognized that from just the pattern
if you ever see something "a-squared minus b-squared"
it's "a plus b times a minus b"
you can verify that for yourself
multiply this out; you'll get "a-squared minus b-squared"
so the width can be factored into "a plus 3 times a minus 3"
so let's see if we can do something for the denominator