so we've got the function f of x is equal
to x squared, and what I am concerned with is finding
the area under the curve y is equal to f of x
that's my y-axis, this is my
my x-axis, they'll let me draw my function
my function looks like this, at least in the
first quadrant, that's why I'll graph it for now, I could also graph it on the
in the second quadrant, but what I care about is the area
under this curve and above the positive x-axis
between x equals 1 and x
equals 4, and I'm tired of
approximating areas, I want to find the exact area under this curve
above the x-axis, and the way we didn't know
the exact area under the curve, this little brown shaded area
is using the definite integral, the definite integral from 1 to 4 of f(x) dx
and the way, i can conceptualise where this notification comes from
is we imagine a bunch of infinite number of infinitely thin rectangles
that we sumed up to find this area
let me draw one of these infinite thin rectangles, maybe its not so infinitely thin
so let me draw like this
so that would be one of the rectangles, there would be another rectangle
they should be run descent over Riemann sum, in facts thats where Riemann integer come from
they know Riemann sum where you have an infinite numbers of these rectangles
where the width of each of these rectangles, this is how I conceptualise it,
is the dx, and the height of this rectangles is function of valuated at x
that's within this interval right over here
and so this part right over here is the area of one of those rectangles
and we're summing them all up, this is kind of elongated S,
replacement over Sigma for summing, we're summing up
and the infinite number of those infinitely thin rectangles
or the area of those infinitely thin rectangles between 1 and 4
so that's what the notation of the definite integral comes from
we still have undone anything, we just written some notation that says
the exact area between 1 and 4 under the curve f(x) and above the x axes
and now we'll actually do really productive with this
we have to turn to the second fundamental theorem of calculus
sometimes called part two of fundamental theorem of calculus
which tell us that if f(x) has an entire derivative
so if we have an entire derivative of f
so f(x) is diretive of some function F(x) on other way we can say
F(x) is entire derivatived of f(x)
then I can evaluate this thing, we can do the whole video conceptually understanding why this make sence
we can evaluate this by evaluating the entire derivative of f
or any entire derivative of f, at four, and from that subtracts the entire derivative valuated at one
So let's do it for this particular case right over here
so we're taking, we rewrite this statement instead of x we have x squared
so the definite integral from 1 to 4 of x squared dx
well we just gonna figure out what the entire derivative is
so if f(x)=x^2, what is capital F(x) equal to?
What is the entire derivative?
Well you might remember from your power rule,
that if you take the derivative with respect x of x to the third
you're going to get three x squared, which is pretty dare close to x squared
except of this factor of 3 so let's divide both sides by three
let's divide both sides by three and
you get the derivative of x to the third divided by three is indeed x squared
or you could say that this is the same thing as the derivated with respect of x of x to third over three
take the derivate of this it'll be
3 times 1/3 and than you'll decrement your power just to be x squared
so this right of here once again is x squared, just equal to x squared
so in this case is the capital F(x), our entire derivative, is x to the third over three
and so we just start to evaluate that at 4 and at 1
and sometimes, the way, we would for notational use is entire derivative