In the last video on taxing hamburgers, I did a somewhat
artificial thing where I taxed hamburgers with
an absolute dollar amount.
Typically, consumption taxes are a percentage of the
actual price of the goods. So, for example
sales taxes might be eight percent or nine percent
of whatever you are buying.
So let's think about how the supply curve as perceived
by the consumers would look if we had a percentage tax.
So now our government, instead of taxing one dollar per
hamburger. let's say that their tax - and I'll make it big
just to make it clear so that we can see the result of it,
let's say their tax is twenty percent of the price of the hamburger.
So let's think what's going to happen.
Just like we saw in the last video, in order for producers to
even think about producing that first hamburger, they need to
get two dollars per hamburger for it, because that's their
opportunity cost. Using those same inputs, that
same labour and resources, they could produce, their other opportunity would
give them at least two dollars, so you have
to give them at least two dollars to focus on hamburgers.
And every incremental hamburger after that the opportunity
cost goes more, because now they'll be using
things that are slightly less suited for making
hamburgers, and maybe slightly more suited for making other things.
Now, if that very first hamburger. you need to get two dollars for it,
from a supplier point of view, but from the consumer point
they can't just pay two dollars for it, they're going to have to