Multiply, expressing the product in scientific notation.
So let's multiply first,
and then let's get what we have into scientific notation.
Actually, before we do that,
let's remember what it means to be in scientific notation.
So, to be in scientific notation,
and actually, each of these numbers right here are in scientific notation,
it's going to be the form
"a" times ten to some power,
where "a" can be greater than or equal to one,
and it is going to be less than ten.
So both of these numbers are greater than or equal to one,
and less than ten,
and they are being multiplied by some power of ten.
Let's see how we can multiply this.
So this over her is just the exact same thing as
(I do this part in magenta)
is the same as 9.1 times 10 to the sixth
times ... (let me write it all out with a dot notation...
make it a little more straight forward)
So this is equal to 9.1 times 10 to the sixth
times (in green) 3.2 times ten to the negative fifth power.
Now, in multiplication, this comes from the associative property,
which allows us to essentially remove these parentheses.
It says, hey, you can multiply like that first,
or you can actually multiply these guys first,
you can re-associate them.
And the commutative property tells us that
we can rearrange this thing here.
And what I want to rearrange is,
I want to multiply the 9.1 times the 3.2 first,
and then multiply that by 10 to the sixth times 10 to the negative five.
So I'm just going to rearrange this using the commutative property.
So this is the same thing as 9.1 times 3.2,
and then I'm going to re-associate,
so I'm going to do these first.
And then that times
10 to the 6th times 10 to the negative 5.
And the reason this is useful, is that this is really easy to multiply.
We have the same base here, base 10,
so we can, and we're taking the product,
so we can add the exponents.
So this part right over here,
10 to the 6th times 10 to the negative 5,
that's going to be 10 to the 6 minus 5 power,
so we're essentially just 10 to the first power,
which is really just equal to ten.
and that is going to be multiplied by 9.1 times 3.2
Let me do that over here.
9.1 times 3.2. So first, I'm going to ignore the decimal.
I'm just going to treat it like 91 times 32.
So I have 2 times 1 is 2.
2 times 9 is 18.
Take a zero her because I'm in the tenths place now,
I'm really multiplying by 30,
that's why my zero is there.
I multiply 3 by 1 to get 3.
And then 3 times 9 is 27.
And so it is 2, (I'm adding here), 8 plus 3 is 11,
carry/regroup the one, 1 plus 1 is two, 2 plus 7 is 9,
and then I have a two here.
91 times 32 is 2912,
but I didn't multiply 91 by 32 here,
I multiplied 9.1 times 3.2.
So I want to count the number of digits behind the decimal point.
And I have one, two digits behind the decimal point.
And so I'll have to have two digits behind the decimal point in the answer.
I'll stick the decimal right over there.
So this part right over here,
comes out to be 29.12.
You might say, might feel like we're done.
This kind of looks like scientific notation.
I have a number times a power of ten.
But remember,
this number has to be greater than or equal to one,
which it is, AND less than ten!
But this number is not less than ten.
Therefore, it is not scientific notation.
So what we can do is, let's just write this number in
scientific notation,
and then we can use the multiply by ten part to multiply by
this power of ten.
So 29.12, this is the same thing as 2.912,
notice, what did I do to get from there to there?
I just moved the decimal to the left.
Or, another way to think about it;
if I wanted to go from here to there,
what could I do to this?
I would multiply by ten.
I would move the decimal to the right;
It would go from 2.912 to 29.12.
So if I want to write this value,
this is just this [2.912] times ten.
29.12 is the same thing as 2.912 times 10.
And now, this is in scientific notation,
but that's just this part.
We still have to multiply it by another 10.
So, times another ten.
And so, to finish up this problem,
we get 2.912 times
10 times 10, or 10 to the first times 10 to the first.
Well, what's that?
Well, that's just going to be 10 squared.
So it is 2.912 times 10 to the second power.
And we are done.
Thanks You Sal! You are awesome! :)