Write 7/8 ths as a decimal.
The main realisation here is 7 / 8
is the same thing as 7 รท 8.
These are all the same way or different ways of writing the same thing.
So lets actually divide 8 into 7. I will do it down here.
I am going to divide 8 into 7. And I am going
to add a decimal point here just because we know that this value is going to be less than one.
7 / 8 is less than 1.
We are going to have some digits beyond or to the right of the decimal point.
And let me put the decimal point right up here, right above the decimal point in 7.
And then we start dividing.
And now this really turns into a long division problem
and we just have to make sure that we keep track of the decimal sign.
So 8 does not go into 7 at all, but it does go into 70.
So 8 goes into 70 8 times.
8X8 =64. And then you subtract. 70 - 64 = 6
And then bring down another zero because we still have a remainder.
We want to get to a point that we have no remainders,
assuming that this thing doesn't repeat forever and then there's other ways we can deal with that.
8 goes into 60 7 times
7 X 8 = 56. And then we subtract again.
60-56 = 4, now we can bring down another zero right over here.
8 goes into 40 exactly 5 times. 5 X 8 = 40
We have nothing left over.
And so we are done. 7 รท 8 or 7/8 = .875
But I'll put a leading zero here just so it makes it clear that this is where the decimal is.
0.875. And we are done.