We have our scale again,
with some masses on the left-hand side,
and some masses on the right-hand side
and we see that our scale is balanced.
We have the same total mass on the left-hand side
that we have on the right-hand side.
Instead of labeling the mystery masses with a question mark,
I have labeled them all "x."
Since they all have an 'x' on them, we know
that each of these has the same mass.
What I am curious about is:
what is that mass?
What is the mass of each of these
mystery masses?
I will let you think about this for a second:
how would you figure out what the mystery mass is,
or what this x-value actually is?
How many kilograms is each of these things?
What could you do to either one
or both sides of this scale?
I will give you a few seconds to think about that...
You might be tempted to say,
"If I could end up with just one mystery mass,
and if I keep my scale balanced,
then that thing will be equal
to whatever is on the right-hand side."
And that part would be a true statement.
And to get to just one of these mystery masses,
you might say,
"Why don't I just remove two of them?
Why don't I just remove that one
and that one?
Then I will just be left with that single one."
But if you just removed these two,
the left-hand side would become lighter
than the right-hand side,
So left will move up,
and right will move down.
Now you could say: "OK, I understand!
Whatever I do to the left-hand side,
I have to do to the right-hand side
so I can keep my scale balanced."
So you might say: "Why don't I remove
2 of these mystery masses from the right-hand side?"
But that is a problem too, because
you don't know what this mystery mass is.
You could try to remove two,
but how many of these blocks
represent a mystery mass?
We actually do not know.
But you might then say, "I have got
three of these things here,
If I multiply what I have here by a third,
If I leave a third of the stuff here,
and I leave a third of the stuff here,
then the scales should be balanced."
If this has the same total mass as this,
then 1/3 of this total mass will be equal
to 1/3 of that total mass.
So let's just keep only one-third
of this here.
This is equivalent to multiplying
by one-third.
If we are only going to keep 1/3 there,
we will be left with only one of the masses,
And if we only keep 1/3 here, let's see,
we have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9 masses.
If we multiply this by one-third:
1/3 x 9 is only 3.
So we remove these, and now we have 1/3 of
what we had on the right-hand side,
and 1/3 of what we originally had
on the left-hand side.
And they will be balanced, because
we took 1/3 of the same total masses.
And so, what you are left with is
just one of these mystery masses
- this 'x' thing over here,
whatever x might be -
and you have 3 kilograms on the right-hand side.
So you can make the conclusion,
as you kept this thing balanced the whole time,
that x = 3.