Lets see if we can stumble our way
to another logrithm property
So lets say that
Oh, I dont know
Lets say that
log base x of A
is equal to B, right?
That's the same thing as saying
That's the exact same thing as saying that
x to the B is equal to A
Fair enough
What I want to do is experiment - what happens if I multiply this expression by another variable - let's call it C
Right, so I'm going to multiply both sides of this equation by C
I'm going to switch colours just to keep things interesting
That's not an X that's a dot - times C
So I'm going to multiply both sides of this equation by C
So I get C times log base X of A is equal to
(multiply both sides, right?)
is equal to B times C
Fair enough.