Welcome back.
I shouldn't try to squeeze in videos because then I rush,
and then you won't learn, and everything breaks down.
So problem number 7,a,b,and c are different positive integers
and 2 to the a times 2 to the b times 2 to the c
is equal to 64. They want to know
what is 2 to the a plus 2 to the b plus 2 to the c?
Well, here two things we can use.
We can use our exponent rules where if we have the same base
and we multiply it we can just add the exponents.
So this is equal to 2 to the a plus b plus c.
Then, can we write 64 as a power of 2? Sure.
Let's see, 2 to the third is equal to 8 and 64 is 8 squared.
So if we square both sides of that, that's 2 to the sixth.
You might already know that, 2 to the sixth is 64.
You could think of it as 2 to the fifth is 32.
2 to the sixth is 64, of course.
So a plus b plus c has to equal 6.
What do they tell us?
a, b and c are different positive integers.
So what are a, b and c?
Well let's see, they could be 1, 2 and 3, right?
Because 1 plus 2 plus 3 is equal to 6.
So there we have it. a, b, and c are 1, 2 and 3.
So 2 to the a plus 2 to the b plus 2 to the c is
the same thing as 2 to the 1, plus 2 squared, plus 2 cubed.
That's equal to 2 plus 4 plus 8. 6 plus 8 is equal to 14.
That is choice A.Next problem,I'll switch colors for variety.
Problem number 8, in the xy plane, the center of a circle
has the coordinates 3 comma minus 7.
Let's see if I have to draw this.
If one endpoint of a diameter of the circle
is minus 2 comma 7--
so this is an endpoint of the diameter, this is center--
what are the coordinates of the other endpoint
of this diameter? Well sure, maybe I'll draw it for you,
just so you get a sense of all this action that's going on.
So the center is 3 comma negative 7.
So this is 3-- let me do it in a different color--
3, minus 7. So this is the center.
This one diameter is at negative 2, 7.
Actually, I drew this too big. So this is one endpoint.
So actually the circle is going to be huge.
Actually let me redraw this
because it's going to be a huge circle.
I didn't do this appropriately.
This is the coordinate axes-- I'll draw it big like this.
So the center-- and I'll do it in a different color--
the center is at 3, then minus 7. Right?
And then one endpoint is at minus 2. Oh no. You know what?
I misread the problem.
The other endpoint is at minus 2, minus 7.
So the other endpoint is here, minus 2, minus 7.
So it's here. So I could use this graph.
So the other endpoint is minus 2, minus 7.
It shows you how important it is
to read these problems properly. So if you drew the circle,
the circle actually looks something like this.
The important thing to realize--
and you actually didn't even have to draw the circle--
is that this diameter, it.
this is the diameter that they're talking about.
I know I'm drawing it kind of funny,
but this is the point right here, 3, minus 7.
This is minus 2, minus 7.
So to go from this point to this point
we didn't change our y-coordinates. We just changed x.
What did we do? We went how far back?
We went from x equals 3 to x equals minus 2.
So we went 5 back, right?
So the other endpoint of the diameter--
we just have to go 5 in this direction.
So if we started x equals 3,
we're going to end up with x equals 8.
Then the y is going to stay the same
because we're moving horizontally. So it's 8, negative 7.
That is choice E. Sorry for misreading it at first,
but that shows it can happen to the best of us.
No, just kidding. I'm not even the best of us.
All right, next problem.
9, a regulation for riding a certain amusement park ride
requires that a child be between 30 inches
and 50 inches tall. So between 30,
so height has to be greater than 30
and less than 50 inches tall. Fair enough.
Which of the following inequalities can be used to determine
whether or not a child's height satisfies the regulation
for this ride? OK, so they are essentially
just rewriting this equation and saying it as absolute value.
A number line could probably be useful here.
So if I say--that's my number line--
this is 30 and this is 50.We know, just from this inequality,
that my height can be anywhere around here.
Whenever I see these absolute value problems,
they're really picking kind of a median,
or the middle point, between the two,
and they're using the absolute value to say,
well my distance away from that middle point
can't be more than a certain amount.
So what you can do is you can pick the middle point.
If you want to convert this into an absolute value equation,
you pick the middle point. So what's the middle point?
30 plus 50 is 80. The middle point is 40, right?
I should have been able to do it in my head
because it's 10 away from each other. So we can say--
instead of saying that the height has to be greater than 30
or the height has to be less than 50--
we could say that the difference between the height and 40,
and it's absolute value-- we don't care
if the height is less than 40 or greater than 40--
but that absolute distance between the height
and 40 can't be more than what?
Well, we can't go more than 10 to the positive
and we can't go more than 10 to the negative.
So the absolute value has to be less than 10.
That's how you should you can view this.
If you wanted to convert this to absolute value,
how they tend to do it on the SAT,
pick the average point and then
figure out how far can you vary from the average?
The average point was 40,and you can vary at most 10.
So the difference between the height
and 40 has to be less than 10.
This could also have been written as 40 minus h
is less than 10.
But the choice is h minus 40 is less than 10,
and that is choice D. Problem 10, a right,
circular cylinder with radius 5 and height 4 has volume V.
In terms of V-- oh look at that. OK.
So a right, circular cylinder, so it looks like this.
That's the base. That's the top of the cylinder.
Then you have a line like that and you have a line like that.
What are they telling us? They're telling us it's radius 5.
So this distance is 5, radius 5, height 4. The volume is V.
OK, so the volume is V. So what does V equal?
So V is equal to--
you just have to figure out the area of the space.
Actually I have a minute left.
So I'm going to do problem number 10 in the next video
so as to not rush it.