In the last video I just discussed
a personal balance sheet
and what illiquidity or
what insolvency means.
And if you understood that,
I think we're now ready to tackle
what a balance sheet
of some of these
potentially troubled banks
might look like.
And I'm not going to,
you know, go into the details,
but I'm going to give you the big picture
and I think that's essentially what matters.
So essentially, these banks
have a bunch of assets.
And I'm going to talk about
banks very generally right now
both commercial and
investment banks.
In a future video I'll tell you
the difference between the two
and what regulation means and
what leverage means and all that.
Maybe I'll touch on that
in this video.
But let's just kind of think about
a generic balance sheet for a bank.
So its assets.
So assets.
So, I don't know, I'm just going to make
up some things.
Let's say that it has, I don't know,
$1 billion -- $1 billion in government bonds,
U.S. government bonds.
I'm just throwing that in there
just as filler just to show you that
there could be a lot of
different types of assets in there.
Let's say that it has another, I don't know,
$10 billion in AAA corporate bonds.
So you know these -- these are loans to really
solvent or very creditworthy companies.
So AAA corporate bonds.
Companies that have really
good cash flow.
There's very little chance of them
defaulting on their loans.
And what is a bond?
Well, a bond is just a loan
to another entity, right?
If you loan me money, I could
give you an IOU, right?
saying that Sal owes you whatever, $10.
And that IOU, you could
call that a Sal bond.
So $1 billion of government
bonds, that's an asset that says
the government owes
me a billion dollars.
And in the meantime, it's going
to pay me interest.
Similarly, corporate bonds,
that's saying that these corporations,
whoever these bonds are issued by,
they owe me collectively
$10 billion dollars
and in the meantime, they're
going to pay me interest.
So that's all it is.
And all an asset is, is something
that has some future economic value.
And that's what these are.
These bonds have some future
economic value.
They have the value of the
interest payments,
plus eventually, they're going
to pay you the $10 billion back.
Or maybe it's something
less than that.
So the $10 is the interest payments plus what they're
going to pay you back, which might be $9.9 billion.
I'm making up numbers.
But that's not the issue here.
The crux of the issue is that
there's this stinky asset here.
Actually, let me draw a couple more assets here
just to show you this is the stinkiest of them all.
So let's say I have another
group of assets.
Let's say it's um -- let's say its $10 billion
of commercial mortgages.
Commercial mortgages.
So this is, essentially, I lent money to
companies to buy land or develop land
or buy buildings that they're going
to go rent out to other people.
So once again, it's just
a loan to someone else.
And a loan to someone else that
I've given is an asset.
Because they owe me interest,
and eventually they're going
to pay the money back to me.
And then finally I'm going to throw,
and I'm not being comprehensive here,
I'm going to throw in the crux
of the issue here.
Let's say that I have
two -- Let me see, I have 21 right now,
let me just make it an even number.
Let's say that I have $4 billion,
so it all adds up to 25.
I have $4 billion in
residential CDOs,
collateralized debt
obligations.
Residential
CDOs.
And I've done a video on CDOs,
but just to kind of have review,
CDOs are a
derivative instrument.
I know that sounds complicated,
but that just means they are
derived from another instrument.
Which probably,you know, that's a sign
that the stink is starting to emerge
from this part of the balance sheet.
What does it mean, derivative?
Well, you take a bunch
of mortgages.
So I'll just draw
it down here.
You take a bunch of mortgages,
so you know, these
are house mortgages.
Maybe you take a million
of them.
You group them all together.
And you end up with a mortgage
backed security.
Mortgage backed security.
All a mortgage backed security
is a loan to a big group of people
and you put them all together so that you can kind of,
you know, be able to statistically give it properties.
Because if you lend to any one
person, that's hard to trade.
but if you lend to
a bunch of people,
it starts to become something
that you could trade with other people
because they can understand it.
and, you know, in aggregate, you could say 8% of
people are going to are going to default and all of that.
But anyway, this isn't the
crux of it either.
I have a whole video on mortgage
backed securities.
CDOs, collateralized debt obligations,
are derived from mortgage backed securities.
And that's why they are called
derivative instruments.
What CDOs are, you take these
mortgage backed securities,
you know, they're loans to some people
in some region of the country,
or maybe they're diversified across regions,
then you slice and dice them.
So what you do is,
you slice them into tranches.
And I go into a lot more detail
on this in the other videos.
And you say, this group
of the CDOs,
they'll get the first payments.
or if any payments that go, immediately
go to this very senior tranche, right?
And then the next payments
go to this one.
And then this top tranche, you
could call it the most junior tranche.
it's sometimes called
the equity tranche.
This tranche, they're going to
get whatever is left over.
So if everyone pays,
they get made whole,
but if a lot of people default, all the defaults
are going to hit this tranche, right?
And to kind of make up for the
fact that this is the riskiest tranche,
or essentially these people
are taking on all of the risk,
or essentially these tranches are
giving all the risk to this tranche.
And a tranche is just a
layer, just a slice, ok?
I don't want to use
too fancy words.
But in return for taking on all of the risk,
this person is going to get a higher yield.
So while this person
might be getting 6%,
this person might be
getting 7% on their money,
maybe this person gets
12% on their money.
This is another interesting
thing.
Because this person
is the most secure,
the ratings agency, which I'll probably
do another whole series of videos on,
They might give it,
I don't know, a AAA rating.
And maybe they
give this tranche,
and I'm making up things,
but maybe they give it a AA rating.
But this equity tranche, it
will get a junkier rating.
And because it's a junkier rating,
no one is going to want to buy it.
So the person who constructed this whole
collateralized debt obligations
and who sold these tranches
to the public markets,
and this process by the way is
called securitization,
because you're creating securities out
of these assets that you sell to everyone,
maybe the Chinese, or whoever,
sovereign wealth funds.
But people only want to
buy these tranches.
So the banks have to figure
out what to do with this tranche,
which is the stinky
equity tranche.
So most of them just kept it
on their balance sheet.
They said, oh it looks like
housing never goes down,
we get a really high yield on this,
so we are going to keep
this tranche for ourselves.
And that's what these residential CDOs are,
that are the crux of the issue.
But anyway, that was
just an aside.
And so I wanted to show you this because
these aren't just any residential CDOs.
These aren't the AAAs.
These, they might be, some of them.
But just for the sake of argument,
let's say that these are junky ones
or smelly.
Smelly.
So anyway, that's my example bank,
the asset side of its balance sheet.
Let's think about
its liabilities.
So liabilities.
Liabilities.
We'll just say it
has a bunch of loans, right?
So let's say it has loan A.
Loan A for, I don't know, $10 billion dollars
Let me actually throw
some cash in here.
Let's say it has a billion
dollars of cash.
A bank always has to
keep some cash.
Just in case someone asks for
their money immediately.
That's in the context of
a commercial bank, but anyway,
let's say it has some cash
just for immediate liquidity needs.
So the liability side has loan A.
It owes someone $10 billion.
It has loan B, I don't know,
let's say it's another $10 billion.
And let's say it has loan C.
Loan C is, just to make it interesting,
loan C is... let's say it's for $3 billion.
So in this example right now, if we assumed
that all of these asset values are correct
and all of these liability values are correct,
what is this bank's equity?
And in this case, if it's a
publicly traded company,
what is its shareholders' equity?
Let's figure it out.
It's equity.
Well, its assets are -- let's see one
plus 21, $25, $26 billion in assets
and its liabilities are $23 billion.
So $26 billion of assets minus
$23 billion of liabilities
means that we have $3 billion
of equity -- of shareholders' equity.
And just to make it clear,
what this equity is,
let's say this is a publicly
traded company.
If you own a share of the company,
you own a share of this equity.
So lets --actually,
let's just write it out.
Let's say this company has --um, you know,
let's call this, I don't know, Yachovia Bank.
No, actually, I shouldn't,
that's too close.
Let's call this Bank A.
And let's say that Bank A
Bank A.
has, I don't know, let me make up
something, let's say that it has
a, I don't know, a billion -- let's say
it has 500 million shares.
500 million shares.
Right? If go into Yahoo Finance, you said
how many shares are outstanding?
It has 500 million shares.
So, each share price, or the
book value of each share price,
essentially should be this $3 billion
of equity based on the balance sheet.
And that's why they call
it book equity.
Because the balance sheet
is often called the company's books.
So this is this $3 billion of equity
divided by the number of shares.
So each share should be worth, let's see,
$3 billion divided by 500 million,
it should be $6 of book equity -- of
book equity -- equity -- per share.
And that's something
important to realize
because a lot of people think
that if a stock price goes to zero,
that means that you're getting
the company for nothing.
No, that's not true.
That just means that the
equity is worth zero.
And I just realized that
I'm out of time.
I'm going to continue this
in the next video.
And we'll explore this
a little bit more.
See you soon.