We now know what an oxidation state or and oxidation number is and what it means when things are oxidized
or reduced and lets see how that actually happens in reactions so what we're going to study is this video
is oxidation/reduction reactions and all that is a reaction where somebody is being oxidized, which means
electroons are being taken away from them, and someone's being reduced, which means they are being handed
electrons or they are taking electrons away from someone else, and sometimes this has been termed, because
you have the red in reduction and you have the ox in oxidation an they switch them around and they call i
it a redox reaction, and it sounds like a very fancy chemistry term but it just means a reaction where
something is getting oxidized and if something is getting oxidized, something else is getting reduced,
so lets study a bunch of them. So right here I actually have combustion, this is actually methane, and
you know, methane is a fuel because it used to make a moter powered on methane, right there, its a hydrocarbon,
most fuels that we use are hydrocarbons, most fuels that we use are hydrocarbons which just means carbons ,
bonded in a bunch of different ways to hydrogens and if you add enough heat for the reaction to happen,
so its activation energy if we put it in there with some oxygen around, its going to combust, its going
to produce carbon dioxide and water, and i didnt put it here, and even more heat than ou put into it
so this is an endothermic reaction, it produces more heat than you put into it and ill do a lot more
on that in future videos, about endothermic and exothermic reactions, but anyway, we care about the oxidation
and the reduction, so lets see if anyone is getting oxidized or anyone is getting reduced here, so, lets
look at their oxidation numbers, or their states, here carbon is bonded to four hydrogens, who's giving,
who's taking? the carbon, lets go to our periodic table, carbon is here, hydrogen is here, carbon is
more electronecative, its kind of, its adjacent to the three musketeers of electronegativity, these guys
are the most electronegative, we always ignore the halogens, not the halogens sorry, the noble gasses
because they pretty much dont react at all, they are pretty much happy with their 8 valence electrons,
these guys love to gain electrons, they're small molecules, their outermost shell is close to the nucleus
and they're so close to becoming noble they just love hogging electrons. carbon's almost there, carbon
is much further right on the periodic table than hydrogen, so if you have carbon bonding with hydrogen,
carbon is going to be the electron hog of this situation, lets go down here, so if carbon is the electron
hog, and hydrogen is having its electrond taken away from it, remember this is all kind of hypothetical,
its more partial is the reality, but if you had to pick or choose, hydrogen is going to lose an electron
each, so its going to have an oxidation state of plus one for hydrogen, you have four hydrogens each
giving up an electron, so the carbon must be taking four electrons, so it's oxidation number is minus
4, its taken 4 electrons so its charge will go down by 4, so that's why its negative, fair enough, now
whats the oxidation state of this oxygen right there, well its just bonded to itself, there's no reason
to believe that one oxygen should be able to take any electrons from another oxygen, so it has a zero
oxidation state, its not hogging more than its fair share of electrons that it was initially kind of
born with, now after the combustion occurs, what are the oxidation numbers, well I have oxygen bonded
with carbon, two oxygens bonded with carbon, now we know oxygen, i mean oxidation was something named
after oxygen, it is one of the most electronegative, almost anything bonded with oxygen is going to be
giving up its electrons, we also know that oxygen likes to take two electrons because if it takes one,
two electrons, then it starts having a, it takes one it gets here, it takes two it gets here, it has
8 valence electrons, so it's typical oxidation number is negative two, so, carbon, in this situation,
each oxygen is going to have a minus two oxidation number, each carbon dioxide molecule is neutral, so
everything has to add up to zero, so the oxygens, you have two of them, each one of them with a minus
two for a total of minus four, so carbon must be plus four, plus four, which means that it has given
up four electrons, right, and really it only has four electrons to give up, it has one, two, three, four
valence electrons, in its second shell, which is its reactive shell, so its oxidation number is plus
four. Now lets look at the water, we've done that a bunch, where the hydrogens each give up and electron
and they have and oxidation number of one, each oxygen takes two electrons, there is only one of them,
so its minus two, so whats going on here? Whats getting oxidized and whats getting reduced? You have
the carbon, which went from an oxidation number of minus four to an oxidation number of plus four, so
let me just draw whats happening to the carbon, carbon goes from minus four which means its hogging four
electrons to a situtation where its having four electrons being hogged from it, its kind of giving away
four electrons, so somewhere in this process, this guy must have given away eight electrons, this is
a difference of eight electrons, so plus eight electrons, so what's happened to carbon, carbon has been...,
has it been oxidized or has it been reduced, its charge had gone up, so it hasn't been reduced, another
way you could say electrons have been taken away from it so it has been oxidized, oxidized, carbon had
been oxidized, now lets look at the oxygen, oxygen, over here you have four oxygen molecules, I'll just
write four oxygen molecules, and they all have an oxidation state of zero, because from an oxidation
number point of view they are neutral, and on this side we have two, no we have four oxygen molecules,
and what's there oxidation state? They're all minus two, they're all minus two, so oxygen, each of these
oxygens must have gained an electron, actually, let me rewrite this reaction, let me erase a little bit
of it, so each of these, actually even better let me just move this over, much better, move that over
there you go, and move that over, now let me fill in that so asthetically its pleasing, there you go,
alright, so we have four oxygens witha zero oxidation state turning into four oxygens with a minus two
oxidation state, so each of those four oxigens took two electrons, there's four of them, so we must have
we must have gained eight electrons, so what happened to oxygen, its oxidation number went sown, or its
hypothetical charge went down, it was reduced, its charge was reduced, reduced, ocygen was reduced, what
was it reduced by? It was reduced by the carbon. What was the carbon oxidized by? It was oxidized by
the oxygen. Which oxygen tends to do, it oxidizing things, what is the oxidizing agent, well its the
thing that did the oxidizing. So oxygen is the oxidizing agent. What is the reducing agent? What is the
thing that did the reducing? It is the reducing agent, this is the carbon. you see in this redox reaction,
carbon was oxidized was oxidized, it gave electrons from this state to that state, hypothetically, and
oxygen was reduced, its charge was reduced by a total of eight electrons but two for each oxygen and
so its oxidation number went down. Lets do a couple more, and each of these things i wrote, just to do
a side note, this is called a half reaction because here I'm writing just what happened to the carbon
, and here I'm just what happened to the oxygen. And I did ignore something, I did ignore the hydrogen,
and I encourage you to do something like this with the hydrogen, but you'll see the hydrogen was neither
oxidized or reduced, on both sides of this equation, all of the hydrogens had a plus one oxidation state.
Let
Let's do another one, this is another combustion situation, this is what happened to the hindenburg,
they filled a balloon with hydrogen because they wanted it to float because hydrogen is a very light
gas, unfortunately there must have been a spark, and in the presence of oxygen, and it combusted. and
actually, this is for rocket fuel as well, if you have liquid hydrogen and, actually i don't think they
have liquid hydrogen. Well, I don't know enough about rocket science, I'll have to do another video on
that in the future, but lets look at the oxxidation states, well lets look at the oxidation state of
hydrogen here in its elemental form, its zero, two hydrogens bonded to each other no reason why they
should hog or be hogged by another hydrogen, two oxygen molecules or atoms bonded to each other, once
again zero oxidation state, once they combust and form water, what's their oxidation states? Weve done
this multiple times. This oxygen has a minus two oxidation state, each hydrogen has a plus one, so lets
write the half reactions. We have two hydrogens that are just happy as they are; neutral state. And they
end up with, being, no sorry, two H twos, they turn into two hydrogens, two hydrogen molecules cuz there's
actually four hydrogen atoms,with a plus one oxidation state, so they must have each given away one electron,
now hhow many total hydrogens are there? There are four. So we must have given away four electrons. Plus
four electrons, and this is the half reaction for hydrogen. Now lets do the same thing for our oxygen,
we have some oxygen here, on the left hand side it has a neutral oxidation state, and then it ends up
with a , we end up with two oxygens on the write hand side, I can write it, I'll write it like this.Two
O each with a minus two oxidation state so eac of these oxygens must have gotten two electrons, so it
got two electrons each or it gained four electrons. So what was oxidized? Oxidized means electrons were
taken away from you. the hydrogen was oxidized. This was oxidized, oxidized by oxygen. What was reduced?
The oxygen was reduced by the hydrogen, and if you actually add these two reactions up, if you make this
the left hand side of your equation and you make this your right hand sade of the equation, you can say
"Ok" Let's remove the electrons from both sides and you'll end up with your original reaction. What was,
and just to make sure our terminology is right, what's our oxidizing agent? It's the thing that did
the oxidizing, it's the oxygen. What's the reducing agent? It's the hydrogen. Ket's do one more. So here
I have iron, plus some Hydrochloric acid, let's say this is in an aqueous solution, and you end up with
iron (II) chloride plus some hydrogen. So let's do some oxidation numbers, and I'll do it fast this time.
iron is just by itself it's got a zero oxidation state. Hydrogen with chloride, chlorine's a halogen.
haloge, these guys love to take electrons-they love to take one electron, they typically have a minus
one oxidation state, so the chlorine is going to have minus one, the hydrogen is going to be plus one.
Add them together you get to a neutral compound, fair enough. now you go on this side, what is chlorine's
oxidation state? Well once again it always likes to take one electron. So this is minus one, but I have
two chlorines here, this is a neutral compound so the iron oxidation state must be plus two. Plus two.
What about the hydrogen? Well now it
is jus in its elemental form, so it's going to be neutral and have a zero oxidation state. So what was
oxidized? Our iron, our iron went from neutral to being, to having two electrons taken away from it which
gave it a positive charge, so plus two electrons got taken away, so this was oxidized. This is oxidized.
What about the hydrogen? The hydrogen went from two hydrogens with a plus one oxidation state and essentially
they went to two hydrogens with a neutral state, so two electrons must have been added to the hydrogens.
two electrons were added, their charge was reduced, so they were reduced. And what were they reduced
by? They were reduced by the iron. What was the iron oxidized by? It was oxidized by the hydrogen. What
about the chlorine, the chlorine has a minus one oxidation number here, it has a minus one oxidation
number here, it was neutral relative to the redox reaction, anyway I think you get the point now, and
you can do this with a bunch of reactions, but this will give you a little more insight of actually whats
going on and who's gaining and who's losing electrons and in the future it will also help us think about
alot of the structures of molecules. Anyway, see you in the next video.