Part D- Find the average rate of change of "F" on the interval from x is greater than or equal to -4
is less than equal to x which is less than or equal to 3 so really the interval, whether you picked or not, is right here
right over here. And they say there is no Point C between in that interval where "F" prime is, you
see, equal to the average rate of change. Explain why the statement does not contradict the mean value
here. Fascinating! Alright... let's do this first part first- The average rate of change of "F" on the
interval, sounds like a very fancy thing, but the average rate of change on the interval is really just
the slope of the line that connects the end points of the interval. So this right over here is the end
points and let's figure out the slope of this line. So going from this point to that point are a change in x (this is a color you are not likely to see).
Our change in x over here... is equal to 7. You get that by taking 3 - - 4 or you could just count: 1,2,3,4,5,6,7-
Our change in x and our change in y, when we run over 7, when we go 7 to the right, our change in y... equals
-2. We went from -1 to -3 which is equal to -2. So slope.... which is change- in- y/ change-in-x (rise/run),
is equal to 7 / -2. Or it is the other way around- change in y is -2 / 7 so negative two sevenths. And that's
all it is. You could kind of think of it in a more fancy sense, but you are going to get the same answer
if you said, "Oh WOW loook- the average rate of change of "F" on the interval (well the rate of change)
of "F" is "F" prime of x. That is the rate of change of xf at any point of x. If you were want to find
the average value of this, over the interval, you would integrate it from our starting point from -4
to 3 (dx), then you would divide it by your change in x, so then when you divide it, you would have it
over 1 / 7. But then this part right over here is going to be the same thing as "F" of 3 - "F" of 4, and
then this over here you a 7 in the denominator. SO this is really just your change in x, which is my
definition or how we actually set up this average right over here, and this over here is just your change
in y. So it really is just a slope between the end point. SO we did the first part- the average rate
of change of "F" onto the interval is -2 / 7. Now, let's look at the second part, they say there is no point
see in that interval from which "F" primacy is equal to the average rate of change. Explain why the statement
does not contradict the mean value theorem. The mean value theorem, as a little bit of review..., it says
that if we have some type of an interval (so let me draw some axis right over here) if you have an
interval (and I'll draw my interval like this) and over that interval has a deferential function....so
maybe my function looks like this. It says that there is at least one point C on that interval where
the derivative at that point c is equal to the average rate of change. So the way I've drawn it right over here
the average rate of change of this function (I'll do it in magenta right over here) and the mean value
theorem says that if this is a deferential here is at least one Point C in this interval where I have the
same slope, where the tangid line has the same slope, where the derivative is the same as the
slope as the average slope. And you can see here that it is probably over here where you have a lot of
points or less. If you think about it, it is kind of intuitive that at some point here we obviously have a
larger slope and over here we have a smaller slope and since it is deferential our derivative is continuous
so at some the slope has to get to do the exactly what the average slope is. Lets look at this little
conundrum right over here. Why is there not a Point C where "F" primacy is equal to the average rate
of change. And you can even verify that because from -4 to 0 our slope is positive and then the slope
just jumps down to a negative which is 2 and or -2 it never goes down to -2. This is not a derferential
problem where x = 0 our slope jumps here and because it is not deferential the mean value theorem does
not apply. And you can imagine that if it had some continuous derivative then you would find a pint.
If it looked something like this instead I'll continue over here... the slope would be the same as the average slope
and right over there, it is really because "F" is not deferential over the entire interval. It does
not have a continuous derivative because it jumps straight down to -2 right over here it does not go continuously through all the values in between.