As a pot of tea cools, the temperature of the tea is modelled by a differentiable function h for 0 is
less than equal to t is less than or equal to 10. Where time t is measured in minutes, and temperature h(t)
is measured in degrees Celsius.
Values of h(t) and selected values of time t are shown in the table above,
so that's right over there.
Use the data in the table to approximate the rate of in which the temperature of the t is changing at
time t = 3.5. Show the computations that lead to your answer.
So they give us a bunch of points, so let's just graph this just so we can visualize what this data
is telling us a little bit, and I suspect this might be useful.
So this right over here is our temperature axis, this is our temperature
at any moment in degrees Celcius.
And than this is our time axis and they give us the time 0,2,5,9 and 10
and they give us the temperature at those times.
This is 0,2,5 is a little bit further, 9, and than 10.
And than time 0, the temperature is 66 degrees Celsius, so is it right over there.
And time 2 is 60 degrees Celsius.
And time 5 it is 52 degrees Celsius
So time 5 may be somewhere around here, at 52 degrees Celsius.
At time 9, or after 9 minutes, it is 44 degrees Celsius.