Let's think about how hydrogen bromide might react
with this thing right here.
Let's think about what this would be called.
We have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 carbons.
It has a double bond right here
if we start numbering at this end
because that's where the double bond is
then this would be pent.
the double bond starts at the number 1 carbon, pent-1
and it's obviously an alkene.
It has a double bond, so it's pent-1-ene.
Sometimes this is called 1-pentene, either way.
So let's think about how these two characters
might react with each other in some type of solvent.
Usually when a solvent's not specified
it's usually water or alcohol.
If this was water
then we would have a solution of hydrobromic acid
but let's not worry about that right now.
Let's just worry about how these two characters
might react with each other.
Now, the first thing we might look at
is this hydrogen bromide right there.
And as you get more experience there
you'll say, well, you know
bromine is much more electronegative than hydrogen.
It likes to hog electrons much more.
If that's a completely foreign concept to you
I'll do a little bit of a review.
This is the Periodic Table.
Electronegativity increases from the bottom left
to the top right of the Periodic Table.
Electronegativity.
And really, that's just a fancy way of saying
how much does an atom like to hog electrons.
So, for example, fluorine loves to hog electrons
and calcium doesn't like to hog electrons so much.
So if we think about hydrogen bromide
hydrogen's way up here
on the left side of the Periodic Table
bromine's all the way to the right.
Bromine is much more electronegative.
So in this situation
since bromine is more electronegative
it will hog the electrons in this bond.
And since it's hogging the electrons in this bond
you'll have a partial negative charge
on the bromine end
and you'll have a partial positive charge
on the hydrogen end.
And, whenever you do these reactions
it's actually useful to draw all the valence electrons.
So bromine right here has an atomic number of 35
which means it has 35 electrons in its neutral state.
And we don't have any charge here
so it's in a neutral state.
But you can look at its group.
It's in Group Number 7.
If you just count from here, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7
or has 7 valence electrons. Let me draw that.
Seven electrons in its outermost shell.
Let me draw them right here.
So 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6
and then the 7th is in the bond with the hydrogen.
Hydrogen obviously has one electron.
It's right there.
So these two guys are bonding with each other
and they both allow each other
to pretend that they're part of a pair.
And that's what gives it a lower energy level
or makes it a little more stable.
That's why the bond forms in the first place.
But anyway, let's think about what might happen here.
This guy is really electronegative
so maybe he wants to take this electron away
this green hydrogen electron.
And maybe that happens. Let me just draw it out.
So he takes that electron, that green electron, away.
It's just getting closer and closer.
If there was only some other place
that this hydrogen could get an electron from
then this guy could just go to the bromine
which is what bromine really wants to happen
because it's so electronegative.
So where can the hydrogen get an electron
to replace the one that it's about to lose?
Well, we have a double bond here.
And maybe one of these carbons lose an electron.
And in future videos, we'll talk more about
which one is more likely to give up the electron
at this stage of the reaction.
But just for simplicity, let's assume that
this carbon right here gives up an electron.
Where are its valence electrons?
And just as a bit a review
here's a carbon on the Periodic Table.
it has 6 protons and 6 electrons in its stable state.
Two are sitting in its first shell
and then the other 4 are its valence electrons.
And you can see that. It's in Group 4, right? 1, 2, 3, 4
We can ignore these for now
and usually you're not going to be dealing with
well, we'll ignore those for now.
It has four valence electrons.
Most of what you're going to deal with
you just have to count the group numbers like this.
We won't worry too much about all of the metals
and all of those right now.
That's 4 valence electrons and you see it right here.
It has 1, 2, 3, 4 valence electrons.
It has 2 in its one shell, so it actually has 6
but you only draw the 4 out there.
So what we're saying is
this green electron can go to the bromine
as long as the hydrogen can take an electron
maybe from this carbon right here.
So let's draw that. So this electron right here
is going to go to the hydrogen.
And when that electron goes to the hydrogen
simultaneously that will allow this electron
to go to bromine.
And obviously, they won't be this far when it happens.
There would be some type of collision
that would have to occur in just the right way
with just the right level of energy for this to occur.
Maybe the hydrogen is getting really close to this part
right at the right moment, when this electron
is being sucked away from the bromine
so this has a partial positive charge
attracted to the electron.
That electron goes over there.
It won't always happen
but this is a potential reaction mechanism.
But this whole step happens at once.
This electron goes from this character
to the hydrogen, at the same time
as hydrogen loses its electron to the bromine.
So what's going to happen right after this step?
So right after that happens
what will everything look like?
Well, the bromine will have gained the electron
so it's now a bromide ion.
So let me draw it like this.
So it had its original 7 valence electrons
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7
and now it just stole an electron from the hydrogen.
It was able to swipe an electron off the hydrogen.
That's the electron it swiped off the hydrogen.
And now what will this thing
that was 1-pentene or pent-1-ene
what will this look like now? Let me draw it.
So we have a carbon and a hydrogen and a hydrogen
and then you have a carbon, and then a hydrogen
then you have the rest of the chain right over here.
But this double bond was broken.
This carbon lost an electron, went to the hydrogen.
So this bond right here now forms
between this carbon and that hydrogen.
So let me draw that bond.
You have this electron right there.
That electron will now be with the hydrogen.
So let me draw the electron.
And now we have that orange hydrogen.
I'll try to keep the colors consistent
so that we know where things came from.
And then we have this bond now to the hydrogen.
Now, this carbon now only has 3 valence electrons.
1, 2, 3. It has two sitting in its first shell
so it actually has a total of five electrons.
It has 6 protons, so it has a positive charge.
This carbon right here has a positive charge.
And another way to think about it is
it was completely neutral and then it lost an electron.
So now it will have a positive charge right over there.
So this's what we're left after that step of the reaction.
Oh, and of course, we can't forget.
Bromine over here was neutral.
It had seven valence electrons
and that's when bromine is neutral.
But now it has eight
so now this will have a negative charge
because it gained an electron.
And in general, your total charge
over here our total charge is 0
so our total charge will still be 0.
We have a negative and we have a positive.
They would cancel out, so our total charge is still 0.
So what's likely to happen
for the next step of our reaction?
Well, we have this positive thing here.
Maybe bromine just bumped, just the right way
to let go of this guy and steal his electron.
But now you have this guy who's negative
and this guy who's positive.
Maybe they'll be attracted to each other.
Maybe they'll just bump into each other
at the exact right way.
And if they bump in the exact right way
maybe this guy can swipe the electron
from the bromide ion
from this negative ion right here.
And you might say, hey,
isn't bromine more electronegative than carbon?
Well, it might be, but this guy's electron rich.
It's not just a regular bromine atom.
This is a bromine plus an extra electron.
So he's already hogged an electron
so he's electron rich.
So in this situation, he's negative. He's positive.
He can give this guy an electron.
So if they bump in just the right way, this electron
can be swiped by this carbon right over here.
And this positive carbon
just so it gives you a little terminology
and we'll go over it in more detail in future videos
is actually called a carbocation.
It's a positive ion of carbon.
That's where the word comes from.
But anyway
if this electron gets swiped by this carbon
it will then form a bond.
Because remember, this was the electron
that was originally in a bond with this hydrogen.
It's still going to be, you could imagine, paired up with
this other purple or magenta electron right over there.
So if that happens, then we're going to be left with
so the next step is going to be
so on this end of the molecule
we have C, carbon, hydrogen, hydrogen.
Then we have this orange hydrogen
that we stole from the hydrogen bromide.
Then we have this carbon right here.
It has a hydrogen.
You have the rest of the chain, CH2-CH2-CH3.
And now, since this guy stole an electron
a bond will form with the bromine.
Let me draw it. So he's going to steal this
So a bond will form.
He's stealing this electron
so now this electron is with this carbon
so I can do it as one end of the bond.
The other end of the bond will be
that magenta electron right there on the bromine.
Now the bromine lost an electron. So it's neutral.
It once again has 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7 valence electrons.
Carbon is now neutral, because it gained an electron.
It once again has 1, 2, 3, 4 electrons.
So now everyone is happy again.
In this video, we were able to get a mechanism.
We can talk in the future about
how likely it is to happen
how quickly it might happen.
We were able to start with hydrogen bromide
and 1-pentene, or pent-1-ene, and get to this thing
just by pushing around electrons
and just thinking about what is likely to happen
based on what's electronegative
and what might be able to gain or lose an electron.
And just a bit of a review
what is this thing right here?
This might be-- This is 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 carbons, still.
So it's going to be a pent.
It's now an alkane, no double bond. So it's pentane.
And it has one group on it
so we'll start numbering closer to the group.
So 1, 2. It's 2-bromopentane.
So we were able to figure out a reaction mechanism
to get us from hydrogen bromide and 1-pentene
to 2-bromopentane.