Lets say that I've got a Triangle
This is...this is...this side has length "b"
which is equal to 12...12 units...or whatever
units of measurement we're using
lets say that this side right over
here...this side right over here
has the length "c"
and that happens to be equal to "9"
and that we want to fugure out
we want to figure out...the length
we want to figure out
the length of
this side... and this side has length "a"
so we need to figure out
what "a" is going to be equal to
now we won't be able to figure this out
unless we also know the angle here
because these things could be
could bring, this the blue side
and the green side
close together
then "a" would be small
but if this angle was larger, then "a" would be
larger, so we need to know
what this angle is as well
so we need to know
that this angle
which we will call "theta" is
is equal to 87 degrees
so how do we figure out "a"?
I encourage you to pause this and
try this on your own