And we begin with a very simple question, or --
not a question -- a challenge.
We need to build a machine which takes an input --
(And that input is some integer, 'x.')
And all that machine needs to do
is output 'true' or 'false.'
And that is the first step.
Now we will use the
[Khan Academy] computer-science tool
to actually build this machine together.
And one of the questions
that we will be asking is two things --
two aspects to this machine.
How much time --
That's a clock. [CHUCKLES]
How much time does it take to get the solution?
And how much space does it need?
And when I say 'space,'
I mean -- for example, in the case of
this mechanical calculator -- physical space.
How many rooms do we need to hold our machine?
Or if we're using a computer,
how much memory does it need?
So we will be returning
to these two ideas as we go.