We are looking at a painting at the Museum of Modern Art by Ernst Ludwig Kirchner
It's a street scence in Dresden and it dates to 1908
And Kirchner is known as an expressionist artist that's his classification
He would become a part of a group called "Die Brucke" The Bridge
The bridge meant that they were bridging the past and the future
But it also refers directly to Nietzsche
So the bridge from civilization to the Ubermensch. Crossing the bridge to a journey of self discovery
To individual self actualization
There were so many German artists and craftsmen who were really interested or even obsessed with Nietzsche
What was it about Nietzsche?
He was interested in taking apart ideas of morality wich constricted culture so much I think all over
Europe but escpecially in Germany.
I think the young artists I think Kirchner was not even 30 at this point
The young German artists were all really interested in sort of renewal
and the new and....
Germany was late into coming into the industrail revolution so there is a lot of change happening
In a very compressed time period
They in the later 19th century really tried to catch up to England and France
They worked really hard to do that and then there was alot of growth really fast
But there were all these cultural morays that they worked really hard to break out of
and Nietzsche was totally influential and inspirational because he deposited all of these ways of sort
of breaking out of a really very constritive, proper, individually accountable art form
So that you would not be proper and contained and even in this painting there is a kind of isolation
amongst these figures
Even though its a crowded sort of really dense scence that's pretty wild
I have to say, I know that you like this painting and I have always really not.
I love this painting
Why don't you like this painting?
It feels very like a man looking at women on the street. And I know that there I don't know
It's just that there are... I guess for me it doesn't build all that much more on the 19th century