We're looking at one of the greatest paintings
of the High Renaissance, and really,
one of the paintings that really expresses
what the High Renaissance is.
Yes.
It's Raphael's "The School of Athens,"
and it's in one of the greatest,
most extraordinarily decorated rooms in the Vatican.
In the Papal Palace.
And the name of the room is the "Stanza della segnatura."
It was painted by Raphael between 1509 and 1511, and it's -
- right at the time Michelangelo was painting
the ceiling of the Sistine Chapel.
And they must have gotten to know each other.
I'll bet they did.
It is really an extraordinary expression of
the embrace of the Catholic world during the High Renaissance
of the classical world,
really looking back at the greatest minds of the classical tradition.
Yes. I always think about this as
a kind of humanist's dream come true, you know,
because what we have is under one roof,
all of the greatest scientists and mathematicians
and philosophers and thinkers -
-of ancient Greece.
- of ancient Greece, people who lived at all different time periods,
so it's definitely a kind of fantasy.
It's a fabrication. And actually, a kind of messed up fabrication,
I have to say, because you said under one roof.
If you look at the roof, this is classical Roman architecture,
not classical Greek architecture -
No, that's true.
- so Raphael is actually screwing this up a little bit.
A little bit, yeah.
And in fact, the architecture, while we're on it,
that we see in "The School of Athens,"
is probably, you know, taken from Bramante,
who's there at the same time, redesigning,
or doing the designs for the new Basilica of St. Peter's.
Ah, right. Which is just next door.
Right. So you have St. Peter's being rebuilt
along the lines of ancient Roman architecture;
you have Michelangelo painting the ceiling of the Sistine Chapel;
and at the same time,
What a moment!
Raphael is painting the frescos in the Stanze,
the rooms - "stanze" means rooms - so,
the "Stanza della segnatura" means the "Room of the Signature."
So, this is where the Pope would have signed important documents.
Exactly.
So, there's a lot of figures in here,
there's very complex architecture;
but the architecture, because of the linear perspective,
the orthogonals, really points us to the key figures,
the two central figures.
Yes. And these are not just the two central figures in the painting,
but in a way, the two central figures in Western philosophy,
Western ways of thinking about the world.
And science, really!
And science, right.
Absolutely. So, okay. So we have two figures
that are really beautifully framed by the smallest of the arches,
and actually all of the arches.
You have Plato, and you have his student, Aristotle.
That's right. And they kind of represent the two sides,
in a way, of Western thinking, right?
You have Plato, who -
- He's the figure in the red and the gray -
- Right. And he points upward.
Because he's interested in the spiritual.
But in a world that transcends the everyday world.
So he's pointing up; and actually,
one could argue - and have - that the four elements are here,
that Plato is represented by the red of fire,
and by the gray of what the Greeks would have called ether;
that is, of the nontangible elements.
Mm-hmm. And Aristotle, on the other hand?
Well, he's wearing -
- Holding his hand down.
That's right, actually, to the tangible,
to the actual, to the physical, to the observable.
Right, which is what Aristotle focused on in his philosophy:
What can we observe, how can we make sense
of the world that we can see with our senses?
Not the world that we can't see,
which is what Plato was interested in.
And of course, he's wearing blue and brown,
which would be water and earth,
those elements that respond to gravity.
That are physical.
That's right. We have two different ways
of thinking about the world:
That the world is the way we see it and experience it with our senses,
and this is the way we can approach human understanding and knowledge,
and a sense that there's something higher and greater
and perfect, related to the Divine, for Plato,
which was, in large part, also thought about in terms of mathematics.
Interesting. So, this painting is really a balance
between those two aspects, isn't it?
Yes.
And it's really quite a glorious kind of harmonious expression.
And in fact, all of the figures as they're organized
are really sort of divided between those two sort of schools of thought.
Right. On the side with Plato,
we have the mathematicians, and -
- I think the philosophers that are thinking about
ideas that are not related to the physical, the actual -
not trying to explain the physical and the actual -
That's right, that's right - whereas on Aristotle's side,
you have people who are, in a sense, scientists in some sense.
So maybe what we should do is actually
point out a few of these figures,
and really just speak about them a little bit.
We can do that. Before we do that,
I would like to talk about the architecture -
- Sure.
- as overall. Because, I think that this is,
first of all, in two ways.
We have this really grand architecture
that's really unprecedented.
It's a little over the top.
And you know, it's just, it's an architecture that's very high,
these round arches, these classical sculptures
and niches on either side-
- Which by the way, represent the same kind of -
- duality.
- dualism that we were talking about.
That's right. We have Apollo on Plato's side -
- the god of poetry and music.
- That's right. And we have Athena on Aristotle's side,
war, wisdom -
- More practical..
- a much more earthly kind of figure.
Right. And so, what I was going to say about the architecture
is that it elevates and ennobles the figures.
It creates a context in the way that Leonardo did
in the Last Supper, where the architecture
worked with the figures to help tell the story,
to create meaning. I think here similarly,
the architecture just, you know, I mean,
if you imagine a very different space,
the figures become very different.
It elevates them; it somehow is an architecture
that speaks of the achievements of the mind.
It is absolutely a celebration, as this painting
is a celebration, of the potential of human achievement.
And what could characterize the High Renaissance better
than this idea of what man is capable of,
of reaching almost a kind of divine status in its creations?
Exactly. And I think that the other thing that's important to keep in mind
is just how many figures there are in this painting.
Just, Raphael's achievement!
It's so much fun.
I mean, there's, you know, there's dozens of figures here,
and, there's, you know, this complex composition
where no figure is repeated,
where everything just looks so lifelike and so natural,
like Raphael just, you know, it doesn't even look like
this took any work on his part.
You know, there's a kind of complexity, and -
- There's a kind of facility here that Raphael has.
I mean, there is nobody that paints with more facility than Raphael.
-No.
-He makes it look absolutely natural, and with such ease.
Like there's only one solution.
Like the greatest of ballerinas,
it doesn't look like they practiced for hours and hours.
It's true. I want to go back to a point that you made
a moment ago though, that was important, which is,
what does it mean to have all of these figures together?
You know, it's so interesting.
The Renaissance really came back to this periodically.
If we look at one of the most important texts
to sort of - that is actually pre-Renaissance,
but really sets up the Renaissance,
you could look at Dante's "Inferno."
And in the very beginning of Dante's "Inferno,"
when we actually visit Limbo,
we actually get to meet some of these great Greek figures.
And it was very revolutionary, this idea of retrieving them
from the way in which the medieval tradition had looked at the Greeks,
which was with incredible disdain.
And so, here they're being celebrated.
What a radical reversal.
It is. It is. And it's a moment that won't last long,
in the Church.
No. In fact, it's almost over.
It's almost over! The Reformation is about to happen.
Okay. So let's take a look at some of the primary figures here.
Okay. Should we start with the lower left?
Sure. And actually, let's start sort of actually
lower center left, at the very large,
really the most massive figure in the painting.
The seated figure.
Yeah, wearing those heavy workmen's boots,
crouched over in a sort of leaning and actually,
writing, interestingly enough.
Mmm-hmm, and kind of twisting his body a little.
The figure that's being represented here
is the great ancient Greek philosopher Heraclitus,
who's probably best known for thinking about time
as something that is constantly in flux, you know -
Is he the one who said you can't step into the same river twice?
Same river twice, that's right;
that equated life like a flame, that it was never repeated,
that everything was a sort of infinite variety.
But here, of course, Raphael had no idea
what Heraclitus actually looked like,
so asked somebody that he knew to sit in as a model.
And of course, that was Michelangelo.
Yes! And, but, to me what he did was,
he really tried - not only painted Michelangelo's Heraclitus,
but took on Michelangelo by making him, you know,
sort of painting him in the way that Michelangelo had painted the prophets and the Sibyls,
these large monumental seated figures,
so Raphael sort of taking out Michelangelo's challenge
and saying, "Oh yeah? Well I can do these amazingly beautiful seated figures, too!"
And with the kind of massiveness and majesty
that Michelangelo brings to those seated figures,
whereas so many of the other figures in this painting
are much more delicate in their rendering,
Michelangelo has been rendered as a massive, powerful figure -
- as a Michelangelesque figure!
It's wonderful, isn't it? It's almost a parody.
And interestingly enough, Raphael reminds us here,
because Heraclitus is depicted as writing,
reminds us that Michelangelo was also a poet.
That's true. And so, let's talk about my favorite figure,
who's the figure on the far left.
With the bald head.
With the bald head,
and the beard.
And the beard, and that's Pythagoras,
who we might remember from high school geometry,
a squared + b squared = c squared, the Pythagorean Theorem -
But who was really an entire school of thought unto himself.
Yes. And Pythagoras is doing some diagrams about
how harmony relates to music and numbers,
and how underlying harmony is a kind of mathematical structure.
A kind of rational structure, that could be understood
and, in a sense, measured, really.
Yes.
So, yeah, that's right.
Pythagoras is known for having written the "Harmony of the Spheres,"
which is clearly being referred to here -
this critical ancient text which was missing,
which - where he really asks this fundamental question,
which is: What is beauty?
And in a sense, what could be a more important question for Raphael himself?
Right. What is beauty, how does beauty relate
to harmony, and is there a -
- a divine source.
- sort of underlying - right, an underlying source
and structure in the universe that somehow -
I mean, is beauty then a manifestation -
- of the Divine -
or something created by God, right,
which is such a High Renaissance idea,
that the contemplation of beauty is in a way
a contemplation of the Divine.
And of course, we would see this on Plato's side.
That makes sense.
Because these are absolutely Neoplatonic ideas.
Very much so.
Okay. Should we move over to the right side?
Sure. To Euclid?
Well, here we see, really, the scientists,
the people who tried to understand the universe
and the world and the structures of the world, right?
Yes, and to sort of formulate the structures,
just like Aristotle did with the four elements,
Euclid does with geometry: the point, the line,
the Euclidean - what are they called - theorems,
That's right. Almost all the geometry that we learn
- is Euclid.
- in middle school is Euclidean, absolutely.
And here he's actually in the act of teaching.
Yes.
It's fabulous.
Yes. And you know, one of the things that is so important
about this painting, and makes it so High Renaissance,
is the way that the figures really interact with each other.
Everyone's talking and gesturing, and there's
no sense of stiffness at all, all the groups are so fluid-
- dynamic, absolutely.
and there is, you know, it just -
everyone just looks like they're just hanging out
and talking and having fun and -
This is a forum! It's a -
But how complicated it is, to create these groups of ten people!
It's a dance, really, that he's created.
It's amazing achievement.
Of course, Raphael himself is painted here.
He is.
Among the astronomers, in the lower right corner -
Peeking out -
he's the one who's looking directly at us.
Yes. [chuckles]