Let's do some solid geometry and volume problems.
so they tell us shown is a triangular prism.
and so there's a couple of types of three dimensional figures that deal with triangles.
And this is what a triangular prism looks like
it has a triangle on one two faces and they are kind of separated, they kind of have rectangles in between.
the other kind of triangular three dimensional figures
as you might see would be pyramids
this is a rectangular pyramid, cuz it has a rectangular, or it has a square base, just like that
you could also have a triangular pyramid where literally every side is a triangle.
but this over here is a triangular prism.
I don't want to get to much into the shape classification.
if the base of the triangle b is equal to 7
the height of the triangle 'h' is equal to 3
and the lenght of the prism 'l' is equal to 4
what is the total volume of the prism?
so they are saying that the base is equal to seven
so this right over here is equal to base is equal to seven
the height of the triangle is equal to 3
so this right over here
this distance right over here
'h' is equal to 3
and the length of the prism is equal to 4
so i'm assuming it is this dimension
right over here is equal to 4
so length is equal to four
so in this situation what you really just have to do
is figure out the area of this triangle right over here
we could figure out the area of this triangle
and multiply it by how much you go deep
so multiply it by this length
so the volume is going to be the area of this triangle
let me do it in pink
the area of this triangle
we know that the area of a triangle
is one half, times the base, times the height
so the area
this area right over here is going to be
one half times the base times the height
and we are going to multiply it by like kind of our depth of our triangular prism
so we have a depth of four
so we are going to multiply that
times the four
times this depth
and we get, let's see
one half times four is two
so these guys cancel out, you'll just have a two
and then 2 times 3 is 6
6 times 7 is forty...
is forty two
and it would be in some kind of cubic unit
so if these were in
i don't know
centimeters, it would be centimeters cubed
but they are not making us focus on units in this problem
let's do another one
shown is a cube
if each side is of equal length 'x' is equal to 3
what is the total volume of the cube?
so each side is equal length x
which happens to equal to 3
so this side is 3
this side over here x is equal to 3
every side x is equal to 3
so it's actually the same exercise as the triangular prism
it is actually a bit easier when you are doing it with a cube
where you really just want to find the area of this surface right over here
now this is pretty straight forward
this is just a square
it would be the base times the height
or since they are the same it is just 3 times 3
so the volume is going to be the area of this surface
3 times 3
times the depth
so we go 3 deep
so times
three
and so we get 3 times 3 times 3
so this is 27
or you might recognize this from exponents
this is the same thing as three to the third power
and that is why sometimes if you have something to the third power
they'll say you cubed it
because literally to find the volume of a cube
you take the length of one side and you multiply that number by itself three times
one for each dimension
one for the length, the width, and or I guess the height,
the length and the depth.
depending on how you want to define them.
so it's literally just 3 times 3 times 3