what I have here is a supply and demand curve that represents
you can view as a model for the housing market
or the rental market in a given city
this vertical axis right here is the dollar rented in terms of dollar per squared foot per month
so if you have a 1000 sqft apartment and the price right over here
that means it's being charged 1000 dollar/ month
this axis right here is the squared feet per month in terms of
million squared feet, so 1 million squared feet, 2 million squared feet, 3 million squared feet and so on
and like what we have done in the last few videos
we have been talking about
consumer and producer surplus.
I want to view the demand curve right over here
I want to view that as a marginal benefit curve
so, for the very first squared feet right here
how much benefit is it for the renters, the consumers.
for them it is a huge benefit.
over 4 dollar per foot that is not what they are gonna pay for
but that's what it worth to them. and I am gonna view these this supply curve
as a marginal cost curve or the opportunity cost for producing that extra incremental unit.
so, right down here. where you have very few squared feet.
may be the land is cheap for all this land is available
you just start or the land is most suitable for the building
and so the cost, the opportunity cost for supplier that the few squared feet are very low.
so it makes sense that they will supply it
because they will produce it. the cost to product it is very low
the benefit to the consumers is very high
so the price, the price is anywhere between these two things
the consumer will get some surplus
so the price let's say there
consumer will get some surplus
and the producer will get some surplus
right over there. so the market as a whole
will get a ton of surplus depending on how it's divided
and now we haven't talked about how that price is
just yet, although you see where this is going
so the producer will keep producing more and more units
as long as the marginal benefit is higher than the marginal cost
there is this surplus there that can be divided up
between the consumers and the suppliers
depending on where the price is.
marginal benefit higher than the marginal cost
marginal benefit marginal cost all the way up to that point
all the way till we get to 3,000,000 squared foot per month
after that it doesn't make sense if there is some builder
says, hey let me add some more squared feet to the market
this what it costs, it's gonna cost them over 3 dollars
people are not gonna get 3 dollar benefit from those incremental
squared feet. so no one is gonna get it
so, no reason for anyone to build beyond that point
so that's why this ends up being the equilibrium quantity
and the price where that happens
the price where that happens, I erase this so we
get nice clean numbers, is 3 dollars per squared foot per month
now, 3 dollar per squared foot per month is a pretty
pricy rent. if you've got a 1000 squared foot apartment
1000 squared foot that's my old apartment
that's a 2 bedrooms 2 baths apartment
that's roughly $3,000 per month for that apartment
so that's pretty pricy. so this is type of rent that you will see
in some places in San Francisco
and let's say that the mayor doesn't like this.
this is unaffordable, people aren't gonna be able to live in
our city. and so they, institute rent control
rent control, which is essentially a price ceiling
basically the rent per squared foot can not be above
a certain amount. that's not normally how rent control is instituted
but just for the sake of our model.
normally they say you can increase rent beyond a certain
amount. but let's say rent control. they essentially put
a price ceiling on what rent can be charged
so they put a price ceiling, a price ceiling
or a rent ceiling. a price ceiling at $2 per squared foot per month
$2/sqft/month. so let's think about what's going to happen
and also think about what's happening to the total
surplus. producer and the consumer surplus. so before
actually before we even think about the rent control
let's think about what the total surplus is
you had the consumer surplus. so this is the price right
over here. you had a consumer surplus of this area
right over here. and I don't know if this
if this right over here. let's call it 4 and half.
if this is 4.5
then this side of the triangle right over here is going to be 1.5
that is 1.5
this right over here is 3,000,000
3 million times 1.5 is 4.5 Million
and then you divide by 2
you get 2.25 million
1.5 times one half of 3 you get 2.25 million dollar
so in the equilibrium, if you just let the market be
before the rent control, at this equilibrium price and
equilibrium quantity the consumer surplus is $ 2.25 million dollars
that's how much more benefit the consumers are getting collectively
vs what they have to pay for living in that,
living in those houses. the producer surplus, this entire area
right over here and if we assume. let's say this right over here
i know it doesn't look like, but to make the math easy
let's say that is 50 cents
so this whole side right over here is gonna be $2.50
so this is gonna be 2.5 right over here
this length right over here is still 3
so it's gonna be 2.5 times 3 times a half
2.5 times 3 will give you the area of the whole
rectangle, you have to multiply by a half to get the area of that triangle
so 2 times 3 let me just write this down
so it's 2.5 times 3 is, that is 7.5
25 times 3 is 75
and then 75 divide by 2 get you what it's 37.5
so this is gonna be 3.75. so this the producer surplus is 3.75 million
so this is $3.75 million dollars
and so that's the total value that the producer are getting above and beyond the cost of production
and so the total surplus, the total benefit that the market
as a whole if you add the consumer's and the producer's
2.25 + 3.75 so that gets us to what
that gets us to $6 million dollars of total surplus
so there are $6 million dollars total surplus
so that's good
because we are at efficient price, efficient equilibrium price
and production. we are able to produce all this total surplus.
now let's go back to the rent control situation. where
instituting a price ceiling of $2 per squared foot so the price
is by government mandate being set at $2 per squared foot
$2/sqft right over there
now if the price is set for $2/sqft, what is the quantity is
going to be. how much rent is going to supply
if you can only get $2/sqft maybe some of the landlord say
no I will break down this wall and expand my own apartment
or I'm not going to rent these out as much
or maybe people who are renting out spared bedroom
say, oh i'm not going to rent out those spared bedrooms
anymore, I'm just gonna keep them as guest's room
so the total quantity goes down. total quantity goes down to 2 million squared foot per month
now this is a interesting situation. because 2 million squared
feet a month. the marginal benefit is much higher than the marginal cost
the marginal benefit of one extra unit is over $3 dollars
the marginal cost of an extra unit is right around $2 dollars
so in a open market, an efficient market, unfeded market
people say, oh, just build more unit because people
are going to get benefit from them and we can have a price
between and we both will be ale to experience some surplus
but now you won't. even though there is benefit that's
in excess of $3 dollars, because the price can't be higher
than $2 dollars there is no incentive for any of these
people to either build more unit or maybe offer the units
that they have up for sale. and we shouldn't be talking about
building this for the long run
but even if units are there
I won't want to rent my gust's room out because I'm like
oh, it's too much of that, I'm not going to get my marginal cost
my marginal cost here is over $2 dollars and all I am allowed
to get is is $2 dollars. so I don't want to offer that extra unit
so what happens in this situation. when the price is set right
over here, the consumers who happen to be able to rent at
this price who are able to get these 2 million squared feet
per month. they get even larger at least for those 2 million
squared feet. their consumer surplus is this whole thing right
over here is this thing right over there
and the producer surplus unambiguously shrinks
producer surplus is this stuff right over here
but you see that total surplus is smaller than the total surplus
was when we had the unfedded market. we no longer are able
to access this part right over here of the surplus.
so this right over here you could view this as lost benefit to
society. benefit above the cost. lost surplus
we call this in economic terms. we call this right over
here: the dead weight loss
the dead weight loss
this is benefit to the market that could've gone
to either the consumers or the producers that are somehow
are taken away from the market because the market was
made less efficient by this artificial price ceiling right over here
and you could measure the dead weight loss
once again it's only the area this triangle right over here
and if you say, this right over here,
this length right over here is clearly just one
that's one, and if we say that this height
this height right over here it looks like is
this is about 1 and half
then the area of this white triangle right over here
the dead weight loss is going to be equal to
1 times 1.5 times 0.5.
1 times 1.5 is double the area of the triangle
you multiply it by a half to get the area
so that becomes half times 1.5 which is 0.75
so that gives us the dead weight loss that is 0.75 million
so 750,000 dollars which is lost to the market
so now the total surplus is going to be 750,000 dollars less
than the 6 million dollars
so because of that rent control. it will now go down to 5.25 million
I took 750,000 out of this. So it might have benefited
the renters who happened to who are able to get apartments
it won't benefit the renters who now they are not going to be
able to find any apartment. it unambiguously reduced the producer's surplus
and it reduced the total surplus. the total amount of benefit that the market as a whole was getting
end