In this video I want to do a bunch of example problems that show up on standardized exams
and definitely will help you with our divisibility module because it's asking questions like this
all numbers, and this is just one of the examples,
all numbers divisible by both 12 and 20 are also divisible by
and the trick here is to realize that if a number is both divisible by 12 and 20
it has to be divisible by each of these guy's prime factors
So let's take their prime factorization.
The prime factorization of 12 is 2 time 6
6 isn't prime yet, so 6 is 2 times 3,
So that is prime
so any number divisible by 12 needs to be divisible by 2 times 2 times 3
So it's prime factorization needs to have a 2 times a 2 times a 3 in it
any number that's divisible by 12
Now, any number that's divisible by 20, needs to be divisible by
Let's take it's prime factorization
2 times 10, 10 is 2 times 5
so any number divisible by 20, needs to also be divisible by 2 times 2 times 5
or another way of thinking about it, it needs to have two 2's, and a 5 in it's prime factorization
Now if you're divisible by both, you need to have two 2's, a 3, and a 5.
two 2's and a 3 for 12, and then two 2's and a 5 for 20
and you can verify this for yourself if this is divisible by both
Obviously, if you divide it by 20, is the same thing as dividing it by 2 times 2 times 5
So you're going to have, the 2's are going to cancel out, the 5's are going to cancel out
your just going to have a 3 leftover, so it's clearly divisible by 20
and if you were to divide it by 12, you'd divide it by 2 times 2 times 3
this is the same thing as 12
and so these guys would cancel out, and you would just have a 5 leftover
so it's clearly divisible by both, and this number right here is 60
it's 4 times 3, which is 12, times 5. It's 60
This right here is actually the least common multiple of 12 and 20
Now this isn't the only number divisible by 12 and 20
You could multiply this number here by a whole bunch
of other factors I could call them a, b, and c.
But this is kinda the smallest number thats divisible by 12 and 20
any larger number will also be divisible by the same things as this smaller number
Now, with that said, lets answer the questions.
All numbers divisible by 12 and 20 are also divisible by,
Well we don't know what these numbers are,
So we can't really address it,
They might just be ones, or they might not exist
because the number might be sixty, it might be a hundred twenty
Who knows what this number is? So the only numbers that we know can be divided in to this number
well we know two can be, We know that two is a legitimate answer.
Two is obviously divisible in 2 times 2 times 3 times 5
We know that 2 times 2 is divisible into it.
we have the 2 times 2 over there.
We know that 3 is divisible into it.
We know that 2 times 3 is divisible into it.
so that's six
We know that 2 times 2 times 3 is divisible into it
I could go through every combination of these numbers right here
We know that 3 times 5 is divisible into it
We know that 2 times 3 times 5 is divisible into it
So, in general you can look at these prime factors,
and any combination of these prime factors is divisible into
any number that's divisible by both 12 and 20
So if this was a multiple choice question
and the choices were 7, and 9 and 12 and 8
You would say
7 is not of these prime factors over here,
9 is 3 times 3 so I'd need to have two threes over here, so nine doesn't work
7 doesn't work, 9 doesn't work,
12 is 4 times 3, or another way to divide it,
12 is 2 times 2 times 3
Well there is a 2 times 2 times 3 in this prime factorization
of this LCM of these two numbers
So this is a 12. So a 12 would work
8 is 2 times 2 times 2, you would need three 2's in the prime factorization
we don't have three twos, so this doesn't work.
Let's try another example, just so that we understand this fairly well
So let's say we want to know, we'll ask the same question
All numbers divisible by 9 and 24 are also divisible by
and once again we just do the prime factorization
We essentially think of the least common multiple
of 9 and 24
We take the prime factorization of 9
is 3 times 3
and we're done
prime factorization fo 24 is 2 times 12
12 is 2 times 6
6 is 2 times 3
So anything divisible by 9 has to have a 9 in it's factorization
or it's prime factorization would have be a 3 times 3
anything divisible by 24 has to have three 2's in it
So it's gotta have a 2 times 2 times 2
and it's gotta have at least one three and we already have a three from the nine
So we have that, so this number right here is divisible by both
9 and 24. This number right here is actually 72.
This is 8 times 9 which is 72
So for the choices for this question
Let's assume that it was multiple choice
Let's say the choices here were 16, 27, 5, 11, and 9
So 16 if you were to do it's prime factorization
is 2 times 2 times 2 times 2, its 2 to the fourth power
So you would need 4 two's here, we don't have 4 2's here
I mean there could some other numbers, but we don't know what they are
These are the only numbers that we can assume are the prime factorization
of something divisible by both 9 and 24
So we can rule out 16 because we don't have four 2's in it
27 is equal to 3 times 3 times 3.
We don't have three 3's, we only have two of them
So once again, cancel that out
5, 5's a prime number, no 5 here, so rule that out
11, once again prime number, no eleven's here, rule that out
9 is equal to 3 times 3
And I just realized that's a silly answer
because all numbers divisible by 9 and 24 are divisible
by 9
So obviously 9 is gonna work but I shouldn't have made that a choice
Because that's in the problem
But 9 would work. And what also would work is if
8 was one of the choices, because 8 is equal to
2 times 2 times 2, and we have a 2 times 2 times 2 here
4 would also have worked. That's 2 times 2
6 would work. Because that's 2 times 3
18 would work. Because that's 2 times 3 times 3
So anything that's made up of a combination of these prime factors
will be divisible into something that's divisible by
both 9 and 24
Hopefully that doesn't confuse you too much.