Consider the following story:
Bob is in the room and he has two coins.
One fair coin and one double-sided coin.
He picks one at random,
flips it,
and shouts the result. "Heads!"
Now what is the probability
that he flipped the fair coin?
To answer this question, we need only
rewind and grow a tree.
The first event he picks one of two coins.
So our tree grows two branches
leading to two equally likely outcomes -
fair or unfair.
The next event, he flips the coin, we grow again.
If he had the fair coin, we know this flip can result
in two equally likely outcomes -
heads and tails.
While the unfair coin results in
two outcomes - both heads.
Our tree is finished.
And we see it has four leaves,
representing four equally likely outcomes.
The final step - new evidence.
He says: "Heads!"
Whenever we gain evidence,
we must trim our tree.
We cut any branch leading to tails
because we know tails did not occur.
And that is it.
So the probability that he chose the fair coin
is the one fair outcome leading to heads
divided by the three possible
outcomes leading to heads
or - one-third.
What happens if he flips again
and reports: "Heads!" ?
Remember, after each event our tree grows.
The fair coins leaves result in
two equally likely outcomes -
heads and tails.
The unfair coin leaves result
in two equally likely outcomes -
heads and heads.
After we hear the second "Heads!",
we cut any braches leading to tails.
Therefore the probability the coin is fair
after two heads in a row
is the one fair outcome leading to heads,
divided by all possible outcomes leading to heads.
Or - one-fifth.
Notice our confindence in the fair coins is dropping
as more heads occur -
though, realize it will never reach zero.
No matter how many flips occur,
we can be never be 100 % certain the coin is unfair.
In fact, all conditional probability questions
can be solved by growing trees.
Lets do one more to be sure.
Bob has three coins.
Two are fair.
One is biased - which is weighted to land
heads two-thirds of the time, and tails one-third.
He choses the coin at random, and flips it.
"Heads!"
Now, what is the probability he chose the biased coin?
Lets rewind and build a tree.
The first event - choosing the coin -
can lead to three equally likely outcomes:
fair coin, fair coin and unfair coin.
The next event, the coin is flipped.
Each fair coin leads to two equally likely leaves -
heads and tails.
The biased coin leads to three equally likely leaves -
two representing heads, and one representing tails.
Now the trick is to always make sure our tree is balanced _
meaning an equal amount of leaves growing out of each branch.
To do this, we simply scale up the number
of branches to the least common multiple.
For two and three, this is six.
And finally we label our leaves.
The fair coin now splits into
six equally likely leaves -
three heads and three tails.
For the biased coin, we now have
two tail leaves and four head leaves -
and that is it.
When Bob shouts the result, "Heads!",
this new evindence allows us
to trim all branches leading to tails,
since tails did not occur.
So the probability that he chose
the biased coin, given heads occur?
Well, four leaves can come from the biased coin,
divided by all possible leaves.
Four divided by ten - or 40%.
When in doubt, it's always possible to answer
conditional probability questions by base theorem.
It tells us the probability of event A
given some new evidence B.
Though if you forgot it, no worries.
You need only know how to grow
stories with trimmed trees.